Deuteronomy

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30

31
32
33
34

The Fifth Book of Moses, called Deuteronomy

1

1 These be the words which Moses spake unto all Israel on this side Jordan in the wilderness, in the plain over against [∥]the Red sea, between Paran, and Tophel, and Laban, and Hazeroth, and Dizahab. 2 (There are eleven days’ journey from Horeb by the way of mount Seir unto Kadesh-barnea.) 3  And it came to pass in the fortieth year, in the eleventh month, on the first day of the month, that Moses spake unto the children of Israel, according unto all that the LORD had given him in commandment unto them; 4 [*] After he had slain Sihon the king of the Amorites, which dwelt in Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, which dwelt at Astaroth in Edrei: 5  On this side Jordan, in the land of Moab, began Moses to declare this law, saying, 6  The LORD our God spake unto us in Horeb, saying, Ye have dwelt long enough in this mount: 7  Turn you, and take your journey, and go to the mount of the Amorites, and unto [†]all the places nigh thereunto, in the plain, in the hills, and in the vale, and in the south, and by the sea side, to the land of the Canaanites, and unto Lebanon, unto the great river, the river Euphrates. 8  Behold, I have [†]set the land before you: go in and possess the land which the LORD sware unto your fathers, [*]Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, to give unto them and to their seed after them.

9 ¶ And I spake unto you at that time, saying, I am not able to bear you myself alone: 10  The LORD your God hath multiplied you, and, behold, ye are this day as the stars of heaven for multitude. 11 (The LORD God of your fathers make you a thousand times so many more as ye are, and bless you, as he hath promised you!) 12  How can I myself alone bear your cumbrance, and your burden, and your strife? 13 [†] Take you wise men, and understanding, and known among your tribes, and I will make them rulers over you. 14  And ye answered me, and said, The thing which thou hast spoken is good for us to do. 15  So I took the chief of your tribes, wise men, and known, and [†]made them heads over you, captains over thousands, and captains over hundreds, and captains over fifties, and captains over tens, and officers among your tribes. 16  And I charged your judges at that time, saying, Hear the causes between your brethren, and [*]judge righteously between every man and his brother, and the stranger that is with him. 17 [*] Ye shall not [†]respect persons in judgment; but ye shall hear the small as well as the great; ye shall not be afraid of the face of man; for the judgment is God’s: and the cause that is too hard for you, bring it unto me, and I will hear it. 18  And I commanded you at that time all the things which ye should do.

19 ¶ And when we departed from Horeb, we went through all that great and terrible wilderness, which ye saw by the way of the mountain of the Amorites, as the LORD our God commanded us; and we came to Kadesh-barnea. 20  And I said unto you, Ye are come unto the mountain of the Amorites, which the LORD our God doth give unto us. 21  Behold, the LORD thy God hath set the land before thee: go up and possess it, as the LORD God of thy fathers hath said unto thee; fear not, neither be discouraged.

22 ¶ And ye came near unto me every one of you, and said, We will send men before us, and they shall search us out the land, and bring us word again by what way we must go up, and into what cities we shall come. 23  And the saying pleased me well: and [*]I took twelve men of you, one of a tribe: 24  And [*]they turned and went up into the mountain, and came unto the valley of Eshcol, and searched it out. 25  And they took of the fruit of the land in their hands, and brought it down unto us, and brought us word again, and said, It is a good land which the LORD our God doth give us. 26  Notwithstanding ye would not go up, but rebelled against the commandment of the LORD your God: 27  And ye murmured in your tents, and said, Because the LORD hated us, he hath brought us forth out of the land of Egypt, to deliver us into the hand of the Amorites, to destroy us. 28  Whither shall we go up? our brethren have [†]discouraged our heart, saying, The people is greater and taller than we; the cities are great and walled up to heaven; and moreover we have seen the sons of the [*]Anakims there. 29  Then I said unto you, Dread not, neither be afraid of them. 30  The LORD your God which goeth before you, he shall fight for you, according to all that he did for you in Egypt before your eyes; 31  And in the wilderness, where thou hast seen how that the LORD thy God bare thee, as a man doth bear his son, in all the way that ye went, until ye came into this place. 32  Yet in this thing ye did not believe the LORD your God, 33 [*] Who went in the way before you, to search you out a place to pitch your tents in, in fire by night, to shew you by what way ye should go, and in a cloud by day. 34  And the LORD heard the voice of your words, and was wroth, and sware, saying, 35 [*] Surely there shall not one of these men of this evil generation see that good land, which I sware to give unto your fathers, 36  Save Caleb the son of Jephunneh; he shall see it, and to him will I give the land that he hath trodden upon, and to his children, because he hath [†]wholly followed the LORD. 37 [*] Also the LORD was angry with me for your sakes, saying, [*]Thou also shalt not go in thither. 38  But Joshua the son of Nun, which standeth before thee, he shall go in thither: encourage him: for he shall cause Israel to inherit it. 39  Moreover your little ones, which ye said should be a prey, and your children, which in that day had no knowledge between good and evil, they shall go in thither, and unto them will I give it, and they shall possess it. 40 But as for you, turn you, and take your journey into the wilderness by the way of the Red sea. 41  Then ye answered and said unto me, [*]We have sinned against the LORD, we will go up and fight, according to all that the LORD our God commanded us. And when ye had girded on every man his weapons of war, ye were ready to go up into the hill. 42  And the LORD said unto me, Say unto them, Go not up, neither fight; for I am not among you; lest ye be smitten before your enemies. 43  So I spake unto you; and ye would not hear, but rebelled against the commandment of the LORD, and [†]went presumptuously up into the hill. 44  And the Amorites, which dwelt in that mountain, came out against you, and chased you, as bees do, and destroyed you in Seir, even unto Hormah. 45  And ye returned and wept before the LORD; but the LORD would not hearken to your voice, nor give ear unto you. 46  So ye abode in Kadesh many days, according unto the days that ye abode there.

2

1  Then we turned, and took our journey into the wilderness by the way of the Red sea, as the LORD spake unto me: and we compassed mount Seir many days. 2  And the LORD spake unto me, saying, 3  Ye have compassed this mountain long enough: turn you northward. 4  And command thou the people, saying, Ye are to pass through the coast of your brethren the children of Esau, which dwell in Seir; and they shall be afraid of you: take ye good heed unto yourselves therefore: 5  Meddle not with them; for I will not give you of their land, [†]no, not so much as a foot breadth; [*]because I have given mount Seir unto Esau for a possession. 6  Ye shall buy meat of them for money, that ye may eat; and ye shall also buy water of them for money, that ye may drink. 7  For the LORD thy God hath blessed thee in all the works of thy hand: he knoweth thy walking through this great wilderness: these forty years the LORD thy God hath been with thee; thou hast lacked nothing.

8  And when we passed by from our brethren the children of Esau, which dwelt in Seir, through the way of the plain from Elath, and from Ezion-gaber, we turned and passed by the way of the wilderness of Moab. 9  And the LORD said unto me, [∥]Distress not the Moabites, neither contend with them in battle: for I will not give thee of their land for a possession; because I have given Ar unto the children of Lot for a possession. 10  The Emims dwelt therein in times past, a people great, and many, and tall, as the Anakims; 11  Which also were accounted giants, as the Anakims; but the Moabites call them Emims. 12 [*] The Horims also dwelt in Seir beforetime; but the children of Esau [†]succeeded them, when they had destroyed them from before them, and dwelt in their [∥]stead; as Israel did unto the land of his possession, which the LORD gave unto them. 13  Now rise up, said I, and get you over [*]the [∥]brook Zered. And we went over the brook Zered. 14  And the space in which we came from Kadesh-barnea, until we were come over the brook Zered, was thirty and eight years; until all the generation of the men of war were wasted out from among the host, as the LORD sware unto them. 15  For indeed the hand of the LORD was against them, to destroy them from among the host, until they were consumed.

16 ¶ So it came to pass, when all the men of war were consumed and dead from among the people, 17  That the LORD spake unto me, saying, 18  Thou art to pass over through Ar, the coast of Moab, this day: 19 And when thou comest nigh over against the children of Ammon, distress them not, nor meddle with them: for I will not give thee of the land of the children of Ammon any possession; because I have given it unto the children of Lot for a possession. 20 (That also was accounted a land of giants: giants dwelt therein in old time; and the Ammonites call them Zamzummims; 21  A people great, and many, and tall, as the Anakims; but the LORD destroyed them before them; and they succeeded them, and dwelt in their stead: 22  As he did to the children of Esau, which dwelt in Seir, when he destroyed the Horims from before them; and they succeeded them, and dwelt in their stead even unto this day: 23  And the Avims which dwelt in Hazerim, even unto Azzah, the Caphtorims, which came forth out of Caphtor, destroyed them, and dwelt in their stead.)

24 ¶ Rise ye up, take your journey, and pass over the river Arnon: behold, I have given into thine hand Sihon the Amorite, king of Heshbon, and his land: [†]begin to possess it, and contend with him in battle. 25  This day will I begin to put the dread of thee and the fear of thee upon the nations that are under the whole heaven, who shall hear report of thee, and shall tremble, and be in anguish because of thee.

26 ¶ And I sent messengers out of the wilderness of Kedemoth unto Sihon king of Heshbon with words of peace, saying, 27 [*] Let me pass through thy land: I will go along by the high way, I will neither turn unto the right hand nor to the left. 28  Thou shalt sell me meat for money, that I may eat; and give me water for money, that I may drink: only I will pass through on my feet; 29 (As the children of Esau which dwell in Seir, and the Moabites which dwell in Ar, did unto me;) until I shall pass over Jordan into the land which the LORD our God giveth us. 30  But Sihon king of Heshbon would not let us pass by him: for the LORD thy God hardened his spirit, and made his heart obstinate, that he might deliver him into thy hand, as appeareth this day. 31  And the LORD said unto me, Behold, I have begun to give Sihon and his land before thee: begin to possess, that thou mayest inherit his land. 32 [*] Then Sihon came out against us, he and all his people, to fight at Jahaz. 33  And the LORD our God delivered him before us; and we smote him, and his sons, and all his people. 34  And we took all his cities at that time, and utterly destroyed [†]the men, and the women, and the little ones, of every city, we left none to remain: 35  Only the cattle we took for a prey unto ourselves, and the spoil of the cities which we took. 36  From Aroer, which is by the brink of the river of Arnon, and from the city that is by the river, even unto Gilead, there was not one city too strong for us: the LORD our God delivered all unto us: 37  Only unto the land of the children of Ammon thou camest not, nor unto any place of the river Jabbok, nor unto the cities in the mountains, nor unto whatsoever the LORD our God forbad us.

3

1  Then we turned, and went up the way to Bashan: and [*]Og the king of Bashan came out against us, he and all his people, to battle at Edrei. 2  And the LORD said unto me, Fear him not: for I will deliver him, and all his people, and his land, into thy hand; and thou shalt do unto him as thou didst unto [*]Sihon king of the Amorites, which dwelt at Heshbon. 3  So the LORD our God delivered into our hands [*]Og also, the king of Bashan, and all his people: and we smote him until none was left to him remaining. 4  And we took all his cities at that time, there was not a city which we took not from them, threescore cities, all the region of Argob, the kingdom of Og in Bashan. 5  All these cities were fenced with high walls, gates, and bars; beside unwalled towns a great many. 6  And we utterly destroyed them, as we did unto Sihon king of Heshbon, utterly destroying the men, women, and children, of every city. 7  But all the cattle, and the spoil of the cities, we took for a prey to ourselves. 8  And we took at that time out of the hand of the two kings of the Amorites the land that was on this side Jordan, from the river of Arnon unto mount Hermon; 9 (Which Hermon the Sidonians call Sirion; and the Amorites call it Shenir;) 10  All the cities of the plain, and all Gilead, and all Bashan, unto Salchah and Edrei, cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan. 11  For only Og king of Bashan remained of the remnant of giants; behold, his bedstead was a bedstead of iron; is it not in Rabbath of the children of Ammon? nine cubits was the length thereof, and four cubits the breadth of it, after the cubit of a man.

12  And this land, which we possessed at that time, from Aroer, which is by the river Arnon, and half mount Gilead, and [*]the cities thereof, gave I unto the Reubenites and to the Gadites. 13  And the rest of Gilead, and all Bashan, being the kingdom of Og, gave I unto the half tribe of Manasseh; all the region of Argob, with all Bashan, which was called the land of giants. 14  Jair the son of Manasseh took all the country of Argob unto the coasts of Geshuri and Maachathi; and called them after his own name, Bashan-[*]havoth-jair, unto this day. 15  And I gave Gilead unto Machir. 16  And unto the Reubenites and unto the Gadites I gave from Gilead even unto the river Arnon half the valley, and the border even unto the river Jabbok, which is the border of the children of Ammon; 17  The plain also, and Jordan, and the coast thereof, from Chinnereth even unto the sea of the plain, even the salt sea, [∥]under Ashdoth-pisgah eastward.

18 ¶ And I commanded you at that time, saying, The LORD your God hath given you this land to possess it: [*]ye shall pass over armed before your brethren the children of Israel, all that are [†]meet for the war. 19  But your wives, and your little ones, and your cattle, (for I know that ye have much cattle,) shall abide in your cities which I have given you; 20  Until the LORD have given rest unto your brethren, as well as unto you, and until they also possess the land which the LORD your God hath given them beyond Jordan: and then shall ye [*]return every man unto his possession, which I have given you.

21 ¶ And [*]I commanded Joshua at that time, saying, Thine eyes have seen all that the LORD your God hath done unto these two kings: so shall the LORD do unto all the kingdoms whither thou passest. 22  Ye shall not fear them: for the LORD your God he shall fight for you. 23  And I besought the LORD at that time, saying, 24  O Lord GOD, thou hast begun to shew thy servant thy greatness, and thy mighty hand: for what God is there in heaven or in earth, that can do according to thy works, and according to thy might? 25  I pray thee, let me go over, and see the good land that is beyond Jordan, that goodly mountain, and Lebanon. 26  But the LORD [*]was wroth with me for your sakes, and would not hear me: and the LORD said unto me, Let it suffice thee; speak no more unto me of this matter. 27  Get thee up into the top of [∥]Pisgah, and lift up thine eyes westward, and northward, and southward, and eastward, and behold it with thine eyes: for thou shalt not go over this Jordan. 28  But charge Joshua, and encourage him, and strengthen him: for he shall go over before this people, and he shall cause them to inherit the land which thou shalt see. 29  So we abode in the valley over against Beth-peor.

4

1  Now therefore hearken, O Israel, unto the statutes and unto the judgments, which I teach you, for to do them, that ye may live, and go in and possess the land which the LORD God of your fathers giveth you. 2 [*] Ye shall not add unto the word which I command you, neither shall ye diminish ought from it, that ye may keep the commandments of the LORD your God which I command you. 3  Your eyes have seen what the LORD did because of [*]Baal-peor: for all the men that followed Baal-peor, the LORD thy God hath destroyed them from among you. 4  But ye that did cleave unto the LORD your God are alive every one of you this day. 5  Behold, I have taught you statutes and judgments, even as the LORD my God commanded me, that ye should do so in the land whither ye go to possess it. 6  Keep therefore and do them; for this is your wisdom and your understanding in the sight of the nations, which shall hear all these statutes, and say, Surely this great nation is a wise and understanding people. 7  For what nation is there so great, who hath God so nigh unto them, as the LORD our God is in all things that we call upon him for? 8  And what nation is there so great, that hath statutes and judgments so righteous as all this law, which I set before you this day? 9  Only take heed to thyself, and keep thy soul diligently, lest thou forget the things which thine eyes have seen, and lest they depart from thy heart all the days of thy life: but teach them thy sons, and thy sons’ sons; 10  Specially the day that thou stoodest before the LORD thy God in Horeb, when the LORD said unto me, Gather me the people together, and I will make them hear my words, that they may learn to fear me all the days that they shall live upon the earth, and that they may teach their children. 11  And ye came near and stood under the mountain; and the [*]mountain burned with fire unto the [†]midst of heaven, with darkness, clouds, and thick darkness. 12  And the LORD spake unto you out of the midst of the fire: ye heard the voice of the words, but saw no similitude; [†]only ye heard a voice. 13  And he declared unto you his covenant, which he commanded you to perform, even ten commandments; and he wrote them upon two tables of stone.

14 ¶ And the LORD commanded me at that time to teach you statutes and judgments, that ye might do them in the land whither ye go over to possess it. 15  Take ye therefore good heed unto yourselves; for ye saw no manner of similitude on the day that the LORD spake unto you in Horeb out of the midst of the fire: 16  Lest ye corrupt yourselves, and make you a graven image, the similitude of any figure, the likeness of male or female, 17  The likeness of any beast that is on the earth, the likeness of any winged fowl that flieth in the air, 18  The likeness of any thing that creepeth on the ground, the likeness of any fish that is in the waters beneath the earth: 19  And lest thou lift up thine eyes unto heaven, and when thou seest the sun, and the moon, and the stars, even all the host of heaven, shouldest be driven to worship them, and serve them, which the LORD thy God hath [∥]divided unto all nations under the whole heaven. 20  But the LORD hath taken you, and brought you forth out of the iron furnace, even out of Egypt, to be unto him a people of inheritance, as ye are this day. 21  Furthermore the LORD was angry with me for your sakes, and sware that I should not go over Jordan, and that I should not go in unto that good land, which the LORD thy God giveth thee for an inheritance: 22  But I must die in this land, I must not go over Jordan: but ye shall go over, and possess that good land. 23  Take heed unto yourselves, lest ye forget the covenant of the LORD your God, which he made with you, and make you a graven image, or the likeness of any thing, which the LORD thy God hath forbidden thee. 24  For [*]the LORD thy God is a consuming fire, even a jealous God.

25 ¶ When thou shalt beget children, and children’s children, and [‡]ye shall have remained long in the land, and shall corrupt yourselves, and make a graven image, or the likeness of any thing, and shall do evil in the sight of the LORD thy God, to provoke him to anger: 26  I call heaven and earth to witness against you this day, that ye shall soon utterly perish from off the land whereunto ye go over Jordan to possess it; ye shall not prolong your days upon it, but shall utterly be destroyed. 27  And the LORD shall scatter you among the nations, and ye shall be left few in number among the heathen, whither the LORD shall lead you. 28  And there ye shall serve gods, the work of men’s hands, wood and stone, which neither see, nor hear, nor eat, nor smell. 29  But if from thence thou shalt seek the LORD thy God, thou shalt find him, if thou seek him with all thy heart and with all thy soul. 30  When thou art in tribulation, and all these things [†]are come upon thee, even in the latter days, if thou turn to the LORD thy God, and shalt be obedient unto his voice; 31 (For the LORD thy God is a merciful God;) he will not forsake thee, neither destroy thee, nor forget the covenant of thy fathers which he sware unto them. 32  For ask now of the days that are past, which were before thee, since the day that God created man upon [‡]the earth, and ask from the one side of heaven unto the other, whether there hath been any such thing as this great thing is, or hath been heard like it? 33 Did ever people hear the voice of God speaking out of the midst of the fire, as thou hast heard, and live? 34  Or hath God assayed to go and take him a nation from the midst of another nation, by temptations, by signs, and by wonders, and by war, and by a mighty hand, and by a stretched out arm, and by great terrors, according to all that the LORD your God did for you in Egypt before your eyes? 35  Unto thee it was shewed, that thou mightest know that the LORD he is God; there is none else beside him. 36  Out of heaven he made thee to hear his voice, that he might instruct thee: and upon earth he shewed thee his great fire; and thou heardest his words out of the midst of the fire. 37  And because he loved thy fathers, therefore he chose their seed after them, and brought thee out in his sight with his mighty power out of Egypt; 38  To drive out nations from before thee greater and mightier than thou art, to bring thee in, to give thee their land for an inheritance, as it is this day. 39  Know therefore this day, and consider it in thine heart, that the LORD he is God in heaven above, and upon the earth beneath: there is none else. 40  Thou shalt keep therefore his statutes, and his commandments, which I command thee this day, that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee, and that thou mayest prolong thy days upon the earth, which the LORD thy God giveth thee, for ever.

41 ¶ Then Moses severed three cities on this side Jordan toward the sunrising; 42  That the slayer might flee thither, which should kill his neighbour unawares, and hated him not in times past; and that fleeing unto one of these cities he might live: 43  Namely, [*]Bezer in the wilderness, in the plain country, of the Reubenites; and Ramoth in Gilead, of the Gadites; and Golan in Bashan, of the Manassites.

44 ¶ And this is the law which Moses set before the children of Israel: 45 These are the testimonies, and the statutes, and the judgments, which Moses spake unto the children of Israel, after they came forth out of Egypt, 46  On this side Jordan, in the valley over against Beth-peor, in the land of Sihon king of the Amorites, who dwelt at Heshbon, whom Moses and the children of Israel [*]smote, after they were come forth out of Egypt: 47  And they possessed his land, and the land [*]of Og king of Bashan, two kings of the Amorites, which were on this side Jordan toward the sunrising; 48  From Aroer, which is by the bank of the river Arnon, even unto mount Sion, which is Hermon, 49  And all the plain [‡]on this side Jordan eastward, even unto the sea of the plain, under the [*]springs of Pisgah.

5

1  And Moses called all Israel, and said unto them, Hear, O Israel, the statutes and judgments which I speak in your ears this day, that ye may learn them, and [†]keep, and do them. 2 [*] The LORD our God made a covenant with us in Horeb. 3  The LORD made not this covenant with our fathers, but with us, even us, who are all of us here alive this day. 4  The LORD talked with you face to face in the mount out of the midst of the fire, 5 (I stood between the LORD and you at that time, to shew you the word of the LORD: for ye were afraid by reason of the fire, and went not up into the mount;) saying,

6 ¶ [*]I am the LORD thy God, which brought thee out of the land of Egypt, from the house of [†]bondage. 7  Thou shalt have none other gods before me. 8  Thou shalt not make thee any graven image, or any likeness of any thing that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the waters beneath the earth: 9  Thou shalt not bow down thyself unto them, nor serve them: for I the LORD thy God am a jealous God, [*]visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children unto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me, 10 [*] And shewing mercy unto thousands of them that love me and keep my commandments. 11  Thou shalt not take the name of the LORD thy God in vain: for the LORD will not hold him guiltless that taketh his name in vain. 12  Keep the sabbath day to sanctify it, as the LORD thy God hath commanded thee. 13  Six days thou shalt labour, and do all thy work: 14  But the seventh day is the [*]sabbath of the LORD thy God: in it thou shalt not do any work, thou, nor thy son, nor thy daughter, nor thy manservant, nor thy maidservant, nor thine ox, nor thine ass, nor any of thy cattle, nor thy stranger that is within thy gates; that thy manservant and thy maidservant may rest as well as thou. 15  And remember that thou wast a servant in the land of Egypt, and that the LORD thy God brought thee out thence through a mighty hand and by a stretched out arm: therefore the LORD thy God commanded thee to keep the sabbath day.

16 ¶ Honour thy father and thy mother, as the LORD thy God hath commanded thee; that thy days may be prolonged, and that it may go well with thee, in the land which the LORD thy God giveth thee. 17 [*] Thou shalt not kill. 18 [*] Neither shalt thou commit adultery. 19 [*] Neither shalt thou steal. 20  Neither shalt thou bear false witness against thy neighbour. 21 [*] Neither shalt thou desire thy neighbour’s wife, neither shalt thou covet thy neighbour’s house, his field, or his manservant, or his maidservant, his ox, or his ass, or any thing that is thy neighbour’s.

22 ¶ These words the LORD spake unto all your assembly in the mount out of the midst of the fire, of the cloud, and of the thick darkness, with a great voice: and he added no more. And he wrote them in two tables of stone, and delivered them unto me.

23  And it came to pass, when ye heard the voice out of the midst of the darkness, (for the mountain did burn with fire,) that ye came near unto me, even all the heads of your tribes, and your elders; 24  And ye said, Behold, the LORD our God hath shewed us his glory and his greatness, and [*]we have heard his voice out of the midst of the fire: we have seen this day that God doth talk with man, and he [*]liveth. 25  Now therefore why should we die? for this great fire will consume us: if we [†]hear the voice of the LORD our God any more, then we shall die. 26 For who is there of all flesh, that hath heard the voice of the living God speaking out of the midst of the fire, as we have, and lived? 27  Go thou near, and hear all that the LORD our God shall say: and [*]speak thou unto us all that the LORD our God shall speak unto thee; and we will hear it, and do it. 28  And the LORD heard the voice of your words, when ye spake unto me; and the LORD said unto me, I have heard the voice of the words of this people, which they have spoken unto thee: they have well said all that they have spoken. 29  O that there were such an heart in them, that they would fear me, and keep [‡]all my commandments always, that it might be well with them, and with their children for ever! 30  Go say to them, Get you into your tents again. 31  But as for thee, stand thou here by me, and I will speak unto thee all the commandments, and the statutes, and the judgments, which thou shalt teach them, that they may do them in the land which I give them to possess it. 32  Ye shall observe to do therefore as the LORD your God hath commanded you: ye shall not turn aside to the right hand or to the left. 33  Ye shall walk in all the ways which the LORD your God hath commanded you, that ye may live, and that it may be well with you, and that ye may prolong your days in the land which ye shall possess.

6

1 Now these are the commandments, the statutes, and the judgments, which the LORD your God commanded to teach you, that ye might do them in the land whither ye [†]go to possess it: 2  That thou mightest fear the LORD thy God, to keep all his statutes and his commandments, which I command thee, thou, and thy son, and thy son’s son, all the days of thy life; and that thy days may be prolonged.

3 ¶ Hear therefore, O Israel, and observe to do it; that it may be well with thee, and that ye may increase mightily, as the LORD God of thy fathers hath promised thee, in the land that floweth with milk and honey.

4  Hear, O Israel: The LORD our God is one LORD: 5  And [*]thou shalt love the LORD thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy might. 6  And [*]these words, which I command thee this day, shall be in thine heart: 7  And thou shalt [†]teach them diligently unto thy children, and shalt talk of them when thou sittest in thine house, and when thou walkest by the way, and when thou liest down, and when thou risest up. 8  And thou shalt bind them for a sign upon thine hand, and they shall be as frontlets between thine eyes. 9  And thou shalt write them upon the posts of thy house, and on thy gates. 10  And it shall be, when the LORD thy God shall have brought thee into the land which he sware unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give thee great and goodly cities, which thou buildedst not, 11  And houses full of all good things, which thou filledst not, and wells digged, which thou diggedst not, vineyards and olive trees, which thou plantedst not; [*]when thou shalt have eaten and be full; 12  Then beware lest thou forget the LORD, which brought thee forth out of the land of Egypt, from the house of [†]bondage. 13  Thou shalt [*]fear the LORD thy God, and serve him, and shalt swear by his name. 14  Ye shall not go after other gods, of the gods of the people which are round about you; 15 (For the LORD thy God is a jealous God among you) lest the anger of the LORD thy God be kindled against thee, and destroy thee from off the face of the earth.

16 ¶ [*]Ye shall not tempt the LORD your God, [*]as ye tempted him in Massah.

17  Ye shall diligently keep the commandments of the LORD your God, and his testimonies, and his statutes, which he hath commanded thee. 18  And thou shalt do that which is right and good in the sight of the LORD: that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest go in and possess the good land which the LORD sware unto thy fathers, 19  To cast out all thine enemies from before thee, as the LORD hath spoken. 20  And when thy son asketh thee [†]in time to come, saying, What mean the testimonies, and the statutes, and the judgments, which the LORD our God hath commanded you? 21  Then thou shalt say unto thy son, We were Pharaoh’s bondmen in Egypt; and the LORD brought us out of Egypt with a mighty hand: 22  And the LORD shewed signs and wonders, great and [†]sore, upon Egypt, upon Pharaoh, and upon all his household, before our eyes: 23  And he brought us out from thence, that he might bring us in, to give us the land which he sware unto our fathers. 24  And the LORD commanded us to do all these statutes, to fear the LORD our God, for our good always, that he might preserve us alive, as it is at this day. 25  And it shall be our righteousness, if we observe to do all these commandments before the LORD our God, as he hath commanded us.

7

1  When the [*]LORD thy God shall bring thee into the land whither thou goest to possess it, and hath cast out many nations before thee, the Hittites, and the Girgashites, and the Amorites, and the Canaanites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, seven nations greater and mightier than thou; 2  And when the LORD thy God shall deliver them before thee; thou shalt smite them, and utterly destroy them; [*]thou shalt make no covenant with them, nor shew mercy unto them: 3  Neither shalt thou make marriages with them; thy daughter thou shalt not give unto his son, nor his daughter shalt thou take unto thy son. 4  For they will turn away thy son from following me, that they may serve other gods: so will the anger of the LORD be kindled against you, and destroy thee suddenly. 5  But thus shall ye deal with them; ye shall destroy their altars, and break down their [†]images, and cut down their groves, and burn their graven images with fire. 6 [*]For thou art an holy people unto the LORD thy God: [*]the LORD thy God hath chosen thee to be a special people unto himself, above all people that are upon the face of the earth. 7  The LORD did not set his love upon you, nor choose you, because ye were more in number than any people; for ye were the fewest of all people: 8  But because the LORD loved you, and because he would keep the oath which he had sworn unto your fathers, hath the LORD brought you out with a mighty hand, and redeemed you out of the house of bondmen, from the hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt. 9  Know therefore that the LORD thy God, he is God, the faithful God, which keepeth covenant and mercy with them that love him and keep his commandments to a thousand generations; 10  And repayeth them that hate him to their face, to destroy them: he will not be slack to him that hateth him, he will repay him to his face. 11  Thou shalt therefore keep the commandments, and the statutes, and the judgments, which I command thee this day, to do them.

12 ¶ Wherefore it shall come to pass, [†]if ye hearken to these judgments, and keep, and do them, that the LORD thy God shall keep unto thee the covenant and the mercy which he sware unto thy fathers: 13  And he will love thee, and bless thee, and multiply thee: he will also bless the fruit of thy womb, and the fruit of thy land, thy corn, and thy wine, and thine oil, the increase of thy kine, and the flocks of thy sheep, in the land which he sware unto thy fathers to give thee. 14  Thou shalt be blessed above all people: [*]there shall not be male or female barren among you, or among your cattle. 15  And the LORD will take away from thee all sickness, and will put none of the [*]evil diseases of Egypt, which thou knowest, upon thee; but will lay them upon all them that hate thee. 16  And thou shalt consume all the people which the LORD thy God shall deliver thee; thine eye shall have no pity upon them: neither shalt thou serve their gods; for that will be [*]a snare unto thee. 17  If thou shalt say in thine heart, These nations are more than I; how can I dispossess them? 18  Thou shalt not be afraid of them: but shalt well remember what the LORD thy God did unto Pharaoh, and unto all Egypt; 19  The great temptations which thine eyes saw, and the signs, and the wonders, and the mighty hand, and the stretched out arm, whereby the LORD thy God brought thee out: so shall the LORD thy God do unto all the people of whom thou art afraid. 20 [*] Moreover the LORD thy God will send the hornet among them, until they that are left, and hide themselves from thee, be destroyed. 21  Thou shalt not be affrighted at them: for the LORD thy God is among you, a mighty God and terrible. 22  And the LORD thy God will [†]put out those nations before thee by little and little: thou mayest not consume them at once, lest the beasts of the field increase upon thee. 23  But the LORD thy God shall deliver them [†]unto thee, and shall destroy them with a mighty destruction, until they be destroyed. 24  And he shall deliver their kings into thine hand, and thou shalt destroy their name from under heaven: there shall no man be able to stand before thee, until thou have destroyed them. 25  The graven images of their gods [*]shall ye burn with fire: thou [*]shalt not desire the silver or gold that is on them, nor take it unto thee, lest thou be snared therein: for it is an abomination to the LORD thy God. 26  Neither shalt thou bring an abomination into thine house, lest thou be a cursed thing like it: but thou shalt utterly detest it, and thou shalt utterly abhor it; [*]for it is a cursed thing.

8

1  All the commandments which I command thee this day shall ye observe to do, that ye may live, and multiply, and go in and possess the land which the LORD sware unto your fathers. 2  And thou shalt remember all the way which the LORD thy God led thee these forty years in the wilderness, to humble thee, and to prove thee, to know what was in thine heart, whether thou wouldest keep his commandments, or no. 3  And he humbled thee, and suffered thee to hunger, and fed thee with manna, which thou knewest not, neither did thy fathers know; that he might make thee know that man doth [*]not live by bread only, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of the LORD doth man live. 4 [*] Thy raiment waxed not old upon thee, neither did thy foot swell, these forty years. 5  Thou shalt also consider in thine heart, that, as a man chasteneth his son, so the LORD thy God chasteneth thee. 6  Therefore thou shalt keep the commandments of the LORD thy God, to walk in his ways, and to fear him. 7  For the LORD thy God bringeth thee into a good land, a land of brooks of water, of fountains and depths that spring out of valleys and hills; 8  A land of wheat, and barley, and vines, and fig trees, and pomegranates; a land [†]of oil olive, and honey; 9  A land wherein thou shalt eat bread without scarceness, thou shalt not lack any thing in it; a land whose stones are iron, and out of whose hills thou mayest dig brass.

10 [*] When thou hast eaten and art full, then thou shalt bless the LORD thy God for the good land which he hath given thee. 11  Beware that thou forget not the LORD thy God, in not keeping his commandments, and his judgments, and his statutes, which I command thee this day: 12 Lest when thou hast eaten and art full, and hast built goodly houses, and dwelt therein; 13 And when thy herds and thy flocks multiply, and thy silver and thy gold is multiplied, and all that thou hast is multiplied; 14  Then thine heart be lifted up, and thou forget the LORD thy God, which brought thee forth out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage; 15  Who led thee through that great and terrible wilderness, wherein were fiery serpents, and scorpions, and drought, where there was no water; [*]who brought thee forth water out of the rock of flint; 16  Who fed thee in the wilderness with [*]manna, which thy fathers knew not, that he might humble thee, and that he might prove thee, to do thee good at thy latter end; 17  And thou say in thine heart, My power and the might of mine hand hath gotten me this wealth. 18  But thou shalt remember the LORD thy God: for it is he that giveth thee power to get wealth, that he may establish his covenant which he sware unto thy fathers, as it is this day. 19  And it shall be, if thou do at all forget the LORD thy God, and walk after other gods, and serve them, and worship them, I testify against you this day that ye shall surely perish. 20  As the nations which the LORD destroyeth before your face, so shall ye perish; because ye would not be obedient unto the voice of the LORD your God.

9

1  Hear, O Israel: Thou art to pass over Jordan this day, to go in to possess nations greater and mightier than thyself, cities great and fenced up to heaven, 2  A people great and tall, [*]the children of the Anakims, whom thou knowest, and of whom thou hast heard say, Who can stand before the children of Anak! 3  Understand therefore this day, that the LORD thy God is he which goeth over before thee; as a [*]consuming fire he shall destroy them, and he shall bring them down before thy face: so shalt thou drive them out, and destroy them quickly, as the LORD hath said unto thee. 4  Speak not thou in thine heart, after that the LORD thy God hath cast them out from before thee, saying, For my righteousness the LORD hath brought me in to possess this land: but for the wickedness of these nations the LORD doth drive them out from before thee. 5  Not for thy righteousness, or for the uprightness of thine heart, dost thou go to possess their land: but for the wickedness of these nations the LORD thy God doth drive them out from before thee, and that he may perform the word which the LORD sware unto thy fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. 6  Understand therefore, that the LORD thy God giveth thee not this good land to possess it for thy righteousness; for thou art a stiffnecked people.

7 ¶ Remember, and forget not, how thou provokedst the LORD thy God to wrath in the wilderness: from the day that thou didst depart out of the land of Egypt, until ye came unto this place, ye have been rebellious against the LORD. 8  Also in Horeb ye provoked the LORD to wrath, so that the LORD was angry with you to have destroyed you. 9  When I was gone up into the mount to receive the tables of stone, even the tables of the covenant which the LORD made with you, then [*]I abode in the mount forty days and forty nights, I neither did eat bread nor drink water: 10 [*] And the LORD delivered unto me two tables of stone written with the finger of God; and on them was written according to all the words, which the LORD spake with you in the mount out of the midst of [‡]the fire in the day of the assembly. 11  And it came to pass at the end of forty days and forty nights, that the LORD gave me the two tables of stone, even the tables of the covenant. 12  And the LORD said unto me, [*]Arise, get thee down quickly from hence; for thy people which thou hast brought forth out of Egypt have corrupted themselves; they are quickly turned aside out of the way which I commanded them; they have made them a molten image. 13  Furthermore the LORD spake unto me, saying, I have seen this people, and, behold, it is a stiffnecked people: 14  Let me alone, that I may destroy them, and blot out their name from under heaven: and I will make of thee a nation mightier and greater than they. 15  So I turned and came down from the mount, and the mount burned with fire: and the two tables of the covenant were in my two hands. 16  And I looked, and, behold, ye had sinned against the LORD your God, and had made you a molten calf: ye had turned aside quickly out of the way which the LORD had commanded you. 17  And I took the two tables, and cast them out of my two hands, and brake them before your eyes. 18  And I fell down before the LORD, as at the first, forty days and forty nights: I did neither eat bread, nor drink water, because of all your sins which ye sinned, in doing wickedly in the sight of the LORD, to provoke him to anger. 19  For I was afraid of the anger and hot displeasure, wherewith the LORD was wroth against you to destroy you. But the LORD hearkened unto me at that time also. 20  And the LORD was very angry with Aaron to have destroyed him: and I prayed for Aaron also the same time. 21  And I took your sin, the calf which ye had made, and burnt it with fire, and stamped it, and ground it very small, even until it was as small as dust: and I cast the dust thereof into the brook that descended out of the mount. 22  And at [*]Taberah, and at [*]Massah, and at [*]Kibroth-hattaavah, ye provoked the LORD to wrath. 23  Likewise when the LORD sent you from Kadesh-barnea, saying, Go up and possess the land which I have given you; then ye rebelled against the commandment of the LORD your God, and ye believed him not, nor hearkened to his voice. 24  Ye have been rebellious against the LORD from the day that I knew you. 25  Thus I fell down before the LORD forty days and forty nights, as I fell down at the first; because the LORD had said he would destroy you. 26  I prayed therefore unto the LORD, and said, O Lord GOD, destroy not thy people and thine inheritance, which thou hast redeemed through thy greatness, which thou hast brought forth out of Egypt with a mighty hand. 27  Remember thy servants, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob; look not unto the stubbornness of this people, nor to their wickedness, nor to their sin: 28  Lest the land whence thou broughtest us out say, [*]Because the LORD was not able to bring them into the land which he promised them, and because he hated them, he hath brought them out to slay them in the wilderness. 29 Yet they are thy people and thine inheritance, which thou broughtest out by thy mighty power and by thy stretched out arm.

10

1  At that time the LORD said unto me, [*]Hew thee two tables of stone like unto the first, and come up unto me into the mount, and make thee an ark of wood. 2  And I will write on the tables the words that were in the first tables which thou brakest, and thou shalt put them in the ark. 3  And I made an ark of shittim wood, and hewed two tables of stone like unto the first, and went up into the mount, having the two tables in mine hand. 4  And he wrote on the tables, according to the first writing, the ten [†]commandments, which the LORD spake unto you in the mount out of the midst of the fire in the day of the assembly: and the LORD gave them unto me. 5  And I turned myself and came down from the mount, and put the tables in the ark which I had made; and there they be, as the LORD commanded me.

6 ¶ And the children of Israel took their journey from Beeroth of the children of Jaakan to [*]Mosera: [*]there Aaron died, and there he was buried; and Eleazar his son ministered in the priest’s office in his stead. 7  From thence they journeyed unto Gudgodah; and from Gudgodah to Jotbath, a land of rivers of waters.

8 ¶ At that time the LORD separated the tribe of Levi, to bear the ark of the covenant of the LORD, to stand before the LORD to minister unto him, and to bless in his name, unto this day. 9 [*] Wherefore Levi hath no part nor inheritance with his brethren; the LORD is his inheritance, according as the LORD thy God promised him. 10  And I stayed in the mount, according to the [∥]first time, forty days and forty nights; and the LORD hearkened unto me at that time also, and the LORD would not destroy thee. 11  And the LORD said unto me, Arise, [†]take thy journey before the people, that they may go in and possess the land, which I sware unto their fathers to give unto them.

12 ¶ And now, Israel, what doth the LORD thy God require of thee, but to fear the LORD thy God, to walk in all his ways, and to love him, and to serve the LORD thy God with all thy heart and with all thy soul, 13  To keep the commandments of the LORD, and his statutes, which I command thee this day for thy good? 14  Behold, the heaven and the heaven of heavens is the LORD’s thy God, [*]the earth also, with all that therein is. 15  Only the LORD had a delight in thy fathers to love them, and he chose their seed after them, even you above all people, as it is this day. 16  Circumcise therefore the foreskin of your heart, and be no more stiffnecked. 17  For the LORD your God is God of gods, and Lord of lords, a great God, a mighty, and a terrible, which [*]regardeth not persons, nor taketh reward: 18  He doth execute the judgment of the fatherless and widow, and loveth the stranger, in giving him food and raiment. 19  Love ye therefore the stranger: for ye were strangers in the land of Egypt. 20 [*] Thou shalt fear the LORD thy God; him shalt thou serve, and to him shalt thou [*]cleave, and swear by his name. 21 He is thy praise, and he is thy God, that hath done for thee these great and terrible things, which thine eyes have seen. 22  Thy fathers went down into Egypt [*]with threescore and ten persons; and now the LORD thy God hath made thee [*]as the stars of heaven for multitude.

11

1  Therefore thou shalt love the LORD thy God, and keep his charge, and his statutes, and his judgments, and his commandments, alway. 2  And know ye this day: for I speak not with your children which have not known, and which have not seen the chastisement of the LORD your God, his greatness, his mighty hand, and his stretched out arm, 3  And his miracles, and his acts, which he did in the midst of Egypt unto Pharaoh the king of Egypt, and unto all his land; 4  And what he did unto the army of Egypt, unto their horses, and to their chariots; how he made the water of the Red sea to overflow them as they pursued after you, and how the LORD hath destroyed them unto this day; 5  And what he did unto you in the wilderness, until ye came into this place; 6  And [*]what he did unto Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, the son of Reuben: how the earth opened her mouth, and swallowed them up, and their households, and their tents, and all the [∥]substance that [†]was in their possession, in the midst of all Israel: 7  But your eyes have seen all the great acts of the LORD which he did.

8  Therefore shall ye keep all the commandments which I command you this day, that ye may be strong, and go in and possess the land, whither ye go to possess it; 9  And that ye may prolong your days in the land, which the LORD sware unto your fathers to give unto them and to their seed, a land that floweth with milk and honey.

10 ¶ For the land, whither thou goest in to possess it, is not as the land of Egypt, from whence ye came out, where thou sowedst thy seed, and wateredst it with thy foot, as a garden of herbs: 11  But the land, whither ye go to possess it, is a land of hills and valleys, and drinketh water of the rain of heaven: 12  A land which the LORD thy God [†]careth for: the eyes of the LORD thy God are always upon it, from the beginning of the year even unto the end of the year.

13 ¶ And it shall come to pass, if ye shall hearken diligently unto my commandments which I command you this day, to love the LORD your God, and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul, 14  That I will give you the rain of your land in his due season, the first rain and the latter rain, that thou mayest gather in thy corn, and thy wine, and thine oil. 15  And I will [†]send grass in thy fields for thy cattle, that thou mayest eat and be full. 16  Take heed to yourselves, that your heart be not deceived, and ye turn aside, and serve other gods, and worship them; 17 And then the LORD’s wrath be kindled against you, and he shut up the heaven, that there be no rain, and that the land yield not her fruit; and lest ye perish quickly from off the good land which the LORD giveth you.

18 ¶ Therefore shall ye lay up these my words in your heart and in your soul, and [*]bind them for a sign upon your hand, that they may be as frontlets between your eyes. 19 [*] And ye shall teach them your children, speaking of them when thou sittest in thine house, and when thou walkest by the way, when thou liest down, and when thou risest up. 20  And thou shalt write them upon the door posts of thine house, and upon thy gates: 21  That your days may be multiplied, and the days of your children, in the land which the LORD sware unto your fathers to give them, as the days of heaven upon the earth.

22 ¶ For if ye shall diligently keep all these commandments which I command you, to do them, to love the LORD your God, to walk in all his ways, and to cleave unto him; 23  Then will the LORD drive out all these nations from before you, and ye shall possess greater nations and mightier than yourselves. 24 [*] Every place whereon the soles of your feet shall tread shall be yours: from the wilderness and Lebanon, from the river, the river Euphrates, even unto the uttermost sea shall your coast be. 25  There shall no man be able to stand before you: for the LORD your God shall lay the fear of you and the dread of you upon all the land that ye shall tread upon, as he hath said unto you.

26 ¶ Behold, I set before you this day a blessing and a curse; 27 [*] A blessing, if ye obey the commandments of the LORD your God, which I command you this day: 28  And a [*]curse, if ye will not obey the commandments of the LORD your God, but turn aside out of the way which I command you this day, to go after other gods, which ye have not known. 29  And it shall come to pass, when the LORD thy God hath brought thee in unto the land whither thou goest to possess it, that thou shalt put [*]the blessing upon mount Gerizim, and the curse upon mount Ebal. 30  Are they not on the other side Jordan, by the way where the sun goeth down, in the land of the Canaanites, which dwell in the champaign over against Gilgal, beside the plains of Moreh? 31  For ye shall pass over Jordan to go in to possess the land which the LORD your God giveth you, and ye shall possess it, and dwell therein. 32  And ye shall observe [*]to do all the statutes and judgments which I set before you this day.

12

1 These are the statutes and judgments, which ye shall observe to do in the land, which the LORD God of thy fathers giveth thee to possess it, all the days that ye live upon the earth. 2 [*] Ye shall utterly destroy all the places, wherein the nations which ye shall [∥]possess served their gods, upon the high mountains, and upon the hills, and under every green tree: 3  And [*]ye shall [†]overthrow their altars, and break their pillars, and burn their groves with fire; and ye shall hew down the graven images of their gods, and destroy the names of them out of that place. 4  Ye shall not do so unto the LORD your God.

5  But unto the place which the LORD your God shall [*]choose out of all your tribes to put his name there, even unto his habitation shall ye seek, and thither thou shalt come: 6  And thither ye shall bring your burnt offerings, and your sacrifices, and your tithes, and heave offerings of your hand, and your vows, and your freewill offerings, and the firstlings of your herds and of your flocks: 7  And there ye shall eat before the LORD your God, and ye shall rejoice in all that ye put your hand unto, ye and your households, wherein the LORD thy God hath blessed thee. 8  Ye shall not do after all the things that we do here this day, every man whatsoever is right in his own eyes. 9  For ye are not as yet come to the rest and to the inheritance, which the LORD your God giveth you. 10 But when ye go over Jordan, and dwell in the land which the LORD your God giveth you to inherit, and when he giveth you rest from all your enemies round about, so that ye dwell in safety; 11  Then there shall be a place which the LORD your God shall choose to cause his name to dwell there; thither shall ye bring all that I command you; your burnt offerings, and your sacrifices, your tithes, and the heave offering of your hand, and all [†]your choice vows which ye vow unto the LORD: 12  And ye shall rejoice before the LORD your God, ye, and your sons, and your daughters, and your menservants, and your maidservants, and the Levite that is within your gates; forasmuch as [*]he hath no part nor inheritance with you. 13  Take heed to thyself that thou offer not thy burnt offerings in every place that thou seest: 14  But in the place which the LORD shall choose in one of thy tribes, there thou shalt offer thy burnt offerings, and there thou shalt do all that I command thee. 15  Notwithstanding thou mayest kill and eat flesh in all thy gates, whatsoever thy soul lusteth after, according to the blessing of the LORD thy God which he hath given thee: the unclean and the clean may eat thereof, as of the roebuck, and as of the hart. 16 [*] Only ye shall not eat the blood; ye shall pour it upon the earth as water.

17 ¶ Thou mayest not eat within thy gates the tithe of thy corn, or of thy wine, or of thy oil, or the firstlings of thy herds or of thy flock, nor any of thy vows which thou vowest, nor thy freewill offerings, or heave offering of thine hand: 18  But thou must eat them before the LORD thy God in the place which the LORD thy God shall choose, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy manservant, and thy maidservant, and the Levite that is within thy gates: and thou shalt rejoice before the LORD thy God in all that thou puttest thine hands unto. 19 [*] Take heed to thyself that thou forsake not the Levite [†]as long as thou livest upon the earth.

20 ¶ When the LORD thy God shall enlarge thy border, [*]as he hath promised thee, and thou shalt say, I will eat flesh, because thy soul longeth to eat flesh; thou mayest eat flesh, whatsoever thy soul lusteth after. 21  If the place which the LORD thy God hath chosen to put his name there be too far from thee, then thou shalt kill of thy herd and of thy flock, which the LORD hath given thee, as I have commanded thee, and thou shalt eat in thy gates whatsoever thy soul lusteth after. 22  Even as the roebuck and the hart is eaten, so thou shalt eat them: the unclean and the clean shall eat of them alike. 23  Only [†]be sure that thou eat not the blood: for the blood is the life; and thou mayest not eat the life with the flesh. 24  Thou shalt not eat it; thou shalt pour it upon the earth as water. 25  Thou shalt not eat it; that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee, when thou shalt do that which is right in the sight of the LORD. 26  Only thy holy things which thou hast, and thy vows, thou shalt take, and go unto the place which the LORD shall choose: 27  And thou shalt offer thy burnt offerings, the flesh and the blood, upon the altar of the LORD thy God: and the blood of thy sacrifices shall be poured out upon the altar of the LORD thy God, and thou shalt eat the flesh. 28  Observe and hear all these words which I command thee, that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee for ever, when thou doest that which is good and right in the sight of the LORD thy God.

29 ¶ When the LORD thy God shall cut off the nations from before thee, whither thou goest to possess them, and thou [†]succeedest them, and dwellest in their land; 30  Take heed to thyself that thou be not snared [†]by following them, after that they be destroyed from before thee; and that thou enquire not after their gods, saying, How did these nations serve their gods? even so will I do likewise. 31  Thou shalt not do so unto the LORD thy God: for every [†]abomination to the LORD, which he hateth, have they done unto their gods; for even their sons and their daughters they have burnt in the fire to their gods. 32  What thing soever I command you, observe to do it: [*]thou shalt not add thereto, nor diminish from it.

13

1  If there arise among you a prophet, or a dreamer of dreams, and giveth thee a sign or a wonder, 2  And the sign or the wonder come to pass, whereof he spake unto thee, saying, Let us go after other gods, which thou hast not known, and let us serve them; 3  Thou shalt not hearken unto the words of that prophet, or that dreamer of dreams: for the LORD your God proveth you, to know whether ye love the LORD your God with all your heart and with all your soul. 4  Ye shall walk after the LORD your God, and fear him, and keep his commandments, and obey his voice, and ye shall serve him, and [*]cleave unto him. 5  And that prophet, or that dreamer of dreams, shall be put to death; because he hath [†]spoken to turn you away from the LORD your God, which brought you out of the land of Egypt, and redeemed you out of the house of bondage, to thrust thee out of the way which the LORD thy God commanded thee to walk in. So shalt thou put the evil away from the midst of thee.

6 ¶ If thy brother, the son of thy mother, or thy son, or thy daughter, or the wife of thy bosom, or thy friend, which is as thine own soul, entice thee secretly, saying, Let us go and serve other gods, which thou hast not known, thou, nor thy fathers; 7  Namely, of the gods of the people which are round about you, nigh unto thee, or far off from thee, from the one end of the earth even unto the other end of the earth; 8  Thou shalt not consent unto him, nor hearken unto him; neither shall thine eye pity him, neither shalt thou spare, neither shalt thou conceal him: 9  But [*]thou shalt surely kill him; thine hand shall be first upon him to put him to death, and afterwards the hand of all the people. 10  And thou shalt stone him with stones, that he die; because he hath sought to thrust thee away from the LORD thy God, which brought thee out of the land of Egypt, from the house of [†]bondage. 11  And [*]all Israel shall hear, and fear, and shall do no more any such wickedness as this is among you.

12 ¶ If thou shalt hear say in one of thy cities, which the LORD thy God hath given thee to dwell there, saying, 13  Certain men, [∥]the children of Belial, are gone out from among you, and have withdrawn the inhabitants of their city, saying, Let us go and serve other gods, which ye have not known; 14  Then shalt thou enquire, and make search, and ask diligently; and, behold, if it be truth, and the thing certain, that such abomination is wrought among you; 15  Thou shalt surely smite the inhabitants of that city with the edge of the sword, destroying it utterly, and all that is therein, and the cattle thereof, with the edge of the sword. 16  And thou shalt gather all the spoil of it into the midst of the street thereof, and shalt burn with fire the city, and all the spoil thereof every whit, for the LORD thy God: and it shall be an heap for ever; it shall not be built again. 17  And there shall cleave nought of the [∥]cursed thing to thine hand: that the LORD may turn from the fierceness of his anger, and shew thee mercy, and have compassion upon thee, and multiply thee, as he hath sworn unto thy fathers; 18  When thou shalt hearken to the voice of the LORD thy God, to keep all his commandments which I command thee this day, to do that which is right in the eyes of the LORD thy God.

14

1 Ye are the children of the LORD your God: [*]ye shall not cut yourselves, nor make any baldness between your eyes for the dead. 2 [*]For thou art an holy people unto the LORD thy God, and the LORD hath chosen thee to be a peculiar people unto himself, above all the nations that are upon the earth.

3 ¶ Thou shalt not eat any abominable thing. 4 [*]These are the beasts which ye shall eat: the ox, the sheep, and the goat, 5  The hart, and the roebuck, and the fallow deer, and the wild goat, and the [∥][†]pygarg, and the wild ox, and the chamois. 6  And every beast that parteth the hoof, and cleaveth the cleft into two claws, and cheweth the cud among the beasts, that ye shall eat. 7  Nevertheless these ye shall not eat of them that chew the cud, or of them that divide the cloven hoof; as the camel, and the hare, and the coney: for they chew the cud, but divide not the hoof; therefore they are unclean unto you. 8  And the swine, because it divideth the hoof, yet cheweth not the cud, it is unclean unto you: ye shall not eat of their flesh, nor touch their dead carcase.

9 ¶ [*]These ye shall eat of all that are in the waters: all that have fins and scales shall ye eat: 10  And whatsoever hath not fins and scales ye may not eat; it is unclean unto you.

11 ¶ Of all clean birds ye shall eat. 12 But these are they of which ye shall not eat: the eagle, and the ossifrage, and the ospray, 13  And the glede, and the kite, and the vulture after his kind, 14  And every raven after his kind, 15  And the owl, and the night hawk, and the cuckow, and the hawk after his kind, 16  The little owl, and the great owl, and the swan, 17  And the pelican, and the gier eagle, and the cormorant, 18  And the stork, and the heron after her kind, and the lapwing, and the [*]bat. 19  And every creeping thing that flieth is unclean unto you: they shall not be eaten. 20  But of all clean fowls ye may eat.

21 ¶ Ye shall not eat of any thing that dieth of itself: thou shalt give it unto the stranger that is in thy gates, that he may eat it; or thou mayest sell it unto an alien: for thou art an holy people unto the LORD thy God. [*]Thou shalt not seethe a kid in his mother’s milk.

22  Thou shalt truly tithe all the increase of thy seed, that the field bringeth forth year by year. 23  And thou shalt eat before the LORD thy God, in the place which he shall choose to place his name there, the tithe of thy corn, of thy wine, and of thine oil, and the firstlings of thy herds and of thy flocks; that thou mayest learn to fear the LORD thy God always. 24  And if the way be too long for thee, so that thou art not able to carry it; or if the place be too far from thee, which the LORD thy God shall choose to set his name there, when the LORD thy God hath blessed thee: 25  Then shalt thou turn it into money, and bind up the money in thine hand, and shalt go unto the place which the LORD thy God shall choose: 26  And thou shalt bestow that money for whatsoever thy soul lusteth after, for oxen, or for sheep, or for wine, or for strong drink, or for whatsoever thy soul [†]desireth: and thou shalt eat there before the LORD thy God, and thou shalt rejoice, thou, and thine household, 27  And [*]the Levite that is within thy gates; thou shalt not forsake him; for he hath no part nor inheritance with thee.

28 ¶ At the end of three years thou shalt bring forth all the tithe of thine increase the same year, and shalt lay it up within thy gates: 29  And the Levite, (because he hath no part nor inheritance with thee,) and the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, which are within thy gates, shall come, and shall eat and be satisfied; that the LORD thy God may bless thee in all the work of thine hand which thou doest.

15

1  At the end of [*]every seven years thou shalt make a release. 2 And this is the manner of the release: Every [†]creditor that lendeth ought unto his neighbour shall release it; he shall not exact it of his neighbour, or of his brother; because it is called the LORD’s release. 3  Of a foreigner thou mayest exact it again: but that which is thine with thy brother thine hand shall release; 4 [∥] Save when there shall be no poor among you; for the LORD shall greatly bless thee in the land which the LORD thy God giveth thee for an inheritance to possess it: 5  Only if thou carefully hearken unto the voice of the LORD thy God, to observe to do all these commandments which I command thee this day. 6  For the LORD thy God blesseth thee, as he promised thee: and [*]thou shalt lend unto many nations, but thou shalt not borrow; and thou shalt reign over many nations, but they shall not reign over thee.

7 ¶ If there be among you a poor man of one of thy brethren within any of thy gates in thy land which the LORD thy God giveth thee, thou shalt not harden thine heart, nor shut thine hand from thy poor brother: 8 [*] But thou shalt open thine hand wide unto him, and shalt surely lend him sufficient for his need, in that which he wanteth. 9  Beware that there be not a [†]thought in thy [†]wicked heart, saying, The seventh year, the year of release, is at hand; and thine eye be evil against thy poor brother, and thou givest him nought; and he cry unto the LORD against thee, and it be sin unto thee. 10  Thou shalt surely give him, and thine heart shall not be grieved when thou givest unto him: because that for this thing the LORD thy God shall bless thee in all thy works, and in all that thou puttest thine hand unto. 11  For the poor shall never cease out of the land: therefore I command thee, saying, Thou shalt open thine hand wide unto thy brother, to thy poor, and to thy needy, in [‡]thy land.

12 ¶ And [*]if thy brother, an Hebrew man, or an Hebrew woman, be sold unto thee, and serve thee six years; then in the seventh year thou shalt let him go free from thee. 13  And when thou sendest him out free from thee, thou shalt not let him go away empty: 14  Thou shalt furnish him liberally out of thy flock, and out of thy floor, and out of thy winepress: of that wherewith the LORD thy God hath blessed thee thou shalt give unto him. 15  And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in the land of Egypt, and the LORD thy God redeemed thee: therefore I command thee this thing to day. 16  And it shall be, if he say unto thee, I will not go away from thee; because he loveth thee and thine house, because he is well with thee; 17 [*] Then thou shalt take an aul, and thrust it through his ear unto the door, and he shall be thy servant for ever. And also unto thy maidservant thou shalt do likewise. 18  It shall not seem hard unto thee, when thou sendest him away free from thee; for he hath been worth a double hired servant to thee, in serving thee six years: and the LORD thy God shall bless thee in all that thou doest.

19 ¶ [*]All the firstling males that come of thy herd and of thy flock thou shalt sanctify unto the LORD thy God: thou shalt do no work with the firstling of thy bullock, nor shear the firstling of thy sheep. 20  Thou shalt eat it before the LORD thy God year by year in the place which the LORD shall choose, thou and thy household. 21 [*]And if there be any blemish therein, as if it be lame, or blind, or have any ill blemish, thou shalt not sacrifice it unto the LORD thy God. 22  Thou shalt eat it within thy gates: the unclean and the clean person shall eat it alike, as the roebuck, and as the hart. 23 [*] Only thou shalt not eat the blood thereof; thou shalt pour it upon the ground as water.

16

1  Observe the [*]month of Abib, and keep the passover unto the LORD thy God: for [*]in the month of Abib the LORD thy God brought thee forth out of Egypt by night. 2  Thou shalt therefore sacrifice the passover unto the LORD thy God, of the flock and the herd, in the [*]place which the LORD shall choose to place his name there. 3 [*] Thou shalt eat no leavened bread with it; seven days shalt thou eat unleavened bread therewith, even the bread of affliction; for thou camest forth out of the land of Egypt in haste: that thou mayest remember the day when thou camest forth out of the land of Egypt all the days of thy life. 4 [*] And there shall be no leavened bread seen with thee in all thy [‡]coast seven days; neither shall there any thing of the flesh, which thou sacrificedst the first day at even, remain all night until the morning. 5  Thou mayest not [∥]sacrifice the passover within any of [‡]thy gates, which the LORD thy God giveth thee: 6  But at the place which the LORD thy God shall choose to place his name in, there thou shalt sacrifice the passover at even, at the going down of the sun, at the season that thou camest forth out of Egypt. 7  And thou shalt roast and eat it in the place which the LORD thy God shall choose: and thou shalt turn in the morning, and go unto thy tents. 8  Six days thou shalt eat unleavened bread: and on the seventh day shall be a [†]solemn assembly to the LORD thy God: thou shalt do no work therein.

9 ¶ [*]Seven weeks shalt thou number unto thee: begin to number the seven weeks from such time as thou beginnest to put the sickle to the corn. 10  And thou shalt keep the feast of weeks unto the LORD thy God with [∥]a tribute of a freewill offering of thine hand, which thou shalt give unto the Lord thy God, according as the LORD thy God hath blessed thee: 11  And thou shalt rejoice before the LORD thy God, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy manservant, and thy maidservant, and the Levite that is within thy gates, and the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, that are among you, in the place which the LORD thy God hath chosen to place his name there. 12  And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in Egypt: and thou shalt observe and do these statutes.

13 ¶ Thou shalt observe the feast of tabernacles seven days, after that thou hast gathered in thy [†]corn and thy wine: 14  And thou shalt rejoice in thy feast, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy manservant, and thy maidservant, and the Levite, the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, that are within thy gates. 15  Seven days shalt thou keep a solemn feast unto the LORD thy God in the place which the LORD shall choose: because the LORD thy God shall bless thee in all thine increase, and in all the works of thine hands, therefore thou shalt surely rejoice.

16 ¶ [*]Three times in a year shall all thy males appear before the LORD thy God in the place which he shall choose; in the feast of unleavened bread, and in the feast of weeks, and in the feast of tabernacles: and [*]they shall not appear before the LORD empty: 17  Every man shall give [†]as he is able, according to the blessing of the LORD thy God which he hath given thee.

18 ¶ Judges and officers shalt thou make thee in all thy gates, which the LORD thy God giveth thee, throughout thy tribes: and they shall judge the people with just judgment. 19  Thou shalt not wrest judgment; thou shalt not respect persons, [*]neither take a gift: for a gift doth blind the eyes of the wise, and pervert the [∥]words of the righteous. 20 [†] That which is altogether just shalt thou follow, that thou mayest live, and inherit the land which the LORD thy God giveth thee.

21 ¶ Thou shalt not plant thee a grove of any trees near unto the altar of the LORD thy God, which thou shalt make thee. 22 [*] Neither shalt thou set thee up any [∥]image; which the LORD thy God hateth.

17

1  Thou shalt not sacrifice unto the LORD thy God any bullock, or [∥]sheep, wherein is blemish, or any evilfavouredness: for that is an abomination unto the LORD thy God.

2 ¶ If there be found among you, within any of thy gates which the LORD thy God giveth thee, man or woman, that hath wrought wickedness in the sight of the LORD thy God, in transgressing his covenant, 3  And hath gone and served other gods, and worshipped them, either the sun, or moon, or any of the host of heaven, which I have not commanded; 4  And it be told thee, and thou hast heard of it, and enquired diligently, and, behold, it be true, and the thing certain, that such abomination is wrought in Israel: 5  Then shalt thou bring forth that man or that woman, which have committed that wicked thing, unto thy gates, even that man or that woman, and shalt stone them with stones, till they die. 6 [*] At the mouth of two witnesses, or three witnesses, shall he that is worthy of death be put to death; but at the mouth of one witness he shall not be put to death. 7  The hands of the witnesses shall be first upon him to put him to death, and afterward the hands of all the people. So thou shalt put the evil away from among you.

8 ¶ If there arise a matter too hard for thee in judgment, between blood and blood, between plea and plea, and between stroke and stroke, being matters of controversy within thy gates: then shalt thou arise, and get thee up into the place which the LORD thy God shall choose; 9  And thou shalt come unto the priests the Levites, and unto the judge that shall be in those days, and enquire; and they shall shew thee the sentence of judgment: 10  And thou shalt do according to the sentence, which they of that place which the LORD shall choose shall shew thee; and thou shalt observe to do according to all that they inform thee: 11  According to the sentence of the law which they shall teach thee, and according to the judgment which they shall tell thee, thou shalt do: thou shalt not decline from the sentence which they shall shew thee, to the right hand, nor to the left. 12  And the man that will do presumptuously, [†]and will not hearken unto the priest that standeth to minister there before the LORD thy God, or unto the judge, even that man shall die: and thou shalt put away the evil from Israel. 13  And all the people shall hear, and fear, and do no more presumptuously.

14 ¶ When thou art come unto the land which the LORD thy God giveth thee, and shalt possess it, and shalt dwell therein, and shalt say, I will set a king over me, like as all the nations that are about me; 15  Thou shalt in any wise set him king over thee, whom the LORD thy God shall choose: one from among thy brethren shalt thou set king over thee: thou mayest not set a stranger over thee, which is not thy brother. 16  But he shall not multiply horses to himself, nor cause the people to return to Egypt, to the end that he should multiply horses: forasmuch as the LORD hath said unto you, Ye shall henceforth return no more that way. 17  Neither shall he multiply wives to himself, that his heart turn not away: neither shall he greatly multiply to himself silver and gold. 18  And it shall be, when he sitteth upon the throne of his kingdom, that he shall write him a copy of this law in a book out of that which is before the priests the Levites: 19  And it shall be with him, and he shall read therein all the days of his life: that he may learn to fear the LORD his God, to keep all the words of this law and these statutes, to do them: 20  That his heart be not lifted up above his brethren, and that he turn not aside from the commandment, to the right hand, or to the left: to the end that he may prolong his days in his kingdom, he, and his children, in the midst of Israel.

18

1  The priests the Levites, and all the tribe of Levi, [*]shall have no part nor inheritance with Israel: they [*]shall eat the offerings of the LORD made by fire, and his inheritance. 2  Therefore shall they have no inheritance among their brethren: the LORD is their inheritance, as he hath said unto them.

3 ¶ And this shall be the priest’s due from the people, from them that offer a sacrifice, whether it be ox or sheep; and they shall give unto the priest the shoulder, and the two cheeks, and the maw. 4  The firstfruit also of thy corn, of thy wine, and of thine oil, and the first of the fleece of thy sheep, shalt thou give him. 5  For the LORD thy God hath chosen him out of all thy tribes, to stand to minister in the name of the LORD, him and his sons for ever.

6 ¶ And if a Levite come from any of thy gates out of all Israel, where he sojourned, and come with all the desire of his mind unto the place which the LORD shall choose; 7  Then he shall minister in the name of the LORD his God, as all his brethren the Levites do, which stand there before the LORD. 8  They shall have like portions to eat, beside [†]that which cometh of the sale of his patrimony.

9 ¶ When thou art come into the land which the LORD thy God giveth thee, thou shalt not learn to do after the abominations of those nations. 10  There shall not be found among you any one that maketh his son or his daughter [*]to pass through the fire, or that useth divination, or an observer of times, or an enchanter, or a witch, 11 [*] Or a charmer, or a consulter with familiar spirits, or a wizard, or a [*]necromancer. 12  For all that do these things are an abomination unto the LORD: and because of these abominations the LORD thy God doth drive them out from before thee. 13  Thou shalt be [∥]perfect with the LORD thy God. 14  For these nations, which thou shalt [∥]possess, hearkened unto observers of times, and unto diviners: but as for thee, the LORD thy God hath not suffered thee so to do.

15 ¶ [*]The LORD thy God will raise up unto thee a Prophet from the midst of thee, of thy brethren, like unto me; unto him ye shall hearken; 16  According to all that thou desiredst of the LORD thy God in Horeb in the day of the assembly, saying, [*]Let me not hear again the voice of the LORD my God, neither let me see this great fire any more, that I die not. 17  And the LORD said unto me, They have well spoken that which they have spoken. 18 [*] I will raise them up a Prophet from among their brethren, like unto thee, and will put my words in his mouth; and he shall speak unto them all that I shall command him. 19 And it shall come to pass, that whosoever will not hearken unto my words which he shall speak in my name, I will require it of him. 20  But the prophet, which shall presume to speak a word in my name, which I have not commanded him to speak, or that shall speak in the name of other gods, even that prophet shall die. 21  And if thou say in thine heart, How shall we know the word which the LORD hath not spoken? 22  When a prophet speaketh in the name of the LORD, if the thing follow not, nor come to pass, that is the thing which the LORD hath not spoken, but the prophet hath spoken it presumptuously: thou shalt not be afraid of him.

19

1  When the LORD thy God [*]hath cut off the nations, whose land the LORD thy God giveth thee, and thou [†]succeedest them, and dwellest in their cities, and in their houses; 2 [*] Thou shalt separate three cities for thee in the midst of thy land, which the LORD thy God giveth thee to possess it. 3  Thou shalt prepare thee a way, and divide the coasts of thy land, which the LORD thy God giveth thee to inherit, into three parts, that every slayer may flee thither.

4 ¶ And this is the case of the slayer, which shall flee thither, that he may live: Whoso killeth his neighbour ignorantly, whom he hated not [†]in time past; 5  As when a man goeth into the wood with his neighbour to hew wood, and his hand fetcheth a stroke with the axe to cut down the tree, and the [†]head slippeth from the [†]helve, and [†]lighteth upon his neighbour, that he die; he shall flee unto one of those cities, and live: 6  Lest the avenger of the blood pursue the slayer, while his heart is hot, and overtake him, because the way is long, and [†]slay him; whereas he was not worthy of death, inasmuch as he hated him not [†]in time past. 7  Wherefore I command thee, saying, Thou shalt separate three cities for thee. 8  And if the LORD thy God [*]enlarge thy coast, as he hath sworn unto thy fathers, and give thee all the land which he promised to give unto thy fathers; 9  If thou shalt keep all these commandments to do them, which I command thee this day, to love the LORD thy God, and to walk ever in his ways; [*]then shalt thou add three cities more for thee, beside these three: 10  That innocent blood be not shed in thy land, which the LORD thy God giveth thee for an inheritance, and so blood be upon thee.

11 ¶ But if any man hate his neighbour, and lie in wait for him, and rise up against him, and smite him [†]mortally that he die, and fleeth into one of these cities: 12  Then the elders of his city shall send and fetch him thence, and deliver him into the hand of the avenger of blood, that he may die. 13  Thine eye shall not pity him, but thou shalt put away the guilt of innocent blood from Israel, that it may go well with thee.

14 ¶ Thou shalt not remove thy neighbour’s landmark, which they of old time have set in thine inheritance, which thou shalt inherit in the land that the LORD thy God giveth thee to possess it.

15 ¶ [*]One witness shall not rise up against a man for any iniquity, or for any sin, in any sin that he sinneth: at the mouth of two witnesses, or at the mouth of three witnesses, shall the matter be established.

16 ¶ If a false witness rise up against any man to testify against him [∥]that which is wrong; 17  Then both the men, between whom the controversy is, shall stand before the LORD, before the priests and the judges, which shall be in those days; 18  And the judges shall make diligent inquisition: and, behold, if the witness be a false witness, and hath testified falsely against his brother; 19 [*] Then shall ye do unto him, as he had thought to have done unto his brother: so shalt thou put the evil away from among you. 20  And those which remain shall hear, and fear, and shall henceforth commit no more any such evil among you. 21  And thine eye shall not pity; but [*]life shall go for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot.

20

1  When thou goest out to battle against thine enemies, and seest horses, and chariots, and a people more than thou, be not afraid of them: for the LORD thy God is with thee, which brought thee up out of the land of Egypt. 2  And it shall be, when ye are come nigh unto the battle, that the priest shall approach and speak unto the people, 3  And shall say unto them, Hear, O Israel, ye approach this day unto battle against your enemies: let not your hearts [†]faint, fear not, and do not [†]tremble, neither be ye terrified because of them; 4  For the LORD your God is he that goeth with you, to fight for you against your enemies, to save you.

5 ¶ And the officers shall speak unto the people, saying, What man is there that hath built a new house, and hath not dedicated it? let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man dedicate it. 6  And what man is he that hath planted a vineyard, and hath not yet [†]eaten of it? let him also go and return unto his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man eat of it. 7 [*] And what man is there that hath betrothed a wife, and hath not taken her? let him go and return unto his house, lest he die in [‡]the battle, and another man take her. 8  And the officers shall speak further unto the people, and they shall say, [*]What man is there that is fearful and fainthearted? let him go and return unto his house, lest his brethren’s heart [†]faint as well as his heart. 9  And it shall be, when the officers have made an end of speaking unto the people, that they shall make captains of the armies [†]to lead the people.

10 ¶ When thou comest nigh unto a city to fight against it, then proclaim peace unto it. 11  And it shall be, if it make thee answer of peace, and open unto thee, then it shall be, that all the people that is found therein shall be tributaries unto thee, and they shall serve thee. 12  And if it will make no peace with thee, but will make war against thee, then thou shalt besiege it: 13  And when the LORD thy God hath delivered it into thine hands, thou shalt smite every male thereof with the edge of the sword: 14  But the women, and the little ones, and [*]the cattle, and all that is in the city, even all the spoil thereof, shalt thou [†]take unto thyself; and thou shalt eat the spoil of thine enemies, which the LORD thy God hath given thee. 15  Thus shalt thou do unto all the cities which are very far off from thee, which are not of the cities of these nations. 16  But of the cities of these people, which the LORD thy God doth give thee for an inheritance, thou shalt save alive nothing that breatheth: 17  But thou shalt utterly destroy them; namely, the Hittites, and the Amorites, the Canaanites, and the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites; as the LORD thy God hath commanded thee: 18  That they teach you not to do after all their abominations, which they have done unto their gods; so should ye sin against the LORD your God.

19 ¶ When thou shalt besiege a city a long time, in making war against it to take it, thou shalt not destroy the trees thereof by forcing an axe against them: for thou mayest eat of them, and thou shalt not cut them down ([∥]for the tree of the field is man’s life) [†]to employ them in the siege: 20  Only the trees which thou knowest that they be not trees for meat, thou shalt destroy and cut them down; and thou shalt build bulwarks against the city that maketh war with thee, until [†]it be subdued.

21

1 If one be found slain in the land which the LORD thy God giveth thee to possess it, lying in the field, and it be not known who hath slain him: 2  Then thy elders and thy judges shall come forth, and they shall measure unto the cities which are round about him that is slain: 3 And it shall be, that the city which is next unto the slain man, even the elders of that city shall take an heifer, which hath not been wrought with, and which hath not drawn in the yoke; 4  And the elders of that city shall bring down the heifer unto a rough valley, which is neither eared nor sown, and shall strike off the heifer’s neck there in the valley: 5  And the priests the sons of Levi shall come near; for them the LORD thy God hath chosen to minister unto him, and to bless in the name of the LORD; and by their [†]word shall every controversy and every stroke be tried: 6  And all the elders of that city, that are next unto the slain man, shall wash their hands over the heifer that is beheaded in the valley: 7  And they shall answer and say, Our hands have not shed this blood, neither have our eyes seen it. 8  Be merciful, O LORD, unto thy people Israel, whom thou hast redeemed, and lay not innocent blood [†]unto thy people of Israel’s charge. And the blood shall be forgiven them. 9  So shalt thou put away the guilt of innocent blood from among you, when thou shalt do that which is right in the sight of the LORD.

10 ¶ When thou goest forth to war against thine enemies, and the LORD thy God hath delivered them into thine hands, and thou hast taken them captive, 11  And seest among the captives a beautiful woman, and hast a desire unto her, that thou wouldest have her to thy wife; 12  Then thou shalt bring her home to thine house; and she shall shave her head, and [∥][†]pare her nails; 13  And she shall put the raiment of her captivity from off her, and shall remain in thine house, and bewail her father and her mother a full month: and after that thou shalt go in unto her, and be her husband, and she shall be thy wife. 14  And it shall be, if thou have no delight in her, then thou shalt let her go whither she will; but thou shalt not sell her at all for money, thou shalt not make merchandise of her, because thou hast humbled her.

15 ¶ If a man have two wives, one beloved, and another hated, and they have born him children, both the beloved and the hated; and if the firstborn son be hers that was hated: 16  Then it shall be, when he maketh his sons to inherit that which he hath, that he may not make the son of the beloved firstborn before the son of the hated, which is indeed the firstborn: 17  But he shall acknowledge the son of the hated for the firstborn, by giving him a double portion of all [†]that he hath: for he is the beginning of his strength; the right of the firstborn is his.

18 ¶ If a man have a stubborn and rebellious son, which will not obey the voice of his father, or the voice of his mother, and that, when they have chastened him, will not hearken unto them: 19  Then shall his father and his mother lay hold on him, and bring him out unto the elders of his city, and unto the gate of his place; 20  And they shall say unto the elders of his city, This our son is stubborn and rebellious, he will not obey our voice; he is a glutton, and a drunkard. 21  And all the men of his city shall stone him with stones, that he die: so shalt thou put evil away from among you; and all Israel shall hear, and fear.

22 ¶ And if a man have committed a sin worthy of death, and he be to be put to death, and thou hang him on a tree: 23  His body shall not remain all night upon the tree, but thou shalt in any wise bury him that day; (for [*]he that is hanged is [†]accursed of God;) that thy land be not defiled, which the LORD thy God giveth thee for an inheritance.

22

1  Thou [*]shalt not see thy brother’s ox or his sheep go astray, and hide thyself from them: thou shalt in any case bring them again unto thy brother. 2  And if thy brother be not nigh unto thee, or if thou know him not, then thou shalt bring it unto thine own house, and it shall be with thee until thy brother seek after it, and thou shalt restore it to him again. 3  In like manner shalt thou do with his ass; and so shalt thou do with his raiment; and with all lost thing of thy brother’s, which he hath lost, and thou hast found, shalt thou do likewise: thou mayest not hide thyself.

4 ¶ Thou shalt not see thy brother’s ass or his ox fall down by the way, and hide thyself from them: thou shalt surely help him to lift them up again.

5 ¶ The woman shall not wear that which pertaineth unto a man, neither shall a man put on a woman’s garment: for all that do so are abomination unto the LORD thy God.

6 ¶ If a bird’s nest chance to be before thee in the way in any tree, or on the ground, whether they be young ones, or eggs, and the dam sitting upon the young, or upon the eggs, thou shalt not take the dam with the young: 7  But thou shalt in any wise let the dam go, and take the young to thee; that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest prolong thy days.

8 ¶ When thou buildest a new house, then thou shalt make a battlement for thy roof, that thou bring not blood upon thine house, if any man fall from thence.

9 ¶ Thou shalt not sow thy vineyard with divers seeds: lest the [†]fruit of thy seed which thou hast sown, and the fruit of thy vineyard, be defiled.

10 ¶ Thou shalt not plow with an ox and an ass together.

11 ¶ [*]Thou shalt not wear a garment of divers sorts, as of woollen and linen together.

12 ¶ Thou shalt make thee [*]fringes upon the four [†]quarters of thy vesture, wherewith thou coverest thyself.

13 ¶ If any man take a wife, and go in unto her, and hate her, 14  And give occasions of speech against her, and bring up an evil name upon her, and say, I took this woman, and when I came to her, I found her not a maid: 15  Then shall the father of the damsel, and her mother, take and bring forth the tokens of the damsel’s virginity unto the elders of the city in the gate: 16  And the damsel’s father shall say unto the elders, I gave my daughter unto this man to wife, and he hateth her; 17  And, lo, he hath given occasions of speech against her, saying, I found not thy daughter a maid; and yet these are the tokens of my daughter’s virginity. And they shall spread the cloth before the elders of the city. 18  And the elders of that city shall take that man and chastise him; 19  And they shall amerce him in an hundred shekels of silver, and give them unto the father of the damsel, because he hath brought up an evil name upon a virgin of Israel: and she shall be his wife; he may not put her away all his days. 20  But if this thing be true, and the tokens of virginity be not found for the damsel: 21  Then they shall bring out the damsel to the door of her father’s house, and the men of her city shall stone her with stones that she die: because she hath wrought folly in Israel, to play the whore in her father’s house: so shalt thou put evil away from among you.

22 ¶ [*]If a man be found lying with a woman married to an husband, then they shall both of them die, both the man that lay with the woman, and the woman: so shalt thou put away evil from Israel.

23 ¶ If a damsel that is a virgin be betrothed unto an husband, and a man find her in the city, and lie with her; 24  Then ye shall bring them both out unto the gate of that city, and ye shall stone them with stones that they die; the damsel, because she cried not, being in the city; and the man, because he hath humbled his neighbour’s wife: so thou shalt put away evil from among you.

25 ¶ But if a man find a betrothed damsel in the field, and the man [∥]force her, and lie with her: then the man only that lay with her shall die: 26  But unto the damsel thou shalt do nothing; there is in the damsel no sin worthy of death: for as when a man riseth against his neighbour, and slayeth him, even so is this matter: 27  For he found her in the field, and the betrothed damsel cried, and there was none to save her.

28 ¶ [*]If a man find a damsel that is a virgin, which is not betrothed, and lay hold on her, and lie with her, and they be found; 29  Then the man that lay with her shall give unto the damsel’s father fifty shekels of silver, and she shall be his wife; because he hath humbled her, he may not put her away all his days.

30 ¶ [*]A man shall not take his father’s wife, nor discover his father’s skirt.

23

1  He that is wounded in the stones, or hath his privy member cut off, shall not enter into the congregation of the LORD. 2  A bastard shall not enter into the congregation of the LORD; even to his tenth generation shall he not enter into the congregation of the LORD. 3 [*] An Ammonite or Moabite shall not enter into the congregation of the LORD; even to their tenth generation shall they not enter into the congregation of the LORD for ever: 4  Because they met you not with bread and with water in the way, when ye came forth out of Egypt; and [*]because they hired against thee Balaam the son of Beor of Pethor of Mesopotamia, to curse thee. 5  Nevertheless the LORD thy God would not hearken unto Balaam; but the LORD thy God turned the curse into a blessing unto thee, because the LORD thy God loved thee. 6  Thou shalt not seek their peace nor their [†]prosperity all thy days for ever.

7 ¶ Thou shalt not abhor an Edomite; for he is thy brother: thou shalt not abhor an Egyptian; because thou wast a stranger in his land. 8  The children that are begotten of them shall enter into the congregation of the LORD in their third generation.

9 ¶ When the host goeth forth against thine enemies, then keep thee from every wicked thing.

10 ¶ If there be among you any man, that is not clean by reason of uncleanness that chanceth him by night, then shall he go abroad out of the camp, he shall not come within the camp: 11  But it shall be, when evening [†]cometh on, he shall wash himself with water: and when the sun is down, he shall come into the camp again.

12 ¶ Thou shalt have a place also without the camp, whither thou shalt go forth abroad: 13  And thou shalt have a paddle upon thy weapon; and it shall be, when thou [†]wilt ease thyself abroad, thou shalt dig therewith, and shalt turn back and cover that which cometh from thee: 14  For the LORD thy God walketh in the midst of thy camp, to deliver thee, and to give up thine enemies before thee; therefore shall thy camp be holy: that he see no [†]unclean thing in thee, and turn away from thee.

15 ¶ Thou shalt not deliver unto his master the servant which is escaped from his master unto thee: 16  He shall dwell with thee, even among you, in that place which he shall choose in one of thy gates, where it [†]liketh him best: thou shalt not oppress him.

17 ¶ There shall be no [∥]whore of the daughters of Israel, nor a sodomite of the sons of Israel. 18  Thou shalt not bring the hire of a whore, or the price of a dog, into the house of the LORD thy God for any vow: for even both these are abomination unto the LORD thy God.

19 ¶ [*]Thou shalt not lend upon usury to thy brother; usury of money, usury of victuals, usury of any thing that is lent upon usury: 20  Unto a stranger thou mayest lend upon usury; but unto thy brother thou shalt not lend upon usury: that the LORD thy God may bless thee in all that thou settest thine hand to in the land whither thou goest to possess it.

21 ¶ [*]When thou shalt vow a vow unto the LORD thy God, thou shalt not slack to pay it: for the LORD thy God will surely require it of thee; and it would be sin in thee. 22  But if thou shalt forbear to vow, it shall be no sin in thee. 23  That which is gone out of thy lips thou shalt keep and perform; even a freewill offering, according as thou hast vowed unto the LORD thy God, which thou hast promised with thy mouth.

24 ¶ When thou comest into thy neighbour’s vineyard, then thou mayest eat grapes thy fill at thine own pleasure; but thou shalt not put any in thy vessel. 25  When thou comest into the standing corn of thy [‡]neighbour, [*]then thou mayest pluck the ears with thine hand; but thou shalt not move a sickle unto thy neighbour’s standing corn.

24

1  When a [*]man hath taken a wife, and married her, and it come to pass that she find no favour in his eyes, because he hath found [†]some uncleanness in her: then let him write her a bill of [†]divorcement, and give it in her hand, and send her out of his house. 2  And when she is departed out of his house, she may go and be another man’s wife. 3 And if the latter husband hate her, and write her a bill of divorcement, and giveth it in her hand, and sendeth her out of his house; or if the latter husband die, which took her to be his wife; 4  Her former husband, which sent her away, may not take her again to be his wife, after that she is defiled; for that is abomination before the LORD: and thou shalt not cause the land to sin, which the LORD thy God giveth thee for an inheritance.

5 ¶ [*]When a man hath taken a new wife, he shall not go out to war, [†]neither shall he be charged with any business: but he shall be free at home one year, and shall cheer up his wife which he hath taken.

6 ¶ No man shall take the nether or the upper millstone to pledge: for he taketh a man’s life to pledge.

7 ¶ If a man be found stealing any of his brethren of the children of Israel, and maketh merchandise of him, or selleth him; then that thief shall die; and thou shalt put evil away from among you.

8 ¶ Take heed in the [*]plague of leprosy, that thou observe diligently, and do according to all that the priests the Levites shall teach you: as I commanded them, so ye shall observe to do. 9  Remember what the LORD thy God did [*]unto Miriam by the way, after that ye were come forth out of Egypt.

10 ¶ When thou dost [†]lend thy brother any thing, thou shalt not go into his house to fetch his pledge. 11  Thou shalt stand abroad, and the man to whom thou dost lend shall bring out the pledge abroad unto thee. 12  And if the man be poor, thou shalt not sleep with his pledge: 13  In any case thou shalt deliver him the pledge again when the sun goeth down, that he may sleep in his own raiment, and bless thee: and it shall be righteousness unto thee before the LORD thy God.

14 ¶ Thou shalt not oppress an hired servant that is poor and needy, whether he be of thy brethren, or of thy strangers that are in thy land within thy gates: 15  At his day [*]thou shalt give him his hire, neither shall the sun go down upon it; for he is poor, and [†]setteth his heart upon it: lest he cry against thee unto the LORD, and it be sin unto thee. 16 [*] The fathers shall not be put to death for the children, neither shall the children be put to death for the fathers: every man shall be put to death for his own sin.

17 ¶ Thou shalt not pervert the judgment of the stranger, nor of the fatherless; nor take a widow’s raiment to pledge: 18  But thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in Egypt, and the LORD thy God redeemed thee thence: therefore I command thee to do this thing.

19 ¶ [*]When thou cuttest down thine harvest in thy field, and hast forgot a sheaf in the field, thou shalt not go again to fetch it: it shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow: that the LORD thy God may bless thee in all the work of thine hands. 20  When thou beatest thine olive tree, [†]thou shalt not go over the boughs again: it shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow. 21  When thou gatherest the grapes of thy vineyard, thou shalt not glean it [†]afterward: it shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow. 22  And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in the land of Egypt: therefore I command thee to do this thing.

25

1  If there be a controversy between men, and they come unto judgment, that the judges may judge them; then they shall justify the righteous, and condemn the wicked. 2  And it shall be, if the wicked man be worthy to be beaten, that the judge shall cause him to lie down, and to be beaten before his face, according to his fault, by a certain number. 3 [*] Forty stripes he may give him, and not exceed: lest, if he should exceed, and beat him above these with many stripes, then thy brother should seem vile unto thee.

4 ¶ [*]Thou shalt not muzzle the ox when he [†]treadeth out the corn.

5 ¶ [*]If brethren dwell together, and one of them die, and have no child, the wife of the dead shall not marry without unto a stranger: her [∥]husband’s brother shall go in unto her, and take her to him to wife, and perform the duty of an husband’s brother unto her. 6 And it shall be, that the firstborn which she beareth shall succeed in the name of his brother which is dead, that his name be not put out of Israel. 7  And if the man like not to take his [∥]brother’s wife, then let his brother’s wife go up to the gate unto the elders, and say, [*]My husband’s brother refuseth to raise up unto his brother a name in Israel, he will not perform the duty of my husband’s brother. 8  Then the elders of his city shall call him, and speak unto him: and if he stand to it, and say, I like not to take her; 9  Then shall his brother’s wife come unto him in the presence of the elders, and loose his shoe from off his foot, and spit in his face, and shall answer and say, So shall it be done unto that man that will not build up his brother’s house. 10  And his name shall be called in Israel, The house of him that hath his shoe loosed.

11 ¶ When men strive together one with another, and the wife of the one draweth near for to deliver her husband out of the hand of him that smiteth him, and putteth forth her hand, and taketh him by the secrets: 12  Then thou shalt cut off her hand, thine eye shall not pity her.

13 ¶ Thou shalt not have in thy bag [†]divers weights, a great and a small. 14  Thou shalt not have in thine house [†]divers measures, a great and a small. 15  But thou shalt have a perfect and just weight, a perfect and just measure shalt thou have: that thy days may be lengthened in the land which the LORD thy God giveth thee. 16  For all that do such things, and all that do unrighteously, are an abomination unto the LORD thy God.

17 ¶ [*]Remember what Amalek did unto thee by the way, when ye were come forth out of Egypt; 18  How he met thee by the way, and smote the hindmost of thee, even all that were feeble behind thee, when thou wast faint and weary; and he feared not God. 19  Therefore it shall be, when the LORD thy God hath given thee rest from all thine enemies round about, in the land which the LORD thy God giveth thee for an inheritance to possess it, that thou shalt blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under heaven; thou shalt not forget it.

26

1 And it shall be, when thou art come in unto the land which the LORD [‡]thy God giveth thee for an inheritance, and possessest it, and dwellest therein; 2  That thou shalt take of the first of all the fruit of the earth, which thou shalt bring of thy land that the LORD thy God giveth thee, and shalt put it in a basket, and shalt go unto the place which the LORD thy God shall choose to place his name there. 3  And thou shalt go unto the priest that shall be in those days, and say unto him, I profess this day unto the LORD thy God, that I am come unto the country which the LORD sware unto our fathers for to give us. 4  And the priest shall take the basket out of thine hand, and set it down before the altar of the LORD thy God. 5  And thou shalt speak and say before the LORD thy God, A Syrian ready to perish was my father, and he went down into Egypt, and sojourned there with a few, and became there a nation, great, mighty, and populous: 6  And the Egyptians evil entreated us, and afflicted us, and laid upon us hard bondage: 7  And when we cried unto the LORD God of our fathers, the LORD heard our voice, and looked on our affliction, and our labour, and our oppression: 8  And the LORD brought us forth out of Egypt with a mighty hand, and with an outstretched arm, and with great terribleness, and with signs, and with wonders: 9  And he hath brought us into this place, and hath given us this land, even a land that floweth with milk and honey. 10  And now, behold, I have brought the firstfruits of the land, which thou, O LORD, hast given me. And thou shalt set it before the LORD thy God, and worship before the LORD thy God: 11  And thou shalt rejoice in every good thing which the LORD thy God hath given unto thee, and unto thine house, thou, and the Levite, and the stranger that is among you.

12 ¶ When thou hast made an end of tithing all the tithes of thine increase the third year, which is [*]the year of tithing, and hast given it unto the Levite, the stranger, the fatherless, and the widow, that they may eat within thy gates, and be filled; 13  Then thou shalt say before the LORD thy God, I have brought away the hallowed things out of mine house, and also have given them unto the Levite, and unto the stranger, to the fatherless, and to the widow, according to all thy commandments which thou hast commanded me: I have not transgressed thy commandments, neither have I forgotten them: 14  I have not eaten thereof in my mourning, neither have I taken away ought thereof for any unclean use, nor given ought thereof for the dead: but I have hearkened to the voice of the LORD my God, and have done according to all that thou hast commanded me. 15 [*] Look down from thy holy habitation, from heaven, and bless thy people Israel, and the land which thou hast given us, as thou swarest unto our fathers, a land that floweth with milk and honey.

16 ¶ This day the LORD thy God hath commanded thee to do these statutes and judgments: thou shalt therefore keep and do them with all thine heart, and with all thy soul. 17  Thou hast avouched the LORD this day to be thy God, and to walk in his ways, and to keep his statutes, and his commandments, and his judgments, and to hearken unto his voice: 18  And [*]the LORD hath avouched thee this day to be his peculiar people, as he hath promised thee, and that thou shouldest keep all his commandments; 19  And to make thee high above all nations which he hath made, in praise, and in name, and in honour; and that thou mayest be an holy people unto the LORD thy God, as he hath spoken.

27

1  And Moses with the elders of Israel commanded the people, saying, Keep all the commandments which I command you this day. 2  And it shall be on the day [*]when ye shall pass over Jordan unto the land which the LORD thy God giveth thee, that thou shalt set thee up great stones, and plaister them with plaister: 3  And thou shalt write upon them all the words of this law, when thou art passed over, that thou mayest go in unto the land which the LORD thy God giveth thee, a land that floweth with milk and honey; as the LORD God of thy fathers hath promised thee. 4  Therefore it shall be when ye be gone over Jordan, that ye shall set up these stones, which I command you this day, in mount Ebal, and thou shalt plaister them with plaister. 5  And there shalt thou build an altar unto the LORD thy God, an altar of stones: [*]thou shalt not lift up any iron tool upon them. 6  Thou shalt build the altar of the LORD thy God of whole stones: and thou shalt offer burnt offerings thereon unto the LORD thy God: 7  And thou shalt offer peace offerings, and shalt eat there, and rejoice before the LORD thy God. 8  And thou shalt write upon the stones all the words of this law very plainly.

9 ¶ And Moses and the priests the Levites spake unto all Israel, saying, Take heed, and hearken, O Israel; this day thou art become the people of the LORD thy God. 10  Thou shalt therefore obey the voice of the LORD thy God, and do his commandments and his statutes, which I command thee this day.

11 ¶ And Moses charged the people the same day, saying, 12  These shall stand upon mount Gerizim to bless the people, when ye are come over Jordan; Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Joseph, and Benjamin: 13  And these shall stand upon mount Ebal [†]to curse; Reuben, Gad, and Asher, and Zebulun, Dan, and Naphtali.

14 ¶ And [*]the Levites shall speak, and say unto all the men of Israel with a loud voice, 15  Cursed be the man that maketh any graven or molten image, an abomination unto the LORD, the work of the hands of the craftsman, and putteth it in a secret place. And all the people shall answer and say, Amen. 16  Cursed be he that setteth light by his father or his mother. And all the people shall say, Amen. 17  Cursed be he that removeth his neighbour’s landmark. And all the people shall say, Amen. 18  Cursed be he that maketh the blind to wander out of the way. And all the people shall say, Amen. 19  Cursed be he that perverteth the judgment of the stranger, fatherless, and widow. And all the people shall say, Amen. 20  Cursed be he that lieth with his father’s wife; because he uncovereth his father’s skirt. And all the people shall say, Amen. 21  Cursed be he that lieth with any manner of beast. And all the people shall say, Amen. 22  Cursed be he that lieth with his sister, the daughter of his father, or the daughter of his mother. And all the people shall say, Amen. 23  Cursed be he that lieth with his mother in law. And all the people shall say, Amen. 24  Cursed be he that smiteth his neighbour secretly. And all the people shall say, Amen. 25 [*] Cursed be he that taketh reward to slay an innocent person. And all the people shall say, Amen. 26 [*] Cursed be he that confirmeth not all the words of this law to do them. And all the people shall say, Amen.

28

1  And it shall come to pass, [*]if thou shalt hearken diligently unto the voice of the LORD thy God, to observe and to do all his commandments which I command thee this day, that the LORD thy God will set thee on high above all nations of the earth: 2  And all these blessings shall come on thee, and overtake thee, if thou shalt hearken unto the voice of the LORD thy God. 3  Blessed shalt thou be in the city, and blessed shalt thou be in the field. 4  Blessed shall be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy ground, and the fruit of thy cattle, the increase of thy kine, and the flocks of thy sheep. 5  Blessed shall be thy basket and thy [∥]store. 6  Blessed shalt thou be when thou comest in, and blessed shalt thou be when thou goest out. 7  The LORD shall cause thine enemies that rise up against thee to be smitten before thy face: they shall come out against thee one way, and flee before thee seven ways. 8  The LORD shall command the blessing upon thee in thy [∥]storehouses, and in all that thou settest thine hand unto; and he shall bless thee in the land which the LORD thy God giveth thee. 9  The LORD shall establish thee an holy people unto himself, as he hath sworn unto thee, if thou shalt keep the commandments of the LORD thy God, and walk in his ways. 10  And all people of the earth shall see that thou art called by the name of the LORD; and they shall be afraid of thee. 11  And [*]the LORD shall make thee plenteous [∥]in goods, in the fruit of thy [†]body, and in the fruit of thy cattle, and in the fruit of thy ground, in the land which the LORD sware unto thy fathers to give thee. 12  The LORD shall open unto thee his good treasure, the heaven to give the rain unto thy land in his season, and to bless all the work of thine hand: and [*]thou shalt lend unto many nations, and thou shalt not borrow. 13  And the LORD shall make thee the head, and not the tail; and thou shalt be above only, and thou shalt not be beneath; if that thou hearken unto the commandments of the LORD thy God, which I command thee this day, to observe and to do them: 14  And thou shalt not go aside from any of the words which I command thee this day, to the right hand, or to the left, to go after other gods to serve them.

15 ¶ But it shall come to pass, [*]if thou wilt not hearken unto the voice of the LORD thy God, to observe to do all his commandments and his statutes which I command thee this day; that all these curses shall come upon thee, and overtake thee: 16  Cursed shalt thou be in the city, and cursed shalt thou be in the field. 17  Cursed shall be thy basket and thy store. 18  Cursed shall be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy land, the increase of thy kine, and the flocks of thy sheep. 19  Cursed shalt thou be when thou comest in, and cursed shalt thou be when thou goest out. 20  The LORD shall send upon thee cursing, vexation, and rebuke, in all that thou settest thine hand unto [†]for to do, until thou be destroyed, and until thou perish quickly; because of the wickedness of thy doings, whereby thou hast forsaken me. 21  The LORD shall make the pestilence cleave unto thee, until he have consumed thee from off the land, whither thou goest to possess it. 22 [*] The LORD shall smite thee with a consumption, and with a fever, and with an inflammation, and with an extreme burning, and with the [∥]sword, and with blasting, and with mildew; and they shall pursue thee until thou perish. 23  And [‡]thy heaven that is over thy head shall be brass, and the earth that is under thee shall be iron. 24  The LORD shall make the rain of thy land powder and dust: from heaven shall it come down upon thee, until thou be destroyed. 25  The LORD shall cause thee to be smitten before thine enemies: thou shalt go out one way against them, and flee seven ways before them: and shalt be [†]removed into all the kingdoms of the earth. 26  And thy carcase shall be meat unto all fowls of the air, and unto the beasts of the earth, and no man shall fray them away. 27  The LORD will smite thee with the botch of Egypt, and with the emerods, and with the scab, and with the itch, whereof thou canst not be healed. 28  The LORD shall smite thee with madness, and blindness, and astonishment of heart: 29  And thou shalt grope at [‡]noonday, as the blind gropeth in darkness, and thou shalt not prosper in thy ways: and thou shalt be only oppressed and spoiled evermore, and no man shall save thee. 30  Thou shalt betroth a wife, and another man shall lie with her: thou shalt build an house, and thou shalt not dwell therein: [*]thou shalt plant a vineyard, and shalt not [†]gather the grapes thereof. 31  Thine ox shall be slain before thine eyes, and thou shalt not eat thereof: thine ass shall be violently taken away from before thy face, and [†]shall not be restored to thee: thy sheep shall be given unto thine enemies, and thou shalt have none to rescue them. 32  Thy sons and thy daughters shall be given unto another people, and thine eyes shall look, and fail with longing for them all the day long: and there shall be no might in thine hand. 33  The fruit of thy land, and all thy labours, shall a nation which thou knowest not eat up; and thou shalt be only oppressed and crushed alway: 34  So that thou shalt be mad for the sight of thine eyes which thou shalt see. 35  The LORD shall smite thee in the knees, and in the legs, with a sore botch that cannot be healed, from the sole of thy foot unto the top of thy head. 36  The LORD shall bring thee, and thy king which thou shalt set over thee, unto a nation which neither thou nor thy fathers have known; and there shalt thou serve other gods, wood and stone. 37  And thou shalt become [*]an astonishment, a proverb, and a byword, among all nations whither the LORD shall lead thee. 38 [*] Thou shalt carry much seed out into the field, and shalt gather but little in; for the locust shall consume it. 39  Thou shalt plant vineyards, and dress them, but shalt neither drink of the wine, nor gather the grapes; for the worms shall eat them. 40  Thou shalt have olive trees throughout all thy coasts, but thou shalt not anoint thyself with the oil; for thine olive shall cast his fruit. 41  Thou shalt beget sons and daughters, but [†]thou shalt not enjoy them; for they shall go into captivity. 42  All thy trees and fruit of thy land shall the [‡]locust [∥]consume. 43  The stranger that is within thee shall get up above thee very high; and thou shalt come down very low. 44  He shall lend to thee, and thou shalt not lend to him: he shall be the head, and thou shalt be the tail.

45  Moreover all these curses shall come upon thee, and shall pursue thee, and overtake thee, till thou be destroyed; because thou hearkenedst not unto the voice of the LORD thy God, to keep his commandments and his statutes which he commanded thee: 46  And they shall be upon thee for a sign and for a wonder, and upon thy seed for ever. 47  Because thou servedst not the LORD thy God with joyfulness, and with gladness of heart, for the abundance of all things; 48  Therefore shalt thou serve thine enemies which the LORD shall send against thee, in hunger, and in thirst, and in nakedness, and in want of all things: and he shall put a yoke of iron upon thy neck, until he have destroyed thee. 49  The LORD shall bring a nation against thee from far, from the end of the earth, as swift as the eagle flieth; a nation whose tongue thou shalt not [†]understand; 50  A nation [†]of fierce countenance, which shall not regard the person of the old, nor shew favour to the young: 51  And he shall eat the fruit of thy cattle, and the fruit of thy land, until thou be destroyed: which also shall not leave thee either corn, wine, or oil, or the increase of thy kine, or flocks of thy sheep, until he have destroyed thee. 52  And he shall besiege thee in all thy gates, until thy high and fenced walls come down, wherein thou trustedst, throughout all thy land: and he shall besiege thee in all thy gates throughout all thy land, which the LORD thy God hath given thee. 53  And [*]thou shalt eat the fruit of thine own [†]body, the flesh of thy sons and of thy daughters, which the LORD thy God hath given thee, in the siege, and in the straitness, wherewith thine enemies shall distress thee: 54  So that the man that is tender among you, and very delicate, his eye shall be evil toward his brother, and toward the wife of his bosom, and toward the remnant of his children which he shall leave: 55  So that he will not give to any of them of the flesh of his children whom he shall eat: because he hath nothing left him in the siege, and in the straitness, wherewith thine enemies shall distress thee in all thy gates. 56  The tender and delicate woman among you, which would not adventure to set the sole of her foot upon the ground for delicateness and tenderness, her eye shall be evil toward the husband of her bosom, and toward her son, and toward her daughter, 57  And toward her [†]young one that cometh out from between her feet, and toward her children which she shall bear: for she shall eat them for want of all things secretly in the siege and straitness, wherewith thine enemy shall distress thee in thy gates. 58  If thou wilt not observe to do all the words of this law that are written in this book, that thou mayest fear this glorious and fearful name, THE LORD THY GOD; 59  Then the LORD will make thy plagues wonderful, and the plagues of thy seed, even great plagues, and of long continuance, and sore sicknesses, and of long continuance. 60  Moreover he will bring upon thee all the diseases of Egypt, which thou wast afraid of; and they shall cleave unto thee. 61  Also every sickness, and every plague, which is not written in the book of this law, them will the LORD [†]bring upon thee, until thou be destroyed. 62  And ye shall be left few in number, whereas ye were [*]as the stars of heaven for multitude; because thou wouldest not obey the voice of the LORD thy God. 63 And it shall come to pass, that as the LORD rejoiced over you to do you good, and to multiply you; so the LORD will rejoice over you to destroy you, and to bring you to nought; and ye shall be plucked from off the land whither thou goest to possess it. 64  And the LORD shall scatter thee among all people, from the one end of the earth even unto the other; and there thou shalt serve other gods, which neither thou nor thy fathers have known, even wood and stone. 65  And among these nations shalt thou find no ease, neither shall the sole of thy foot have rest: but the LORD shall give thee there a trembling heart, and failing of eyes, and sorrow of mind: 66  And thy life shall hang in doubt before thee; and thou shalt fear day and night, and shalt have none assurance of thy life: 67  In the morning thou shalt say, Would God it were even! and at even thou shalt say, Would God it were morning! for the fear of thine heart wherewith thou shalt fear, and for the sight of thine eyes which thou shalt see. 68  And the LORD shall bring thee into Egypt again with ships, by the way whereof I spake unto thee, Thou shalt see it no more again: and there ye shall be sold unto your enemies for bondmen and bondwomen, and no man shall buy you.

29

1 These are the words of the covenant, which the LORD commanded Moses to make with the children of Israel in the land of Moab, beside the covenant which he made with them in Horeb.

2 ¶ And Moses called unto all Israel, and said unto them, [*]Ye have seen all that the LORD did before your eyes in the land of Egypt unto Pharaoh, and unto all his servants, and unto all his land; 3  The great temptations which thine eyes have seen, the signs, and those great miracles: 4  Yet the LORD hath not given you an heart to perceive, and eyes to see, and ears to hear, unto this day. 5  And I have led you forty years in the wilderness: your clothes are not waxen old upon you, and thy shoe is not waxen old upon thy foot. 6  Ye have not eaten bread, neither have ye drunk wine or strong drink: that ye might know that I am the LORD your God. 7  And when ye came unto this place, Sihon the king of Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, came out against us unto battle, and we smote them: 8  And we took their land, and gave it for an inheritance unto the Reubenites, and to the Gadites, and to the half tribe of Manasseh. 9 [*] Keep therefore the words of this covenant, and do them, that ye may prosper in all that ye do.

10 ¶ Ye stand this day all of you before the LORD your God; your captains of your tribes, your elders, and your officers, with all the men of Israel, 11  Your little ones, your wives, and thy stranger that is in thy camp, from the hewer of thy wood unto the drawer of thy water: 12  That thou shouldest [†]enter into covenant with the LORD thy God, and into his oath, which the LORD thy God maketh with thee this day: 13  That he may establish thee to day for a people unto himself, and that he may be unto thee a God, as he hath said unto thee, and as he hath sworn unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob. 14  Neither with you only do I make this covenant and this oath; 15 But with him that standeth here with us this day before the LORD our God, and also with him that is not here with us this day: 16 (For ye know how we have dwelt in the land of Egypt; and how we came through the nations which ye passed by; 17  And ye have seen their abominations, and their [†]idols, wood and stone, silver and gold, which were among them:) 18  Lest there should be among you man, or woman, or family, or tribe, whose heart turneth away this day from the LORD our God, to go and serve the gods of these nations; lest there should be among you a root that beareth [∥][†]gall and wormwood; 19  And it come to pass, when he heareth the words of this curse, that he bless himself in his heart, saying, I shall have peace, though I walk in the [∥]imagination of mine heart, to add [†]drunkenness to thirst: 20  The LORD will not spare him, but then the anger of the LORD and his jealousy shall smoke against that man, and all the curses that are written in this book shall lie upon him, and the LORD shall blot out his name from under heaven. 21  And the LORD shall separate him unto evil out of all the tribes of Israel, according to all the curses of the covenant that [†]are written in this book of the law: 22  So that the generation to come of your children that shall rise up after you, and the stranger that shall come from a far land, shall say, when they see the plagues of that land, and the sicknesses [†]which the LORD hath laid upon it; 23  And that the whole land thereof is brimstone, and salt, and burning, that it is not sown, nor beareth, nor any grass groweth therein, [*]like the overthrow of Sodom, and Gomorrah, Admah, and Zeboim, which the LORD overthrew in his anger, and in his wrath: 24  Even all nations shall say, [*]Wherefore hath the LORD done thus unto this land? what meaneth the heat of this great anger? 25  Then men shall say, Because they have forsaken the covenant of the LORD God of their fathers, which he made with them when he brought them forth out of the land of Egypt: 26  For they went and served other gods, and worshipped them, gods whom they knew not, and [∥]whom he had not [†]given unto them: 27  And the anger of the LORD was kindled against this land, to bring upon it all the curses that are written in this book: 28  And the LORD rooted them out of their land in anger, and in wrath, and in great indignation, and cast them into another land, as it is this day. 29  The secret things belong unto the LORD our God: but those things which are revealed belong unto us and to our children for ever, that we may do all the words of this law.

30

1  And it shall come to pass, when all these things are come upon thee, the blessing and the curse, which I have set before thee, and thou shalt call them to mind among all the nations, whither the LORD thy God hath driven thee, 2  And shalt return unto the LORD thy God, and shalt obey his voice according to all that I command thee this day, thou and thy children, with all thine heart, and with all thy soul; 3  That then the LORD thy God will turn thy captivity, and have compassion upon thee, and will return and gather thee from all the nations, whither the LORD thy God hath scattered thee. 4 [*]If any of thine be driven out unto the outmost parts of heaven, from thence will the LORD thy God gather thee, and from thence will he fetch thee: 5  And the LORD thy God will bring thee into the land which thy fathers possessed, and thou shalt possess it; and he will do thee good, and multiply thee above thy fathers. 6  And the LORD thy God will circumcise thine heart, and the heart of thy seed, to love the LORD thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy soul, that thou mayest live. 7  And the LORD thy God will put all these curses upon thine enemies, and on them that hate thee, which persecuted thee. 8  And thou shalt return and obey the voice of the LORD, and do all his commandments which I command thee this day. 9 [*] And the LORD thy God will make thee plenteous in every work of thine hand, in the fruit of thy body, and in the fruit of thy cattle, and in the fruit of thy land, for good: for the LORD will again rejoice over thee for good, as he rejoiced over thy fathers: 10  If thou shalt hearken unto the voice of the LORD thy God, to keep his commandments and his statutes which are written in this book of the law, and if thou turn unto the LORD thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy soul.

11 ¶ For this commandment which I command thee this day, it is not hidden from thee, neither is it far off. 12 [*]It is not in heaven, that thou shouldest say, Who shall go up for us to heaven, and bring it unto us, that we may hear it, and do it? 13 Neither is it beyond the sea, that thou shouldest say, Who shall go over the sea for us, and bring it unto us, that we may hear it, and do it? 14  But the word is very nigh unto thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou mayest do it.

15 ¶ See, I have set before thee this day life and good, and death and evil; 16  In that I command thee this day to love the LORD thy God, to walk in his ways, and to keep his commandments and his statutes and his judgments, that thou mayest live and multiply: and the LORD thy God shall bless thee in the land whither thou goest to possess it. 17  But if thine heart turn away, so that thou wilt not hear, but shalt be drawn away, and worship other gods, and serve them; 18  I denounce unto you this day, that ye shall surely perish, and that ye shall not prolong your days upon the land, whither thou passest over Jordan to go to possess it. 19 [*] I call heaven and earth to record this day against you, that I have set before you life and death, blessing and cursing: therefore choose life, that both thou and thy seed may live: 20  That thou mayest love the LORD thy God, and that thou mayest obey his voice, and that thou mayest cleave unto him: for he is thy life, and the length of thy days: that thou mayest dwell in the land which the LORD sware unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give them.

31

1  And Moses went and spake these words unto all Israel. 2  And he said unto them, I am an hundred and twenty years old this day; I can no more go out and come in: also the LORD hath said unto me, [*]Thou shalt not go over this Jordan. 3  The LORD thy God, he will go over before thee, and he will destroy these nations from before thee, and thou shalt possess them: and Joshua, he shall go over before thee, [*]as the LORD hath said. 4  And the LORD shall do unto them as he did to Sihon and to Og, kings of the Amorites, and unto the land of them, whom he destroyed. 5  And [*]the LORD shall give them up before your face, that ye may do unto them according unto all the commandments which I have commanded you. 6  Be strong and of a good courage, fear not, nor be afraid of them: for the LORD thy God, he it is that doth go with thee; he will not fail thee, nor forsake thee.

7 ¶ And Moses called unto Joshua, and said unto him in the sight of all Israel, Be strong and of a good courage: for thou must go with this people unto the land which the LORD hath sworn unto their fathers to give them; and thou shalt cause them to inherit it. 8  And the LORD, he it is that doth go before thee; he will be with thee, he will not fail thee, neither forsake thee: fear not, neither be dismayed.

9 ¶ And Moses wrote this law, and delivered it unto the priests the sons of Levi, which bare the ark of the covenant of the LORD, and unto all the elders of Israel. 10  And Moses commanded them, saying, At the end of every seven years, in the solemnity of the [*]year of release, in the feast of tabernacles, 11  When all Israel is come to appear before the LORD thy God in the place which he shall choose, thou shalt read this law before all Israel in their hearing. 12  Gather the people together, men, and women, and children, and thy stranger that is within thy gates, that they may hear, and that they may learn, and fear the LORD your God, and observe to do all the words of this law: 13 And that their children, which have not known any thing, may hear, and learn to fear the LORD your God, as long as ye live in the land whither ye go over Jordan to possess it.

14 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Behold, thy days approach that thou must die: call Joshua, and present yourselves in the tabernacle of the congregation, that I may give him a charge. And Moses and Joshua went, and presented themselves in the tabernacle of the congregation. 15  And the LORD appeared in the tabernacle in a pillar of a cloud: and the pillar of the cloud stood over the door of the tabernacle.

16 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Behold, thou shalt [†]sleep with thy fathers; and this people will rise up, and go a whoring after the gods of the strangers of the land, whither they go to be among them, and will forsake me, and break my covenant which I have made with them. 17  Then my anger shall be kindled against them in that day, and I will forsake them, and I will hide my face from them, and they shall be devoured, and many evils and troubles shall [†]befall them; so that they will say in that day, Are not these evils come upon us, because our God is not among us? 18  And I will surely hide my face in that day for all the evils which they shall have wrought, in that they are turned unto other gods. 19  Now therefore write ye this song for you, and teach it the children of Israel: put it in their mouths, that this song may be a witness for me against the children of Israel. 20  For when I shall have brought them into the land which I sware unto their fathers, that floweth with milk and honey; and they shall have eaten and filled themselves, and waxen fat; then will they turn unto other gods, and serve them, and provoke me, and break my covenant. 21  And it shall come to pass, when many evils and troubles are befallen them, that this song shall testify [†]against them as a witness; for it shall not be forgotten out of the mouths of their seed: for I know their imagination which they [†]go about, even now, before I have brought them into the land which I sware.

22 ¶ Moses therefore wrote this song the same day, and taught it the children of Israel. 23  And he gave Joshua the son of Nun a charge, and said, [*]Be strong and of a good courage: for thou shalt bring the children of Israel into the land which I sware unto them: and I will be with thee.

24 ¶ And it came to pass, when Moses had made an end of writing the words of this law in a book, until they were finished, 25  That Moses commanded the Levites, which bare the ark of the covenant of the LORD, saying, 26  Take this book of the law, and put it in the side of the ark of the covenant of the LORD your God, that it may be there for a witness against thee. 27  For I know thy rebellion, and thy stiff neck: behold, while I am yet alive with you this day, ye have been rebellious against the LORD; and how much more after my death?

28 ¶ Gather unto me all the elders of your tribes, and your officers, that I may speak these words in their ears, and call heaven and earth to record against them. 29  For I know that after my death ye will utterly corrupt yourselves, and turn aside from the way which I have commanded you; and evil will befall you in the latter days; because ye will do evil in the sight of the LORD, to provoke him to anger through the work of your hands. 30  And Moses spake in the ears of all the congregation of Israel the words of this song, until they were ended.

32

1  Give ear, O ye heavens, and I will speak; and hear, O earth, the words of my mouth. 2  My doctrine shall drop as the rain, my speech shall distil as the dew, as the small rain upon the tender herb, and as the showers upon the grass: 3  Because I will publish the name of the LORD: ascribe ye greatness unto our God. 4  He is the Rock, his work is perfect: for all his ways are judgment: a God of truth and without iniquity, just and right is he. 5 [†] They have corrupted themselves, [∥]their spot is not the spot of his children: they are a perverse and crooked generation. 6  Do ye thus requite the LORD, O foolish people and unwise? is not he thy father that hath bought thee? hath he not made thee, and established thee?

7 ¶ Remember the days of old, consider the years of [†]many generations: ask thy father, and he will shew thee; thy elders, and they will tell thee. 8  When the most High divided to the nations their inheritance, when he separated the sons of Adam, he set the bounds of the people according to the number of the children of Israel. 9  For the LORD’s portion is his people; Jacob is the [†]lot of his inheritance. 10  He found him in a desert land, and in the waste howling wilderness; he [∥]led him about, he instructed him, he kept him as the apple of his eye. 11  As an eagle stirreth up her nest, fluttereth over her young, spreadeth abroad her wings, taketh them, beareth them on her wings: 12  So the LORD alone did lead him, and there was no strange god with him. 13  He made him ride on the high places of the earth, that he might eat the increase of the fields; and he made him to suck honey out of the rock, and oil out of the flinty rock; 14  Butter of kine, and milk of sheep, with fat of lambs, and rams of the breed of Bashan, and goats, with the fat of kidneys of wheat; and thou didst drink the pure blood of the grape.

15 ¶ But Jeshurun waxed fat, and kicked: thou art waxen fat, thou art grown thick, thou art covered with fatness; then he forsook God which made him, and lightly esteemed the Rock of his salvation. 16  They provoked him to jealousy with strange gods, with abominations provoked they him to anger. 17  They sacrificed unto devils, [∥]not to God; to gods whom they knew not, to new gods that came newly up, whom your fathers feared not. 18  Of the Rock that begat thee thou art unmindful, and hast forgotten God that formed thee.

19  And when the LORD saw it, he [∥]abhorred them, because of the provoking of his sons, and of his daughters. 20  And he said, I will hide my face from them, I will see what their end shall be: for they are a very froward generation, children in whom is no faith. 21  They have moved me to jealousy with that which is not God; they have provoked me to anger with their vanities: and [*]I will move them to jealousy with those which are not a people; I will provoke them to anger with a foolish nation. 22  For a fire is kindled in mine anger, and [∥]shall burn unto the lowest hell, and [∥]shall consume the earth with her increase, and set on fire the foundations of the mountains. 23  I will heap mischiefs upon them; I will spend mine arrows upon them. 24  They shall be burnt with hunger, and devoured with [†]burning heat, and with bitter destruction: I will also send the teeth of beasts upon them, with the poison of serpents of the dust. 25  The sword without, and terror [†]within, shall [†]destroy both the young man and the virgin, the suckling also with the man of gray hairs.

26  I said, I would scatter them into corners, I would make the remembrance of them to cease from among men: 27  Were it not that I feared the wrath of the enemy, lest their adversaries should behave themselves strangely, and lest they should say, [∥]Our hand is high, and the LORD hath not done all this. 28 For they are a nation void of counsel, neither is there any understanding in them. 29  O that they were wise, that they understood this, that they would consider their latter end! 30  How should [*]one chase a thousand, and two put ten thousand to flight, except their Rock had sold them, and the LORD had shut them up? 31  For their rock is not as our Rock, even our enemies themselves being judges. 32  For their vine [∥]is of the vine of Sodom, and of the fields of Gomorrah: their grapes are grapes of gall, their clusters are bitter: 33  Their wine is the poison of dragons, and the cruel venom of asps. 34  Is not this laid up in store with me, and sealed up among my treasures? 35 To me belongeth [*]vengeance, and recompence; their foot shall slide in due time: for the day of their calamity is at hand, and the things that shall come upon them make haste. 36  For the LORD shall judge his people, and repent himself for his servants, when he seeth that their [†]power is gone, and there is none shut up, or left. 37  And he shall say, Where are their gods, their rock in whom they trusted, 38  Which did eat the fat of their sacrifices, and drank the wine of their drink offerings? let them rise up and help you, and be [†]your protection.

39  See now that I, even I, am he, and there is no god with me: [*]I kill, and I make alive; I wound, and I heal: neither is there any that can deliver out of my hand. 40  For I lift up my hand to heaven, and say, I live for ever. 41  If I whet my glittering sword, and mine hand take hold on judgment; I will render vengeance to mine enemies, and will reward them that hate me. 42  I will make mine arrows drunk with blood, and my sword shall devour flesh; and that with the blood of the slain and of the captives, from the beginning of revenges upon the enemy. 43 [∥][*] Rejoice, O ye nations, with his people: for he will avenge the blood of his servants, and will render vengeance to his adversaries, and will be merciful unto his land, and to his people.

44 ¶ And Moses came and spake all the words of this song in the ears of the people, he, and [∥]Hoshea the son of Nun. 45  And Moses made an end of speaking all these words to all Israel: 46  And he said unto them, [*]Set your hearts unto all the words which I testify among you this day, which ye shall command your children to observe to do, all the words of this law. 47 For it is not a vain thing for you; because it is your life: and through this thing ye shall prolong your days in the land, whither ye go over Jordan to possess it. 48 [*] And the LORD spake unto Moses that selfsame day, saying, 49  Get thee up into this mountain Abarim, unto mount Nebo, which is in the land of Moab, that is over against Jericho; and behold the land of Canaan, which I give unto the children of Israel for a possession: 50  And die in the mount whither thou goest up, and be gathered unto thy people; as [*]Aaron thy brother died in mount Hor, and was gathered unto his people: 51  Because [*]ye trespassed against me among the children of Israel at the waters of [∥]Meribah-Kadesh, in the wilderness of Zin; because ye sanctified me not in the midst of the children of Israel. 52  Yet thou shalt see the land before thee; but thou shalt not go thither unto the land which I give the children of Israel.

33

1 And this is the blessing, wherewith Moses the man of God blessed the children of Israel before his death. 2  And he said, The LORD came from Sinai, and rose up from Seir unto them; he shined forth from mount Paran, and he came with ten thousands of saints: from his right hand went [†]a fiery law for them. 3  Yea, he loved the people; all his saints are in thy hand: and they sat down at thy feet; every one shall receive of thy words. 4  Moses commanded us a law, even the inheritance of the congregation of Jacob. 5  And he was king in Jeshurun, when the heads of the people and the tribes of Israel were gathered together.

6 ¶ Let Reuben live, and not die; and let not his men be few.

7 ¶ And this is the blessing of Judah: and he said, Hear, LORD, the voice of Judah, and bring him unto his people: let his hands be sufficient for him; and be thou an help to him from his enemies.

8 ¶ And of Levi he said, [*]Let thy Thummim and thy Urim be with thy holy one, whom thou didst prove at Massah, and with whom thou didst strive at the waters of Meribah; 9  Who said unto his father and to his mother, I have not seen him; neither did he acknowledge his brethren, nor knew his own children: for they have observed thy word, and kept thy covenant. 10 [∥] They shall teach Jacob thy judgments, and Israel thy law: [∥]they shall put incense [†]before thee, and whole burnt sacrifice upon thine altar. 11  Bless, LORD, his substance, and accept the work of his hands: smite through the loins of them that rise against him, and of them that hate him, that they rise not again.

12 ¶ And of Benjamin he said, The beloved of the LORD shall dwell in safety by him; and the Lord shall cover him all the day long, and he shall dwell between his shoulders.

13 ¶ And of Joseph he said, [*]Blessed of the LORD be his land, for the precious things of heaven, for the dew, and for the deep that coucheth beneath, 14  And for the precious fruits brought forth by the sun, and for the precious things [†]put forth by the [†]moon, 15  And for the chief things of the ancient mountains, and for the precious things of the lasting hills, 16  And for the precious things of the earth and fulness thereof, and for the good will of him that dwelt in the bush: let the blessing come upon the head of Joseph, and upon the top of the head of him that was [*]separated from his brethren. 17  His glory is like the firstling of his bullock, and his horns are like the horns of unicorns: with them he shall push the people together to the ends of the earth: and they are the ten thousands of Ephraim, and they are the thousands of Manasseh.

18 ¶ And of Zebulun he said, Rejoice, Zebulun, in thy going out; and, Issachar, in thy tents. 19  They shall call the people unto the mountain; there they shall offer sacrifices of righteousness: for they shall suck of the abundance of the seas, and of treasures hid in the sand.

20 ¶ And of Gad he said, Blessed be he that enlargeth Gad: he dwelleth as a lion, and teareth the arm with the crown of the head. 21  And he provided the first part for himself, because there, in a portion of the lawgiver, was he [†]seated; and he came with the heads of the people, he executed the justice of the LORD, and his judgments with Israel.

22 ¶ And of Dan he said, Dan is a lion’s whelp: he shall leap from Bashan.

23 ¶ And of Naphtali he said, O Naphtali, satisfied with favour, and full with the blessing of the LORD: possess thou the west and the south.

24 ¶ And of Asher he said, Let Asher be blessed with children; let him be acceptable to his brethren, and let him dip his foot in oil. 25 [∥] Thy shoes shall be iron and brass; and as thy days, so shall thy strength be.

26 ¶ There is none like unto the God of Jeshurun, who rideth upon the heaven in thy help, and in his excellency on the sky. 27  The eternal God is thy refuge, and underneath are the everlasting arms: and he shall thrust out the enemy from before thee; and shall say, Destroy them. 28 [*] Israel then shall dwell in safety alone: the fountain of Jacob shall be upon a land of corn and wine; also his heavens shall drop down dew. 29  Happy art thou, O Israel: who is like unto thee, O people saved by the LORD, the shield of thy help, and who is the sword of thy excellency! and thine enemies [∥]shall be found liars unto thee; and thou shalt tread upon their high places.

34

1  And Moses went up from the plains of Moab unto the mountain of Nebo, to the top of [∥]Pisgah, that is over against Jericho. And the LORD shewed him [*]all the land of Gilead, unto Dan, 2  And all Naphtali, and the land of Ephraim, and Manasseh, and all the land of Judah, unto the utmost sea, 3  And the south, and the plain of the valley of Jericho, the city of palm trees, unto Zoar. 4  And the LORD said unto him, [*]This is the land which I sware unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob, saying, I will give it unto thy seed: I have caused thee to see it with thine eyes, but thou shalt not go over thither.

5 ¶ So Moses the servant of the LORD died there in the land of Moab, according to the word of the LORD. 6  And he buried him in a valley in the land of Moab, over against Beth-peor: but no man knoweth of his sepulchre unto this day.

7 ¶ And Moses was an hundred and twenty years old when he died: his eye was not dim, nor his [†]natural force [†]abated.

8 ¶ And the children of Israel wept for Moses in the plains of Moab thirty days: so the days of weeping and mourning for Moses were ended.

9 ¶ And Joshua the son of Nun was full of the spirit of wisdom; for Moses had laid his hands upon him: and the children of Israel hearkened unto him, and did as the LORD commanded Moses.

10 ¶ And there arose not a prophet since in Israel like unto Moses, whom the LORD knew face to face, 11  In all the signs and the wonders, which the LORD sent him to do in the land of Egypt to Pharaoh, and to all his servants, and to all his land, 12  And in all that mighty hand, and in all the great terror which Moses shewed in the sight of all Israel.

∥ 1.1 Or, Zuph.

* 1.4 Num. 21. 24.

† 1.7 Heb. all his neighbours.

† 1.8 Heb. given.

* 1.8 Gen. 15. 18. &c 17. 7, 8.

† 1.13 Heb. Give.

† 1.15 Heb. gave.

* 1.16 John 7. 24.

* 1.17 Lev. 19. 15. ch. 16. 19. 1 Sam. 16. 7. Prov. 24. 23.

† 1.17 Heb. acknowledge faces.

* 1.23 Num 13. 3

* 1.24 Num. 13. 24.

† 1.28 Heb melted.

* 1.28 Num. 13 29.

* 1.33 Ex. 13. 21.

* 1.35 Num. 14. 29.

† 1.36 Heb. fulfilled to go after.

* 1.37 Num. 20 12. &c 27. 14.

* 1.37 ch. 3. 26. &c 4. 21. &c 34. 4.

* 1.41 Num. 14. 40.

† 1.43 Heb. ye were presumptuous, and went up.

† 2.5 Heb. even to the treading of the sole of the foot.

* 2.5 Gen. 36. 8.

∥ 2.9 Or, Use no hostility against Moab.

* 2.12 Gen. 36. 20.

† 2.12 Heb. inherited them.

∥ 2.12 Or, room

* 2.13 Num. 21. 12.

∥ 2.13 Or, valley.

† 2.24 Heb. begin, possess.

* 2.27 Num 21 21, 22.

* 2.32 Num. 21. 23.

† 2.34 Heb. every city of men, and women, and little ones.

* 3.1 Num. 21. 33, &c. ch. 29. 7.

* 3.2 Num. 21. 24.

* 3.3 Num. 21. 33.

* 3.12 Num. 32. 33. Josh. 13. 8, &c.

* 3.14 Num. 32. 41.

∥ 3.17 Or, under the springs of Pisgah, or, the hill.

* 3.18 Num. 32. 20.

† 3.18 Heb. sons of power.

* 3.20 Josh. 22. 4.

* 3.21 Num. 27. 18.

* 3.26 Num. 20. 12. ch. 1. 37.

∥ 3.27 Or, The hill.

* 4.2 ch 12 32. Josh. 1. 7. Prov. 30. 6. Rev. 22. 18.

* 4.3 Num 25. 4, &c

* 4.11 Ex. 19. 18.

† 4.11 Heb. heart.

† 4.12 Heb. save a voice.

∥ 4.19 Or, imparted.

* 4.24 ch 9. 3. Heb. 12. 29.

‡ 4.25 [1611 shalt]

† 4.30 Heb. have found thee.

‡ 4.32 [1611 omits the]

* 4.43 Josh. 20. 8.

* 4.46 Num. 21. 24. ch. 1 4.

* 4.47 Num. 21. 33. ch. 3. 3.

‡ 4.49 [1611 of]

* 4.49 ch. 3. 17.

† 5.1 Heb. keep to do them.

* 5.2 Ex. 19. 5.

* 5.6 Ex. 20. 2. &c. Lev. 26. 1. Ps. 81. 10.

† 5.6 Heb. servants.

* 5.9 Ex. 84. 7.

* 5.10 Jer. 32. 18.

* 5.14 Gen. 2. 2. Heb. 4. 4.

* 5.17 Matt. 5. 21.

* 5.18 Luke 18. 20.

* 5.19 Rom. 13. 9.

* 5.21 Rom. 7. 7.

* 5.24 Ex. 19. 19.

* 5.24 ch. 4. 33.

† 5.25 Heb. add to hear.

* 5.27 Ex 20. 19.

‡ 5.29 [1611 omits all]

† 6.1 Heb. pass over.

* 6.5 ch 10 12. Matt. 22. 37. Mark 12. 30. Luke 10. 27.

* 6.6 ch 11. 18.

† 6.7 Heb. whet, or, sharpen.

* 6.11 ch 8. 9, 10, &c

† 6.12 Heb bondmen, or, servants.

* 6.13 ch. 10. 12, 20 &c 13. 4

* 6.16 Matt. 4. 7.

* 6.16 Ex. 17 2.

† 6.20 Heb. to morrow.

† 6.22 Heb. evil.

* 7.1 ch. 31. 3.

* 7.2 Ex. 23. 32. &c 34. 12.

† 7.5 Heb. statues, or, pillars

* 7.6 ch. 14. 2. &c 26. 19.

* 7.6 Ex. 19. 5. 1 Pet. 2. 9.

† 7.12 Heb. because.

* 7.14 Ex. 23. 26, &c.

* 7.15 Ex. 9. 14 &c 15. 26.

* 7.16 Ex. 23. 33.

* 7.20 Ex. 23. 28. Josh. 24. 12.

† 7.22 Heb. pluck off.

† 7.23 Heb. before thy face.

* 7.25 ch. 12. 3

* 7.25 Josh. 7. 1, 21. 2 Mac. 12. 40.

* 7.26 ch. 13. 17.

* 8.3 Matt. 4. 4. Luke 4. 4.

* 8.4 Neh. 9. 21.

† 8.8 Heb. of olive tree of oil.

* 8.10 ch. 6. 12, 13.

* 8.15 Num. 20 11.

* 8.16 Ex. 16. 15.

* 9.2 Num. 13. 28.

* 9.3 ch. 4. 24. Heb. 12. 29.

* 9.9 Ex. 24. 18. &c 34. 28.

* 9.10 Ex. 31. 18.

‡ 9.10 [1611 omits the]

* 9.12 Ex. 32. 7.

* 9.22 Num. 11 1, 3.

* 9.22 Ex. 17. 7.

* 9.22 Num. 11. 34.

* 9.28 Num. 14. 16.

* 10.1 Ex. 34. 1.

† 10.4 Heb. words.

* 10.6 Num. 33. 30.

* 10.6 Num. 20. 28.

* 10.9 Num. 18. 20.

∥ 10.10 Or, former days.

† 10.11 Heb. go in journey.

* 10.14 Ps. 24. 1.

* 10.17 2 Chr. 19. 7. Job 34. 19. Acts 10. 34. Rom. 2. 11. Gal. 2 6. Eph. 6. 9. Col 3. 25. 1 Pet. 1. 17.

* 10.20 ch. 6. 13. Matt. 4. 10. Luke 4. 3.

* 10.20 ch. 13. 4.

* 10.22 Gen. 46 27. Ex. 1. 5.

* 10.22 Gen. 15. 5.

* 11.6 Num. 16. 31. &c 27. 3. Ps. 106. 17.

∥ 11.6 Or, living substance which followed them.

† 11.6 Heb. was at their feet.

† 11.12 Heb. seeketh.

† 11.15 Heb. give.

* 11.18 ch. 6. 8.

* 11.19 ch. 4. 10. &c 6. 7.

* 11.24 Josh. 1. 3.

* 11.27 ch. 23. 2.

* 11.28 ch. 28. 15.

* 11.29 ch. 27. 13 Josh. 8. 33.

* 11.32 ch. 5. 32.

* 12.2 ch. 7. 5.

∥ 12.2 Or, inherit.

* 12.3 Judg. 2. 2.

† 12.3 Heb. break down.

* 12.5 1 Kings 8 29. 2 Chr. 7. 12.

† 12.11 Heb. the choice of your vows.

* 12.12 ch. 10 9.

* 12.16 ch. 15. 23.

* 12.19 ch. 14. 27 Ecclus. 7 31.

† 12.19 Heb. all thy days

* 12.20 Gen. 28. 14 ch. 19. 8.

† 12.23 Heb. be strong.

† 12.29 Heb. inheritest, or, possessest them.

† 12.30 Heb. after them.

† 12.31 Heb. abomination of the.

* 12.32 ch. 4. 2. Josh. 1. 7. Prov. 30. 6 Rev. 22. 18.

* 13.4 ch. 10. 20.

† 13.5 Heb. spoken recolt against the Lord.

* 13.9 ch. 17. 7.

† 13.10 Heb. bondmen.

* 13.11 ch. 17. 13.

∥ 13.13 Or, naughty men

∥ 13.17 Or, devoted

* 14.1 Lev. 19. 28.

* 14.2 ch. 7 6 &c 26. 18.

* 14.4 Lev. 11. 2, &c.

∥ 14.5 Or, bison.

† 14.5 Heb. dishon.

* 14.9 Lev. 11. 9.

* 14.18 Lev. 11 19.

* 14.21 Ex. 23. 19. &c 34. 26.

† 14.26 Heb. asketh of thee.

* 14.27 ch. 12. 19

* 15.1 Lev. 25. 2, 4.

† 15.2 Heb. master of the lending of his hand.

∥ 15.4 Or, To the end that there be no poor among you.

* 15.6 ch. 28. 12.

* 15.8 Matt. 5. 42. Luke 6. 34.

† 15.9 Heb. word.

† 15.9 Heb Belial.

‡ 15.11 [1611 the]

* 15.12 Ex. 21. 2. Jer. 34. 14.

* 15.17 Ex. 21. 6.

* 15.19 Ex 34. 19.

* 15.21 Lev. 22. 20. ch. 17. 1. Ecclus. 35. 12.

* 15.23 ch. 13. 16, 23.

* 16.1 Ex. 12. 2, &c.

* 16.1 Ex. 13. 4.

* 16.2 ch. 12. 5.

* 16.3 Ex. 12. 15.

* 16.4 Ex. 34. 25.

‡ 16.4 [1611 coasts]

∥ 16.5 Or, kill.

‡ 16.5 [1611 the]

† 16.8 Heb restraint.

* 16.9 Lev. 23. 15.

∥ 16.10 Or, sufficiency.

† 16.13 Heb. floor and thy winepress.

* 16.16 Ex. 23. 14. &c 34. 23.

* 16.16 Ecclus. 35. 4.

† 16.17 Heb. according to the gift of his hand.

* 16.19 Ex. 23. 8

∥ 16.19 Or, matters.

† 16.20 Heb. Justice, justice.

* 16.22 Lev. 26. 1.

∥ 16.22 Or, statue, or, pillar.

∥ 17.1 Or, goat.

* 17.6 Num. 35 30. ch. 19. 15 Matt. 18. 16. John 8. 17. 2 Cor. 13. 1. Heb. 10. 28.

† 17.12 Heb. not to hearken.

* 18.1 Num. 18. 20. ch. 10. 9.

* 18.1 1 Cor. 9. 13.

† 18.8 Heb. his sales by the fathers.

* 18.10 Lev. 18. 21.

* 18.11 Lev. 20 27.

* 18.11 1 Sam. 28. 7.

∥ 18.13 Or, upright, or, sincere.

∥ 18.14 Or, inherit.

* 18.15 John 1. 45 Acts 3. 22. &c 7. 37.

* 18.16 Ex. 20. 19.

* 18.18 John 1. 45. Acts 3. 22 &c 7. 37.

* 19.1 ch. 12. 29.

† 19.1 Heb. inheritest, or, possessest.

* 19.2 Ex. 21. 13 Num. 35. 10. Josh. 20. 2.

† 19.4 Heb from yesterday the third day.

† 19.5 Heb. iron.

† 19.5 Heb wood.

† 19.5 Heb findeth.

† 19.6 Heb. smite him in life.

† 19.6 Heb. from yesterday the third day.

* 19.8 ch. 12 20.

* 19.9 Josh. 20. 7.

† 19.11 Heb in life.

* 19.15 Num. 35 30. ch. 17. 6. Matt. 18. 16. John 8 17. 2 Cor. 13. 1. Heb. 10. 28.

∥ 19.16 Or, falling away.

* 19.19 Prov. 19. 5, 9. Dan. 6. 24.

* 19.21 Ex. 21. 23. Lev. 24. 20. Matt. 5. 38.

† 20.3 Heb be tender.

† 20.3 Heb. make haste.

† 20.6 Heb. made it common See Lev. 19. 23

* 20.7 ch. 24. 5.

‡ 20.7 [1611 omits the]

* 20.8 Judg. 7. 3

† 20.8 Heb. melt.

† 20.9 Heb. to be in the head of the people.

* 20.14 Josh. 8. 2.

† 20.14 Heb. spoil.

∥ 20.19 Or, for, O man, the tree of the fickt is to be employed in the siege.

† 20.19 Heb. to go from before thee.

† 20.20 Heb. it come down.

† 21.5 Heb. mouth.

† 21.8 Heb. in the midst.

∥ 21.12 Or, suffer to grow.

† 21.12 Heb. make, or, dress.

† 21.17 Heb. that is found with him.

* 21.23 Gal. 3. 18.

† 21.23 Heb. the curse of God.

* 22.1 Ex. 23. 4.

† 22.9 Heb. fulness of the seed.

* 22.11 Lev. 19. 19.

* 22.12 Num. 15. 38.

† 22.12 Heb. wings.

* 22.22 Lev. 20. 10.

∥ 22.25 Or, take strong hold of her.

* 22.28 Ex. 22. 16.

* 22.30 Lev. 18. 8.

* 23.3 Neh. 13. 1.

* 23.4 Num. 22. 5, 6.

† 23.6 Heb. good.

† 23.11 Heb turncth toward.

† 23.13 Heb. sittest down.

† 23.14 Heb. nakedness of any thing.

† 23.16 Heb. is good for him.

∥ 23.17 Or, sodomitess.

* 23.19 Ex. 22. 25 Lev. 25. 36. Ps. 15. 5.

* 23.21 Eccles. 5. 4.

‡ 23.25 [1611 neighbour's]

* 23.25 Matt. 12. 1. Mark 2. 23 Luke 6. 1.

* 24.1 Matt. 5. 31. &c 19 7. Mark 10. 4.

† 24.1 Heb. matter of nakedness

† 24.1 Heb. cutting off.

* 24.5 ch. 20. 7.

† 24.5 Heb. not any thing shall pass upon him.

* 24.8 Lev. 13 2.

* 24.9 Num. 12. 10.

† 24.10 Heb. lend the loan of any thing to, &c.

* 24.15 Lev. 19 13. Tob. 4. 14.

† 24.15 Heb. he lifteth his soul unto it.

* 24.16 2 Kings 14. 6. 2 Chr. 25. 4. Jer 31. 29. 30. Ezek. 18. 20.

* 24.19 Lev. 19. 9. &c 23. 22.

† 24.20 Heb. thou shall not bough it after thee.

† 24.21 Heb. after thee.

* 25.3 2 Cor. 11. 24.

* 25.4 1 Cor. 9. 9. 1 Tim. 5 18.

† 25.4 Heb. thresheth.

* 25.5 Matt. 22. 24. Mark 12 19. Luke 20. 28.

∥ 25.5 Or, next kinsman.

∥ 25.7 Or, next kinsman's wife.

* 25.7 Ruth 4. 7.

† 25.13 Heb a stone and a stone.

† 25.14 Heb an ephah and an ephah.

* 25.17 Ex 17. 8

‡ 26.1 [1611 omits thy God]

* 26.12 ch. 14. 28

* 26.15 Isai. 63. 15.

* 26.18 ch. 7. 6.

* 27.2 Josh. 4. 1

* 27.5 Ex. 20. 25. Josh. 8. 31.

† 27.13 Heb. for a cursing.

* 27.14 Dan. 9. 11.

* 27.25 Ezek. 22. 12.

* 27.26 Gal. 2. 10.

* 28.1 Lev. 26. 3.

∥ 28.5 Or, dough, or, kneading-troughs.

∥ 28.8 Or, barns.

* 28.11 ch. 30. 9, &c.

∥ 28.11 Or, for good.

† 28.11 Heb. belly.

* 28.12 ch. 15. 6.

* 28.15 Lev. 26. 14. Lam. 2. 17. Mal. 2. 2. Bar. 1. 20.

† 28.20 Heb. which thou wouldest do.

* 28.22 Lev. 26 16.

∥ 28.22 Or, drought.

‡ 28.23 [1611 the]

† 28.25 Heb. for a removing.

‡ 28.29 [1611 noon days]

* 28.30 ch. 20. 6.

† 28.30 Heb. profane, or, use it as common meat.

† 28.31 Heb. shall not return to thee.

* 28.37 1 Kings 9. 7. Jer. 24. 9. &c 25. 9.

* 28.38 Mic. 6. 15. Hag. 1. 6.

† 28.41 Heb. they shall not be thine.

‡ 28.42 [1611 locusts]

∥ 28.42 Or, possess.

† 28.49 Heb. hear.

† 28.50 Heb. strong of face.

* 28.53 Lev. 26. 29. 2 Kings 6 29. Lam. 4. 10 Bar. 2. 3.

† 28.53 Heb. belly.

† 28.57 Heb. afterbirth.

† 28.61 Heb. cause to ascend

* 28.62 ch 10. 22.

* 29.2 Ex. 19. 4.

* 29.9 ch. 4. 6. 1 Kings 2. 2. Josh 1. 7.

† 29.12 Heb. pass.

† 29.17 Heb dungy gods.

∥ 29.18 Or, a poisonful herb

† 29.18 Heb. rosh.

∥ 29.19 Or, stubbornness.

† 29.19 Heb. the drunken to the thirsty.

† 29.21 Heb. is written.

† 29.22 Heb wherewith the Lord hath made it sick.

* 29.23 Gen. 19. 24. 25.

* 29.24 1 Kings 9. 8 Jer. 22. 8.

∥ 29.26 Or, who had not given to them any portion.

† 29.26 Heb. divided.

* 30.4 Neh. 1. 9.

* 30.9 ch. 28. 11.

* 30.12 Rom. 10 6, &c.

* 30.19 ch. 4. 26.

* 31.2 Num. 20 12. ch. 3. 27.

* 31.3 Num. 27. 21.

* 31.5 ch. 7. 2.

* 31.10 ch. 15. 1.

† 31.16 Heb. lie down.

† 31.17 Heb. find them.

† 31.21 Heb. before.

† 31.21 Heb. do.

* 31.23 Josh. 1. 6.

† 32.5 Heb. He hath corrupted to himself.

∥ 32.5 Or, that they are not his children, that is their blot.

† 32.7 Heb. generation and generation.

† 32.9 Heb. cord.

∥ 32.10 Or, compassed him about.

∥ 32.17 Or, which were not God.

∥ 32.19 Or, despised.

* 32.21 Rom. 10. 9.

∥ 32.22 Or, hath burned.

∥ 32.22 Or, hath consumed.

† 32.24 Heb. burning coals.

† 32.25 Heb. from the chambers.

† 32.25 Heb. bereave.

∥ 32.27 Or, Our high hand, and not the Lord, hath done all this.

* 32.30 Josh. 23. 10.

∥ 32.32 Or, is worse than the vine of Sodom, &c.

* 32.35 Ecclus. 28 1. Rom. 12. 19. Heb. 10. 30.

† 32.36 Heb. hand.

† 32.38 Heb. an hiding for you.

* 32.39 1 Sam. 2 6. Tob. 13. 2 Wisd. 16. 13.

∥ 32.43 Or, Praise his people, ye nations. Or, Sing ye.

* 32.43 Matt. 7. 6. Rom. 15. 10.

∥ 32.44 Or, Joshua.

* 32.46 ch. 6 6. &c 11. 18.

* 32.48 Num. 27. 12.

* 32.50 Num. 20. 25, 28. &c 33. 38.

* 32.51 Num. 20. 12, 13. &c 27. 14.

∥ 32.51 Or, Strife at Kadesh.

† 33.2 Heb. a fire of law.

* 33.8 Ex. 28. 30.

∥ 33.10 Or, Let them teach, &c.

∥ 33.10 Or, let them put incense.

† 33.10 Heb. at thy nose.

* 33.13 Gen. 49. 25.

† 33.14 Heb. thrust forth.

† 33.14 Heb. moons.

* 33.16 Gen. 49. 26.

† 33.21 Heb. cieled.

∥ 33.25 Or, Under thy shoes shall be iron.

* 33.28 Jer. 23. 6.

∥ 33.29 Or, shall be subdued.

∥ 34.1 Or, The kill.

* 34.1 ch. 3. 27. 2 Mac. 2. 4.

* 34.4 Gen. 12 7. &c 13. 15.

† 34.7 Heb. moisture.

† 34.7 Heb. fied.

Ecclesiastes

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12

Ecclesiastes or, the Preacher

1

1  The words of the Preacher, the son of David, king in Jerusalem. 2 [*] Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher, vanity of vanities; all is vanity. 3 [*] What profit hath a man of all his labour which he taketh under the sun?

4  One generation passeth away, and another generation cometh: [*]but the earth abideth for ever. 5  The sun also ariseth, and the sun goeth down, and [†]hasteth to [‡]his place where he arose. 6  The wind goeth toward the south, and turneth about unto the north; it whirleth about continually, and the wind returneth again according to his circuits. 7 [*] All the rivers run into the sea; yet the sea is not full; unto the place from whence the rivers come, thither they [†]return again. 8  All things are full of labour; man cannot utter it: the eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing.

9 [*]The thing that hath been, it is that which shall be; and that which is done is that which shall be done: and there is no new thing under the sun. 10  Is there any thing whereof it may be said, See, this is new? it hath been already of old time, which was before us. 11  There is no remembrance of former things; neither shall there be any remembrance of things that are to come with those that shall come after.

12 ¶ I the Preacher was king over Israel in Jerusalem. 13  And I gave my heart to seek and search out by wisdom concerning all things that are done under heaven: this sore travail hath God given to the sons of man [∥]to be exercised therewith. 14  I have seen all the works that are done under the sun; and, behold, all is vanity and vexation of spirit. 15 [*] That which is crooked cannot be made straight: and [†]that which is wanting cannot be numbered. 16  I communed with mine own heart, saying, Lo, I am come to great estate, and have gotten [*]more wisdom than all they that have been before me in Jerusalem: yea, my heart [†]had great experience of wisdom and knowledge. 17 [*] And I gave my heart to know wisdom, and to know madness and folly: I perceived that this also is vexation of spirit. 18  For in much wisdom is much grief: and he that increaseth knowledge increaseth sorrow.

2

1  I said in mine heart, Go to now, I will prove thee with mirth, therefore enjoy pleasure: and, behold, this also is vanity. 2  I said of laughter, It is mad: and of mirth, What doeth it? 3 [*] I sought in mine heart [†]to give myself unto wine, yet acquainting mine heart with wisdom; and to lay hold on folly, till I might see what was that good for the sons of men, which they should do under the heaven [†]all the days of their life. 4  I made me great works; I builded me houses; I planted me vineyards: 5  I made me gardens and orchards, and I planted trees in them of all kind of fruits: 6  I made me pools of water, to water therewith the wood that bringeth forth trees: 7  I got me servants and maidens, and had [†]servants born in my house; also I had great possessions of great and small cattle above all that were in Jerusalem before me: 8 [*] I gathered me also silver and gold, and the peculiar treasure of kings and of the provinces: I gat me men singers and women singers, and the delights of the sons of men, as [†]musical instruments, and that of all sorts. 9  So I was great, and increased more than all that were before me in Jerusalem: also my wisdom remained with me. 10  And whatsoever mine eyes desired I kept not from them, I withheld not my heart from any joy; for my heart rejoiced in all my labour: and this was my portion of all my labour. 11  Then I looked on all the works that my hands had wrought, and on the labour that I had laboured to do: and, behold, all was [*]vanity and vexation of spirit, and there was no profit under the sun.

12 ¶ And I turned myself to behold wisdom, [*]and madness, and folly: for what can the man do that cometh after the king? [∥]even that which hath been already done. 13  Then I saw [†]that wisdom excelleth folly, as far as light excelleth darkness. 14 [*] The wise man’s eyes are in his head; but the fool walketh in darkness: and I myself perceived also that one event happeneth to them all. 15  Then said I in my heart, As it happeneth to the fool, so it [†]happeneth even to me; and why was I then more wise? Then I said in my heart, that this also is vanity. 16 For there is no remembrance of the wise more than of the fool for ever; seeing that which now is in the days to come shall [‡]all be forgotten. And how dieth the wise man? as the fool.

17  Therefore I hated life; because the work that is wrought under the sun is grievous unto me: for all is vanity and vexation of spirit.

18 ¶ Yea, I hated all my labour which I had [†]taken under the sun: because [*]I should leave it unto the man that shall be after me. 19  And who knoweth whether he shall be a wise man or a fool? yet shall he have rule over all my labour wherein I have laboured, and wherein I have shewed myself wise under the sun. This is also vanity. 20  Therefore I went about to cause my heart to despair of all the labour which I took under the sun. 21  For there is a man whose labour is in wisdom, and in knowledge, and in equity; yet to a man that hath not laboured therein shall he [†]leave it for his portion. This also is vanity and a great evil. 22 [*] For what hath man of all his labour, and of the vexation of his heart, wherein he hath laboured under the sun? 23  For all his days are [*]sorrows, and his travail grief; yea, his heart taketh not rest in the night. This is also vanity.

24 ¶ [*]There is nothing better for a man, than that he should eat and drink, and that he [∥]should make his soul enjoy good in his labour. This also I saw, that it was from the hand of God. 25  For who can eat, or who else can hasten hereunto, more than I? 26 For God giveth to a man that is good [†]in his sight wisdom, and knowledge, and joy: but to the sinner he giveth travail, to gather and to heap up, that [*]he may give to him that is good before God. This also is vanity and vexation of spirit.

3

1 To every thing there is a season, and a time to every purpose under the heaven: 2  A time [†]to be born, and a time to die; a time to plant, and a time to pluck up that which is planted; 3  A time to kill, and a time to heal; a time to break down, and a time to build up; 4  A time to weep, and a time to laugh; a time to mourn, and a time to dance; 5  A time to cast away stones, and a time to gather stones together; a time to embrace, and a time [†]to refrain from embracing; 6  A time to [∥]get, and a time to lose; a time to keep, and a time to cast away; 7  A time to rend, and a time to sew; a time to keep silence, and a time to speak; 8  A time to love, and a time to hate; a time of war, and a time of peace. 9 [*] What profit hath he that worketh in that wherein he laboureth? 10  I have seen the travail, which God hath given to the sons of men to be exercised in it.

11  He hath made every thing beautiful in his time: also he hath set the world in their heart, so that no man can find out the work that God maketh from the beginning to the end. 12  I know that there is no good in them, but for a man to rejoice, and to do good in his life. 13  And also that every man should eat and drink, and enjoy the good of all his labour, it is the gift of God. 14  I know that, whatsoever God doeth, it shall be for ever: nothing can be put to it, nor any thing taken from it: and God doeth it, that men should fear before him. 15 [*] That which hath been is now; and that which is to be hath already been; and God requireth [†]that which is past.

16 ¶ And moreover I saw under the sun the place of judgment, that wickedness was there; and the place of righteousness, that iniquity was there. 17  I said in mine heart, God shall judge the righteous and the wicked: for there is [*]a time there for every purpose and for every work. 18  I said in mine heart concerning the estate of the sons of men, [∥]that God might manifest them, and that they might see that they themselves are beasts. 19 [*] For that which befalleth the sons of men befalleth beasts; even one thing befalleth them: as the one dieth, so dieth the other; yea, they have all one breath; so that a man hath no preeminence above a beast: for all is vanity. 20  All go unto one place; all are of the dust, and all turn to dust again. 21  Who knoweth the spirit [†]of man that [†]goeth upward, and the spirit of the beast that goeth downward to the earth? 22 [*] Wherefore I perceive that there is nothing better, than that a man should rejoice in his own works; for that is his portion: for who shall bring him to see what shall be after him?

4

1  So I returned, and considered all the [*]oppressions that are done under the sun: and behold the tears of such as were oppressed, and they had no comforter; and on the [†]side of their oppressors there was power; but they had no comforter. 2 [*] Wherefore I praised the dead which are already dead more than the living which are yet alive. 3 [*] Yea, better is he than both they, which hath not yet been, who hath not seen the evil work that is done under the sun.

4 ¶ Again, I considered all travail, and [†]every right work, that [†]for this a man is envied of his neighbour. This is also vanity and vexation of spirit. 5 [*] The fool foldeth his hands together, and eateth his own flesh. 6 [*] Better is an handful with quietness, than both the hands full with travail and vexation of spirit.

7 ¶ Then I returned, and I saw vanity under the sun. 8  There is one alone, and there is not a second; yea, he hath neither child nor brother: yet is there no end of all his labour; neither is his eye satisfied with riches; neither saith he, For whom do I labour, and bereave my soul of good? This is also vanity, yea, it is a sore travail.

9 ¶ Two are better than one; because they have a good reward for their labour. 10  For if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow: but woe to him that is alone when he falleth; for he hath not another to help him up. 11  Again, if two lie together, then they have heat: but how can one be warm alone? 12  And if one prevail against him, two shall withstand him; and a threefold cord is not quickly broken.

13 ¶ Better is a poor and a wise child than an old and foolish king, [†]who will no more be admonished. 14  For out of prison he cometh to reign; whereas also he that is born in his kingdom becometh poor. 15  I considered all the living which walk under the sun, with the second child that shall stand up in his stead. 16  There is no end of all the people, even of all that have been before them: they also that come after shall not rejoice in him. Surely this also is vanity and vexation of spirit.

5

1  Keep thy foot when thou goest to the house of God, and be more ready to hear, [*]than to give the sacrifice of fools: for they consider not that they do evil. 2  Be not rash with thy mouth, and let not thine heart be hasty to utter any [∥]thing before God: for God is in heaven, and thou upon earth: therefore let thy words be [*]few. 3  For a dream cometh through the multitude of business; and a fool’s voice is known by multitude of words.

4 [*] When thou vowest a vow unto God, defer not to pay it; for he hath no pleasure in fools: [*]pay that which thou hast vowed. 5  Better is it that thou shouldest not vow, than that thou shouldest vow and not pay. 6  Suffer not thy mouth to cause thy flesh to sin; neither say thou before the angel, that it was an error: wherefore should God be angry at thy voice, and destroy the work of thine hands? 7  For in the multitude of dreams and many words there are also divers vanities: but fear thou God.

8 ¶ If thou seest the oppression of the poor, and violent perverting of judgment and justice in a province, marvel not [†]at the matter: for he that is higher than the highest regardeth; and there be higher than they.

9 ¶ Moreover the profit of the earth is for all: the king himself is served by the field. 10  He that loveth silver shall not be satisfied with silver; nor he that loveth abundance with increase: this is also vanity. 11  When goods increase, they are increased that eat them: and what good is there to the owners thereof, saving the beholding of them with their eyes? 12  The sleep of a labouring man is sweet, whether he eat little or much: but the abundance of the rich will not suffer him to sleep. 13  There is a sore evil which I have seen under the sun, namely, riches kept for the owners thereof to their hurt. 14  But those riches perish by evil travail: and he begetteth a son, and there is nothing in his hand. 15 [*] As he came forth of his mother’s womb, naked shall he return to go as he came, and shall take nothing of his labour, which he may carry away in his hand. 16  And this also is a sore evil, that in all points as he came, so shall he go: and [*]what profit hath he that hath laboured for the wind? 17  All his days also he eateth in darkness, and he hath much sorrow and wrath with his sickness.

18 ¶ Behold that which I have seen: [*][†]it is good and comely for one to eat and to drink, and to enjoy the good of all his labour that he taketh under the sun [†]all the days of his life, which God giveth him: for it is his portion. 19  Every man also to whom God hath given riches and wealth, and hath given him power to eat thereof, and to take his portion, and to rejoice in his labour; this is the gift of God. 20 [∥] For he shall not much remember the days of his life; because God answereth him in the joy of his heart.

6

1  There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, and it is common among men: 2  A man to whom God hath given riches, wealth, and honour, so that he wanteth nothing for his soul of all that he desireth, yet God giveth him not power to eat thereof, but a stranger eateth it: this is vanity, and it is an evil disease.

3 ¶ If a man beget an hundred children, and live many years, so that the days of his years be many, and his soul be not filled with good, and also that he have no burial; I say, that an untimely birth is better than he. 4  For he cometh in with vanity, and departeth in darkness, and his name shall be covered with darkness. 5  Moreover he hath not seen the sun, nor known any thing: this hath more rest than the other.

6 ¶ Yea, though he live a thousand years twice told, yet hath he seen no good: do not all go to one place?

7  All the labour of man is for his mouth, and yet the [†]appetite is not filled. 8  For what hath the wise more than the fool? what hath the poor, that knoweth to walk before the living?

9 ¶ Better is the sight of the eyes [†]than the wandering of the desire: this is also vanity and vexation of spirit. 10  That which hath been is named already, and it is known that it is man: neither may he contend with him that is mightier than he.

11 ¶ Seeing there be many things that increase vanity, what is man the better? 12  For who knoweth what is good for man in this life, [†]all the days of his vain life which he spendeth as [*]a shadow? for who can tell a man what shall be after him under the sun?

7

1  A [*]good name is better than precious ointment; and the day of death than the day of one’s birth.

2 ¶ It is better to go to the house of mourning, than to go to the house of feasting: for that is the end of all men; and the living will lay it to his heart. 3 [∥] Sorrow is better than laughter: for by the sadness of the countenance the heart is made better. 4  The heart of the wise is in the house of mourning; but the heart of fools is in the house of mirth. 5 [*] It is better to hear the rebuke of the wise, than for a man to hear the song of fools. 6  For as the [†]crackling of thorns under a pot, so is the laughter of the fool: this also is vanity.

7 ¶ Surely oppression maketh a wise man mad; [*]and a gift destroyeth the heart. 8  Better is the end of a thing than the beginning thereof: and the patient in spirit is better than the proud in spirit. 9 [*] Be not hasty in thy spirit to be angry: for anger resteth in the bosom of fools. 10  Say not thou, What is the cause that the former days were better than these? for thou dost not enquire [†]wisely concerning this.

11 ¶ Wisdom [∥]is good with an inheritance: and by it there is profit to them that see the sun. 12  For wisdom is a [†]defence, and money is a defence: but the excellency of knowledge is, that wisdom giveth life to them that have it. 13  Consider the work of God: for [*]who can make that straight, which he hath made crooked? 14  In the day of prosperity be joyful, but in the day of adversity consider: God also hath [†]set the one over against the other, to the end that man should find nothing after him. 15 All things have I seen in the days of my vanity: there is a just man that perisheth in his righteousness, and there is a wicked man that prolongeth his life in his wickedness. 16  Be not righteous over much; neither make thyself over wise: why shouldest thou [†]destroy thyself? 17  Be not over much wicked, neither be thou foolish: why shouldest thou die [†]before thy time? 18  It is good that thou shouldest take hold of this; yea, also from this withdraw not thine hand: for he that feareth God shall come forth of them all. 19 [*] Wisdom strengtheneth the wise more than ten mighty men which are in the city. 20 [*]For there is not a just man upon earth, that doeth good, and sinneth not. 21  Also [†]take no heed unto all words that are spoken; lest thou hear thy servant curse thee: 22  For oftentimes also thine own heart knoweth that thou thyself likewise hast cursed others.

23 ¶ All this have I proved by wisdom: I said, I will be wise; but it was far from me. 24  That which is far off, and exceeding deep, who can find it out? 25 [†] I applied mine heart to know, and to search, and to seek out wisdom, and the reason of things, and to know the wickedness of folly, even of foolishness and madness: 26 [*] And I find more bitter than death the woman, whose heart is snares and nets, and her hands as bands: [†]whoso pleaseth God shall escape from her; but the sinner shall be taken by her. 27  Behold, this have I found, saith the preacher, [∥]counting one by one, to find out the account: 28  Which yet my soul seeketh, but I find not: one man among a thousand have I found; but a woman among all those have I not found. 29  Lo, this only have I found, [*]that God hath made man upright; but they have sought out many inventions.

8

1 Who is as the wise man? and who knoweth the interpretation of a thing? [*]a man’s wisdom maketh his face to shine, and [†]the boldness of his face shall be changed. 2 I counsel thee to keep the king’s commandment, and that in regard of the oath of God. 3  Be not hasty to go out of his sight: stand not in an evil thing; for he doeth whatsoever pleaseth him. 4  Where the word of a king is, there is power: and who may say unto him, What doest thou? 5  Whoso keepeth the commandment [†]shall feel no evil thing: and a wise man’s heart discerneth both time and judgment.

6 ¶ Because to every purpose there is time and judgment, therefore the misery of man is great upon him. 7  For he knoweth not that which shall be: for who can tell him [∥]when it shall be? 8  There is no man that hath power [*]over the spirit to retain the spirit; neither hath he power in the day of death: and there is no [∥]discharge in that war; neither shall wickedness deliver those that are given to it.

9  All this have I seen, and applied my heart unto every work that is done under the sun: there is a time wherein one man ruleth over another to his own hurt. 10  And so I saw the wicked buried, who had come and gone from the place of the holy, and they were forgotten in the city where they had so done: this is also vanity. 11  Because sentence against an evil work is not executed speedily, therefore the heart of the sons of men is fully set in them to do evil.

12 ¶ Though a sinner do evil an hundred times, and his days be prolonged, yet surely I know that [*]it shall be well with them that fear God, which fear before him: 13  But it shall not be well with the wicked, neither shall he prolong his days, which are as a shadow; because he feareth not before God.

14  There is a vanity which is done upon the earth; that there be just men, unto whom it [*]happeneth according to the work of the wicked; again, there be wicked men, to whom it happeneth according to the work of the righteous: I said that this also is vanity. 15 [*] Then I commended mirth, because a man hath no better thing under the sun, than to eat, and to drink, and to be merry: for that shall abide with him of his labour the days of his life, which God giveth him under the sun.

16 ¶ When I applied mine heart to know wisdom, and to see the business that is done upon the earth: (for also there is that neither day nor night seeth sleep with his eyes:) 17  Then I beheld all the work of God, that a man cannot find out the work that is done under the sun: because though a man labour to seek it out, [‡]yet he shall not find it; yea further; though a wise man think to know it, yet shall he not be able to find it.

9

1  For all this [†]I considered in my heart even to declare all this, that the righteous, and the wise, and their works, are in the hand of God: no man knoweth either love or hatred by all that is before them. 2 [*]All things come alike to all: there is one event to the righteous, and to the wicked; to the good and to the clean, and to the unclean; to him that sacrificeth, and to him that sacrificeth not: as is the good, so is the sinner; and he that sweareth, as he that feareth an oath. 3 This is an evil among all things that are done under the sun, that there is one event unto all: yea, also the heart of the sons of men is full of evil, and madness is in their heart while they live, and after that they go to the dead.

4 ¶ For to him that is joined to all the living there is hope: for a living dog is better than a dead lion. 5  For the living know that they shall die: but the dead know not any thing, neither have they any more a reward; for the memory of them is forgotten. 6  Also their love, and their hatred, and their envy, is now perished; neither have they any more a portion for ever in any thing that is done under the sun.

7 ¶ Go thy way, eat thy bread with joy, and drink thy wine with a merry heart; for God now accepteth thy works. 8  Let thy garments be always white; and let thy head lack no ointment. 9 [†] Live joyfully with the wife whom thou lovest all the days of the life of thy vanity, which he hath given thee under the sun, all the days of thy vanity: [*]for that is thy portion in this life, and in thy labour which thou takest under the sun. 10  Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with thy might; for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in the grave, whither thou goest.

11 ¶ I returned, and saw under the sun, that the race is not to the swift, nor the battle to the strong, neither yet bread to the wise, nor yet riches to men of understanding, nor yet favour to men of skill; but time and chance happeneth to them all. 12  For man also knoweth not his time: as the fishes that are taken in an evil net, and as the birds that are caught in the snare; so are the sons of men [*]snared in an evil time, when it falleth suddenly upon them.

13 ¶ This wisdom have I seen also under the sun, and it seemed great unto me: 14  There was a little city, and few men within it; and there came a great king against it, and besieged it, and built great bulwarks against it: 15  Now there was found in it a poor wise man, and he by his wisdom delivered the city; yet no man remembered that same poor man. 16 [*] Then said I, Wisdom is better than strength: nevertheless the poor man’s wisdom is despised, and his words are not heard. 17  The words of wise men are heard in quiet more than the cry of him that ruleth among fools. 18  Wisdom is better than weapons of war: but one sinner destroyeth much good.

10

1  Dead [†]flies cause the ointment of the apothecary to send forth a stinking savour: so doth a little folly him that is in reputation for wisdom and honour. 2  A wise man’s heart is at his right hand; but a fool’s heart at his left. 3  Yea also, when he that is a fool walketh by the way, [†]his wisdom faileth him, and he saith to every one that he is a fool.

4  If the spirit of the ruler rise up against thee, leave not thy place; for yielding pacifieth great offences. 5  There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, as an error which proceedeth [†]from the ruler: 6  Folly is set [†]in great dignity, and the rich sit in low place. 7  I have seen servants [*]upon horses, and princes walking as servants upon the earth. 8 [*] He that diggeth a pit shall fall into it; and whoso breaketh an hedge, a serpent shall bite him. 9  Whoso removeth stones shall be hurt therewith; and he that cleaveth wood shall be endangered thereby. 10  If the iron be blunt, and he do not whet the edge, then must he put to more strength: but wisdom is profitable to direct. 11  Surely the serpent will bite without enchantment; and [†]a babbler is no better.

12 [*] The words of a wise man’s mouth are [†]gracious; but the lips of a fool will swallow up himself. 13  The beginning of the words of his mouth is foolishness: and the end of [†]his talk is mischievous madness. 14 [*] A fool also [†]is full of words: a man cannot tell what shall be; and [*]what shall be after him, who can tell him? 15  The labour of the foolish wearieth every one of them, because he knoweth not how to go to the city.

16 ¶ [*]Woe to thee, O land, when thy king is a child, and thy princes eat in the morning! 17  Blessed art thou, O land, when thy king is the son of nobles, and thy princes eat in due season, for strength, and not for drunkenness!

18 ¶ By much slothfulness the building decayeth; and through idleness of the hands the house droppeth through.

19 ¶ A feast is made for laughter, and [*]wine [†]maketh merry: but money answereth all things.

20 ¶ [*]Curse not the king, no not in thy [∥]thought; and curse not the rich in thy bedchamber: for a bird of the air shall carry the voice, and that which hath wings shall tell the matter.

11

1  Cast thy bread [†]upon the waters: for thou shalt find it after [*]many days. 2  Give a portion to seven, and also to eight; for thou knowest not what evil shall be upon the earth. 3  If the clouds be full of rain, they empty themselves upon the earth: and if the tree fall toward the south, or toward the north, in the place where the tree falleth, there it shall be. 4  He that observeth the wind shall not sow; and he that regardeth the clouds shall not reap. 5  As thou knowest not what is the way of the spirit, nor how the bones do grow in the womb of her that is with child: even so thou knowest not the works of God who maketh all. 6  In the morning sow thy seed, and in the evening withhold not thine hand: for thou knowest not whether [†]shall prosper, either this or that, or whether they both shall be alike good.

7 ¶ Truly the light is sweet, and a pleasant thing it is for the eyes to behold the sun: 8  But if a man live many years, and rejoice in them all; yet let him remember the days of darkness; for they shall be many. All that cometh is vanity.

9 ¶ Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth; and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thine heart, and in the sight of thine eyes: but know thou, that for all these things God will bring thee into judgment. 10  Therefore remove [∥]sorrow from thy heart, and put away evil from thy flesh: for childhood and youth are vanity.

12

1  Remember [*]now thy Creator in the days of thy youth, while the evil days come not, nor the years draw nigh, when thou shalt say, I have no pleasure in them; 2  While the sun, or the light, or the moon, or the stars, be not darkened, nor the clouds return after the rain: 3  In the day when the keepers of the house shall tremble, and the strong men shall bow themselves, and [∥]the grinders cease because they are few, and those that look out of the windows be darkened, 4  And the doors shall be shut in the streets, when the sound of the grinding is low, and he shall rise up at the voice of the bird, and all the daughters of musick shall be brought low; 5 Also when they shall be afraid of that which is high, and fears shall be in the way, and the almond tree shall flourish, and the grasshopper shall be a burden, and desire shall fail: because man goeth to his long home, and the mourners go about the streets: 6  Or ever the silver cord be loosed, or the golden bowl be broken, or the pitcher be broken at the fountain, or the wheel broken at the cistern. 7 [*] Then shall the dust return to the earth as it was: and the spirit shall return unto God who gave it.

8 ¶ [*]Vanity of vanities, saith the preacher; all is vanity. 9  And [∥]moreover, because the preacher was wise, he still taught the people knowledge; yea, he gave good heed, and sought out, and [*]set in order many proverbs. 10  The preacher sought to find out [†]acceptable words: and that which was written was upright, even words of truth. 11  The words of the wise are as goads, and as nails fastened by the masters of assemblies, which are given from one shepherd. 12  And further, by these, my son, be admonished: of making many books there is no end; and much [∥]study is a weariness of the flesh.

13 ¶ [∥]Let us hear the conclusion of the whole matter: Fear God, and keep his commandments: for this is the whole duty of man. 14  For [*]God shall bring every work into judgment, with every secret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.

* 1.2 Ps. 39. 5, 6. &c 62. 9. &c 144 4. ch. 12. 8

* 1.3 ch. 2. 22. &c 3. 9.

* 1.4 Ps. 104. 5. &c 119. 90.

† 1.5 Heb. panteth.

‡ 1.5 [1611 the]

* 1.7 Job 38. 10. Ps. 104. 8, 9.

† 1.7 Heb. return to go.

* 1.9 ch. 3. 15.

∥ 1.13 Or, to afflict them.

* 1.15 ch. 7 13.

† 1.15 Heb. defect.

* 1.16 1 Kin. 4. 30. &c 10. 7, 23.

† 1.16 Heb. had seen much.

* 1.17 ch. 2. 12 &c 7. 23.

* 2.3 ch. 1. 17.

† 2.3 Heb to draw my flesh with wine.

† 2.3 Heb. the number of the days of their life.

† 2.7 Heb. sons of my house

* 2.8 1 Kin. 9 28 &c 10. 14.

† 2.8 Heb musical instrument and instruments.

* 2.11 ch. 1. 3

* 2.12 ch 1. 17. &c 7. 25.

∥ 2.12 Or, in those things which have been already done.

† 2.13 Heb. that there is an excellency in wisdom more than in folly, &c.

* 2.14 Prov. 17. 24. ch. 8. 1.

† 2.15 Heb. happeneth to me, even to me.

‡ 2.16 [1611 omits all]

† 2.18 Heb. laboured.

* 2.18 Ps. 49. 10.

† 2.21 Heb. give.

* 2.22 ch. 1 3 &c 3. 9.

* 2.23 Job 14. 1.

* 2.24 ch 3. 12, 13, 22. &c 6. 18. &c 8. 15.

∥ 2.24 Or, delight his senses.

† 2.26 Heb. before him.

* 2.26 Job 27. 17.

† 3.2 Heb. to bear.

† 3.5 Heb. to be far from.

∥ 3.6 Or, seek.

* 3.9 ch. 1. 3

* 3.15 ch. 1. 9.

† 3.15 Heb. that which is driven away.

* 3.17 ver. 1.

∥ 3.18 Or, that they might clear God, and see, &c.

* 3.19 Ps. 49. 12. ch. 2. 16.

† 3.21 Heb. of the sons of man.

† 3.21 Heb. is ascending.

* 3.22 ch. 2. 24. &c 5. 18.

* 4.1 ch. 5. 8.

† 4.1 Heb. hand.

* 4.2 Job 3. 17, &c.

* 4.3 Job 3. 11, 16, 21.

† 4.4 Heb. all the rightness of work.

† 4.4 Heb. this is the envy of a man from his neighbour.

* 4.5 Prov. 6. 10. &c 24. 33.

* 4.6 Prov. 15. 16. &c 16. 8.

† 4.13 Heb. who knoweth not to be admonished.

* 5.1 1 Sam. 15. 22. Ps. 50. 8. Prov. 15. 8. &c 21. 27.

∥ 5.2 Or, word.

* 5.2 Prov. 10. 19. Matt. 6. 7.

* 5.4 Deut. 23. 21.

* 5.4 Ps. 66. 13. 14.

† 5.8 Heb. at the will, or, purpose.

* 5.15 Job 1. 21 Ps. 49 17. 1 Tim. 6. 7.

* 5.16 ch. 1. 3.

* 5.18 ch. 2. 24. &c 3. 12.

† 5.18 Heb. there is a good which is comely, &c.

† 5.18 Heb. the number of the days.

∥ 5.20 Or, Though he give not much, yet he remembereth, &c.

† 6.7 Heb. soul.

† 6.9 Heb. than the walking of the soul.

† 6.12 Heb. the number of the days of the life of his vanity.

* 6.12 Ps. 144. 4.

* 7.1 Prov. 15. 80. &c 22. 1.

∥ 7.3 Or, Anger.

* 7.5 Prov. 13. 18 &c 15. 31, 32.

† 7.6 Heb. sound.

* 7.7 Deut. 16. 19.

* 7.9 Prov. 14 17. &c 16. 32.

† 7.10 Heb. out of wisdom

∥ 7.11 Or, as good as an inheritance, yea, better too.

† 7.12 Heb. shadow.

* 7.13 ch 1 15.

† 7.14 Heb. made.

† 7.16 Heb. be desolate?

† 7.17 Heb not in thy time?

* 7.19 Prov. 21. 22. &c 24 5. ch. 9. 16

* 7.20 1 Kin. 8. 46. Prov. 20. 9. 1 John 1 8.

† 7.21 Heb. give not thine heart.

† 7.25 Heb. I and mine heart compassed.

* 7.26 Prov. 22 14.

† 7.26 Heb. he that is good before God.

∥ 7.27 Or, weighing one thing after another to find out the reason.

* 7.29 Gen. 1. 27.

* 8.1 Prov. 17. 24.

† 8.1 Heb. the strength.

† 8.5 Heb. shall know.

∥ 8.7 Or, how it shall be?

* 8.8 Job 14. 5.

∥ 8.8 Or, casting off weapons.

* 8.12 Ps. 37. 11, 18, 19.

* 8.14 Ps. 73. 14.

* 8.15 ch. 3. 22.

‡ 8.17 [1611 omits yet he shall not find it]

† 9.1 Heb. I gave, or, set to my heart.

* 9.2 Ps. 73. 3, 12, 13. Mal. 3. 15.

† 9.9 Heb. See, or, enjoy life.

* 9.9 ch 2. 24. &c 3 13. &c 5. 18.

* 9.12 Prov. 29. 6.

* 9.16 Prov. 21. 22. ch. 7. 19.

† 10.1 Heb. Flies of death.

† 10.3 Heb. his heart.

† 10.5 Heb. from before.

† 10.6 Heb. in great heights

* 10.7 Prov. 30 22.

* 10.8 Ps. 7 15. Prov. 26. 27.

† 10.11 Heb. the master of the tongue.

* 10.12 Prov. 10. 32. &c 12 13.

† 10.12 Heb. grace.

† 10.13 Heb. his mouth.

* 10.14 Prov. 15 2.

† 10.14 Heb. multiplieth words.

* 10.14 ch 3 22. &c 6 12

* 10.16 Is. 3. 4, 5.

* 10.19 Ps. 104. 15,

† 10.19 Heb. maketh glad the life.

* 10.20 Ex. 22. 28.

∥ 10.20 Or, conscience.

† 11.1 Heb. upon the face of the waters.

* 11.1 Deut. 15 10. Prov 19. 17. Matt. 10. 42.

† 11.6 Heb. shall be right.

∥ 11.10 Or, anger.

* 12.1 Prov. 22 6.

∥ 12.3 Or, the grinders fail, because they grind little.

* 12.7 Gen. 3. 19.

* 12.8 ch. 1. 2.

∥ 12.9 Or, the more wise the preacher was, &c.

* 12.9 1 Kin. 4. 32.

† 12.10 Heb. words of delight.

∥ 12.12 Or, reading.

∥ 12.13 Or, The end of the matter, even all that hath been heard, is.

* 12.14 Rom. 2 16. &c 14. 10. 2 Cor. 5. 10.

Esther (Greek)

10

11
12
13
14
15
16

The Rest of the Chapters of the Book of Esther

10

PART OF THE TENTH CHAPTER AFTER THE GREEK

4 Then Mardocheus said, God hath done these things.

5 For I remember [a]a dream which I saw concerning these matters, and nothing thereof hath failed.

6 A little fountain became a river, and there was light, and the sun, and much water: this river is Esther, whom the king married, and made queen:

7 And the two dragons are I and Aman.

8 And the nations were those that were assembled to destroy the name of the Jews:

9 And my nation is this Israel, which cried to God, and were saved: for the Lord hath saved his people, and the Lord hath delivered us from all those evils, and God hath wrought [b]signs and great wonders, which have not been done among the Gentiles.

10 Therefore hath he made two [c]lots, one for the people of God, and another for all the Gentiles.

11 And these two lots came at the hour, and time, and [d]day of judgment, before God among all nations.

12 So God remembered his people, and justified his inheritance.

13 Therefore those days shall be unto them [e]in the month Adar, [e]the fourteenth and fifteenth day of the same month, with an assembly, and joy, and with gladness before God, according to the generations for ever among his people.

11

1 In [*]the fourth year of the reign of [a]Ptolemeus and Cleopatra, Dositheus, who said he was a priest and Levite, and Ptolemeus his son, brought this epistle of [b]Phurim, which they said was the same, and that Lysimachus the son of Ptolemeus, that was in Jerusalem, had interpreted it.

[PLACED IN THE GREEK BEFORE CHAP. 1.1 OF THE HEBREW]

2 In [c]the second year of the reign of Artexerxes the great, in the first day of the month Nisan, [d]Mardocheus the son of Jairus, the son of Semei, the son of Cisai, of the tribe of Benjamin, had [e]a dream;

3 [d]Who was a Jew, and dwelt in the city of [f]Susa, a great man, being a [g]servitor in the king’s court.

4 [h]He was also one of the captives, which Nabuchodonosor the king of Babylon carried from Jerusalem with Jechonias king of Judea; and this was his [e]dream:

5 Behold a noise of a tumult, with thunder, and earthquakes, and uproar in the land:

6 And, behold, two great dragons came forth ready to fight, and their cry was great.

7 And at their cry all nations were prepared to battle, that they might fight against the righteous people.

8 And lo [i]a day of darkness and obscurity, [k]tribulation and anguish, affliction and great uproar, upon earth.

9 And the whole righteous nation was troubled, fearing their own evils, and were ready to perish.

10 Then they cried unto God, and upon their cry, as it were from a little fountain, was made a great flood, even much water.

11 The light and the sun rose up, and the lowly were exalted, and devoured [l]the glorious.

12 Now when Mardocheus, who had seen this [e]dream, and what God had determined to do, was awake, he bare this dream in mind, and until night by all means was desirous to know it.

12

1 And [a]Mardocheus took his rest in the court with Gabatha and Tharra, the two eunuchs of the king, and keepers of the palace.

2 And [b]he heard their devices, and searched out their purposes, and learned that they were about to lay hands upon Artexerxes the king; and so he certified the king of them.

3 Then the king examined the two eunuchs, and after that they had confessed it, they were strangled.

4 And the king made a record of these things, and Mardocheus also wrote thereof.

5 So the king commanded, Mardocheus to serve in the court, and for this he rewarded him.

6 Howbeit [c]Aman the son of Amadathus the [c]Agagite, who was [d]in great honour with the king, sought to molest Mardocheus and his people because of the two eunuchs of the king.

13

[PLACED IN THE GREEK AFTER CHAP. 3.13 OF THE HEBREW]

1 The copy of the letters was this: [a]The great king Artexerxes writeth these things to the princes and governours that are under him [b]from India unto Ethiopia in an hundred and seven and twenty provinces.

2 After that I became lord over many nations and had dominion over the whole [c]world, not lifted up with presumption of my authority, but carrying myself always with equity and mildness, I purposed to settle [cc]my subjects continually in a quiet life, and making my kingdom [*]peaceable, and open for passage to the utmost coasts, to renew peace, which is desired of all men.

3 Now when I asked my counsellors how this might be brought to pass, Aman, that excelled in wisdom among us, and was [d]approved for his constant good will and steadfast fidelity, and [e]had the honour of the second place in the kingdom,

4 [f]Declared unto us, that in all nations throughout [c]the world there was scattered a certain malicious people, that had laws contrary to all nations, and continually despised the commandments of kings, so as the uniting of our kingdoms, honourably [g]intended by us cannot [*]go forward.

5 Seeing then we understand that this people alone is continually in opposition unto all men, differing in the strange manner of their laws, and evil affected to our state, working all the mischief they can that our kingdom may not be firmly established:

6 Therefore have we commanded, that all they that are signified in writing unto you by Aman, who is ordained over the affairs, and is [*]next unto us, shall all, with their wives and children, be utterly destroyed by the sword of their enemies, without all mercy and pity, the [h]fourteenth day of the twelfth month Adar of this present year:

7 That they, who of old and now also are malicious, may in one day with violence go into the grave, and so ever hereafter cause our affairs to be well settled, and without trouble.

[PLACED IN THE GREEK AFTER CHAP. 4.17 OF THE HEBREW]

8 Then Mardocheus thought upon all the works of the Lord, and made his prayer unto him,

9 Saying, O Lord, Lord, the King [i]Almighty: for the whole world is in thy power, and if thou hast appointed to save Israel, there is no man that can gainsay thee:

10 [j]For thou hast made heaven and earth, and all the wondrous things under the heaven.

11 Thou art Lord of all things, and and there is no man that can resist thee, which art the Lord.

12 [k]Thou knowest all things, and thou knowest, Lord, that it was neither in contempt nor pride, nor for any desire of glory, that [l]I did not bow down to proud Aman.

13 For [m]I could have been content with good will for the salvation of Israel to kiss the soles of his feet.

14 But I did this, that I might not prefer the glory of man above the glory of God: [n]neither will I worship any but thee, O God, neither will I do it in pride.

15 And now, O Lord God and King, [o]spare thy people: for their eyes are upon us to bring us to nought; yea, they desire to destroy the inheritance, that hath been thine from the beginning.

16 Despise not the portion, [p]which thou hast delivered out of Egypt for thine own self.

17 Hear my prayer, and be merciful unto thine inheritance: [q]turn our sorrow into joy, that we may live, O Lord, and praise thy name: and [*][r]destroy not the mouths of them that praise thee, O Lord.

18 All Israel in like manner cried [*]most earnestly unto the Lord, because their death was before their eyes.

14

1 Queen Esther also, being in fear of death, resorted unto the Lord:

2 And laid away her glorious apparel, and put on [a]the garments of anguish and mourning: and [b]instead of precious ointments, [a]she covered her head with ashes and dung, and [c]she humbled her body greatly, and all the places of her joy she filled [b][d]with her torn hair.

3 And she prayed unto the Lord God of Israel, saying, O my Lord, thou only art our King: help me, desolate woman, which have no helper but thee:

4 For [e]my danger is in mine hand.

5 From my youth up I have heard in the tribe of my family that thou, O Lord, [f]tookest Israel from among all people, and [g]our fathers from all their predecessors, for a perpetual inheritance, and thou hast performed whatsoever thou didst promise them.

6 [h]And now we have sinned before thee: therefore hast thou given us into the hands of our enemies,

7 Because we worshipped their gods: O Lord, [i]thou art righteous.

8 Nevertheless it satisfieth them not, that we are in bitter captivity: but they have [k]stricken hands with their idols,

9 That they will abolish the thing that thou with thy mouth hast ordained, and destroy thine inheritance, and [l]stop the mouth of them that praise thee, and quench the glory of thy house, and of thine altar,

10 And open the mouths of the heathen to set forth the praises of the [*]idols, and [m]to magnify a fleshly king for ever.

11 O Lord, give not thy sceptre unto them that [*]be nothing, and let them not laugh at our fall; but turn their device upon themselves, and [n]make him an example, that hath begun this against us.

12 Remember, O Lord, [o]make thyself known in time of our affliction, and give me boldness, O King of the [*]nations, and Lord of all power.

13 Give me eloquent speech in my mouth before [p]the lion: turn his heart to hate [q]him that fighteth against us, that there may be an end of him, and of all that are likeminded to him:

14 But deliver us with thine hand, and help me that am desolate, and which have no other help but thee.

15 [r]Thou knowest all things, O Lord; thou knowest that I hate the glory of the unrighteous, and abhor the bed of the uncircumcised, and of [*]all the heathen.

16 Thou knowest my necessity: for I abhor the sign of my [*]high estate, [s]which is upon mine head in the days wherein I shew myself, and that I abhor it [t]as a menstruous rag, and that I wear it not when I am [*]private by myself.

17 And that thine handmaid [u]hath not eaten at Aman’s table, and that I have not greatly esteemed the king’s feast, nor drunk the wine of the drink offerings.

18 Neither had thine handmaid any joy since the day [*]that I was brought hither to this present, but in thee, O Lord God of Abraham.

19 O thou mighty God above all, hear the voice of the [x]forlorn and deliver us out of the hands of the mischievous, and deliver me out of [y]my fear.

15

1 [*]And upon the third day, when she had ended her prayers, [a]she laid away her mourning garments, and put on her glorious apparel.

2 And being gloriously adorned, after she had called upon God, who is the [b]beholder and [c]saviour of all things, she took two [d]maids with her:

3 And upon the one she leaned, as carrying herself [*]daintily;

4 And the other followed, bearing up her train.

5 And she was [*]ruddy through the perfection of her beauty, and her countenance was cheerful [*]and very amiable: but her heart was in anguish [e]for fear.

6 Then having passed through all the doors, she stood before the king, who sat upon his royal throne, and was clothed with all his robes of majesty, all glittering with gold and precious stones; and he was very dreadful.

7 Then lifting up his countenance that shone with majesty, he looked very fiercely upon her: and the queen fell down, and was pale, and [h]fainted, and bowed herself upon the head of the [d]maid that went [*]before her.

8 Then God changed the spirit of the king into mildness, who [*]in a fear leaped from his throne, and took her in his arms, till she came to herself again, and comforted her with loving words and said unto her,

9 Esther, what is the matter? I am [f]thy brother, be of good cheer:

10 Thou shalt not die, though our commandment be [*]general: come near.

11 And so he held up his golden sceptre, and laid it upon her neck,

12 And embraced her, and said, Speak unto me.

13 Then said she unto him, I saw thee, my lord, [g]as an angel of God, and my heart was troubled for fear of thy majesty.

14 For wonderful art thou, lord, and thy countenance is full of grace.

15 And as she was speaking, [*]she fell down for [h]faintness.

16 Then the king was troubled, and all his servants comforted her.

16

[PLACED IN THE GREEK AFTER CHAP. 8.12 OF THE HEBREW]

1 [a]The great king Artexerxes unto the princes and governors of an hundred and seven and twenty provinces [b]from India unto Ethiopia, and unto all [*]our faithful subjects, greeting.

2 Many, the more often they are honoured with the great bounty of [*]their gracious princes, the more proud they are waxen,

3 And endeavour to hurt not [c]our subjects only, but not being able to bear abundance, do take in hand to practise also against those that do them good:

4 And take not only thankfulness away from among men, but also lifted up with the glorious words of [*]lewd persons, [*]that were never good, they think to escape the justice of God, [d]that seeth all things and hateth evil.

5 Oftentimes also fair speech [*]of those, that are put in trust to manage their friends’ affairs, hath caused many that are in authority to be partakers of innocent blood, and hath enwrapped them in remediless calamities:

6 Beguiling with the falsehood and deceit of their [e]lewd disposition the innocency and goodness of princes.

7 Now ye may see this, as we have declared, not so much by ancient histories, as ye may, if ye search what hath been wickedly done of late through the pestilent behaviour of them that are unworthily placed in authority.

8 And we must take care for the time to come, that our kingdom may be quiet and peaceable for all men,

9 Both by changing our purposes, and always judging things that are evident with more equal proceeding.

10 For Aman, [f]a Macedonian, the son of [g]Amadatha, being indeed a stranger from the Persian blood, and far distant from our goodness, and as a stranger received of us,

11 Had so far forth obtained the favour that we shew toward every nation, as that he was called our [h]father, and was continually honoured of all [i]the next person unto the king.

12 But he, not bearing his [j]great dignity, went about to deprive us of our kingdom and life:

13 Having by manifold and cunning deceits sought of us the destruction, as well of Mardocheus, who saved our life, and continually procured our good, as also of blameless Esther, partaker of our kingdom, with their whole nation.

14 For by these means he thought, finding us destitute of friends, to have translated the kingdom of the Persians to the Macedonians.

15 But we find that the Jews, whom this wicked wretch hath delivered to utter destruction, are no evildoers, but live by most just laws:

16 And that they be children of [k]the most high and most mighty, [l]living God, who hath [*]ordered the kingdom both unto us and to our progenitors in the most excellent manner.

17 Wherefore ye shall do well not to put in execution the letters sent unto you by Aman the son of [g]Amadatha.

18 For he that was the worker of these things, [m]is hanged at the gates of [n]Susa [o]with all his family: God, who ruleth all things, speedily rendering vengeance to him according to his deserts.

19 Therefore ye shall publish the copy of this letter in all places, that the Jews may freely live after their own laws.

20 And ye shall aid them, that even the same day, being the thirteenth day of the twelfth month Adar, they may be avenged on them, who in the time of their affliction shall set upon them.

21 For [p]Almighty God hath turned to joy unto them the day, wherein [q]the chosen people should have perished.

22 Ye shall therefore among your solemn feasts keep it an high day with all feasting:

23 That both now and hereafter there may be safety to us and the well affected Persians; but to those which do conspire against us a memorial of destruction.

24 Therefore [r]every city and country whatsoever, which shall not do according to these things, shall be destroyed without mercy with fire and sword, and shall be made not only unpassable for men, but also most hateful to wild beasts and fowls for ever.

a 10.5 ch. 11. 2, 4–11.

b 10.9 So Ex. 7. 3.

c 10.10 Comp. ch. 3. 7.

d 10.11 See Judith 16. 17.

e 10.13 ch. 9. 21.

e 10.13 ch. 9. 21.

* 11.1 [B.C. 177].

a 11.1 1 Macc. 1. 18. & 10. 51, 55, 57. & 11. 3, 8, 13, 15, 17, 18. 2 Macc. 4. 21. [Joseph. Antiq. lib. 13. cap. 3].

b 11.1 ch. 9. 26, 28, 29.

c 11.2 Comp. ch. 1. 3.

d 11.2 ch. 2. 5 (Gk.).

e 11.2 ch. 10. 5–12.

d 11.3 ch. 2. 5 (Gk.).

f 11.3 See Neh. 1. 1.

g 11.3 2 Kin. 4. 43 (Engl.).

h 11.4 ch. 2. 6.

e 11.4 ch. 10. 5–12.

i 11.8 Joel 2. 2 (Gk.).

k 11.8 2 Esdr. 16. 19. Rom. 2. 9. & 8. 35.

l 11.11 ch. 12. 6 (Gk.).

e 11.12 ch. 10. 5–12.

a 12.1 Comp. ch. 2. 21. & 6. 2.

b 12.2 Comp. ch. 2. 22.

c 12.6 ch. 3. 1 (Gk.). Comp. ch. 16. 10.

c 12.6 ch. 3. 1 (Gk.). Comp. ch. 16. 10.

d 12.6 ch. 11. 11 (Gk.).

a 13.1 To ver. 7, Joseph. Antiq. lib. 11. cap. 6. [6].

b 13.1 ch. 1. 1. & 16. 1.

c 13.2 ver. 4. Wisd. 1. 7. Baruch 6. 62. Song 22. See Matt. 24. 14.

cc 13.2 ch. 16. 3.

* 13.2 Or, mild. 1 Tim. 2. 2 (Gk.).

d 13.3 Acts 2. 22.

e 13.3 So ver. 6. See ch. 10. 3.

f 13.4 ch. 3. 8.

c 13.4 ver. 4. Wisd. 1. 7. Baruch 6. 62. Song 22. See Matt. 24. 14.

g 13.4 ch. 16. 16 (Gk.).

* 13.4 Or, be settled.

* 13.6 Or, second from us. So Judith 2. 4. ver. 3. ch. 16. 11.

h 13.6 Comp. ch. 3. 13.

i 13.9 So ch. 16. 21. See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

j 13.10 See Judith 16. 14.

k 13.12 So ch. 14. 15. John 21. 17. See 1 Sam. 16. 7.

l 13.12 ch. 3. 2, 5.

m 13.13 Comp. Rom. 9. 3 (Gk.).

n 13.14 ver. 12.

o 13.15 Joel 2. 17. 2 Esdr. 8. 45.

p 13.16 Deut. 9. 26. 2 Sam. 7. 23.

q 13.17 So Jer. 31. 13. John 16. 20.

* 13.17 Or, shut, or, stop not.

r 13.17 ch. 14. 9.

* 13.18 Gr. mightily.

a 14.2 So Baruch 4. 20. See ch. 4. 1.

b 14.2 So Isai. 3. 24.

a 14.2 So Baruch 4. 20. See ch. 4. 1.

c 14.2 ch. 4. 16.

b 14.2 So Isai. 3. 24.

d 14.2 So Ezra 9. 3.

e 14.4 Judg. 12. 3. 1 Sam. 19. 5. & 28. 21. Job 13. 14. Ps. 119. 109.

f 14.5 Deut. 4. 34.

g 14.5 Josh. 24. 2, 3.

h 14.6 So Judg. 2. 11–15.

i 14.7 See Ezra 9. 15.

k 14.8 See 1 Chr. 29. 24.

l 14.9 Gk. not as ch. 13. 17 marg.

* 14.10 Gr. vain things.

m 14.10 Judith 3. 8.

* 14.11 Gr. be not. Comp. Ecclus. 38. 11. & 44. 9.

n 14.11 Matt. 1. 19. Heb. 6. 6 in the Gk.

o 14.12 So Ezek. 35. 11.

* 14.12 Or, gods.

p 14.13 2 Tim. 4. 17.

q 14.13 ch. 3. 6.

r 14.15 See ch. 13. 12.

* 14.15 Gr. every stranger.

* 14.16 Gr. pride. ch. 16. 12 (Gk.).

s 14.16 ch. 2. 17.

t 14.16 Isai. 30. 22.

* 14.16 Gr. quiet, or, private.

u 14.17 So Judith 12. 2. See Tobit 1. 10.

* 14.18 Gr. of my change.

x 14.19 Judith 9. 11 (Gk.).

y 14.19 ch. 15. 5. So ver. 1.

* 15.1 [To ver. 16, substituted in the Greek for ch. 5. 1, 2 of the Hebrew].

a 15.1 ch. 14. 2. Comp. Baruch 5. 1.

b 15.2 So ch. 16. 4. Wisd. 1. 6.

c 15.2 Judith 9. 11.

d 15.2 See Judith 8. 33.

* 15.3 Or, delicately.

* 15.5 Or, rosecoloured.

* 15.5 Or, as amiable, or, smiling.

e 15.5 ch. 14. 19.

h 15.7 ver. 7 (Gk.).

d 15.7 See Judith 8. 33.

* 15.7 Or, with her, or, by her. Comp. ver. 2, 3.

* 15.8 Gr. in an agony. So ch. 14. 1 (Gk.).

f 15.9 Comp. Tobit 5. 20. & 7. 16. & 8. 4, 7. See Cant. 4. 9.

* 15.10 Or, as well thine as mine.

g 15.13 See 1 Sam. 29. 9.

* 15.15 Or, she fell in a swoon.

h 15.15 ver. 7 (Gk.).

a 16.1 To ver. 24, Joseph. Antiq. lib. 11. cap. 6. [12.].

b 16.1 ch. 1. 1. & 13. 1.

* 16.1 Or, well affected to our state.

* 16.2 Gr. their benefactors.

c 16.3 ch. 13. 2.

* 16.4 Or, needy.

* 16.4 Or, that never tasted prosperity.

d 16.4 See ch. 15. 2.

* 16.5 Or, of our friends, put in trust to manage the affairs.

e 16.6 Rom. 1. 29 (Gk.).

f 16.10 Comp. ch. 12. 6.

g 16.10 Gk. as ch. 12. 6. Comp. ch. 3. 1.

h 16.11 Gen. 45. 8.

i 16.11 See ch. 13. 6.

j 16.12 ch. 14. 16 (Gk.).

k 16.16 See 1 Esdr. 6. 31.

l 16.16 Bel and Drag. 5, 24. So 2 Macc. 7. 33. & 15. 4. See Ps. 42. 2.

* 16.16 Or, prospered. ch. 13. 4 (Gk.).

g 16.17 Gk. as ch. 12. 6. Comp. ch. 3. 1.

m 16.18 ch. 7. 10.

n 16.18 See Neh. 1. 1.

o 16.18 ch. 9. 10.

p 16.21 So ch. 13. 9. See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

q 16.21 2 Esdr. 15. 21, 53, 56. & 16. 73. Tobit 8. 15 (Gk.). Wisd. 3. 9. & 4. 15. Ecclus. 17. 10. & 46. 1. & 47. 22. & 49. 13.

r 16.24 So ch. 8. 11.

Exodus

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30

31
32
33
34
35
36
37
38
39
40

The Second Book of Moses, called Exodus

1

1 Now [*]these are the names of the children of Israel, which came into Egypt; every man and his household came with Jacob. 2  Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah, 3  Issachar, Zebulun, and Benjamin, 4  Dan, and Naphtali, Gad, and Asher. 5  And all the souls that came out of the [†]loins of Jacob were [*]seventy souls: for Joseph was in Egypt already. 6  And Joseph died, and all his brethren, and all that generation.

7 ¶ [*]And the children of Israel were fruitful, and increased abundantly, and multiplied, and waxed exceeding mighty; and the land was filled with them.

8  Now there arose up a new king over Egypt, which knew not Joseph. 9  And he said unto his people, Behold, the people of the children of Israel are more and mightier than we: 10  Come on, let us deal wisely with them; lest they multiply, and it come to pass, that, when there falleth out any war, they join also unto our enemies, and fight against us, and so get them up out of the land. 11  Therefore they did set over them taskmasters to afflict them with their burdens. And they built for Pharaoh treasure cities, Pithom and Raamses. 12 [†] But the more they afflicted them, the more they multiplied and grew. And they were grieved because of the children of Israel. 13  And the Egyptians made the children of Israel to serve with rigour: 14  And they made their lives bitter with hard bondage, in morter, and in brick, and in all manner of service in the field: all their service, wherein they made them serve, was with rigour.

15 ¶ And the king of Egypt spake to the Hebrew midwives, of which the name of the one was Shiphrah, and the name of the other Puah: 16  And he said, When ye do the office of a midwife to the Hebrew women, and see them upon the stools; if it be a son, then ye shall kill him: but if it be a daughter, then she shall live. 17  But the midwives feared God, and did not as the king of Egypt commanded them, but saved the men children alive. 18  And the king of Egypt called for the midwives, and said unto them, Why have ye done this thing, and have saved the men children alive? 19  And the midwives said unto Pharaoh, Because the Hebrew women are not as the Egyptian women; for they are lively, and are delivered ere the midwives come in unto them. 20  Therefore God dealt well with the midwives: and the people multiplied, and waxed very mighty. 21  And it came to pass, because the midwives feared God, that he made them houses. 22  And Pharaoh charged all his people, saying, Every son that is born ye shall cast into the river, and every daughter ye shall save alive.

2

1  And there went [*]a man of the house of Levi, and took to wife a daughter of Levi. 2  And the woman conceived, and bare a son: and when she saw him that he was a goodly child, she [*]hid him three months. 3  And when she could not longer hide him, she took for him an ark of bulrushes, and daubed it with slime and with pitch, and put the child therein; and she laid it in the flags by the river’s brink. 4  And his sister stood afar off, to wit what would be done to him.

5 ¶ And the daughter of Pharaoh came down to wash herself at the river; and her maidens walked along by the river’s side; and when she saw the ark among the flags, she sent her maid to fetch it. 6  And when she had opened it, she saw the child: and, behold, the babe wept. And she had compassion on him, and said, This is one of the Hebrews’ children. 7  Then said his sister to Pharaoh’s daughter, Shall I go and call to thee a nurse of the Hebrew women, that she may nurse the child for thee? 8  And Pharaoh’s daughter said to her, Go. And the maid went and called the child’s mother. 9  And Pharaoh’s daughter said unto her, Take this child away, and nurse it for me, and I will give thee thy wages. And the woman took the child, and nursed it. 10  And the child grew, and she brought him unto Pharaoh’s daughter, and he became her son. And she called his name [∥]Moses: and she said, Because I drew him out of the water.

11 ¶ And it came to pass in those days, when Moses was grown, that he went out unto his brethren, and looked on their burdens: and he spied an Egyptian smiting an Hebrew, one of his brethren. 12  And he looked this way and that way, and when he saw that there was no man, he slew the Egyptian, and hid him in the sand. 13  And when he went out the second day, behold, two men of the Hebrews strove together: and he said to him that did the wrong, Wherefore smitest thou thy fellow? 14  And he said, Who made thee [†]a prince and a judge over us? intendest thou to kill me, as thou killedst the Egyptian? And Moses feared, and said, Surely this thing is known. 15  Now when Pharaoh heard this thing, he sought to slay Moses. But Moses fled from the face of Pharaoh, and dwelt in the land of Midian: and he sat down by a well.

16  Now the [∥]priest of Midian had seven daughters: and they came and drew water, and filled the troughs to water their father’s flock. 17  And the shepherds came and drove them away: but Moses stood up and helped them, and watered their flock. 18  And when they came to Reuel their father, he said, How is it that ye are come so soon to day? 19  And they said, An Egyptian delivered us out of the hand of the shepherds, and also drew water enough for us, and watered the flock. 20  And he said unto his daughters, And where is he? why is it that ye have left the man? call him, that he may eat bread. 21  And Moses was content to dwell with the man: and he gave Moses Zipporah his daughter. 22  And she bare him a son, and he called his name [*]Gershom: for he said, I have been a stranger in a strange land.

23 ¶ And it came to pass in process of time, that the king of Egypt died: and the children of Israel sighed by reason of the bondage, and they cried, and their cry came up unto God by reason of the bondage. 24  And God heard their groaning, and God remembered his [*]covenant with Abraham, with Isaac, and with Jacob. 25  And God looked upon the children of Israel, and God [†]had respect unto them.

3

1  Now Moses kept the flock of Jethro his father in law, the priest of Midian: and he led the flock to the backside of the desert, and came to the mountain of God, even to Horeb. 2  And the angel of the LORD appeared unto him in a [*]flame of fire out of the midst of a bush: and he looked, and, behold, the bush burned with fire, and the bush was not consumed. 3  And Moses said, I will now turn aside, and see this great sight, why the bush is not burnt. 4  And when the LORD saw that he turned aside to see, God called unto him out of the midst of the bush, and said, Moses, Moses. And he said, Here am I. 5  And he said, Draw not nigh hither: [*]put off thy shoes from off thy feet, for the place whereon thou standest is holy ground. 6  Moreover he said, [*]I am the God of thy father, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob. And Moses hid his face; for he was afraid to look upon God.

7 ¶ And the LORD said, I have surely seen the affliction of my people which are in Egypt, and have heard their cry by reason of their taskmasters; for I know their sorrows; 8  And I am come down to deliver them out of the hand of the Egyptians, and to bring them up out of that land unto a good land and a large, unto a land flowing with milk and honey; unto the place of the Canaanites, and the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites. 9  Now therefore, behold, the cry of the children of Israel is come unto me: and I have also seen the oppression wherewith the Egyptians oppress them. 10  Come now therefore, and I will send thee unto Pharaoh, that thou mayest bring forth my people the children of Israel out of Egypt.

11 ¶ And Moses said unto God, Who am I, that I should go unto Pharaoh, and that I should bring forth the children of Israel out of Egypt? 12  And he said, Certainly I will be with thee; and this shall be a token unto thee, that I have sent thee: When thou hast brought forth the people out of Egypt, ye shall serve God upon this mountain. 13  And Moses said unto God, Behold, when I come unto the children of Israel, and shall say unto them, The God of your fathers hath sent me unto you; and they shall say to me, What is his name? what shall I say unto them? 14  And God said unto Moses, I AM THAT I AM: and he said, Thus shalt thou say unto the children of Israel, I AM hath sent me unto you. 15  And God said moreover unto Moses, Thus shalt thou say unto the children of Israel, The LORD God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, hath sent me unto you: this is my name for ever, and this is my memorial unto all generations.

16  Go, and gather the elders of Israel together, and say unto them, The LORD God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Jacob, appeared unto me, saying, I have surely visited you, and seen that which is done to you in Egypt: 17  And I have said, I will bring you up out of the affliction of Egypt unto the land of the Canaanites, and the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, unto a land flowing with milk and honey. 18  And they shall hearken to thy voice: and thou shalt come, thou and the elders of Israel, unto the king of Egypt, and ye shall say unto him, The LORD God of the Hebrews hath met with us: and now let us go, we beseech thee, three days’ journey into the wilderness, that we may sacrifice to the LORD our God.

19 ¶ And I am sure that the king of Egypt will not let you go, [∥]no, not by a mighty hand. 20  And I will stretch out my hand, and smite Egypt with all my wonders which I will do in the midst thereof: and after that he will let you go. 21  And I will give this people favour in the sight of the Egyptians: and it shall come to pass, that, when ye go, ye shall not go empty: 22 [*] But every woman shall borrow of her neighbour, and of her that sojourneth in her house, jewels of silver, and jewels of gold, and raiment: and ye shall put them upon your sons, and upon your daughters; and ye shall spoil [∥]the Egyptians.

4

1  And Moses answered and said, But, behold, they will not believe me, nor hearken unto my voice: for they will say, The LORD hath not appeared unto thee. 2  And the LORD said unto him, What is that in thine hand? And he said, A rod. 3  And he said, Cast it on the ground. And he cast it on the ground, and it became a serpent; and Moses fled from before it. 4  And the LORD said unto Moses, Put forth thine hand, and take it by the tail. And he put forth his hand, and caught it, and it became a rod in his hand: 5  That they may believe that the LORD God of their fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, hath appeared unto thee.

6 ¶ And the LORD said furthermore unto him, Put now thine hand into thy bosom. And he put his hand into his bosom: and when he took it out, behold, his hand was leprous as snow. 7  And he said, Put thine hand into thy bosom again. And he put his hand into his bosom again; and plucked it out of his bosom, and, behold, it was turned again as his other flesh. 8  And it shall come to pass, if they will not believe thee, neither hearken to the voice of the first sign, that they will believe the voice of the latter sign. 9  And it shall come to pass, if they will not believe also these two signs, neither hearken unto thy voice, that thou shalt take of the water of the river, and pour it upon the dry land: and the water which thou takest out of the river [†]shall become blood upon the dry land.

10 ¶ And Moses said unto the LORD, O my Lord, I am not [†]eloquent, neither [†]heretofore, nor since thou hast spoken unto thy servant: but I am slow of speech, and of a slow tongue. 11  And the LORD said unto him, Who hath made man’s mouth? or who maketh the dumb, or deaf, or the seeing, or the blind? have not I the LORD? 12  Now therefore go, and I will be [*]with thy mouth, and teach thee what thou shalt say. 13  And he said, O my Lord, send, I pray thee, by the hand of him whom thou [∥]wilt send. 14  And the anger of the LORD was kindled against Moses, and he said, Is not Aaron the Levite thy brother? I know that he can speak well. And also, behold, he cometh forth to meet thee: and when he seeth thee, he will be glad in his heart. 15  And thou shalt speak unto him, and put words in his mouth: and I will be with thy mouth, and with his mouth, and will teach you what ye shall do. 16  And he shall be thy spokesman unto the people: and he shall be, even he shall be to thee instead of a mouth, and [*]thou shalt be to him instead of God. 17  And thou shalt take this rod in thine hand, wherewith thou shalt do signs.

18 ¶ And Moses went and returned to Jethro his father in law, and said unto him, Let me go, I pray thee, and return unto my brethren which are in Egypt, and see whether they be yet alive. And Jethro said to Moses, Go in peace. 19  And the LORD said unto Moses in Midian, Go, return into Egypt: for all the men are dead which sought thy life. 20  And Moses took his wife and his sons, and set them upon an ass, and he returned to the land of Egypt: and Moses took the rod of God in his hand. 21  And the LORD said unto Moses, When thou goest to return into Egypt, see that thou do all those wonders before Pharaoh, which I have put in thine hand: but I will harden his heart, that he shall not let the people go. 22  And thou shalt say unto Pharaoh, Thus saith the LORD, Israel is my son, even my firstborn: 23  And I say unto thee, Let my son go, that he may serve me: and if thou refuse to let him go, behold, I will slay thy son, even thy firstborn.

24 ¶ And it came to pass by the way in the inn, that the LORD met him, and sought to kill him. 25  Then Zipporah took a sharp [∥]stone, and cut off the foreskin of her son, and [†]cast it at his feet, and said, Surely a bloody husband art thou to me. 26  So he let him go: then she said, A bloody husband thou art, because of the circumcision.

27 ¶ And the LORD said to Aaron, Go into the wilderness to meet Moses. And he went, and met him in the mount of God, and kissed him. 28  And Moses told Aaron all the words of the LORD who had sent him, and all the signs which he had commanded him.

29 ¶ And Moses and Aaron went and gathered together all the elders of the children of Israel: 30  And Aaron spake all the words which the LORD had spoken unto Moses, and did the signs in the sight of the people. 31  And the people believed: and when they heard that the LORD had visited the children of Israel, and that he had looked upon their affliction, then they bowed their heads and worshipped.

5

1  And afterward Moses and Aaron went in, and told Pharaoh, Thus saith the LORD God of Israel, Let my people go, that they may hold a feast unto me in the wilderness. 2  And Pharaoh said, Who is the LORD, that I should obey his voice to let Israel go? I know not the LORD, neither will I let Israel go.

3  And they said, [*]The God of the Hebrews hath met with us: let us go, we pray thee, three days’ journey into the desert, and sacrifice unto the LORD our God; lest he fall upon us with pestilence, or with the sword. 4  And the king of Egypt said unto them, Wherefore do ye, Moses and Aaron, let the people from their works? get you unto your burdens. 5  And Pharaoh said, Behold, the people of the land now are many, and ye make them rest from their burdens. 6  And Pharaoh commanded the same day the taskmasters of the people, and their officers, saying, 7  Ye shall no more give the people straw to make brick, as heretofore: let them go and gather straw for themselves. 8  And the tale of the bricks, which they did make heretofore, ye shall lay upon them; ye shall not diminish ought thereof: for they be idle; therefore they cry, saying, Let us go and sacrifice to our God. 9 [†] Let there more work be laid upon the men, that they may labour therein; and let them not regard vain words.

10 ¶ And the taskmasters of the people went out, and their officers, and they spake to the people, saying, Thus saith Pharaoh, I will not give you straw. 11  Go ye, get you straw where ye can find it: yet not ought of your work shall be diminished. 12  So the people were scattered abroad throughout all the land of Egypt to gather stubble instead of straw. 13  And the taskmasters hasted them, saying, Fulfil your works, your [†]daily tasks, as when there was straw. 14  And the officers of the children of Israel, which Pharaoh’s taskmasters had set over them, were beaten, and demanded, Wherefore have ye not fulfilled your task in making brick both yesterday and to day, as heretofore?

15 ¶ Then the officers of the children of Israel came and cried unto Pharaoh, saying, Wherefore dealest thou thus with thy servants? 16  There is no straw given unto thy servants, and they say to us, Make brick: and, behold, thy servants are beaten; but the fault is in thine own people. 17  But he said, Ye are idle, ye are idle: therefore ye say, Let us go and do sacrifice to the LORD. 18  Go therefore now, and work; for there shall no straw be given you, yet shall ye deliver the tale of bricks. 19  And the officers of the children of Israel did see that they were in evil case, after it was said, Ye shall not minish ought from your bricks of your daily task.

20 ¶ And they met Moses and Aaron, who stood in the way, as they came forth from Pharaoh: 21  And they said unto them, The LORD look upon you, and judge; because ye have made our savour [†]to be abhorred in the eyes of Pharaoh, and in the eyes of his servants, to put a sword in their hand to slay us. 22  And Moses returned unto the LORD, and said, Lord, wherefore hast thou so evil entreated this people? why is it that thou hast sent me? 23  For since I came to Pharaoh to speak in thy name, he hath done evil to this people; [†]neither hast thou delivered thy people at all.

6

1  Then the LORD said unto Moses, Now shalt thou see what I will do to Pharaoh: for with a strong hand shall he let them go, and with a strong hand shall he drive them out of his land. 2  And God spake unto Moses, and said unto him, I am the LORD: 3  And I appeared unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob, by the name of God Almighty, but by my name JEHOVAH was I not known to them. 4  And I have also established my covenant with them, to give them the land of Canaan, the land of their pilgrimage, wherein they were strangers. 5  And I have also heard the groaning of the children of Israel, whom the Egyptians keep in bondage; and I have remembered my covenant. 6  Wherefore say unto the children of Israel, I am the LORD, and I will bring you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians, and I will rid you out of their bondage, and I will redeem you with a stretched out arm, and with great judgments: 7  And I will take you to me for a people, and I will be to you a God: and ye shall know that I am the LORD your God, which bringeth you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians. 8  And I will bring you in unto the land, concerning the which I did [†]swear to give it to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob; and I will give it you for an heritage: I am the LORD.

9 ¶ And Moses spake so unto the children of Israel: but they hearkened not unto Moses for [†]anguish of spirit, and for cruel bondage.

10  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 11  Go in, speak unto Pharaoh king of Egypt, that he let the children of Israel go out of his land. 12  And Moses spake before the LORD, saying, Behold, the children of Israel have not hearkened unto me; how then shall Pharaoh hear me, who am of uncircumcised lips? 13  And the LORD spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, and gave them a charge unto the children of Israel, and unto Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring the children of Israel out of the land of Egypt.

14 ¶ These be the heads of their fathers’ houses: [*]The sons of Reuben the firstborn of Israel; Hanoch, and Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi: these be the families of Reuben. 15 [*] And the sons of Simeon; Jemuel, and Jamin, and Ohad, and Jachin, and Zohar, and Shaul the son of a Canaanitish woman: these are the families of Simeon.

16 ¶ And these are the names of [*]the sons of Levi according to their generations; Gershon, and Kohath, and Merari: and the years of the life of Levi were an hundred thirty and seven years. 17  The sons of Gershon; Libni, and Shimi, according to their families. 18  And [*]the sons of Kohath; Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel: and the years of the life of Kohath were an hundred thirty and three years. 19  And the sons of Merari; Mahali and Mushi: these are the families of Levi according to their generations. 20  And [*]Amram took him Jochebed his father’s sister to wife; and she bare him Aaron and Moses: and the years of the life of Amram were an hundred and thirty and seven years.

21 ¶ And the sons of Izhar; Korah, and Nepheg, and Zichri. 22  And the sons of Uzziel; Mishael, and Elzaphan, and Zithri. 23  And Aaron took him Elisheba, daughter of Amminadab, sister of Naashon, to wife; and she bare him Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. 24  And the sons of Korah; Assir, and Elkanah, and Abiasaph: these are the families of the Korhites. 25  And Eleazar Aaron’s son took him one of the daughters of Putiel to wife; and [*]she bare him Phinehas: these are the heads of the fathers of the Levites according to their families. 26  These are that Aaron and Moses, to whom the LORD said, Bring out the children of Israel from the land of Egypt according to their armies. 27  These are they which spake to Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring out the children of Israel from Egypt: these are that Moses and Aaron.

28 ¶ And it came to pass on the day when the LORD spake unto Moses in the land of Egypt, 29  That the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, I am the LORD: speak thou unto Pharaoh king of Egypt all that I say unto thee. 30  And Moses said before the LORD, Behold, I am of uncircumcised lips, and how shall Pharaoh hearken unto me?

7

1  And the LORD said unto Moses, See, I have made thee a god to Pharaoh: and Aaron thy brother shall be thy prophet. 2  Thou shalt speak all that I command thee: and Aaron thy brother shall speak unto Pharaoh, that he send the children of Israel out of his land. 3  And I will harden Pharaoh’s heart, and multiply my signs and my wonders in the land of Egypt. 4  But Pharaoh shall not hearken unto you, that I may lay my hand upon Egypt, and bring forth mine armies, and my people the children of Israel, out of the land of Egypt by great judgments. 5  And the Egyptians shall know that I am the LORD, when I stretch forth mine hand upon Egypt, and bring out the children of Israel from among them. 6  And Moses and Aaron did as the LORD commanded them, so did they. 7  And Moses was fourscore years old, and Aaron fourscore and three years old, when they spake unto Pharaoh.

8 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, 9  When Pharaoh shall speak unto you, saying, Shew a miracle for you: then thou shalt say unto Aaron, Take thy rod, and cast it before Pharaoh, and it shall become a serpent.

10 ¶ And Moses and Aaron went in unto Pharaoh, and they did so as the LORD had commanded: and Aaron cast down his rod before Pharaoh, and before his servants, and it became a serpent. 11  Then Pharaoh also called the wise men and the sorcerers: now the magicians of Egypt, they also did in like manner with their enchantments. 12  For they cast down every man his rod, and they became serpents: but Aaron’s rod swallowed up their rods. 13  And he hardened Pharaoh’s heart, that he hearkened not unto them; as the LORD had said.

14 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Pharaoh’s heart is hardened, he refuseth to let the people go. 15  Get thee unto Pharaoh in the morning; lo, he goeth out unto the water; and thou shalt stand by the river’s brink against he come; and the rod which was turned to a serpent shalt thou take in thine hand. 16  And thou shalt say unto him, The LORD God of the Hebrews hath sent me unto thee, saying, Let my people go, that they may serve me in the wilderness: and, behold, hitherto thou wouldest not hear. 17  Thus saith the LORD, In this thou shalt know that I am the LORD: behold, I will smite with the rod that is in mine hand upon the waters which are in the river, and they shall be turned to blood. 18  And the fish that is in the river shall die, and the river shall stink; and the Egyptians shall lothe to drink of the water of the river.

19 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, Say unto Aaron, Take thy rod, and stretch out thine hand upon the waters of Egypt, upon their streams, upon their rivers, and upon their ponds, and upon all their [†]pools of water, that they may become blood; and that there may be blood throughout all the land of Egypt, both in vessels of wood, and in vessels of stone. 20  And Moses and Aaron did so, as the LORD commanded; and he [*]lifted up the rod, and smote the waters that were in the river, in the sight of Pharaoh, and in the sight of his servants; and all the [*]waters that were in the river were turned to blood. 21  And the fish that was in the river died; and the river stank, and the Egyptians could not drink of the water of the river; and there was blood throughout all the land of Egypt. 22 [*] And the magicians of Egypt did so with their enchantments: and Pharaoh’s heart was hardened, neither did he hearken unto them; as the LORD had said. 23  And Pharaoh turned and went into his house, neither did he set his heart to this also. 24  And all the Egyptians digged round about the river for water to drink; for they could not drink of the water of the river. 25  And seven days were fulfilled, after that the LORD had smitten the river.

8

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, Go unto Pharaoh, and say unto him, Thus saith the LORD, Let my people go, that they may serve me. 2  And if thou refuse to let them go, behold, I will smite all thy borders with frogs: 3  And the river shall bring forth frogs abundantly, which shall go up and come into thine house, and into thy bedchamber, and upon thy bed, and into the house of thy servants, and upon thy people, and into thine ovens, and into thy [∥]kneadingtroughs: 4  And the frogs shall come up both on thee, and upon thy people, and upon all thy servants.

5 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, Say unto Aaron, Stretch forth thine hand with thy rod over the streams, over the rivers, and over the ponds, and cause frogs to come up upon the land of Egypt. 6  And Aaron stretched out his hand over the waters of Egypt; and the frogs came up, and covered the land of Egypt. 7 [*] And the magicians did so with their enchantments, and brought up frogs upon the land of Egypt.

8 ¶ Then Pharaoh called for Moses and Aaron, and said, Intreat the LORD, that he may take away the frogs from me, and from my people; and I will let the people go, that they may do sacrifice unto the LORD. 9  And Moses said unto Pharaoh, [∥]Glory over me: [∥]when shall I intreat for thee, and for thy servants, and for thy people, [†]to destroy the frogs from thee and thy houses, that they may remain in the river only? 10  And he said, [∥]To morrow. And he said, Be it according to thy word: that thou mayest know that there is none like unto the LORD our God. 11  And the frogs shall depart from thee, and from thy houses, and from thy servants, and from thy people; they shall remain in the river only. 12  And Moses and Aaron went out from Pharaoh: and Moses cried unto the LORD because of the frogs which he had brought against Pharaoh. 13  And the LORD did according to the word of Moses; and the frogs died out of the houses, out of the villages, and out of the fields. 14  And they gathered them together upon heaps: and the land stank. 15  But when Pharaoh saw that there was respite, he hardened his heart, and hearkened not unto them; as the LORD had said.

16 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Say unto Aaron, Stretch out thy rod, and smite the dust of the land, that it may become lice throughout all the land of Egypt. 17  And they did so; for Aaron stretched out his hand with his rod, and smote the dust of the earth, and it became lice in man, and in beast; all the dust of the land became lice throughout all the land of Egypt. 18  And the magicians did so with their enchantments to bring forth lice, but they could not: so there were lice upon man, and upon beast. 19  Then the magicians said unto Pharaoh, This is the finger of God: and Pharaoh’s heart was hardened, and he hearkened not unto them; as the LORD had said.

20 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Rise up early in the morning, and stand before Pharaoh; lo, he cometh forth to the water; and say unto him, Thus saith the LORD, Let my people go, that they may serve me. 21  Else, if thou wilt not let my people go, behold, I will send [∥]swarms of flies upon thee, and upon thy servants, and upon thy people, and into thy houses: and the houses of the Egyptians shall be full of swarms of flies, and also the ground whereon they are. 22  And I will sever in that day the land of Goshen, in which my people dwell, that no swarms of flies shall be there; to the end thou mayest know that I am the LORD in the midst of the earth. 23  And I will put [†]a division between my people and thy people: [∥]to morrow shall this sign be. 24  And the LORD did so; and [*]there came a grievous swarm of flies into the house of Pharaoh, and into his servants’ houses, and into all the land of Egypt: the land was [∥]corrupted by reason of the swarm of flies.

25 ¶ And Pharaoh called for Moses and for Aaron, and said, Go ye, sacrifice to your God in the land. 26  And Moses said, It is not meet so to do; for we shall sacrifice the abomination of the Egyptians to the LORD our God: lo, shall we sacrifice the abomination of the Egyptians before their eyes, and will they not stone us? 27  We will go three days’ journey into the wilderness, and sacrifice to the LORD our God, as [*]he shall command us. 28  And Pharaoh said, I will let you go, that ye may sacrifice to the LORD your God in the wilderness; only ye shall not go very far away: intreat for me. 29  And Moses said, Behold, I go out from thee, and I will intreat the LORD that the swarms of flies may depart from Pharaoh, from his servants, and from his people, to morrow: but let not Pharaoh deal deceitfully any more in not letting the people go to sacrifice to the LORD. 30  And Moses went out from Pharaoh, and intreated the LORD. 31  And the LORD did according to the word of Moses; and he removed the swarms of flies from Pharaoh, from his servants, and from his people; there remained not one. 32  And Pharaoh hardened his heart at this time also, neither would he let the people go.

9

1  Then the LORD said unto Moses, Go in unto Pharaoh, and tell him, Thus saith the LORD God of the Hebrews, Let my people go, that they may serve me. 2  For if thou refuse to let them go, and wilt hold them still, 3  Behold, the hand of the LORD is upon thy cattle which is in the field, upon the horses, upon the asses, upon the camels, upon the oxen, and upon the sheep: there shall be a very grievous murrain. 4  And the LORD shall sever between the cattle of Israel and the cattle of Egypt: and there shall nothing die of all that is the children’s of Israel. 5  And the LORD appointed a set time, saying, To morrow the LORD shall do this thing in the land. 6  And the LORD did that thing on the morrow, and all the cattle of Egypt died: but of the cattle of the children of Israel died not one. 7  And Pharaoh sent, and, behold, there was not one of the cattle of the Israelites dead. And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, and he did not let the people go.

8 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses and unto Aaron, Take to you handfuls of ashes of the furnace, and let Moses sprinkle it toward the heaven in the sight of Pharaoh. 9  And it shall become small dust in all the land of Egypt, and shall be a boil breaking forth with blains upon man, and upon beast, throughout all the land of Egypt. 10  And they took ashes of the furnace, and stood before Pharaoh; and Moses sprinkled it up toward heaven; and it became a boil breaking forth with blains upon man, and upon beast. 11  And the magicians could not stand before Moses because of the boils; for the boil was upon the magicians, and upon all the Egyptians. 12  And the LORD hardened the heart of Pharaoh, and he hearkened not unto them; [*]as the LORD had spoken unto Moses.

13 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Rise up early in the morning, and stand before Pharaoh, and say unto him, Thus saith the LORD God of the Hebrews, Let my people go, that they may serve me. 14  For I will at this time send all my plagues upon thine heart, and upon thy servants, and upon thy people; that thou mayest know that there is none like me in all the earth. 15  For now I will stretch out my hand, that I may smite thee and thy people with pestilence; and thou shalt be cut off from the earth. 16  And in very deed for [*]this cause have I [†]raised thee up, for to shew in thee my power; and that my name may be declared throughout all the earth. 17  As yet exaltest thou thyself against my people, that thou wilt not let them go? 18  Behold, to morrow about this time I will cause it to rain a very grievous hail, such as hath not been in Egypt since the foundation thereof even until now. 19  Send therefore now, and gather thy cattle, and all that thou hast in the field; for upon every man and beast which shall be found in the field, and shall not be brought home, the hail shall come down upon them, and they shall die. 20  He that feared the word of the LORD among the servants of Pharaoh made his servants and his cattle flee into the houses: 21  And he that [†]regarded not the word of the LORD left his servants and his cattle in the field.

22 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Stretch forth thine hand toward heaven, that there may be hail in all the land of Egypt, upon man, and upon beast, and upon every herb of the field, throughout the land of Egypt. 23  And Moses stretched forth his rod toward heaven: and the LORD sent thunder and hail, and the fire ran along upon the ground; and the LORD rained hail upon the land of Egypt. 24  So there was hail, and fire mingled with the hail, very grievous, such as there was none like it in all the land of Egypt since it became a nation. 25  And the hail smote throughout all the land of Egypt all that was in the field, both man and beast; and the hail smote every herb of the field, and brake every tree of the field. 26  Only in the land of Goshen, where the children of Israel were, was there no hail.

27 ¶ And Pharaoh sent, and called for Moses and Aaron, and said unto them, I have sinned this time: the LORD is righteous, and I and my people are wicked. 28  Intreat the LORD (for it is enough) that there be no more [†]mighty thunderings and hail; and I will let you go, and ye shall stay no longer. 29  And Moses said unto him, As soon as I am gone out of the city, I will spread abroad my hands unto the LORD; and the thunder shall cease, neither shall there be any more hail; that thou mayest know how that the [*]earth is the LORD’s. 30  But as for thee and thy servants, I know that ye will not yet fear the LORD God. 31  And the flax and the barley was smitten: for the barley was in the ear, and the flax was bolled. 32  But the wheat and the rie were not smitten: for they were [†]not grown up. 33  And Moses went out of the city from Pharaoh, and spread abroad his hands unto the LORD: and the thunders and hail ceased, and the rain was not poured upon the earth. 34  And when Pharaoh saw that the rain and the hail and the thunders were ceased, he sinned yet more, and hardened his heart, he and his servants. 35  And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, neither would he let the children of Israel go; as the LORD had spoken [†]by Moses.

10

1  And the LORD said unto Moses, Go in unto Pharaoh: [*]for I have hardened his heart, and the heart of his servants, that I might shew these my signs before him: 2  And that thou mayest tell in the ears of thy son, and of thy son’s son, what things I have wrought in Egypt, and my signs which I have done among them; that ye may know how that I am the LORD. 3  And Moses and Aaron came in unto Pharaoh, and said unto him, Thus saith the LORD God of the Hebrews, How long wilt thou refuse to humble thyself before me? let my people go, that they may serve me. 4  Else, if thou refuse to let my people go, behold, to morrow will I bring the [*]locusts into thy coast: 5  And they shall cover the [†]face of the earth, that one cannot be able to see the earth: and they shall eat the residue of that which is escaped, which remaineth unto you from the hail, and shall eat every tree which groweth for you out of the field: 6  And they shall fill thy houses, and the houses of all thy servants, and the houses of all the Egyptians; which neither thy fathers, nor thy fathers’ fathers have seen, since the day that they were upon the earth unto this day. And he turned himself, and went out from Pharaoh. 7  And Pharaoh’s servants said unto him, How long shall this man be a snare unto us? let the men go, that they may serve the LORD their God: knowest thou not yet that Egypt is destroyed? 8  And Moses and Aaron were brought again unto Pharaoh: and he said unto them, Go, serve the LORD your God: but [†]who are they that shall go? 9  And Moses said, We will go with our young and with our old, with our sons and with our daughters, with our flocks and with our herds will we go; for we must hold a feast unto the LORD. 10  And he said unto them, Let the LORD be so with you, as I will let you go, and your little ones: look to it; for evil is before you. 11  Not so: go now ye that are men, and serve the LORD; for that ye did desire. And they were driven out from Pharaoh’s presence.

12 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Stretch out thine hand over the land of Egypt for the locusts, that they may come up upon the land of Egypt, and eat every herb of the land, even all that the hail hath left. 13  And Moses stretched forth his rod over the land of Egypt, and the LORD brought an east wind upon the land all that day, and all that night; and when it was morning, the east wind brought the locusts. 14  And the locusts went up over all the land of Egypt, and rested in all the coasts of Egypt: very grievous were they; before them there were no such locusts as they, neither after them shall be such. 15  For they covered the face of the whole earth, so that the land was darkened; and they did eat every herb of the land, and all the fruit of the trees which the hail had left: and there remained not any green thing in the trees, or in the herbs of the field, through all the land of Egypt.

16 ¶ Then Pharaoh [†]called for Moses and Aaron in haste; and he said, I have sinned against the LORD your God, and against you. 17  Now therefore forgive, I pray thee, my sin only this once, and intreat the LORD your God, that he may take away from me this death only. 18  And he went out from Pharaoh, and intreated the LORD. 19  And the LORD turned a mighty strong west wind, which took away the locusts, and [†]cast them into the Red sea; there remained not one locust in all the coasts of Egypt. 20  But the LORD hardened Pharaoh’s heart, so that he would not let the children of Israel go.

21 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Stretch out thine hand toward heaven, that there may be darkness over the land of Egypt, [†]even darkness which may be felt. 22  And Moses stretched forth his hand toward heaven; and there was a thick darkness in all the land of Egypt three days: 23  They saw not one another, neither rose any from his place for three days: [*]but all the children of Israel had light in their dwellings.

24 ¶ And Pharaoh called unto Moses, and said, Go ye, serve the LORD; only let your flocks and your herds be stayed: let your little ones also go with you. 25  And Moses said, Thou must give [†]us also sacrifices and burnt offerings, that we may sacrifice unto the LORD our God. 26  Our cattle also shall go with us; there shall not an hoof be left behind; for thereof must we take to serve the LORD our God; and we know not with what we must serve the LORD, until we come thither.

27 ¶ But the LORD hardened Pharaoh’s heart, and he would not let them go. 28  And Pharaoh said unto him, Get thee from me, take heed to thyself, see my face no more; for in that day thou seest my face thou shalt die. 29  And Moses said, Thou hast spoken well, I will see thy face again no more.

11

1  And the LORD said unto Moses, Yet will I bring one plague more upon Pharaoh, and upon Egypt; afterwards he will let you go hence: when he shall let you go, he shall surely thrust you out hence altogether. 2  Speak now in the ears of the people, and let every man borrow of his neighbour, and every woman of her neighbour, [*]jewels of silver, and jewels of gold. 3  And the LORD gave the people favour in the sight of the Egyptians. Moreover the man [*]Moses was very great in the land of Egypt, in the sight of Pharaoh’s servants, and in the sight of the people.

4  And Moses said, Thus saith the LORD, [*]About midnight will I go out into the midst of Egypt: 5  And all the firstborn in the land of Egypt shall die, from the firstborn of Pharaoh that sitteth upon his throne, even unto the firstborn of the maidservant that is behind the mill; and all the firstborn of beasts. 6  And there shall be a great cry throughout all the land of Egypt, such as there was none like it, nor shall be like it any more. 7  But against any of the children of Israel shall not a dog move his tongue, against man or beast: that ye may know how that the LORD doth put a difference between the Egyptians and Israel. 8  And all these thy servants shall come down unto me, and bow down themselves unto me, saying, Get thee out, and all the people [†]that follow thee: and after that I will go out. And he went out from Pharaoh in [†]a great anger. 9  And the LORD said unto Moses, Pharaoh shall not hearken unto you; that my wonders may be multiplied in the land of Egypt. 10  And Moses and Aaron did all these wonders before Pharaoh: and the LORD hardened Pharaoh’s heart, so that he would not let the children of Israel go out of his land.

12

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses and Aaron in the land of Egypt, saying, 2  This month shall be unto you the beginning of months: it shall be the first month of the year to you.

3 ¶ Speak ye unto all the congregation of Israel, saying, In the tenth day of this month they shall take to them every man a [∥]lamb, according to the house of their fathers, a lamb for an house: 4  And if the household be too little for the lamb, let him and his neighbour next unto his house take it according to the number of the souls; every man according to his eating shall make your count for the lamb. 5  Your lamb shall be without blemish, a male [†]of the first year: ye shall take it out from the sheep, or from the goats: 6  And ye shall keep it up until the fourteenth day of the same month: and the whole assembly of the congregation of Israel shall kill it [†]in the evening. 7  And they shall take of the blood, and strike it on the two side posts and on the upper door post of the houses, wherein they shall eat it. 8  And they shall eat the flesh in that night, roast with fire, and unleavened bread; and with bitter herbs they shall eat it. 9  Eat not of it raw, nor sodden at all with water, but roast with fire; his head with his legs, and with the purtenance thereof. 10  And ye shall let nothing of it remain until the morning; and that which remaineth of it until the morning ye shall burn with fire.

11 ¶ And thus shall ye eat it; with your loins girded, your shoes on your feet, and your staff in your hand; and ye shall eat it in haste: it is the LORD’s passover. 12  For I will pass through the land of Egypt this night, and will smite all the firstborn in the land of Egypt, both man and beast; and against all the [∥]gods of Egypt I will execute judgment: I am the LORD. 13  And the blood shall be to you for a token upon the houses where ye are: and when I see the blood, I will pass over you, and the plague shall not be upon you [†]to destroy you, when I smite the land of Egypt. 14  And this day shall be unto you for a memorial; and ye shall keep it a feast to the LORD throughout your generations; ye shall keep it a feast by an ordinance for ever. 15  Seven days shall ye eat unleavened bread; even the first day ye shall put away leaven out of your houses: for whosoever eateth leavened bread from the first day until the seventh day, that soul shall be cut off from Israel. 16  And in the first day there shall be an holy convocation, and in the seventh day there shall be an holy convocation to you; no manner of work shall be done in them, save that which every [†]man must eat, that only may be done of you. 17  And ye shall observe the feast of unleavened bread; for in this selfsame day have I brought your armies out of the land of Egypt: therefore shall ye observe this day in your generations by an ordinance for ever.

18 ¶ [*]In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month at even, ye shall eat unleavened bread, until the one and twentieth day of the month at even. 19  Seven days shall there be no leaven found in your houses: for whosoever eateth that which is leavened, even that soul shall be cut off from the congregation of Israel, whether he be a stranger, or born in the land. 20  Ye shall eat nothing leavened; in all your habitations shall ye eat unleavened bread.

21 ¶ Then Moses called for all the elders of Israel, and said unto them, Draw out and take you a [∥]lamb according to your families, and kill the passover. 22 [*] And ye shall take a bunch of hyssop, and dip it in the blood that is in the bason, and strike the lintel and the two side posts with the blood that is in the bason; and none of you shall go out at the door of his house until the morning. 23  For the LORD will pass through to smite the Egyptians; and when he seeth the blood upon the lintel, and on the two side posts, the LORD will pass over the door, and will not suffer the destroyer to come in unto your houses to smite you. 24  And ye shall observe this thing for an ordinance to thee and to thy sons for ever. 25  And it shall come to pass, when ye be come to the land which the LORD will give you, according as he hath promised, that ye shall keep this service. 26 [*] And it shall come to pass, when your children shall say unto you, What mean ye by this service? 27  That ye shall say, It is the sacrifice of the LORD’s passover, who passed over the houses of the children of Israel in Egypt, when he smote the Egyptians, and delivered our houses. And the people bowed the head and worshipped. 28  And the children of Israel went away, and did as the LORD had commanded Moses and Aaron, so did they.

29 ¶ [*]And it came to pass, that at midnight the LORD smote all the firstborn in the land of Egypt, [*]from the firstborn of Pharaoh that sat on his throne unto the firstborn of the captive that was in the [†]dungeon; and all the firstborn of cattle. 30  And Pharaoh rose up in the night, he, and all his servants, and all the Egyptians; and there was a great cry in Egypt; for there was not a house where there was not one dead.

31 ¶ And he called for Moses and Aaron by night, and said, Rise up, and get you forth from among my people, both ye and the children of Israel; and go, serve the LORD, as ye have said. 32  Also take your flocks and your herds, as ye have said, and be gone; and bless me also. 33  And the Egyptians were urgent upon the people, that they might send them out of the land in haste; for they said, We be all dead men. 34  And the people took their dough before it was leavened, their [∥]kneadingtroughs being bound up in their clothes upon their shoulders. 35  And the children of Israel did according to the word of Moses; and they borrowed of the Egyptians [*]jewels of silver, and jewels of gold, and raiment: 36  And the LORD gave the people favour in the sight of the Egyptians, so that they lent unto them such things as they required. And they spoiled the Egyptians.

37 ¶ And [*]the children of Israel journeyed from Rameses to Succoth, about six hundred thousand on foot that were men, beside children. 38  And [†]a mixed multitude went up also with them; and flocks, and herds, even very much cattle. 39  And they baked unleavened cakes of the dough which they brought forth out of Egypt, for it was not leavened; because they were thrust out of Egypt, and could not tarry, neither had they prepared for themselves any victual.

40 ¶ Now the sojourning of the children of Israel, who dwelt in Egypt, was [*]four hundred and thirty years. 41  And it came to pass at the end of the four hundred and thirty years, even the selfsame day it came to pass, that all the hosts of the LORD went out from the land of Egypt. 42 It is [†]a night to be much observed unto the LORD for bringing them out from the land of Egypt: this is that night of the LORD to be observed of all the children of Israel in their generations.

43 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses and Aaron, This is the ordinance of the passover: There shall no stranger eat thereof: 44  But every man’s servant that is bought for money, when thou hast circumcised him, then shall he eat thereof. 45  A foreigner and an hired servant shall not eat thereof. 46  In one house shall it be eaten; thou shalt not carry forth ought of the flesh abroad out of the house; [*]neither shall ye break a bone thereof. 47  All the congregation of Israel shall [†]keep it. 48  And when a stranger shall sojourn with thee, and will keep the passover to the LORD, let all his males be circumcised, and then let him come near and keep it; and he shall be as one that is born in the land: for no uncircumcised person shall eat thereof. 49  One law shall be to him that is homeborn, and unto the stranger that sojourneth among you. 50  Thus did all the children of Israel; as the LORD commanded Moses and Aaron, so did they. 51  And it came to pass the selfsame day, that the LORD did bring the children of Israel out of the land of Egypt by their armies.

13

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2 [*] Sanctify unto me all the firstborn, whatsoever openeth the womb among the children of Israel, both of man and of beast: it is mine.

3 ¶ And Moses said unto the people, Remember this day, in which ye came out from Egypt, out of the house of [†]bondage; for by strength of hand the LORD brought you out from this place: there shall no leavened bread be eaten. 4  This day came ye out in the month Abib.

5 ¶ And it shall be when the LORD shall bring thee into the land of the Canaanites, and the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, which he sware unto thy fathers to give thee, a land flowing with milk and honey, that thou shalt keep this service in this month. 6  Seven days thou shalt eat unleavened bread, and in the seventh day shall be a feast to the LORD. 7  Unleavened bread shall be eaten seven days; and there shall no leavened bread be seen with thee, neither shall there be leaven seen with thee in all thy quarters.

8 ¶ And thou shalt shew thy son in that day, saying, This is done because of that which the LORD did unto me when I came forth out of Egypt. 9  And it shall be for a sign unto thee upon thine hand, and for a memorial between thine eyes, that the LORD’s law may be in thy mouth: for with a strong hand hath the LORD brought thee out of Egypt. 10  Thou shalt therefore keep this ordinance in his season from year to year.

11 ¶ And it shall be when the LORD shall bring thee into the land of the Canaanites, as he sware unto thee and to thy fathers, and shall give it thee, 12 [*] That thou shalt [†]set apart unto the LORD all that openeth the matrix, and every firstling that cometh of a beast which thou hast; the males shall be the LORD’s. 13  And every firstling of an ass thou shalt redeem with a [∥]lamb; and if thou wilt not redeem it, then thou shalt break his neck: and all the firstborn of man among thy children shalt thou redeem.

14 ¶ And it shall be when thy son asketh thee [†]in time to come, saying, What is this? that thou shalt say unto him, By strength of hand the LORD brought us out from Egypt, from the house of bondage: 15  And it came to pass, when Pharaoh would hardly let us go, that the LORD slew all the firstborn in the land of Egypt, both the firstborn of man, and the firstborn of beast: therefore I sacrifice to the LORD all that openeth the matrix, being males; but all the firstborn of my children I redeem. 16  And it shall be for a token upon thine hand, and for frontlets between thine eyes: for by strength of hand the LORD brought us forth out of Egypt.

17 ¶ And it came to pass, when Pharaoh had let the people go, that God led them not through the way of the land of the Philistines, although that was near; for God said, Lest peradventure the people repent when they see war, and they return to Egypt: 18  But God led the people about, through the way of the wilderness of the Red sea: and the children of Israel went up [∥]harnessed out of the land of Egypt. 19  And Moses took the bones of Joseph with him: for he had straitly sworn the children of Israel, saying, [*]God will surely visit you; and ye shall carry up my bones away hence with you.

20 ¶ And [*]they took their journey from Succoth, and encamped in Etham, in the edge of the wilderness. 21  And [*]the LORD went before them by day in a pillar of a cloud, to lead them the way; and by night in a pillar of fire, to give them light; to go by day and night: 22  He took not away the pillar of the cloud by day, [*]nor the pillar of fire by night, from before the people.

14

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2  Speak unto the children of Israel, that they turn and encamp before [*]Pi-hahiroth, between Migdol and the sea, over against Baal-zephon: before it shall ye encamp by the sea. 3  For Pharaoh will say of the children of Israel, They are entangled in the land, the wilderness hath shut them in. 4  And I will harden Pharaoh’s heart, that he shall follow after them; and I will be honoured upon Pharaoh, and upon all his host; that the Egyptians may know that I am the LORD. And they did so.

5 ¶ And it was told the king of Egypt that the people fled: and the heart of Pharaoh and of his servants was turned against the people, and they said, Why have we done this, that we have let Israel go from serving us? 6  And he made ready his chariot, and took his people with him: 7  And he took six hundred chosen chariots, and all the chariots of Egypt, and captains over every one of them. 8  And the LORD hardened the heart of Pharaoh king of Egypt, and he pursued after the children of Israel: and the children of Israel went out with an high hand. 9  But the [*]Egyptians pursued after them, all the horses and chariots of Pharaoh, and his horsemen, and his army, and overtook them encamping by the sea, beside Pi-hahiroth, before Baal-zephon.

10 ¶ And when Pharaoh drew nigh, the children of Israel lifted up their eyes, and, behold, the Egyptians marched after them; and they were sore afraid: and the children of Israel cried out unto the LORD. 11  And they said unto Moses, Because there were no graves in Egypt, hast thou taken us away to die in the wilderness? wherefore hast thou dealt thus with us, to carry us forth out of Egypt? 12 [*] Is not this the word that we did tell thee in Egypt, saying, Let us alone, that we may serve the Egyptians? For it had been better for us to serve the Egyptians, than that we should die in the wilderness.

13 ¶ And Moses said unto the people, Fear ye not, stand still, and see the salvation of the LORD, which he will shew to you to day: [∥]for the Egyptians whom ye have seen to day, ye shall see them again no more for ever. 14  The LORD shall fight for you, and ye shall hold your peace.

15 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Wherefore criest thou unto me? speak unto the children of Israel, that they go forward: 16  But lift thou up thy rod, and stretch out thine hand over the sea, and divide it: and the children of Israel shall go on dry ground through the midst of the sea. 17  And I, behold, I will harden the hearts of the Egyptians, and they shall follow them: and I will get me honour upon Pharaoh, and upon all his host, upon his chariots, and upon his horsemen. 18  And the Egyptians shall know that I am the LORD, when I have gotten me honour upon Pharaoh, upon his chariots, and upon his horsemen.

19 ¶ And the angel of God, which went before the camp of Israel, removed and went behind them; and the pillar of the cloud went from before their face, and stood behind them: 20  And it came between the camp of the Egyptians and the camp of Israel; and it was a cloud and darkness to them, but it gave light by night to these: so that the one came not near the other all the night.

21  And Moses stretched out his hand over the sea; and the LORD caused the sea to go back by a strong east wind all that night, and made the sea dry land, and the waters were [*]divided. 22  And [*]the children of Israel went into the midst of the sea upon the dry ground: and the waters were a wall unto them on their right hand, and on their left.

23 ¶ And the Egyptians pursued, and went in after them to the midst of the sea, even all Pharaoh’s horses, his chariots, and his horsemen. 24  And it came to pass, that in the morning watch the LORD looked unto the host of the Egyptians through the pillar of fire and of the cloud, and troubled the host of the Egyptians, 25  And took off their chariot wheels, [∥]that they drave them heavily: so that the Egyptians said, Let us flee from the face of Israel; for the LORD fighteth for them against the Egyptians.

26 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Stretch out thine hand over the sea, that the waters may come again upon the Egyptians, upon their chariots, and upon their horsemen. 27  And Moses stretched forth his hand over the sea, and the sea returned to his strength when the morning appeared; and the Egyptians fled against it; and the LORD [†]overthrew the Egyptians in the midst of the sea. 28  And the waters returned, and covered the chariots, and the horsemen, and all the host of Pharaoh that came into the sea after them; there remained not so much as [*]one of them. 29  But the children of Israel walked upon dry land in the midst of the sea; and the waters were a wall unto them on their right hand, and on their left. 30  Thus the LORD saved Israel that day out of the hand of the Egyptians; and Israel saw the Egyptians dead upon the sea shore. 31  And Israel saw that great [†]work which the LORD did upon the Egyptians: and the people feared the LORD, and believed the LORD, and his servant Moses.

15

1  Then sang [*]Moses and the children of Israel this song unto the LORD, and spake, saying, I will sing unto the LORD, for he hath triumphed gloriously: the horse and his rider hath he thrown into the sea. 2  The LORD is my strength and song, and he is become my salvation: he is my God, and I will prepare him an habitation; my father’s God, and I will exalt him. 3  The LORD is a man of war: the LORD is his name. 4  Pharaoh’s chariots and his host hath he cast into the sea: his chosen captains also are drowned in the Red sea. 5  The depths have covered them: they sank into the bottom as a stone. 6  Thy right hand, O LORD, is become glorious in power: thy right hand, O LORD, hath dashed in pieces the enemy. 7  And in the greatness of thine excellency thou hast overthrown them that rose up against thee: thou sentest forth thy wrath, which consumed them as stubble. 8  And with the blast of thy nostrils the waters were gathered together, the floods stood upright as an heap, and the depths were congealed in the heart of the sea. 9  The enemy said, I will pursue, I will overtake, I will divide the spoil; my lust shall be satisfied upon them; I will draw my sword, my hand shall [∥]destroy them. 10  Thou didst blow with thy wind, the sea covered them: they sank as lead in the mighty waters. 11 Who is like unto thee, O LORD, among the [∥]gods? who is like thee, glorious in holiness, fearful in praises, doing wonders? 12  Thou stretchedst out thy right hand, the earth swallowed them. 13  Thou in thy mercy hast led forth the people which thou hast redeemed: thou hast guided them in thy strength unto thy holy habitation. 14 [*] The people shall hear, and be afraid: sorrow shall take hold on the inhabitants of Palestina. 15  Then the dukes of Edom shall be amazed; the mighty men of Moab, trembling shall take hold upon them; all the inhabitants of Canaan shall melt away. 16 [*] Fear and dread shall fall upon them; by the greatness of thine arm they shall be as still as a stone; till thy people pass over, O LORD, till the people pass over, which thou hast purchased. 17  Thou shalt bring them in, and plant them in the mountain of thine inheritance, in the place, O LORD, which thou hast made for thee to dwell in, in the Sanctuary, O Lord, which thy hands have established. 18  The LORD shall reign for ever and ever. 19  For the horse of Pharaoh went in with his chariots and with his horsemen into the sea, and the LORD brought again the waters of the sea upon them; but the children of Israel went on dry land in the midst of the sea.

20 ¶ And Miriam the prophetess, the sister of Aaron, took a timbrel in her hand; and all the women went out after her with timbrels and with dances. 21  And Miriam answered them, Sing ye to the LORD, for he hath triumphed gloriously; the horse and his rider hath he thrown into the sea.

22  So Moses brought Israel from the Red sea, and they went out into the wilderness of Shur; and they went three days in the wilderness, and found no water.

23 ¶ And when they came to Marah, they could not drink of the waters of Marah, for they were bitter: therefore the name of it was called [∥]Marah. 24  And the people murmured against Moses, saying, What shall we drink? 25  And he cried unto the LORD; and the LORD shewed him a [*]tree, which when he had cast into the waters, the waters were made sweet: there he made [‡]for them a statute and an ordinance, and there he proved them, 26  And said, If thou wilt diligently hearken to the voice of the LORD thy God, and wilt do that which is right in his sight, and wilt give ear to his commandments, and keep all his statutes, I will put none of these diseases upon thee, which I have brought upon the Egyptians: for I am the LORD that healeth thee.

27 ¶ [*]And they came to Elim, where were twelve wells of water, and threescore and ten palm trees: and they encamped there by the waters.

16

1  And they took their journey from Elim, and all the congregation of the children of Israel came unto the wilderness of Sin, which is between Elim and Sinai, on the fifteenth day of the second month after their departing out of the land of Egypt. 2  And the whole congregation of the children of Israel murmured against Moses and Aaron in the wilderness: 3  And the children of Israel said unto them, Would to God we had died by the hand of the LORD in the land of Egypt, when we sat by the flesh pots, and when we did eat bread to the full; for ye have brought us forth into this wilderness, to kill this whole assembly with hunger.

4 ¶ Then said the LORD unto Moses, Behold, I will rain bread from heaven for you; and the people shall go out and gather [†]a certain rate every day, that I may prove them, whether they will walk in my law, or no. 5  And it shall come to pass, that on the sixth day they shall prepare that which they bring in; and it shall be twice as much as they gather daily. 6  And Moses and Aaron said unto all the children of Israel, At even, then ye shall know that the LORD hath brought you out from the land of Egypt: 7  And in the morning, then ye shall see the glory of the LORD; for that he heareth your murmurings against the LORD: and what are we, that ye murmur against us? 8  And Moses said, This shall be, when the LORD shall give you in the evening flesh to eat, and in the morning bread to the full; for that the LORD heareth your murmurings which ye murmur against him: and what are we? your murmurings are not against us, but against the LORD.

9 ¶ And Moses spake unto Aaron, Say unto all the congregation of the children of Israel, Come near before the LORD: for he hath heard your murmurings. 10  And it came to pass, as Aaron spake unto the whole congregation of the children of Israel, that they looked toward the wilderness, and, behold, the glory of the LORD [*]appeared in the cloud.

11 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 12  I have heard the murmurings of the children of Israel: speak unto them, saying, At even ye shall eat flesh, and in the morning ye shall be filled with bread; and ye shall know that I am the LORD your God.

13  And it came to pass, that at even [*]the quails came up, and covered the camp: and in the morning the dew lay round about the host. 14  And when [*]the dew that lay was gone up, behold, upon the face of the wilderness there lay a small round thing, as small as the hoar frost on the ground. 15  And when the children of Israel saw it, they said one to another, [∥]It is manna: for they wist not what it was. And Moses said unto them, [*]This is the bread which the LORD hath given you to eat.

16 ¶ This is the thing which the LORD hath commanded, Gather of it every man according to his eating, an omer [†]for every man, according to the number of your [†]persons; take ye every man for them which are in his tents. 17  And the children of Israel did so, and gathered, some more, some less. 18  And when they did mete it with an omer, [*]he that gathered much had nothing over, and he that gathered little had no lack; they gathered every man according to his eating. 19  And Moses said, Let no man leave of it till the morning. 20  Notwithstanding they hearkened not unto Moses; but some of them left of it until the morning, and it bred worms, and stank: and Moses was wroth with them. 21  And they gathered it every morning, every man according to his eating: and when the sun waxed hot, it melted.

22 ¶ And it came to pass, that on the sixth day they gathered twice as much bread, two omers for one man: and all the rulers of the congregation came and told Moses. 23  And he said unto them, This is that which the LORD hath said, To morrow is the rest of the holy sabbath unto the LORD: bake that which ye will bake to day, and seethe that ye will seethe; and that which remaineth over lay up for you to be kept until the morning. 24  And they laid it up till the morning, as Moses bade: and it did not stink, neither was there any worm therein. 25  And Moses said, Eat that to day; for to day is a sabbath unto the LORD: to day ye shall not find it in the field. 26  Six days ye shall gather it; but on the seventh day, which is the sabbath, in it there shall be none.

27 ¶ And it came to pass, that there went out some of the people on the seventh day for to gather, and they found none. 28  And the LORD said unto Moses, How long refuse ye to keep my commandments and my laws? 29  See, for that the LORD hath given you the sabbath, therefore he giveth you on the sixth day the bread of two days; abide ye every man in his place, let no man go out of his place on the seventh day. 30  So the people rested on the seventh day. 31  And the house of Israel called the name thereof Manna: and it was like coriander seed, white; and the taste of it was like wafers made with honey.

32 ¶ And Moses said, This is the thing which the LORD commandeth, Fill an omer of it to be kept for your generations; that they may see the bread wherewith I have fed you in the wilderness, when I brought you forth from the land of Egypt. 33  And Moses said unto Aaron, Take a pot, and put an omer full of manna therein, and lay it up before the LORD, to be kept for your generations. 34  As the LORD commanded Moses, so Aaron laid it up before the Testimony, to be kept. 35  And the children of Israel did eat manna forty years, [*]until they came to a land inhabited; they did eat manna, until they came unto the borders of the land of Canaan. 36  Now an omer is the tenth part of an ephah.

17

1  And all the congregation of the children of Israel journeyed from the wilderness of Sin, after their journeys, according to the commandment of the LORD, and pitched in Rephidim: and there was no water for the people to drink. 2  Wherefore [*]the people did chide with Moses, and said, Give us water that we may drink. And Moses said unto them, Why chide ye with me? wherefore do ye tempt the LORD? 3  And the people thirsted there for water; and the people murmured against Moses, and said, Wherefore is this that thou hast brought us up out of Egypt, to kill us and our children and our cattle with thirst? 4  And Moses cried unto the LORD, saying, What shall I do unto this people? they be almost ready to stone me. 5  And the LORD said unto Moses, Go on before the people, and take with thee of the elders of Israel; and thy rod, wherewith [*]thou smotest the river, take in thine hand, and go. 6 [*] Behold, I will stand before thee there upon the rock in Horeb; and thou shalt smite the rock, and there shall come water out of it, that the people may drink. And Moses did so in the sight of the elders of Israel. 7  And he called the name of the place [∥]Massah, and [∥]Meribah, because of the chiding of the children of Israel, and because they tempted the LORD, saying, Is the LORD among us, or not?

8 ¶ [*]Then came Amalek, and fought with Israel in Rephidim. 9  And Moses said unto [*]Joshua, Choose us out men, and go out, fight with Amalek: to morrow I will stand on the top of the hill with the rod of God in mine hand. 10  So Joshua did as Moses had said to him, and fought with Amalek: and Moses, Aaron, and Hur went up to the top of the hill. 11  And it came to pass, when Moses held up his hand, that Israel prevailed: and when he let down his hand, Amalek prevailed. 12  But Moses’ hands were heavy; and they took a stone, and put it under him, and he sat thereon; and Aaron and Hur stayed up his hands, the one on the one side, and the other on the other side; and his hands were steady until the going down of the sun. 13  And Joshua discomfited Amalek and his people with the edge of the sword. 14  And the LORD said unto Moses, Write this for a memorial in a book, and rehearse it in the ears of Joshua: for [*]I will utterly put out the remembrance of Amalek from under heaven. 15  And Moses built an altar, and called the name of it [∥]Jehovah-nissi: 16  For he said, [∥]Because [†]the LORD hath sworn that the LORD will have war with Amalek from generation to generation.

18

1  When [*]Jethro, the priest of Midian, Moses’ father in law, heard of all that God had done for Moses, and for Israel his people, and that the LORD had brought Israel out of Egypt; 2  Then Jethro, Moses’ father in law, took Zipporah, Moses’ wife, after he had sent her back, 3  And her two sons; of which the [*]name of the one was [∥]Gershom; for he said, I have been an alien in a strange land: 4  And the name of the other was [∥]Eliezer; for the God of my father, said he, was mine help, and delivered me from the sword of Pharaoh: 5  And Jethro, Moses’ father in law, came with his sons and his wife unto Moses into the wilderness, where he encamped at the mount of God: 6  And he said unto Moses, I thy father in law Jethro am come unto thee, and thy wife, and her two sons with her.

7 ¶ And Moses went out to meet his father in law, and did obeisance, and kissed him; and they asked each other of their [†]welfare; and they came into the tent. 8  And Moses told his father in law all that the LORD had done unto Pharaoh and to the Egyptians for Israel’s sake, and all the travail that had [†]come upon them by the way, and how the LORD delivered them. 9  And Jethro rejoiced for all the goodness which the LORD had done to Israel, whom he had delivered out of the hand of the Egyptians. 10  And Jethro said, Blessed be the LORD, who hath delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of Pharaoh, who hath delivered the people from under the hand of the Egyptians. 11  Now I know that the LORD is greater than all gods: [*]for in the thing wherein they dealt proudly he was above them. 12  And Jethro, Moses’ father in law, took a burnt offering and sacrifices for God: and Aaron came, and all the elders of Israel, to eat bread with Moses’ father in law before God.

13 ¶ And it came to pass on the morrow, that Moses sat to judge the people: and the people stood by Moses from the morning unto the evening. 14  And when Moses’ father in law saw all that he did to the people, he said, What is this thing that thou doest to the people? why sittest thou thyself alone, and all the people stand by thee from morning unto even? 15  And Moses said unto his father in law, Because the people come unto me to enquire of God: 16  When they have a matter, they come unto me; and I judge between [†]one and another, and I do make them know the statutes of God, and his laws. 17  And Moses’ father in law said unto him, The thing that thou doest is not good. 18 [†] Thou wilt surely wear away, both thou, and this people that is with thee: for this thing is too heavy for thee; [*]thou art not able to perform it thyself alone. 19  Hearken now unto my voice, I will give thee counsel, and God shall be with thee: Be thou for the people to God-ward, that thou mayest bring the causes unto God: 20  And thou shalt teach them ordinances and laws, and shalt shew them the way wherein they must walk, and the work that they must do. 21  Moreover thou shalt provide out of all the people able men, such as fear God, men of truth, hating covetousness; and place such over them, to be rulers of thousands, and rulers of hundreds, rulers of fifties, and rulers of tens: 22  And let them judge the people at all seasons: and it shall be, that every great matter they shall bring unto thee, but every small matter they shall judge: so shall it be easier for thyself, and they shall bear the burden with thee. 23  If thou shalt do this thing, and God command thee so, then thou shalt be able to endure, and all this people shall also go to their place in peace. 24  So Moses hearkened to the voice of his father in law, and did all that he had said. 25  And Moses chose able men out of all Israel, and made them heads over the people, rulers of thousands, rulers of hundreds, rulers of fifties, and rulers of tens. 26  And they judged the people at all seasons: the hard causes they brought unto Moses, but every small matter they judged themselves.

27 ¶ And Moses let his father in law depart; and he went his way into his own land.

19

1  In the third month, when the children of Israel were gone forth out of the land of Egypt, the same day came they into the wilderness of Sinai. 2  For they were departed from Rephidim, and were come to the desert of Sinai, and had pitched in the wilderness; and there Israel camped before the mount. 3  And [*]Moses went up unto God, and the LORD called unto him out of the mountain, saying, Thus shalt thou say to the house of Jacob, and tell the children of Israel; 4 [*] Ye have seen what I did unto the Egyptians, and how I bare you on eagles’ wings, and brought you unto myself. 5  Now [*]therefore, if ye will obey my voice indeed, and keep my covenant, then ye shall be a peculiar treasure unto me above all people: for [*]all the earth is mine: 6  And ye shall be unto me a [*]kingdom of priests, and an holy nation. These are the words which thou shalt speak unto the children of Israel.

7 ¶ And Moses came and called for the elders of the people, and laid before their faces all these words which the LORD commanded him. 8  And [*]all the people answered together, and said, All that the LORD hath spoken we will do. And Moses returned the words of the people unto the LORD.

9  And the LORD said unto Moses, Lo, I come unto thee in a thick cloud, that the people may hear when I speak with thee, and believe thee for ever. And Moses told the words of the people unto the LORD.

10 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Go unto the people, and sanctify them to day and to morrow, and let them wash their clothes, 11  And be ready against the third day: for the third day the LORD will come down in the sight of all the people upon mount Sinai. 12  And thou shalt set bounds unto the people round about, saying, Take heed to yourselves, that ye go not up into the mount, or touch the border of it: [*]whosoever toucheth the mount shall be surely put to death: 13  There shall not an hand touch it, but he shall surely be stoned, or shot through; whether it be beast or man, it shall not live: when the [∥]trumpet soundeth long, they shall come up to the mount.

14 ¶ And Moses went down from the mount unto the people, and sanctified the people; and they washed their clothes. 15  And he said unto the people, Be ready against the third day: come not at your wives.

16 ¶ And it came to pass on the third day in the morning, that there were thunders and lightnings, and a thick cloud upon the mount, and the voice of the trumpet exceeding loud; so that all the people that was in the camp trembled. 17  And Moses brought forth the people out of the camp to meet with God; and they stood at the nether part of the mount. 18  And [*]mount Sinai was altogether on a smoke, because the LORD descended upon it in fire: and the smoke thereof ascended as the smoke of a furnace, and the whole mount quaked greatly. 19  And when the voice of the trumpet sounded long, and waxed louder and louder, Moses spake, and God answered him by a voice. 20  And the LORD came down upon mount Sinai, on the top of the mount: and the LORD called Moses up to the top of the mount; and Moses went up. 21  And the LORD said unto Moses, Go down, [†]charge the people, lest they break through unto the LORD to gaze, and many of them perish. 22  And let the priests also, which come near to the LORD, sanctify themselves, lest the LORD break forth upon them. 23  And Moses said unto the LORD, The people cannot come up to mount Sinai: for thou chargedst us, saying, Set bounds about the mount, and sanctify it. 24  And the LORD said unto him, Away, get thee down, and thou shalt come up, thou, and Aaron with thee: but let not the priests and the people break through to come up unto the LORD, lest he break forth upon them. 25  So Moses went down unto the people, and spake unto them.

20

1  And God spake all these words, saying, 2 [*]I am the LORD thy God, which have brought thee out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of [†]bondage. 3  Thou shalt have no other gods before me. 4 [*] Thou shalt not make unto thee any graven image, or any likeness of any thing that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth: 5  Thou shalt not bow down thyself to them, nor serve them: for I the LORD thy God am a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children unto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me; 6  And shewing mercy unto thousands of them that love me, and keep my commandments. 7 [*] Thou shalt not take the name of the LORD thy God in vain; for the LORD will not hold him guiltless that taketh his name in vain. 8  Remember the sabbath day, to keep it holy. 9 [*] Six days shalt thou labour, and do all thy work: 10  But the seventh day is the sabbath of the LORD thy God: in it thou shalt not do any work, thou, nor thy son, nor thy daughter, thy manservant, nor thy maidservant, nor thy cattle, nor thy stranger that is within thy gates: 11 For [*]in six days the LORD made heaven and earth, the sea, and all that in them is, and rested the seventh day: wherefore the LORD blessed the sabbath day, and hallowed it.

12 ¶ [*]Honour thy father and thy mother: that thy days may be long upon the land which the LORD thy God giveth thee. 13 [*] Thou shalt not kill. 14  Thou shalt not commit adultery. 15  Thou shalt not steal. 16  Thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbour. 17 [*] Thou shalt not covet thy neighbour’s house, thou shalt not covet thy neighbour’s wife, nor his manservant, nor his maidservant, nor his ox, nor his ass, nor any thing that is thy neighbour’s.

18 ¶ And [*]all the people saw the thunderings, and the lightnings, and the noise of the trumpet, and the mountain smoking: and when the people saw it, they removed, and stood afar off. 19  And they said unto Moses, [*]Speak thou with us, and we will hear: but let not God speak with us, lest we die. 20  And Moses said unto the people, Fear not: for God is come to prove you, and that his fear may be before your faces, that ye sin not. 21  And the people stood afar off, and Moses drew near unto the thick darkness where God was.

22 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Thus thou shalt say unto the children of Israel, Ye have seen that I have talked with you from heaven. 23  Ye shall not make with me gods of silver, neither shall ye make unto you gods of gold.

24 ¶ An altar of earth thou shalt make unto me, and shalt sacrifice thereon thy burnt offerings, and thy peace offerings, thy sheep, and thine oxen: in all places where I record my name I will come unto thee, and I will bless thee. 25  And [*]if thou wilt make me an altar of stone, thou shalt not [†]build it of hewn stone: for if thou lift up thy tool upon it, thou hast polluted it. 26  Neither shalt thou go up by steps unto mine altar, that thy nakedness be not discovered thereon.

21

1 Now these are the judgments which thou shalt set before them. 2 [*] If thou buy an Hebrew servant, six years he shall serve: and in the seventh he shall go out free for nothing. 3  If he came in [†]by himself, he shall go out by himself: if he were married, then his wife shall go out with him. 4  If his master have given him a wife, and she have born him sons or daughters; the wife and her children shall be her master’s, and he shall go out by himself. 5  And if the servant [†]shall plainly say, I love my master, my wife, and my children; I will not go out free: 6  Then his master shall bring him unto the judges; he shall also bring him to the door, or unto the door post; and his master shall bore his ear through with an aul; and he shall serve him for ever.

7 ¶ And if a man sell his daughter to be a maidservant, she shall not go out as the menservants do. 8  If she [†]please not her master, who hath betrothed her to himself, then shall he let her be redeemed: to sell her unto a strange nation he shall have no power, seeing he hath dealt deceitfully with her. 9  And if he have betrothed her unto his son, he shall deal with her after the manner of daughters. 10  If he take him another wife; her food, her raiment, and her duty of marriage, shall he not diminish. 11  And if he do not these three unto her, then shall she go out free without money.

12 ¶ [*]He that smiteth a man, so that he die, shall be surely put to death. 13  And if a man lie not in wait, but God deliver him into his hand; then [*]I will appoint thee a place whither he shall flee. 14  But if a man come presumptuously upon his neighbour, to slay him with guile; thou shalt take him from mine altar, that he may die.

15 ¶ And he that smiteth his father, or his mother, shall be surely put to death.

16 ¶ And he that stealeth a man, and selleth him, or if he be found in his hand, he shall surely be put to death.

17 ¶ And [*]he that [∥]curseth his father, or his mother, shall surely be put to death.

18 ¶ And if men strive together, and one smite [∥]another with a stone, or with his fist, and he die not, but keepeth his bed: 19  If he rise again, and walk abroad upon his staff, then shall he that smote him be quit: only he shall pay for [†]the loss of his time, and shall cause him to be thoroughly healed.

20 ¶ And if a man smite his servant, or his maid, with a rod, and he die under his hand; he shall be surely [†]punished. 21  Notwithstanding, if he continue a day or two, he shall not be punished: for he is his money.

22 ¶ If men strive, and hurt a woman with child, so that her fruit depart from her, and yet no mischief follow: he shall be surely punished, according as the woman’s husband will lay upon him; and he shall pay as the judges determine. 23 And if any mischief follow, then thou shalt give life for life, 24 [*] Eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot, 25  Burning for burning, wound for wound, stripe for stripe.

26 ¶ And if a man smite the eye of his servant, or the eye of his maid, that it perish; he shall let him go free for his eye’s sake. 27  And if he smite out his manservant’s tooth, or his maidservant’s tooth; he shall let him go free for his tooth’s sake.

28 ¶ If an ox gore a man or a woman, that they die: then [*]the ox shall be surely stoned, and his flesh shall not be eaten; but the owner of the ox shall be quit. 29  But if the ox were wont to push with his horn in time past, and it hath been testified to his owner, and he hath not kept him in, but that he hath killed a man or a woman; the ox shall be stoned, and his owner also shall be put to death. 30  If there be laid on him a sum of money, then he shall give for the ransom of his life whatsoever is laid upon him. 31  Whether he have gored a son, or have gored a daughter, according to this judgment shall it be done unto him. 32  If the ox shall push a manservant or a maidservant; he shall give unto their master thirty shekels [‡]of silver, and the ox shall be stoned.

33 ¶ And if a man shall open a pit, or if a man shall dig a pit, and not cover it, and an ox or an ass fall therein; 34  The owner of the pit shall make it good, and give money unto the owner of them; and the dead beast shall be his.

35 ¶ And if one man’s ox hurt another’s, that he die; then they shall sell the live ox, and divide the money of it; and the dead ox also they shall divide. 36  Or if it be known that the ox hath used to push in time past, and his owner hath not kept him in; he shall surely pay ox for ox; and the dead shall be his own.

22

1  If a man shall steal an ox, or a [∥]sheep, and kill it, or sell it; he shall restore five oxen for an ox, and [*]four sheep for a sheep.

2 ¶ If a thief be found breaking up, and be smitten that he die, there shall no blood be shed for him. 3  If the sun be risen upon him, there shall be blood shed for him; for he should make full restitution; if he have nothing, then he shall be sold for his theft. 4  If the theft be certainly found in his hand alive, whether it be ox, or ass, or sheep; he shall restore double.

5 ¶ If a man shall cause a field or vineyard to be eaten, and shall put in his beast, and shall feed in another man’s field; of the best of his own field, and of the best of his own vineyard, shall he make restitution.

6 ¶ If fire break out, and catch in thorns, so that the stacks of corn, or the standing corn, or the field, be consumed therewith; he that kindled the fire shall surely make restitution.

7 ¶ If a man shall deliver unto his neighbour money or stuff to keep, and it be stolen out of the man’s house; if the thief be found, let him pay double. 8  If the thief be not found, then the master of the house shall be brought unto the judges, to see whether he have put his hand unto his neighbour’s goods. 9  For all manner of trespass, whether it be for ox, for ass, for sheep, for raiment, or for any manner of lost thing, which another challengeth to be his, the cause of both parties shall come before the judges; and whom the judges shall condemn, he shall pay double unto his neighbour. 10  If a man deliver unto his neighbour an ass, or an ox, or a sheep, or any beast, to keep; and it die, or be hurt, or driven away, no man seeing it: 11  Then shall an oath of the LORD be between them both, that he hath not put his hand unto his neighbour’s goods; and the owner of it shall accept thereof, and he shall not make it good. 12  And [*]if it be stolen from him, he shall make restitution unto the owner thereof. 13  If it be torn in pieces, then let him bring it for witness, and he shall not make good that which was torn.

14 ¶ And if a man borrow ought of his neighbour, and it be hurt, or die, the owner thereof being not with it, he shall surely make it good. 15  But if the owner thereof be with it, he shall not make it good: if it be an hired thing, it came for his hire.

16 ¶ And [*]if a man entice a maid that is not betrothed, and lie with her, he shall surely endow her to be his wife. 17  If her father utterly refuse to give her unto him, he shall [†]pay money according to the dowry of virgins.

18 ¶ Thou shalt not suffer a witch to live.

19 ¶ Whosoever lieth with a beast shall surely be put to death.

20 ¶ [*]He that sacrificeth unto any god, save unto the LORD only, he shall be utterly destroyed.

21 ¶ [*]Thou shalt neither vex a stranger, nor oppress him: for ye were strangers in the land of Egypt.

22 ¶ [*]Ye shall not afflict any widow, or fatherless child. 23  If thou afflict them in any wise, and they cry at all unto me, I will surely hear their cry; 24  And my wrath shall wax hot, and I will kill you with the sword; and your wives shall be widows, and your children fatherless.

25 ¶ [*]If thou lend money to any of my people that is poor by thee, thou shalt not be to him as an usurer, neither shalt thou lay upon him usury. 26  If thou at all take thy neighbour’s raiment to pledge, thou shalt deliver it unto him by that the sun goeth down: 27 For that is his covering only, it is his raiment for his skin: wherein shall he sleep? and it shall come to pass, when he crieth unto me, that I will hear; for I am gracious.

28 ¶ [*]Thou shalt not revile the [∥]gods, nor curse the ruler of thy people.

29 ¶ Thou shalt not delay to offer [†]the first of thy ripe fruits, and of thy [†]liquors: [*]the firstborn of thy sons shalt thou give unto me. 30  Likewise shalt thou do with thine oxen, and with thy sheep: seven days it shall be with his dam; on the eighth day thou shalt give it me.

31 ¶ And ye shall be holy men unto me: [*]neither shall ye eat any flesh that is torn of beasts in the field; ye shall cast it to the dogs.

23

1  Thou shalt not [∥]raise a false report: put not thine hand with the wicked to be an unrighteous witness.

2 ¶ Thou shalt not follow a multitude to do evil; neither shalt thou [†]speak in a cause to decline after many to wrest judgment:

3 ¶ Neither shalt thou countenance a poor man in his cause.

4 ¶ If thou meet thine enemy’s ox or his ass going astray, thou shalt surely bring it back to him again. 5 [*] If thou see the ass of him that hateth thee lying under his burden, [∥]and wouldest forbear to help him, thou shalt surely help with him. 6  Thou shalt not wrest the judgment of thy poor in his cause. 7  Keep thee far from a false matter; and the innocent and righteous slay thou not: for I will not justify the wicked.

8 ¶ And [*]thou shalt take no gift: for the gift blindeth [†]the wise, and perverteth the words of the righteous.

9 ¶ Also thou shalt not oppress a stranger: for ye know the [†]heart of a stranger, seeing ye were strangers in the land of Egypt.

10  And [*]six years thou shalt sow thy land, and shalt gather in the fruits thereof: 11  But the seventh year thou shalt let it rest and lie still; that the poor of thy people may eat: and what they leave the beasts of the field shall eat. In like manner thou shalt deal with thy vineyard, and with thy [∥]oliveyard. 12 [*] Six days thou shalt do thy work, and on the seventh day thou shalt rest: that thine ox and thine ass may rest, and the son of thy handmaid, and the stranger, may be refreshed. 13 And in all things that I have said unto you be circumspect: and make no mention of the [‡]name of other gods, neither let it be heard out of thy mouth.

14 ¶ [*]Three times thou shalt keep a feast unto me in the year. 15 [*] Thou shalt keep the feast of unleavened bread: (thou shalt eat unleavened bread seven days, as I commanded thee, in the time appointed of the month Abib; for in it thou camest out from Egypt: [*]and none shall appear before me empty:) 16  And the feast of harvest, the firstfruits of thy labours, which thou hast sown in the field: and the feast of ingathering, which is in the end of the year, when thou hast gathered in thy labours out of the field. 17  Three times in the year all thy males shall appear before the Lord GOD. 18  Thou shalt not offer the blood of my sacrifice with leavened bread; neither shall the fat of my [∥]sacrifice remain until the morning. 19 [*] The first of the firstfruits of thy land thou shalt bring into the house of the LORD thy God. [*]Thou shalt not seethe a kid in his mother’s milk.

20 ¶ [*]Behold, I send an Angel before thee, to keep thee in the way, and to bring thee into the place which I have prepared. 21  Beware of him, and obey his voice, provoke him not; for he will not pardon your transgressions: for my name is in him. 22  But if thou shalt indeed obey his voice, and do all that I speak; then I will be an enemy unto thine enemies, and an [∥]adversary unto thine adversaries. 23 [*] For mine Angel shall go before thee, and [*]bring thee in unto the Amorites, and the Hittites, and the Perizzites, and the Canaanites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites: and I will cut them off. 24  Thou shalt not bow down to their gods, nor serve them, nor do after their works: [*]but thou shalt utterly overthrow them, and quite break down their images. 25  And ye shall serve the LORD your God, and he shall bless thy bread, and thy water; and I will take sickness away from the midst of thee.

26 ¶ [*]There shall nothing cast their young, nor be barren, in thy land: the number of thy days I will fulfil. 27  I will send my fear before thee, and will destroy all the people to whom thou shalt come, and I will make all thine enemies turn their [†]backs unto thee. 28  And [*]I will send hornets before thee, which shall drive out the Hivite, the Canaanite, and the Hittite, from before thee. 29  I will not drive them out from before thee in one year; lest the land become desolate, and the beast of the field multiply against thee. 30  By little and little I will drive them out from before thee, until thou be increased, and inherit the land. 31  And I will set thy bounds from the Red sea even unto the sea of the Philistines, and from the desert unto the river: for I will deliver the inhabitants of the land into your hand; and thou shalt drive them out before thee. 32 [*] Thou shalt make no covenant with them, nor with their gods. 33  They shall not dwell in thy land, lest they make thee sin against me: for if thou serve their gods, [*]it will surely be a snare unto thee.

24

1  And he said unto Moses, Come up unto the LORD, thou, and Aaron, Nadab, and Abihu, and seventy of the elders of Israel; and worship ye afar off. 2  And Moses alone shall come near the LORD: but they shall not come nigh; neither shall the people go up with him.

3 ¶ And Moses came and told the people all the words of the LORD, and all the judgments: and all the people answered with one voice, and said, [*]All the words which the LORD hath said will we do. 4  And Moses wrote all the words of the LORD, and rose up early in the morning, and builded an altar under the hill, and twelve pillars, according to the twelve tribes of Israel. 5  And he sent young men of the children of Israel, which offered burnt offerings, and sacrificed peace offerings of oxen unto the LORD. 6  And Moses took half of the blood, and put it in basons; and half of the blood he sprinkled on the altar. 7  And he took the book of the covenant, and read in the audience of the people: and they said, [*]All that the LORD hath said will we do, and be obedient. 8  And Moses took the blood, and sprinkled it on the people, and said, Behold [*]the blood of the covenant, which the LORD hath made with you concerning all these words.

9 ¶ Then went up Moses, and Aaron, Nadab, and Abihu, and seventy of the elders of Israel: 10  And they saw the God of Israel: and there was under his feet as it were a paved work of a sapphire stone, and as it were the body of heaven in his clearness. 11  And upon the nobles of the children of Israel he laid not his hand: also they saw God, and did eat and drink.

12 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Come up to me into the mount, and be there: and I will give thee tables of stone, and a law, and commandments which I have written; that thou mayest teach them. 13  And Moses rose up, and his minister Joshua: and Moses went up into the mount of God. 14  And he said unto the elders, Tarry ye here for us, until we come again unto you: and, behold, Aaron and Hur are with you: if any man have any matters to do, let him come unto them. 15  And Moses went up into the mount, and a cloud covered the mount. 16  And the glory of the LORD abode upon mount Sinai, and the cloud covered it six days: and the seventh day he called unto Moses out of the midst of the cloud. 17  And the sight of the glory of the LORD was like devouring fire on the top of the mount in the eyes of the children of Israel. 18  And Moses went into the midst of the cloud, and gat him up into the mount: and [*]Moses was in the mount forty days and forty nights.

25

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2  Speak unto the children of Israel, that they [†]bring me an [†]offering: [*]of every man that giveth it willingly with his heart ye shall take my offering. 3 And this is the offering which ye shall take of them; gold, and silver, and brass, 4  And blue, and purple, and scarlet, and [∥]fine linen, and goats’ hair, 5  And rams’ skins dyed red, and badgers’ skins, and shittim wood, 6  Oil for the light, spices for anointing oil, and for sweet incense, 7  Onyx stones, and stones to be set in the [*]ephod, and in the [*]breastplate. 8  And let them make me a sanctuary; that I may dwell among them. 9  According to all that I shew thee, after the pattern of the tabernacle, and the pattern of all the instruments thereof, even so shall ye make it.

10 ¶ [*]And they shall make an ark of shittim wood: two cubits and a half shall be the length thereof, and a cubit and a half the breadth thereof, and a cubit and a half the height thereof. 11  And thou shalt overlay it with pure gold, within and without shalt thou overlay it, and shalt make upon it a crown of gold round about. 12  And thou shalt cast four rings of gold for it, and put them in the four corners thereof; and two rings shall be in the one side of it, and two rings in the other side of it. 13  And thou shalt make staves of shittim wood, and overlay them with gold. 14  And thou shalt put the staves into the rings by the sides of the ark, that the ark may be borne with them. 15  The staves shall be in the rings of the ark: they shall not be taken from it. 16  And thou shalt put into the ark the testimony which I shall give thee. 17  And thou shalt make a mercy seat of pure gold: two cubits and a half shall be the length thereof, and a cubit and a half the breadth thereof. 18  And thou shalt make two cherubims of gold, of beaten work shalt thou make them, in the two ends of the mercy seat. 19  And make one cherub on the one end, and the other cherub on the other end: even [∥]of the mercy seat shall ye make the cherubims on the two ends thereof. 20  And the cherubims shall stretch forth their wings on high, covering the mercy seat with their wings, and their faces shall look one to another; toward the mercy seat shall the faces of the cherubims be. 21  And thou shalt put the mercy seat above upon the ark; and in the ark thou shalt put the testimony that I shall give thee. 22  And there I will meet with thee, and I will commune with thee from above the mercy seat, from [*]between the two cherubims which are upon the ark of the testimony, of all things which I will give thee in commandment unto the children of Israel.

23 ¶ [*]Thou shalt also make a table of shittim wood: two cubits shall be the length thereof, and a cubit the breadth thereof, and a cubit and a half the height thereof. 24  And thou shalt overlay it with pure gold, and make thereto a crown of gold round about. 25  And thou shalt make unto it a border of an hand breadth round about, and thou shalt make a golden crown to the border thereof round about. 26  And thou shalt make for it four rings of gold, and put the rings in the four corners that are on the four feet thereof. 27  Over against the border shall the rings be for places of the staves to bear the table. 28  And thou shalt make the staves of shittim wood, and overlay them with gold, that the table may be borne with them. 29  And thou shalt make the dishes thereof, and spoons thereof, and covers thereof, and bowls thereof, [∥]to cover withal: of pure gold shalt thou make them. 30  And thou shalt set upon the table shewbread before me alway.

31 ¶ [*]And thou shalt make a candlestick of pure gold: of beaten work shall the candlestick be made: his shaft, and his branches, his bowls, his knops, and his flowers, shall be of the same. 32  And six branches shall come out of the sides of it; three branches of the candlestick out of the one side, and three branches of the candlestick out of the other side: 33  Three bowls made like unto almonds, with a knop and a flower in one branch; and three bowls made like almonds in the other branch, with a knop and a flower: so in the six branches that come out of the candlestick. 34  And in the candlestick shall be four bowls made like unto almonds, with their knops and their flowers. 35 And there shall be a knop under two branches of the same, and a knop under two branches of the same, and a knop under two branches of the same, according to the six branches that proceed out of the candlestick. 36  Their knops and their branches shall be of the same: all it shall be one beaten work of pure gold. 37  And thou shalt make the seven lamps thereof: and they shall [∥]light the lamps thereof, that they may give light over against [†]it. 38  And the tongs thereof, and the snuffdishes thereof, shall be of pure gold. 39  Of a talent of pure gold shall he make it, with all these vessels. 40  And [*]look that thou make them after their pattern, [†]which was shewed thee in the mount.

26

1  Moreover thou shalt make the tabernacle with ten curtains of fine twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet: with cherubims [†]of cunning work shalt thou make them. 2  The length of one curtain shall be eight and twenty cubits, and the breadth of one curtain four cubits: and every one of the curtains shall have one measure. 3  The five curtains shall be coupled together one to another; and other five curtains shall be coupled one to another. 4  And thou shalt make loops of blue upon the edge of the one curtain from the selvedge in the coupling; and likewise shalt thou make in the uttermost edge of another curtain, in the coupling of the second. 5  Fifty loops shalt thou make in the one curtain, and fifty loops shalt thou make in the edge of the curtain that is in the coupling of the second; that the loops may take hold one of another. 6  And thou shalt make fifty taches of gold, and couple the curtains together with the taches: and it shall be one tabernacle.

7 ¶ And thou shalt make curtains of goats’ hair to be a covering upon the tabernacle: eleven curtains shalt thou make. 8  The length of one curtain shall be thirty cubits, and the breadth of one curtain four cubits: and the eleven [‡]curtains shall be all of one measure. 9  And thou shalt couple five curtains by themselves, and six curtains by themselves, and shalt double the sixth curtain in the forefront of the tabernacle. 10  And thou shalt make fifty loops on the edge of the one curtain that is outmost in the coupling, and fifty loops in the edge of the curtain which coupleth the second. 11  And thou shalt make fifty taches of brass, and put the taches into the loops, and couple the [∥]tent together, that it may be one. 12  And the remnant that remaineth of the curtains of the tent, the half curtain that remaineth, shall hang over the backside of the tabernacle. 13  And a cubit on the one side, and a cubit on the other side [†]of that which remaineth in the length of the curtains of the tent, it shall hang over the sides of the tabernacle on this side and on that side, to cover it. 14  And thou shalt make a covering for the tent of rams’ skins dyed red, and a covering above of badgers’ skins.

15 ¶ And thou shalt make boards for the tabernacle of shittim wood standing up. 16  Ten cubits shall be the length of a board, and a cubit and a half shall be the breadth of one board. 17  Two [†]tenons shall there be in one board, set in order one against another: thus shalt thou make for all the boards of the tabernacle. 18  And thou shalt make the boards for the tabernacle, twenty boards on the south side southward. 19  And thou shalt make forty sockets of silver under the twenty boards; two sockets under one board for his two tenons, and two sockets under another board for his two tenons. 20  And for the second side of the tabernacle on the north side there shall be twenty boards: 21  And their forty sockets of silver; two sockets under one board, and two sockets under another board. 22  And for the sides of the tabernacle westward thou shalt make six boards. 23  And two boards shalt thou make for the corners of the tabernacle in the two sides. 24  And they shall be [†]coupled together beneath, and they shall be coupled together above the head of it unto one ring: thus shall it be for them both; they shall be for the two corners. 25  And they shall be eight boards, and their sockets of silver, sixteen sockets; two sockets under one board, and two sockets under another board.

26 ¶ And thou shalt make bars of shittim wood; five for the boards of the one side of the tabernacle, 27  And five bars for the boards of the other side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the boards of the side of the tabernacle, for the two sides westward. 28  And the middle bar in the midst of the boards shall reach from end to end. 29  And thou shalt overlay the boards with gold, and make their rings of gold for places for the bars: and thou shalt overlay the bars with gold. 30  And thou shalt rear up the tabernacle [*]according to the fashion thereof which was shewed thee in the mount.

31 ¶ And thou shalt make a vail of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen of cunning work: with cherubims shall it be made: 32  And thou shalt hang it upon four pillars of shittim wood overlaid with gold: their hooks shall be of gold, upon the four sockets of silver.

33 ¶ And thou shalt hang up the vail under the taches, that thou mayest bring in thither within the vail the ark of the testimony: and the vail shall divide unto you between the holy place and the most holy. 34  And thou shalt put the mercy seat upon the ark of the testimony in the most holy place. 35  And thou shalt set the table without the vail, and the candlestick over against the table on the side of the tabernacle toward the south: and thou shalt put the table on the north side. 36  And thou shalt make an hanging for the door of the tent, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen, wrought with needlework. 37  And thou shalt make for the hanging five pillars of shittim wood, and overlay them with gold, and their hooks shall be of gold: and thou shalt cast five sockets of brass for them.

27

1  And thou shalt make an altar of shittim wood, five cubits long, and five cubits broad; the altar shall be foursquare: and the height thereof shall be three cubits. 2  And thou shalt make the horns of it upon the four corners thereof: his horns shall be of the same: and thou shalt overlay it with brass. 3  And thou shalt make his pans to receive his ashes, and his shovels, and his basons, and his fleshhooks, and his firepans: all the vessels thereof thou shalt make of brass. 4  And thou shalt make for it a grate of network of brass; and upon the net shalt thou make four brasen rings in the four corners thereof. 5  And thou shalt put it under the compass of the altar beneath, that the net may be even to the midst of the altar. 6  And thou shalt make staves for the altar, staves of shittim wood, and overlay them with brass. 7  And the staves shall be put into the rings, and the staves shall be upon the two sides of the altar, to bear it. 8  Hollow with boards shalt thou make it: as [†]it was shewed thee in the mount, so shall they make it.

9 ¶ And thou shalt make the court of the tabernacle: for the south side southward there shall be hangings for the court of fine twined linen of an hundred cubits long for one side: 10  And the twenty pillars thereof and their twenty sockets shall be of brass; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets shall be of silver. 11  And likewise for the north side in length there shall be hangings of an hundred cubits long, and his twenty pillars and their twenty sockets of brass; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets of silver.

12 ¶ And for the breadth of the court on the west side shall be hangings of fifty cubits: their pillars ten, and their sockets ten. 13  And the breadth of the court on the east side eastward shall be fifty cubits. 14  The hangings of one side of the gate shall be fifteen cubits: their pillars three, and their sockets three. 15  And on the other side shall be hangings fifteen cubits: their pillars three, and their sockets three.

16 ¶ And for the gate of the court shall be an hanging of twenty cubits, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen, wrought with needlework: and their pillars shall be four, and their sockets four. 17  All the pillars round about the court shall be filleted with silver; their hooks shall be of silver, and their sockets of brass.

18 ¶ The length of the court shall be an hundred cubits, and the breadth [†]fifty every where, and the height five cubits of fine twined linen, and their sockets of brass. 19  All the vessels of the tabernacle in all the service thereof, and all the pins thereof, and all the pins of the court, shall be of brass.

20 ¶ And thou shalt command the children of Israel, that they bring thee pure oil olive beaten for the light, to cause the lamp [†]to burn always. 21  In the tabernacle of the congregation without the vail, which is before the testimony, Aaron and his sons shall order it from evening to morning before the LORD: it shall be a statute for ever unto their generations on the behalf of the children of Israel.

28

1  And take thou unto thee Aaron thy brother, and his sons with him, from among the children of Israel, that he may minister unto me in the priest’s office, even Aaron, Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar, Aaron’s sons. 2  And thou shalt make holy garments for Aaron thy brother for glory and for beauty. 3  And thou shalt speak unto all that are wise hearted, whom I have filled with the spirit of wisdom, that they may make Aaron’s garments to consecrate him, that he may minister unto me in the priest’s office. 4 And these are the garments which they shall make; a breastplate, and an ephod, and a robe, and a broidered coat, a mitre, and a girdle: and they shall make holy garments for Aaron thy brother, and his sons, that he may minister unto me in the priest’s office. 5  And they shall take gold, and blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine linen.

6 ¶ And they shall make the ephod of gold, of blue, and of purple, of scarlet, and fine twined linen, with cunning work. 7  It shall have the two shoulderpieces thereof joined at the two edges thereof; and so it shall be joined together. 8  And the [∥]curious girdle of the ephod, which is upon it, shall be of the same, according to the work thereof; even of gold, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen. 9  And thou shalt take two onyx stones, and grave on them the names of the children of Israel: 10  Six of their names on one stone, and the other six names of the rest on the other stone, according to their birth. 11 [*] With the work of an engraver in stone, like the engravings of a signet, shalt thou engrave the two stones with the names of the children of Israel: thou shalt make them to be set in ouches of gold. 12  And thou shalt put the two stones upon the shoulders of the ephod for stones of memorial unto the children of Israel: and Aaron shall bear their names before the LORD upon his two shoulders for a memorial.

13 ¶ And thou shalt make ouches of gold; 14  And two chains of pure gold at the ends; of wreathen work shalt thou make them, and fasten the wreathen chains to the ouches.

15 ¶ And thou shalt make the breastplate of judgment with cunning work; after the work of the ephod thou shalt make it; of gold, of blue, and of purple, and of scarlet, and of fine twined linen, shalt thou make it. 16  Foursquare it shall be being doubled; a span shall be the length thereof, and a span shall be the breadth thereof. 17  And thou shalt [†]set in it settings of stones, even four rows of stones: the first row shall be a [∥]sardius, a topaz, and a carbuncle: this shall be the first row. 18  And the second row shall be an emerald, a sapphire, and a diamond. 19  And the third row a ligure, an agate, and an amethyst. 20  And the fourth row a beryl, and an onyx, and a jasper: they shall be set in gold in their [†]inclosings. 21  And the stones shall be with the names of the children of Israel, twelve, according to their names, like the engravings of a signet; every one with his name shall they be according to the twelve tribes.

22 ¶ And thou shalt make upon the breastplate chains at the ends of wreathen work of pure gold. 23  And thou shalt make upon the breastplate two rings of gold, and shalt put the two rings on the two ends of the breastplate. 24  And thou shalt put the two wreathen chains of gold in the two rings which are on the ends of the breastplate. 25 And the other two ends of the two wreathen chains thou shalt fasten in the two ouches, and put them on the shoulderpieces of the ephod before it.

26 ¶ And thou shalt make two rings of gold, and thou shalt put them upon the two ends of the breastplate in the border thereof, which is in the side of the ephod inward. 27  And two other rings of gold thou shalt make, and shalt put them on the two sides of the ephod underneath, toward the forepart thereof, over against the other coupling thereof, above the curious girdle of the ephod. 28  And they shall bind the breastplate by the rings thereof unto the rings of the ephod with a lace of blue, that it may be above the curious girdle of the ephod, and that the breastplate be not loosed from the ephod. 29  And Aaron shall bear the names of the children of Israel in the breastplate of judgment upon his heart, when he goeth in unto the holy place, for a memorial before the LORD continually.

30 ¶ And thou shalt put in the breastplate of judgment the Urim and the Thummim; and they shall be upon Aaron’s heart, when he goeth in before the LORD: and Aaron shall bear the judgment of the children of Israel upon his heart before the LORD continually.

31 ¶ And thou shalt make the robe of the ephod all of blue. 32  And there shall be an hole in the top of it, in the midst thereof: it shall have a binding of woven work round about the hole of it, as it were the hole of an habergeon, that it be not rent.

33 ¶ And beneath upon the [∥]hem of it thou shalt make pomegranates of blue, and of purple, and of scarlet, round about the hem thereof; and bells of gold between them round about: 34  A golden bell and a pomegranate, a golden bell and a pomegranate, upon the hem of the robe round about. 35 [*] And it shall be upon Aaron to minister: and his sound shall be heard when he goeth in unto the holy place before the LORD, and when he cometh out, that he die not.

36 ¶ And thou shalt make a plate of pure gold, and grave upon it, like the engravings of a signet, HOLINESS TO THE LORD. 37  And thou shalt put it on a blue lace, that it may be upon the mitre; upon the forefront of the mitre it shall be. 38  And it shall be upon Aaron’s forehead, that Aaron may bear the iniquity of the holy things, which the children of Israel shall hallow in all their holy gifts; and it shall be always upon his forehead, that they may be accepted before the LORD.

39 ¶ And thou shalt embroider the coat of fine linen, and thou shalt make the mitre of fine linen, and thou shalt make the girdle of needlework.

40 ¶ And for Aaron’s sons thou shalt make coats, and thou shalt make for them girdles, and bonnets shalt thou make for them, for glory and for beauty. 41  And thou shalt put them upon Aaron thy brother, and his sons with him; and shalt anoint them, and [†]consecrate them, and sanctify them, that they may minister unto me in the priest’s office. 42  And thou shalt make them linen breeches to cover [†]their nakedness; from the loins even unto the thighs they shall [†]reach: 43  And they shall be upon Aaron, and upon his sons, when they come in unto the tabernacle of the congregation, or when they come near unto the altar to minister in the holy place; that they bear not iniquity, and die: it shall be a statute for ever unto him and his seed after him.

29

1 And this is the thing that thou shalt do unto them to hallow them, to minister unto me in the priest’s office: [*]Take one young bullock, and two rams without blemish, 2  And unleavened bread, and cakes unleavened tempered with oil, and wafers unleavened anointed with oil: of wheaten flour shalt thou make them. 3  And thou shalt put them into one basket, and bring them in the basket, with the bullock and the two rams. 4  And Aaron and his sons thou shalt bring unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and shalt wash them with water. 5  And thou shalt take the garments, and put upon Aaron the coat, and the robe of the ephod, and the ephod, and the breastplate, and gird him with the curious girdle of the ephod: 6  And thou shalt put the mitre upon his head, and put the holy crown upon the mitre. 7  Then shalt thou take the anointing [*]oil, and pour it upon his head, and anoint him. 8  And thou shalt bring his sons, and put coats upon them. 9  And thou shalt gird them with girdles, Aaron and his sons, and [†]put the bonnets on them: and the priest’s office shall be theirs for a perpetual statute: and thou shalt [†][*]consecrate Aaron and his sons. 10  And thou shalt cause a bullock to be brought before the tabernacle of the congregation: and [*]Aaron and his sons shall put their hands upon the head of the bullock. 11  And thou shalt kill the bullock before the LORD, by the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. 12  And thou shalt take of the blood of the bullock, and put it upon the horns of the altar with thy finger, and pour all the blood beside the bottom of the altar. 13  And [*]thou shalt take all the fat that covereth the inwards, and [∥]the caul that is above the liver, and the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, and burn them upon the altar. 14  But the flesh of the bullock, and his skin, and his dung, shalt thou burn with fire without the camp: it is a sin offering.

15 ¶ Thou shalt also take one ram; and Aaron and his sons shall put their hands upon the head of the ram. 16  And thou shalt slay the ram, and thou shalt take his blood, and sprinkle it round about upon the altar. 17  And thou shalt cut the ram in pieces, and wash the inwards of him, and his legs, and put them unto his pieces, and [∥]unto his head. 18  And thou shalt burn the whole ram upon the altar: it is a burnt offering unto the LORD: it is a sweet savour, an offering made by fire unto the LORD.

19 ¶ And thou shalt take the other ram; and Aaron and his sons shall put their hands upon the head of the ram. 20  Then shalt thou kill the ram, and take of his blood, and put it upon the tip of the right ear of Aaron, and upon the tip of the right ear of his sons, and upon the thumb of their right hand, and upon the great toe of their right foot, and sprinkle the blood upon the altar round about. 21  And thou shalt take of the blood that is upon the altar, and of the anointing oil, and sprinkle it upon Aaron, and upon his garments, and upon his sons, and upon the garments of his sons with him: and he shall be hallowed, and his garments, and his sons, and his sons’ garments with him. 22  Also thou shalt take of the ram the fat and the rump, and the fat that covereth the inwards, and the caul above the liver, and the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, and the right shoulder; for it is a ram of consecration: 23  And one loaf of bread, and one cake of oiled bread, and one wafer out of the basket of the unleavened bread that is before the LORD: 24  And thou shalt put all in the hands of Aaron, and in the hands of his sons; and shalt [∥]wave them for a wave offering before the LORD. 25  And thou shalt receive them of their hands, and burn them upon the altar for a burnt offering, for a sweet savour before the LORD: it is an offering made by fire unto the LORD. 26  And thou shalt take the breast of the ram of Aaron’s [‡]consecration, and wave it for a wave offering before the LORD: and it shall be thy part. 27  And thou shalt sanctify the breast of the wave offering, and the shoulder of the heave offering, which is waved, and which is heaved up, of the ram of the consecration, even of that which is for Aaron, and of that which is for his sons: 28  And it shall be Aaron’s and his sons’ by a statute for ever from the children of Israel: for it is an heave offering: and it shall be an heave offering from the children of Israel of the sacrifice of their peace offerings, even their heave offering unto the LORD.

29 ¶ And the holy garments of Aaron shall be his sons’ after him, to be anointed therein, and to be consecrated in them. 30  And [†]that son that is priest in his stead shall put them on seven days, when he cometh into the tabernacle of the congregation to minister in the holy place.

31 ¶ And thou shalt take the ram of the consecration, and seethe his flesh in the holy place. 32  And Aaron and his sons shall eat the flesh of the ram, and the [*]bread that is in the basket, by the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. 33  And they shall eat those things wherewith the atonement was made, to consecrate and to sanctify them: but a stranger shall not eat thereof, because they are holy. 34  And if ought of the flesh of the consecrations, or of the bread, remain unto the morning, then thou shalt burn the remainder with fire: it shall not be eaten, because it is holy. 35  And thus shalt thou do unto Aaron, and to his sons, according to all things which I have commanded thee: seven days shalt thou consecrate them. 36  And thou shalt offer every day a bullock for a sin offering for atonement: and thou shalt cleanse the altar, when thou hast made an atonement for it, and thou shalt anoint it, to sanctify it. 37  Seven days thou shalt make an atonement for the altar, and sanctify it; and it shall be an altar most holy: whatsoever toucheth the altar shall be holy.

38 ¶ Now this is that which thou shalt offer upon the altar; [*]two lambs of the first year day by day continually. 39  The one lamb thou shalt offer in the morning; and the other lamb thou shalt offer at even: 40  And with the one lamb a tenth deal of flour mingled with the fourth part of an hin of beaten oil; and the fourth part of an hin of wine for a drink offering. 41  And the other lamb thou shalt offer at even, and shalt do thereto according to the meat offering of the morning, and according to the drink offering thereof, for a sweet savour, an offering made by fire unto the LORD. 42  This shall be a continual burnt offering throughout your generations at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation before the LORD: where I will meet you, to speak there unto thee. 43  And there I will meet with the children of Israel, and [∥]the tabernacle shall be sanctified by my glory. 44  And I will sanctify the tabernacle of the congregation, and the altar: I will sanctify also both Aaron and his sons, to minister to me in the priest’s office.

45 ¶ And [*]I will dwell among the children of Israel, and will be their God. 46  And they shall know that I am the LORD their God, that brought them forth out of the land of Egypt, that I may dwell among them: I am the LORD their God.

30

1  And thou shalt make an altar to burn incense upon: of shittim wood shalt thou make it. 2  A cubit shall be the length thereof, and a cubit the breadth thereof; foursquare shall it be: and two cubits shall be the height thereof: the horns thereof shall be of the same. 3  And thou shalt overlay it with pure gold, the [†]top thereof, and the [†]sides thereof round about, and the horns thereof; and thou shalt make unto it a crown of gold round about. 4  And two golden rings shalt thou make to it under the crown of it, by the two [†]corners thereof, upon the two sides of it shalt thou make it; and they shall be for places for the staves to bear it withal. 5  And thou shalt make the staves of shittim wood, and overlay them with gold. 6  And thou shalt put it before the vail that is by the ark of the testimony, before the mercy seat that is over the testimony, where I will meet with thee. 7  And Aaron shall burn thereon [†]sweet incense every morning: when he dresseth the lamps, he shall burn incense upon it. 8  And when Aaron [∥][†]lighteth the lamps [†]at even, he shall burn incense upon it, a perpetual incense before the LORD throughout your generations. 9  Ye shall offer no strange incense thereon, nor burnt sacrifice, nor meat offering; neither shall ye pour drink offering thereon. 10  And Aaron shall make an atonement upon the horns of it once in a year with the blood of the sin offering of atonements: once in the year shall he make atonement upon it throughout your generations: it is most holy unto the LORD.

11 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 12 [*] When thou takest the sum of the children of Israel after [†]their number, then shall they give every man a ransom for his soul unto the LORD, when thou numberest them; that there be no plague among them, when thou numberest them. 13  This they shall give, every one that passeth among them that are numbered, half a shekel after the shekel of the sanctuary: ([*]a shekel is twenty gerahs:) an half shekel shall be the offering of the LORD. 14  Every one that passeth among them that are numbered, from twenty years old and above, shall give an offering unto the LORD. 15  The rich shall not [†]give more, and the poor shall not [†]give less than half a shekel, when they give an offering unto the LORD, to make an atonement for your souls. 16  And thou shalt take the atonement money of the children of Israel, and shalt appoint it for the service of the tabernacle of the congregation; that it may be a memorial unto the children of Israel before the LORD, to make an atonement for your souls.

17 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 18  Thou shalt also make a laver of brass, and his foot also of brass, to wash withal: and thou shalt put it between the tabernacle of the congregation and the altar, and thou shalt put water therein. 19  For Aaron and his sons shall wash their hands and their feet thereat: 20  When they go into the tabernacle of the congregation, they shall wash with water, that they die not; or when they come near to the altar to minister, to burn offering made by fire unto the LORD: 21  So they shall wash their hands and their feet, that they die not: and it shall be a statute for ever to them, even to him and to his seed throughout their generations.

22 ¶ Moreover the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 23  Take thou also unto thee principal spices, of pure myrrh five hundred shekels, and of sweet cinnamon half so much, even two hundred and fifty shekels, and of sweet calamus two hundred and fifty shekels, 24  And of cassia five hundred shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary, and of oil olive an [*]hin: 25  And thou shalt make it an oil of holy ointment, an ointment compound after the art of the [∥]apothecary: it shall be an holy anointing oil. 26  And thou shalt anoint the tabernacle of the congregation therewith, and the ark of the testimony, 27  And the table and all his vessels, and the candlestick and his vessels, and the altar of incense, 28  And the altar of burnt offering with all his vessels, and the laver and his foot. 29  And thou shalt sanctify them, that they may be most holy: whatsoever toucheth them shall be holy. 30  And thou shalt anoint Aaron and his sons, and consecrate them, that they may minister unto me in the priest’s office. 31  And thou shalt speak unto the children of Israel, saying, This shall be an holy anointing oil unto me throughout your generations. 32  Upon man’s flesh shall it not be poured, neither shall ye make any other like it, after the composition of it: it is holy, and it shall be holy unto you. 33  Whosoever compoundeth any like it, or whosoever putteth any of it upon a stranger, shall even be cut off from his people.

34 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Take unto thee sweet spices, stacte, and onycha, and galbanum; these sweet spices with pure frankincense: of each shall there be a like weight: 35  And thou shalt make it a perfume, a confection after the art of the apothecary, [†]tempered together, pure and holy: 36  And thou shalt beat some of it very small, and put of it before the testimony in the tabernacle of the congregation, where I will meet with thee: it shall be unto you most holy. 37 And as for the perfume which thou shalt make, ye shall not make to yourselves according to the composition thereof: it shall be unto thee holy for the LORD. 38  Whosoever shall make like unto that, to smell thereto, shall even be cut off from his people.

31

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2  See, I have called by name Bezaleel the [*]son of Uri, the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah: 3  And I have filled him with the spirit of God, in wisdom, and in understanding, and in knowledge, and in all manner of workmanship, 4  To devise cunning works, to work in gold, and in silver, and in brass, 5  And in cutting of stones, to set them, and in carving of timber, to work in all manner of workmanship. 6  And I, behold, I have given with him Aholiab, the son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan: and in the hearts of all that are wise hearted I have put wisdom, that they may make all that I have commanded thee; 7  The tabernacle of the congregation, and the ark of the testimony, and the mercy seat that is thereupon, and all the [†]furniture of the tabernacle, 8  And the table and his furniture, and the pure candlestick with all his furniture, and the altar of incense, 9  And the altar of burnt offering with all his furniture, and the laver and his foot, 10  And the cloths of service, and the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons, to minister in the priest’s office, 11  And the anointing oil, and sweet incense for the holy place: according to all that I have commanded thee shall they do.

12 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 13  Speak thou also unto the children of Israel, saying, Verily my sabbaths ye shall keep: for it is a sign between me and you throughout your generations; that ye may know that I am the LORD that doth sanctify you. 14 [*] Ye shall keep the sabbath therefore; for it is holy unto you: every one that defileth it shall surely be put to death: for whosoever doeth any work therein, that soul shall be cut off from among his people. 15  Six days may work be done; but in the seventh is the sabbath of rest, [†]holy to the LORD: whosoever doeth any work in the sabbath day, he shall surely be put to death. 16  Wherefore the children of Israel shall keep the sabbath, to observe the sabbath throughout their generations, for a perpetual covenant. 17 It is a sign between me and the children of Israel for ever: for [*]in six days the LORD made heaven and earth, and on the seventh day he rested, and was refreshed.

18 ¶ And he gave unto Moses, when he had made an end of communing with him upon mount Sinai, [*]two tables of testimony, tables of stone, written with the finger of God.

32

1  And when the people saw that Moses delayed to come down out of the mount, the people gathered themselves together unto Aaron, and said unto him, [*]Up, make us gods, which shall go before us; for as for this Moses, the man that brought us up out of the land of Egypt, we wot not what is become of him. 2  And Aaron said unto them, Break off the golden earrings, which are in the ears of your wives, of your sons, and of your daughters, and bring them unto me. 3  And all the people brake off the golden earrings which were in their ears, and brought them unto Aaron. 4 [*] And he received them at their hand, and fashioned it with a graving tool, after he had made it a molten calf: and they said, These be thy gods, O Israel, which brought thee up out of the land of Egypt. 5  And when Aaron saw it, he built an altar before it; and Aaron made proclamation, and said, To morrow is a feast to the LORD. 6  And they rose up early on the morrow, and offered burnt offerings, and brought peace offerings; and the [*]people sat down to eat and to drink, and rose up to play.

7 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, [*]Go, get thee down; for thy people, which thou broughtest out of the land of Egypt, have corrupted themselves: 8 [*] They have turned aside quickly out of the way which I commanded them: they have made them a molten calf, and have worshipped it, and have sacrificed thereunto, and said, These be thy gods, O Israel, which have brought thee up out of the land of Egypt. 9  And the LORD said unto Moses, [*]I have seen this people, and, behold, it is a stiffnecked people: 10  Now therefore let me alone, that my wrath may wax hot against them, and that I may consume them: and I will make of thee a great nation. 11 [*] And Moses besought [†]the LORD his God, and said, LORD, why doth thy wrath wax hot against thy people, which thou hast brought forth out of the land of Egypt with great power, and with a mighty hand? 12 [*] Wherefore should the Egyptians speak, and say, For mischief did he bring them out, to slay them in the mountains, and to consume them from the face of the earth? Turn from thy fierce wrath, and repent of this evil against thy people. 13  Remember Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, thy servants, to whom thou swarest by thine own self, and saidst unto them, [*]I will multiply your seed as the stars of heaven, and all this land that I have spoken of will I give unto your seed, and they shall inherit it for ever. 14  And the LORD repented of the evil which he thought to do unto his people.

15 ¶ And Moses turned, and went down from the mount, and the two tables of the testimony were in his hand: the tables were written on both their sides; on the one side and on the other were they written. 16  And the [*]tables were the work of God, and the writing was the writing of God, graven upon the tables. 17  And when Joshua heard the noise of the people as they shouted, he said unto Moses, There is a noise of war in the camp. 18  And he said, It is not the voice of them that shout for mastery, neither is it the voice of them that cry for [†]being overcome: but the noise of them that sing do I hear.

19 ¶ And it came to pass, as soon as he came nigh unto the camp, that he saw the calf, and the dancing: and Moses’ anger waxed hot, and he cast the tables out of his hands, and brake them beneath the mount. 20 [*] And he took the calf which they had made, and burnt it in the fire, and ground it to powder, and strawed it upon the water, and made the children of Israel drink of it.

21  And Moses said unto Aaron, What did this people unto thee, that thou hast brought so great a sin upon them? 22  And Aaron said, Let not the anger of my lord wax hot: thou knowest the people, that they are set on mischief. 23  For they said unto me, Make us gods, which shall go before us: for as for this Moses, the man that brought us up out of the land of Egypt, we wot not what is become of him. 24  And I said unto them, Whosoever hath any gold, let them break it off. So they gave it me: then I cast it into the fire, and there came out this calf.

25 ¶ And when Moses saw that the people were naked; (for Aaron had made them naked unto their shame among [†]their enemies:) 26  Then Moses stood in the gate of the camp, and said, Who is on the LORD’s side? let him come unto me. And all the sons of Levi gathered themselves together unto him. 27  And he said unto them, Thus saith the LORD God of Israel, Put every man his sword by his side, and go in and out from gate to gate throughout the camp, and slay every man his brother, and every man his companion, and every man his neighbour. 28  And the children of Levi did according to the word of Moses: and there fell of the people that day about three thousand men. 29 [∥] For Moses had said, [†]Consecrate yourselves to day to the LORD, even every man upon his son, and upon his brother; that he may bestow upon you a blessing this day.

30 ¶ And it came to pass on the morrow, that Moses said unto the people, Ye have sinned a great sin: and now I will go up unto the LORD; peradventure I shall make an atonement for your sin. 31  And Moses returned unto the LORD, and said, Oh, this people have sinned a great sin, and have made them gods of gold. 32  Yet now, if thou wilt forgive their sin—; and if not, blot me, I pray thee, out of thy book which thou hast written. 33  And the LORD said unto Moses, Whosoever hath sinned against me, him will I blot out of my book. 34  Therefore now go, lead the people unto the place of which I have spoken unto thee: behold, mine Angel shall go before thee: nevertheless in the day when I visit I will visit their sin upon them. 35  And the LORD plagued the people, because they made the calf, which Aaron made.

33

1  And the LORD said unto Moses, Depart, and go up hence, thou and the people which thou hast brought up out of the land of Egypt, unto the land which I sware unto Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, saying, [*]Unto thy seed will I give it: 2 [*] And I will send an angel before thee; and I will drive out the Canaanite, the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite: 3  Unto a land flowing with milk and honey: for I will not go up in the midst of thee; for thou art a [*]stiffnecked people: lest I consume thee in the way.

4 ¶ And when the people heard these evil tidings, they mourned: and no man did put on him his ornaments. 5  For the LORD had said unto Moses, Say unto the children of Israel, Ye are a stiffnecked people: I will come up into the midst of thee in a moment, and consume thee: therefore now put off thy ornaments from thee, that I may know what to do unto thee. 6  And the children of Israel stripped themselves of their ornaments by the mount Horeb.

7  And Moses took the tabernacle, and pitched it without the camp, afar off from the camp, and called it the Tabernacle of the congregation. And it came to pass, that every one which sought the LORD went out unto the tabernacle of the congregation, which was without the camp. 8  And it came to pass, when Moses went out unto the tabernacle, that all the people rose up, and stood every man at his tent door, and looked after Moses, until he was gone into the tabernacle. 9  And it came to pass, as Moses entered into the tabernacle, the cloudy pillar descended, and stood at the door of the tabernacle, and the LORD talked with Moses. 10  And all the people saw the cloudy pillar stand at the tabernacle door: and all the people rose up and worshipped, every man in his tent door. 11  And the LORD spake unto Moses face to face, as a man speaketh unto his friend. And he turned again into the camp: but his servant Joshua, the son of Nun, a young man, departed not out of the tabernacle.

12 ¶ And Moses said unto the LORD, See, thou sayest unto me, Bring up this people: and thou hast not let me know whom thou wilt send with me. Yet thou hast said, I know thee by name, and thou hast also found grace in my sight. 13  Now therefore, I pray thee, if I have found grace in thy sight, shew me now thy way, that I may know thee, that I may find grace in thy sight: and consider that this nation is thy people. 14  And he said, My presence shall go with thee, and I will give thee rest. 15  And he said unto him, If thy presence go not with me, carry us not up hence. 16  For wherein shall it be known here that I and thy people have found grace in thy sight? is it not in that thou goest with us? so shall we be separated, I and thy people, from all the people that are upon the face of the earth. 17  And the LORD said unto Moses, I will do this thing also that thou hast spoken: for thou hast found grace in my sight, and I know thee by name. 18  And he said, I beseech thee, shew me thy glory. 19  And he said, I will make all my goodness pass before thee, and I will proclaim the name of the LORD before thee; [*]and will be gracious to whom I will be gracious, and will shew mercy on whom I will shew mercy. 20  And he said, Thou canst not see my face: for there shall no man see me, and live. 21  And the LORD said, Behold, there is a place by me, and thou shalt stand upon a rock: 22  And it shall come to pass, while my glory passeth by, that I will put thee in a clift of the rock, and will cover thee with my hand while I pass by: 23  And I will take away mine hand, and thou shalt see my back parts: but my face shall not be seen.

34

1  And the LORD said unto Moses, [*]Hew thee two tables of stone like unto the first: and I will write upon these tables the words that were in the first tables, which thou brakest. 2  And be ready in the morning, and come up in the morning unto mount Sinai, and present thyself there to me in the top of the mount. 3  And no man shall [*]come up with thee, neither let any man be seen throughout all the mount; neither let the flocks nor herds feed before that mount.

4 ¶ And he hewed two tables of stone like unto the first; and Moses rose up early in the morning, and went up unto mount Sinai, as the LORD had commanded him, and took in his hand the two tables of stone.

5  And the LORD descended in the cloud, and stood with him there, and proclaimed the name of the LORD. 6  And the LORD passed by before him, and proclaimed, The LORD, The LORD God, merciful and gracious, longsuffering, and abundant in goodness and truth, 7  Keeping mercy for thousands, forgiving iniquity and transgression and sin, and that will by no means clear the guilty; [*]visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children, and upon the children’s children, unto the third and to the fourth generation. 8  And Moses made haste, and bowed his head toward the earth, and worshipped. 9  And he said, If now I have found grace in thy sight, O Lord, let my Lord, I pray thee, go among us; for it is a stiffnecked people; and pardon our iniquity and our sin, and take us for thine inheritance.

10 ¶ And he said, Behold, [*]I make a covenant: before all thy people I will do marvels, such as have not been done in all the earth, nor in any nation: and all the people among which thou art shall see the work of the LORD: for it is a terrible thing that I will do with thee. 11  Observe thou that which I command thee this day: behold, I drive out before thee the Amorite, and the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite. 12 [*] Take heed to thyself, lest thou make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land whither thou goest, lest it be for a snare in the midst of thee: 13  But ye shall destroy their altars, break their [†]images, and cut down their groves: 14  For thou shalt worship no other god: for the LORD, whose name is Jealous, is a [*]jealous God: 15  Lest thou make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land, and they go a whoring after their gods, and do sacrifice unto their gods, and one call thee, and thou eat of his sacrifice; 16  And thou take of [*]their daughters unto thy sons, and their daughters go a whoring after their gods, and make thy sons go a whoring after their gods. 17  Thou shalt make thee no molten gods.

18 ¶ The feast of [*]unleavened bread shalt thou keep. Seven days thou shalt eat unleavened bread, as I commanded thee, in the time of the month Abib: for in the [*]month Abib thou camest out from Egypt. 19 [*] All that openeth the matrix is mine; and every firstling among thy cattle, whether ox or sheep, that is male. 20  But the firstling of an ass thou shalt redeem with a [∥]lamb: and if thou redeem him not, then shalt thou break his neck. All the firstborn of thy sons thou shalt redeem. And none shall appear before me [*]empty.

21 ¶ [*]Six days thou shalt work, but on the seventh day thou shalt rest: in earing time and in harvest thou shalt rest.

22 ¶ [*]And thou shalt observe the feast of weeks, of the firstfruits of wheat harvest, and the feast of ingathering at the [†]year’s end.

23 ¶ [*]Thrice in the year shall all your men children appear before the Lord GOD, the God of Israel. 24  For I will cast out the nations before thee, and enlarge thy borders: neither shall any man desire thy land, when thou shalt go up to appear before the LORD thy God thrice in the year. 25 [*] Thou shalt not offer the blood of my sacrifice with leaven; neither shall the sacrifice of the feast of [‡]the passover be left unto the morning. 26  The first of the firstfruits of thy land thou shalt bring unto the house of the LORD thy God. Thou shalt not seethe a [*]kid in his mother’s milk. 27  And the LORD said unto Moses, Write thou [*]these words: for after the tenor of these words I have made a covenant with thee and with Israel.

28 [*] And he was there with the LORD forty days and forty nights; he did neither eat bread, nor drink water. And he wrote upon the tables the words of the covenant, the ten [†]commandments.

29 ¶ And it came to pass, when Moses came down from mount Sinai with the two tables of testimony in Moses’ hand, when he came down from the mount, that Moses wist not that the skin of his face shone while he talked with him. 30  And when Aaron and all the children of Israel saw Moses, behold, the skin of his face shone; and they were afraid to come nigh him. 31  And Moses called unto them; and Aaron and all the rulers of the congregation returned unto him: and Moses talked with them. 32  And afterward all the children of Israel came nigh: and he gave them in commandment all that the LORD had spoken with him in mount Sinai. 33 And till Moses had done speaking with them, he put [*]a vail on his face. 34  But when Moses went in before the LORD to speak with him, he took the vail off, until he came out. And he came out, and spake unto the children of Israel that which he was commanded. 35  And the children of Israel saw the face of Moses, that the skin of Moses’ face shone: and Moses put the vail upon his face again, until he went in to speak with him.

35

1  And Moses gathered all the congregation of the children of Israel together, and said unto them, These are the words which the LORD hath commanded, that ye should do them. 2 [*] Six days shall work be done, but on the seventh day there shall be to you [†]an holy day, a sabbath of rest to the LORD: whosoever doeth work therein shall be put to death. 3  Ye shall kindle no fire throughout your habitations upon the sabbath day.

4 ¶ And Moses spake unto all the congregation of the children of Israel, saying, This is the thing which the LORD commanded, saying, 5  Take ye from among you an offering unto the LORD: [*]whosoever is of a willing heart, let him bring it, an offering of the LORD; gold, and silver, and brass, 6  And blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine linen, and goats’ hair, 7  And rams’ skins dyed red, and badgers’ skins, and shittim wood, 8  And oil for the light, and spices for anointing oil, and for the sweet incense, 9  And onyx stones, and stones to be set for the ephod, and for the breastplate. 10  And every wise hearted among you shall come, and make all that the LORD hath commanded; 11 [*] The tabernacle, his tent, and his covering, his taches, and [‡]his boards, his bars, his pillars, and his sockets, 12  The ark, and the staves thereof, with the mercy seat, and the vail of the covering, 13  The table, and his staves, and all his vessels, and the shewbread, 14  The candlestick also for the light, and his furniture, and his lamps, with the oil for the light, 15 [*] And the incense altar, and his staves, and the anointing oil, and the sweet incense, and the hanging for the door at the entering in of the tabernacle, 16 [*] The altar of burnt offering, with his brasen grate, his staves, and all his vessels, the laver and his foot, 17  The hangings of the court, his pillars, and their sockets, and the hanging for the door of the court, 18  The pins of the tabernacle, and the pins of the court, and their cords, 19  The cloths of service, to do service in the holy place, the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons, to minister in the priest’s office.

20 ¶ And all the congregation of the children of Israel departed from the presence of Moses. 21  And they came, every one whose heart stirred him up, and every one whom his spirit made willing, and they brought the LORD’s offering to the work of the tabernacle of the congregation, and for all his service, and for the holy garments. 22  And they came, both men and women, as many as were willing hearted, and brought bracelets, and earrings, and rings, and tablets, all jewels of gold: and every man that offered offered an offering of gold unto the LORD. 23  And every man, with whom was found blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine linen, and goats’ hair, and red skins of rams, and badgers’ skins, brought them. 24  Every one that did offer an offering of silver and brass brought the LORD’s offering: and every man, with whom was found shittim wood for any work of the service, brought it. 25  And all the women that were wise hearted did spin with their hands, and brought that which they had spun, both of blue, and of purple, and of scarlet, and of fine linen. 26  And all the women whose heart stirred them up in wisdom spun goats’ hair. 27  And the rulers brought onyx stones, and stones to be set, for the ephod, and for the breastplate; 28  And [*]spice, and oil for the light, and for the anointing oil, and for the sweet incense. 29  The children of Israel brought a willing offering unto the LORD, every man and woman, whose heart made them willing to bring for all manner of work, which the LORD had commanded to be made by the [‡]hand of Moses.

30 ¶ And Moses said unto the children of Israel, See, [*]the LORD hath called by name Bezaleel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah; 31  And he hath filled him with the spirit of God, in wisdom, in understanding, and in knowledge, and in all manner of workmanship; 32  And to devise curious works, to work in gold, and in silver, and in brass, 33  And in the cutting of stones, to set them, and in carving of wood, to make any manner of cunning work. 34  And he hath put in his heart that he may teach, both he, and Aholiab, the son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan. 35  Them hath he filled with wisdom of heart, to work all manner of work, of the engraver, and of the cunning workman, and of the embroiderer, in blue, and in purple, in scarlet, and in fine linen, and of the weaver, even of them that do any work, and of those that devise cunning work.

36

1  Then wrought Bezaleel and Aholiab, and every wise hearted man, in whom the LORD put wisdom and understanding to know how to work all manner of work for the service of the sanctuary, according to all that the LORD had commanded. 2  And Moses called Bezaleel and Aholiab, and every wise hearted man, in whose heart the LORD had put wisdom, even every one whose heart stirred him up to come unto the work to do it: 3  And they received of Moses all the offering, which the children of Israel had brought for the work of the service of the sanctuary, to make it withal. And they brought yet unto him free offerings every morning. 4  And all the wise men, that wrought all the work of the sanctuary, came every man from his work which they made;

5 ¶ And they spake unto Moses, saying, The people bring much more than enough for the service of the work, which the LORD commanded to make. 6  And Moses gave commandment, and they caused it to be proclaimed throughout the camp, saying, Let neither man nor woman make any more work for the offering of the sanctuary. So the people were restrained from bringing. 7  For the stuff they had was sufficient for all the work to make it, and too much.

8 ¶ [*]And every wise hearted man among them that wrought the work of the tabernacle made ten curtains of fine twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet: with cherubims of cunning work made he them. 9  The length of one curtain was twenty and eight cubits, and the breadth of one curtain four cubits: the curtains were all of one size. 10  And he coupled the five curtains one unto another: and the other five curtains he coupled one unto another. 11  And he made loops of blue on the edge of one curtain from the selvedge in the coupling: likewise he made in the uttermost side of another curtain, in the coupling of the second. 12 [*] Fifty loops made he in one curtain, and fifty loops made he in the edge of the curtain which was in the coupling of the second: the loops held one curtain to another. 13  And he made fifty taches of gold, and coupled the curtains one unto another with the taches: so it became one tabernacle.

14 ¶ And he made curtains of goats’ hair for the tent over the tabernacle: eleven curtains he made them. 15  The length of one curtain was thirty cubits, and four cubits was the breadth of one curtain: the eleven curtains were of one size. 16  And he coupled five curtains by themselves, and six curtains by themselves. 17  And he made fifty loops upon the uttermost edge of the curtain in the coupling, and fifty loops made he upon the edge of the curtain which coupleth the second. 18  And he made fifty taches of brass to couple the tent together, that it might be one. 19  And he made a covering for the tent of rams’ skins dyed red, and a covering of badgers’ skins above that.

20 ¶ And he made boards for the tabernacle of shittim wood, standing up. 21  The length of a board was ten cubits, and the breadth of a board one cubit and a half. 22  One board had two tenons, equally distant one from another: thus did he make for all the boards of the tabernacle. 23  And he made boards for the tabernacle; twenty boards for the south side southward: 24  And forty sockets of silver he made under the twenty boards; two sockets under one board for his two tenons, and two sockets under another board for his two tenons. 25  And for the other side of the tabernacle, which is toward the north corner, he made twenty boards, 26  And their forty sockets of silver; two sockets under one board, and two sockets under another board. 27  And for the sides of the tabernacle westward he made six boards. 28  And two boards made he for the corners of the tabernacle in the two sides. 29  And they were [†]coupled beneath, and coupled together at the head thereof, to one ring: thus he did to both of them in both the corners. 30  And there were eight boards; and their sockets were sixteen sockets of silver, [†]under every board two sockets.

31 ¶ And he made [*]bars of shittim wood; five for the boards of the one side of the tabernacle, 32  And five bars for the boards of the other side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the boards of the tabernacle for the sides westward. 33  And he made the middle bar to shoot through the boards from the one end to the other. 34  And he overlaid the boards with gold, and made their rings of gold to be places for the bars, and overlaid the bars with gold.

35 ¶ And he made a vail of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen: with cherubims made he it of cunning work. 36  And he made thereunto four pillars of shittim wood, and overlaid them with gold: their hooks were of gold; and he cast for them four sockets of silver.

37 ¶ And he made an hanging for the tabernacle door of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen, [†]of needlework; 38  And the five pillars of it with their hooks: and he overlaid their chapiters and their fillets with gold: but their five sockets were of brass.

37

1  And Bezaleel [*]made the ark of shittim wood: two cubits and a half was the length of it, and a cubit and a half the breadth of it, and a cubit and a half the height of it: 2  And he overlaid it with pure gold within and without, and made a crown of gold to it round about. 3  And he cast for it four rings of gold, to be set by the four corners of it; even two rings upon the one side of it, and two rings upon the other side of it. 4  And he made staves of shittim wood, and overlaid them with gold. 5  And he put the staves into the rings by the sides of the ark, to bear the ark.

6 ¶ And he made the [*]mercy seat of pure gold: two cubits and a half was the length thereof, and one cubit and a half the breadth thereof. 7  And he made two cherubims of gold, beaten out of one piece made he them, on the two ends of the mercy seat; 8 [∥] One cherub [∥]on the end on this side, and another cherub on the other end on that side: out of the mercy seat made he the cherubims on the two ends thereof. 9  And the cherubims spread out their wings on high, and covered with their wings over the mercy seat, with their faces one to another; even to the mercy seatward were the faces of the cherubims.

10 ¶ And he made the table of shittim wood: two cubits was the length thereof, and a cubit the breadth thereof, and a cubit and a half the height thereof: 11  And he overlaid it with pure gold, and made thereunto a crown of gold round about. 12  Also he made thereunto a border of an handbreadth round about; and made a crown of gold for the border thereof round about. 13  And he cast for it four rings of gold, and put the rings upon the four corners that were in the four feet thereof. 14  Over against the border were the rings, the places for the staves to bear the table. 15  And he made the staves of shittim wood, and overlaid them with gold, to bear the table. 16  And he made the vessels which were upon the table, his [*]dishes, and his spoons, and his bowls, and his covers [∥]to cover withal, of pure gold.

17 ¶ And he made the [*]candlestick of pure gold: of beaten work made he the candlestick; his shaft, and his branch, his bowls, his knops, and his flowers, were of the same: 18  And six branches going out of the sides thereof; three branches of the candlestick out of the one side thereof, and three branches of the candlestick out of the other side thereof: 19  Three bowls [‡]made after the fashion of almonds in one branch, a knop and a flower; and three bowls made like almonds in another branch, a knop and a flower: so throughout the six branches going out of the candlestick. 20  And in the candlestick were four bowls made like almonds, his knops, and his flowers: 21  And a knop under two branches of the same, and a knop under two branches of the same, and a knop under two branches of the same, according to the six branches going out of it. 22  Their knops and their branches were of the same: all of it was one beaten work of pure gold. 23  And he made his seven lamps, and his snuffers, and his snuffdishes, of pure gold. 24  Of a talent of pure gold made he it, and all the vessels thereof.

25 ¶ [*]And he made the incense altar of shittim wood: the length of it was a cubit, and the breadth of it a cubit; it was foursquare; and two cubits was the height of it; the horns thereof were of the same. 26  And he overlaid it with pure gold, both the top of it, and the sides thereof round about, and the horns of it: also he made unto it a crown of gold round about. 27  And he made two rings of gold for it under the crown thereof, by the two corners of it, upon the two sides thereof, to be places for the staves to bear it withal. 28  And he made the staves of shittim wood, and overlaid them with gold.

29 ¶ And he made [*]the holy anointing oil, and the pure incense of sweet spices, according to the work of the apothecary.

38

1  And [*]he made the altar of burnt offering of shittim wood: five cubits was the length thereof, and five cubits the breadth thereof; it was foursquare; and three cubits the height thereof. 2  And he made the horns thereof on the four corners of it; the horns thereof were of the same: and he overlaid it with brass. 3  And he made all the vessels of the altar, the pots, and the shovels, and the basons, and the fleshhooks, and the firepans: all the vessels thereof made he of brass. 4  And he made for the altar a brasen grate of network under the compass thereof beneath unto the midst of it. 5  And he cast four rings for the four ends of the grate of brass, to be places for the staves. 6  And he made the staves of shittim wood, and overlaid them with brass. 7  And he put the staves into the rings on the sides of the altar, to bear it withal; he made the altar hollow with boards.

8 ¶ [∥]And he made the laver of brass, and the foot of it of brass, of the lookingglasses of the women [†]assembling, which assembled at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.

9 ¶ And he made the court: on the south side southward the hangings of the court were of fine twined linen, an hundred cubits: 10  Their pillars were twenty, and their brasen sockets twenty; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets were of silver. 11  And for the north side the hangings were an hundred cubits, their pillars were twenty, and their sockets of brass twenty; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets of silver. 12  And for the west side were hangings of fifty cubits, their pillars ten, and their sockets ten; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets of silver. 13  And for the east side eastward fifty cubits. 14  The hangings of the one side of the gate were fifteen cubits; their pillars three, and their sockets three. 15  And for the other side of the court gate, on this hand and that hand, were hangings of fifteen cubits; their pillars three, and their sockets three. 16  All the hangings of the court round about were of fine twined linen. 17  And the sockets for the pillars were of brass; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets of silver; and the overlaying of their chapiters of silver; and all the pillars of the court were filleted with silver. 18  And the hanging for the gate of the court was needlework, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen: and twenty cubits was the length, and the height in the breadth was five cubits, answerable to the hangings of the court. 19  And their pillars were four, and their sockets of brass four; their hooks of silver, and the overlaying of their chapiters and their fillets of silver. 20  And all the [*]pins of the tabernacle, and of the court round about, were of brass.

21 ¶ This is the sum of the tabernacle, even of the tabernacle of testimony, as it was counted, according to the commandment of Moses, for the service of the Levites, by the hand of Ithamar, son to Aaron the priest. 22  And Bezaleel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah, made all that the LORD commanded Moses. 23 And with him was Aholiab, son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan, an engraver, and a cunning workman, and an embroiderer in blue, and in purple, and in scarlet, and fine linen. 24  All the gold that was occupied for the work in all the work of the holy place, even the gold of the offering, was twenty and nine talents, and seven hundred and thirty shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary. 25  And the silver of them that were numbered of the congregation was an hundred talents, and a thousand seven hundred and threescore and fifteen shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary: 26  A bekah for [†]every man, that is, half a shekel, after the shekel of the sanctuary, for every one that went to be numbered, from twenty years old and upward, for six hundred thousand and three thousand and five hundred and fifty men. 27  And of the hundred talents of silver were cast the sockets of the sanctuary, and the sockets of the vail; an hundred sockets of the hundred talents, a talent for a socket. 28  And of the thousand seven hundred seventy and five shekels he made hooks for the pillars, and overlaid their chapiters, and filleted them. 29  And the brass of the offering was seventy talents, and two thousand and four hundred shekels. 30  And therewith he made the sockets to the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and the brasen altar, and the brasen grate for it, and all the vessels of the altar, 31  And the sockets of the court round about, and the sockets of the court gate, and all the pins of the tabernacle, and all the pins of the court round about.

39

1  And of the blue, and purple, and scarlet, they made cloths of service, to do service in the holy place, and [*]made the holy garments for Aaron; as the LORD commanded Moses. 2  And he made the ephod of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen. 3  And they did beat the gold into thin plates, and cut it into wires, to work it in the blue, and in the purple, and in the scarlet, and in the fine linen, with cunning work. 4  They made shoulderpieces for it, to couple it together: by the two edges was it coupled together. 5  And the curious girdle of his ephod, that was upon it, was of the same, according to the work thereof; of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen; as the LORD commanded Moses.

6 ¶ [*]And they wrought onyx stones inclosed in ouches of gold, graven, as signets are graven, with the names of the children of Israel. 7  And he put them on the shoulders of the ephod, that they should be stones for a [*]memorial to the children of Israel; as the LORD commanded Moses.

8 ¶ And he made the breastplate of cunning work, like the work of the ephod; of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen. 9  It was foursquare; they made the breastplate double: a span was the length thereof, and a span the breadth thereof, being doubled. 10  And they set in it four rows of stones: the first row was a [∥]sardius, a topaz, and a carbuncle: this was the first row. 11  And the second row, an emerald, a sapphire, and a diamond. 12  And the third row, a ligure, an agate, and an amethyst. 13  And the fourth row, a beryl, an onyx, and a jasper: they were inclosed in ouches of gold in their inclosings. 14  And the stones were according to the names of the children of Israel, twelve, according to their names, like the engravings of a signet, every one with his name, according to the twelve tribes. 15  And they made upon the breastplate chains at the ends, of wreathen work of pure gold. 16  And they made two ouches of gold, and two gold rings; and put the two rings in the two ends of the breastplate. 17  And they put the two wreathen chains of gold in the two rings on the ends of the breastplate. 18  And the two ends of the two wreathen chains they fastened in the two ouches, and put them on the shoulderpieces of the ephod, before it. 19  And they made two rings of gold, and put them on the two ends of the breastplate, upon the border of it, which was on the side of the ephod inward. 20  And they made two other golden rings, and put them on the two sides of the ephod underneath, toward the forepart of it, over against the other coupling thereof, above the curious girdle of the ephod. 21  And they did bind the breastplate by his rings unto the rings of the ephod with a lace of blue, that it might be above the curious girdle of the ephod, and that the breastplate might not be loosed from the ephod; as the LORD commanded Moses.

22 ¶ And he made the robe of the ephod of woven work, all of blue. 23 And there was an hole in the midst of the robe, as the hole of an habergeon, with a band round about the hole, that it should not rend. 24  And they made upon the hems of the robe pomegranates of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen. 25  And they made [*]bells of pure gold, and put the bells between the pomegranates upon the hem of the robe, round about between the pomegranates; 26  A bell and a pomegranate, a bell and a pomegranate, round about the hem of the robe to minister in; as the LORD commanded Moses.

27 ¶ And they made coats of fine linen of woven work for Aaron, and for his sons, 28  And a mitre of fine linen, and goodly bonnets of fine linen, and [*]linen breeches of fine twined linen, 29  And a girdle of fine twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet, of needlework; as the LORD commanded Moses.

30 ¶ And they made the plate of the holy crown of pure gold, and wrote upon it a writing, like to the engravings of a signet, [*]HOLINESS TO THE LORD. 31  And they tied unto it a lace of blue, to fasten it on high upon the mitre; as the LORD commanded Moses.

32 ¶ Thus was all the work of the tabernacle of the tent of the congregation finished: and the children of Israel did according to all that the LORD commanded Moses, so did they.

33 ¶ And they brought the tabernacle unto Moses, the tent, and all his furniture, his taches, his boards, his bars, and his pillars, and his sockets, 34  And the covering of rams’ skins dyed red, and the covering of badgers’ skins, and the vail of the covering, 35  The ark of the testimony, and the staves thereof, and the mercy seat, 36  The table, and all the vessels thereof, and the shewbread, 37  The pure candlestick, with the lamps thereof, even with the lamps to be set in order, and all the vessels thereof, and the oil for light, 38  And the golden altar, and the anointing oil, and [†]the sweet incense, and the hanging for the tabernacle door, 39  The brasen altar, and his grate of brass, his staves, and all his vessels, the laver and his foot, 40  The hangings of the court, his pillars, and his sockets, and the hanging for the court gate, his cords, and his pins, and all the vessels of the service of the tabernacle, for the tent of the congregation, 41  The cloths of service to do service in the holy place, and the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and his sons’ garments, to minister in the priest’s office. 42  According to all that the LORD commanded Moses, so the children of Israel made all the work. 43  And Moses did look upon all the work, and, behold, they had done it as the LORD had commanded, even so had they done it: and Moses blessed them.

40

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2  On the first day of the first month shalt thou set up the tabernacle of the tent of the congregation. 3  And thou shalt put therein the ark of the testimony, and cover the ark with the vail. 4  And [*]thou shalt bring in the table, and set in order [†]the things that are to be set in order upon it; and thou shalt bring in the candlestick, and light the lamps thereof. 5  And thou shalt set the altar of gold for the incense before the ark of the testimony, and put the hanging of the door to the tabernacle. 6  And thou shalt set the altar of the burnt offering before the door of the tabernacle of the tent of the congregation. 7  And thou shalt set the laver between the tent of the congregation and the altar, and shalt put water therein. 8  And thou shalt set up the court round about, and hang up the hanging at the court gate. 9  And thou shalt take the anointing oil, and anoint the tabernacle, and all that is therein, and shalt hallow it, and all the vessels thereof: and it shall be holy. 10  And thou shalt anoint the altar of the burnt offering, and all his vessels, and sanctify the altar: and it shall be an altar [†]most holy. 11  And thou shalt anoint the laver and his foot, and sanctify it. 12  And thou shalt bring Aaron and his sons unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and wash them with water. 13  And thou shalt put upon Aaron the holy garments, and anoint him, and sanctify him; that he may minister unto me in the priest’s office. 14  And thou shalt bring his sons, and clothe them with coats: 15  And thou shalt anoint them, as thou didst anoint their father, that they may minister unto me in the priest’s office: for their anointing shall surely be an everlasting priesthood throughout their generations.

16  Thus did Moses: according to all that the LORD commanded him, so did he.

17 ¶ And it came to pass in the first month in the second year, on the first day of the month, that the [*]tabernacle was reared up. 18  And Moses reared up the tabernacle, and fastened his sockets, and set up the boards thereof, and put in the bars thereof, and reared up his pillars. 19  And he spread abroad the tent over the tabernacle, and put the covering of the tent above upon it; as the LORD commanded Moses.

20 ¶ And he took and put the testimony into the ark, and set the staves on the ark, and put the mercy seat above upon the ark: 21  And he brought the ark into the tabernacle, and [*]set up the vail of the covering, and covered the ark of the testimony; as the LORD commanded Moses.

22 ¶ And he put the table in the tent of the congregation, upon the side of the tabernacle northward, without the vail. 23  And he set the bread in order upon it before the LORD; as the LORD had commanded Moses.

24 ¶ And he put the candlestick in the tent of the congregation, over against the table, on the side of the tabernacle southward. 25  And he lighted the lamps before the LORD; as the LORD commanded Moses.

26 ¶ And he put the golden altar in the tent of the congregation before the vail: 27  And he burnt sweet incense thereon; as the LORD commanded Moses.

28 ¶ And he set up the hanging at the door of the tabernacle. 29  And he put the altar of burnt offering by the door of the tabernacle of the tent of the congregation, and offered upon it the burnt offering and the meat offering; as the [*]LORD commanded Moses.

30 ¶ And he set the laver between the tent of the congregation and the altar, and put water there, to wash withal. 31  And Moses and Aaron and his sons washed their hands and their feet thereat: 32  When they went into the tent of the congregation, and when they came near unto the altar, they washed; as the LORD commanded Moses. 33  And he reared up the court round about the tabernacle and the altar, and set up the hanging of the court gate. So Moses finished the work.

34 ¶ [*]Then a cloud covered the tent of the congregation, and the glory of the LORD filled the tabernacle. 35  And Moses was not able to enter into the tent of the congregation, because the cloud abode thereon, and the glory of the LORD filled the tabernacle. 36  And when the cloud was taken up from over the tabernacle, the children of Israel [†]went onward in all their journeys: 37  But if the cloud were not taken up, then they journeyed not till the day that it was taken up. 38  For the cloud of the LORD was upon the tabernacle by day, and fire was on it by night, in the sight of all the house of Israel, throughout all their journeys.

* 1.1 Gen. 46. 8. ch. 6. 14.

† 1.5 Heb. thigh.

* 1.5 Gen. 46. 27. Deut. 10. 22

* 1.7 Acts 7. 17.

† 1.12 Heb. And as they afflicted them, so they multiplied, &c.

* 2.1 ch. 6. 20 Num. 26. 59.

* 2.2 Acts 7. 20 Heb. 11. 23.

∥ 2.10 That is, Drawn out.

† 2.14 Heb. a man, a prince.

∥ 2.16 Or, prince.

* 2.22 ch. 18. 3.

* 2.24 Gen. 15. 14. &c 46. 4.

† 2.25 Heb. knew.

* 3.2 Acts 7. 30.

* 3.5 Josh. 5. 15. Acts 7. 33.

* 3.6 Matt. 22 32. Acts 7. 32

∥ 3.19 Or, but by strong hand.

* 3.22 ch. 11. 2 &c 12. 35.

∥ 3.22 Or, Egypt.

† 4.9 Heb. shall be and shall be.

† 4.10 Heb. a man of words.

† 4.10 Heb. since yesterday, nor since the third day.

* 4.12 Matt. 10 19. Mark 13. 11. Luke 12. 11.

∥ 4.13 Or, shouldest.

* 4.16 ch 7. 1.

∥ 4.25 Or, knife.

† 4.25 Heb. made it touch.

* 5.3 ch. 3. 18.

† 5.9 Heb. Let the work be heavy upon the men.

† 5.13 Heb. a matter of a day in his day.

† 5.21 Heb. to stink.

† 5.23 Heb. delivering thou hast not delivered.

† 6.8 Heb. lift up my hand.

† 6.9 Heb. skortness, or straitness.

* 6.14 Gen. 46 9. 1 Chr 5. 3.

* 6.15 1 Chr. 4. 24

* 6.16 Num. 3 17. 1 Chr. 6. 1.

* 6.18 Num 26 57. 1 Chr. 6. 2.

* 6.20 ch. 2 1. Num. 26 59.

* 6.25 Num. 25. 11.

† 7.19 Heb. gathering of their waters.

* 7.20 ch. 17. 5.

* 7.20 Ps. 78. 44.

* 7.22 Wisd. 17. 7.

∥ 8.3 Or, dough.

* 8.7 Wisd. 17. 7.

∥ 8.9 Or, Have this honour over me, &c.

∥ 8.9 Or, against when.

† 8.9 Heb. to cut off.

∥ 8.10 Or, Against to morrow.

∥ 8.21 Or, a mixture of noisome beasts, &c.

† 8.23 Heb. a redemptior.

∥ 8.23 Or, by to morrow.

* 8.24 Wisd. 16. 9.

∥ 8.24 Or, destroyed

* 8.27 ch. 3. 18.

* 9.12 ch. 4. 21.

* 9.16 Rom. 9. 17.

† 9.16 Heb. made thee stand.

† 9.21 Heb. set not his heart unto.

† 9.28 Heb. voices of God.

* 9.29 Ps. 24. 1.

† 9.32 Heb. hidden, or, dark.

† 9.35 Heb. by the hand of Moses.

* 10.1 ch. 4. 21.

* 10.4 Wisd. 16. 9.

† 10.5 Heb. eye.

† 10.8 Heb. who and who, &c.

† 10.16 Heb. hastened to call.

† 10.19 Heb. fastened.

† 10.21 Heb. that one may feel darkness.

* 10.23 Wisd. 18. 1.

† 10.25 Heb. into our hands.

* 11.2 ch. 3. 22 &c 12. 35.

* 11.3 Ecclus. 45. 1.

* 11.4 ch. 12. 29.

† 11.8 Heb. that is at thy feet.

† 11.8 Heb. heat of anger.

∥ 12.3 Or, kid.

† 12.5 Heb. son of a year.

† 12.6 Heb. between the two evenings.

∥ 12.12 Or, princes.

† 12.13 Heb. for a destruction.

† 12.16 Heb. soul.

* 12.18 Lev. 23. 5. Num. 28. 16.

∥ 12.21 Or, kid.

* 12.22 Heb. 11. 28.

* 12.26 Josh. 4 6

* 12.29 ch. 11. 4

* 12.29 Wisd. 18. 11.

† 12.29 Heb. house of the pit.

∥ 12.34 Or, dough.

* 12.35 ch. 3. 22 &c 11. 2.

* 12.37 Num. 33. 3.

† 12.38 Heb. a great mixture.

* 12.40 Gen. 15. 13. Acts 7. 6. Gal. 3. 17.

† 12.42 Heb a night of observations.

* 12.46 Num. 9. 12. John 19. 36.

† 12.47 Heb. do it.

* 13.2 ch. 22. 29. &c 84. 19. Lev. 27. 26. Num. 3. 13 &c 8 16. Luke 2. 23.

† 13.3 Heb. servants.

* 13.12 ch. 22. 29. &c 34. 19. Ezek. 44. 30.

† 13.12 Heb. cause to pass over.

∥ 13.13 Or, kid.

† 13.14 Heb. to morrow.

∥ 13.18 Or, by five in a rank.

* 13.19 Gen. 50. 25. Josh. 24. 32.

* 13.20 Num. 33. 6.

* 13.21 Num. 14 14. Deut. 1. 33 Ps 78. 14. 1 Cor. 10 1.

* 13.22 Neh. 9. 19.

* 14.2 Num. 33 7.

* 14.9 Josh. 24 6. 1 Mac. 4. 23

* 14.12 ch. 6. 9.

∥ 14.13 Or, for whereas you have seen the Egyptians to day, &c.

* 14.21 Josh. 4. 23. l's. 114. 3

* 14.22 Ps. 78. 13 1 Cor. 10. 1. Heb. 11 29.

∥ 14.25 Or, and made them to qo heavily.

† 14.27 Heb. shook off.

* 14.28 Ps. 106. 11.

† 14.31 Heb. hand.

* 15.1 Wisd. 10. 20.

∥ 15.9 Or, repossess.

∥ 15.11 Or, mighty ones?

* 15.14 Deut. 2. 25. Josh. 2. 9.

* 15.16 Deut. 2. 25. Josh. 2. 9.

∥ 15.23 That is, Bitterness.

* 15.25 Ecclus. 38. 5.

‡ 15.25 [1611 omits for them]

* 15.27 Num. 33. 9.

† 16.4 Heb. the portion of a day in his day.

* 16.10 ch. 13. 21.

* 16.13 Num. 11. 31.

* 16.14 Num. 11. 7. Ps. 78. 24. Wisd. 16. 20.

∥ 16.15 Or, What is this? or, It is a portion.

* 16.15 John 6. 31. 1 Cor. 10. 3.

† 16.16 Heb. by the poll, or, head.

† 16.16 Heb. souls.

* 16.18 2 Cor. 8. 15.

* 16.35 Josh. 5. 12. Neh. 9. 15.

* 17.2 Num. 20. 4.

* 17.5 ch. 7. 20.

* 17.6 Num. 20 9. Ps. 78. 15 &c 105. 41. Wisd. 11. 4. 1 Cor. 10. 4.

∥ 17.7 That is, Tentation.

∥ 17.7 That is, Chiding, or, Strife.

* 17.8 Deut. 25. 17. Wisd. 11. 3.

* 17.9 Acts 7. 45.

* 17.14 Num. 24. 20. 1 Sam. 15. 3.

∥ 17.15 That is, The Lord my banner.

∥ 17.16 Or, Because the hand of Amalek is against the throne of the Lord, therefore, &c.

† 17.16 Heb. the hand upon the throne of the Lord.

* 18.1 ch. 2. 16.

* 18.3 ch. 2. 22.

∥ 18.3 That is, A stranger there.

∥ 18.4 That is, My God is an help.

† 18.7 Heb. peace.

† 18.8 Heb. found them.

* 18.11 ch. 1. 10, 16, 22. &c 5. 7. &c 14. 18.

† 18.16 Heb. a man and his fellow.

† 18.18 Heb. Fading thou wilt fade.

* 18.18 Deut. 1. 9.

* 19.3 Acts 7. 38.

* 19.4 Deut. 29. 2.

* 19.5 Deut. 5 2.

* 19.5 Deut. 10. 14. Ps. 24. 1.

* 19.6 1 Pet. 2. 9. Rev. 1. 6.

* 19.8 ch. 24 3, 7. Deut. 5. 27. &c 26. 17.

* 19.12 Heb. 12. 20.

∥ 19.13 Or, cornet.

* 19.18 Deut. 4. 11.

† 19.21 Heb. contest.

* 20.2 Deut. 5. 6. Ps. 81. 10.

† 20.2 Heb. servants.

* 20.4 Lev. 26. 1. Ps. 97. 7.

* 20.7 Lev. 19. 12. Deut. 5. 11. Matt. 5. 33.

* 20.9 ch. 23. 12. Ezek. 20. 12. Luke 13. 14.

* 20.11 Gen. 2. 2.

* 20.12 Deut. 5. 16. Matt. 15. 4. Eph. 6. 2.

* 20.13 Matt. 5. 21.

* 20.17 Rom. 7. 7.

* 20.18 Heb. 12. 18.

* 20.19 Deut. 5 27. &c 18. 16.

* 20.25 Deut. 27. 5. Josh. 8. 31.

† 20.25 Heb. build them with hewing.

* 21.2 Lev. 25 41. Deut. 15. 12. Jer. 34. 14.

† 21.3 Heb. with his body.

† 21.5 Heb. saying shall say.

† 21.8 Heb. be evil in the eyes of, &c.

* 21.12 Lev. 24. 17.

* 21.13 Deut. 19. 3.

* 21.17 Lev. 20 9. Prov. 20. 20 Matt. 15. 4. Mark 7. 10.

∥ 21.17 Or, revileth.

∥ 21.18 Or, his neighbour.

† 21.19 Heb. his ceasing.

† 21.20 Heb avenged.

* 21.24 Lev. 24. 20. Deut. 19. 21. Matt. 5. 38.

* 21.28 Gen. 9. 5.

‡ 21.32 [1611 omits of silver]

∥ 22.1 Or, goat.

* 22.1 2 Sam. 12. 6.

* 22.12 Gen. 31. 39.

* 22.16 Deut. 22. 23.

† 22.17 Heb. weigh.

* 22.20 Deut. 13 13, 14, 15 1 Mac. 2. 24.

* 22.21 Lev. 19 33.

* 22.22 Zech. 7. 10.

* 22.25 Lev. 25. 37. Deut. 23. 19. Pa. 15. 5.

* 22.28 Acts 23. 5.

∥ 22.28 Or, judges.

† 22.29 Heb. thy fulness.

† 22.29 Heb. tear.

* 22.29 ch 13. 2, 12. &c 34. 19.

* 22.31 Lev. 22. 8 Ezek. 44. 31.

∥ 23.1 Or, receive.

† 23.2 Heb. answer.

* 23.5 Deut. 22. 4.

∥ 23.5 Or, wilt thou cease to help him? or, and wouldest cease to leave thy business for him: thou shalt surely leave it to join with him.

* 23.8 Deut. 16. 19. Ecclus. 20. 29.

† 23.8 Heb. the seeing.

† 23.9 Heb. soul.

* 23.10 Lev. 25. 3.

∥ 23.11 Or, olive trees.

* 23.12 ch. 20. 8. Deut. 5. 13. Luke 13. 14.

‡ 23.13 [1611 names]

* 23.14 Deut. 16. 16.

* 23.15 ch. 13. 3. &c 34. 18.

* 23.15 Deut. 16. 16. Ecclus. 35. 4.

∥ 23.18 Or, feast

* 23.19 ch. 34. 26

* 23.19 Deut. 14. 21.

* 23.20 ch. 33. 2.

∥ 23.22 Or, I will afflict them that afflict thee.

* 23.23 ch. 33. 2.

* 23.23 Josh. 24. 11.

* 23.24 Deut. 7. 25.

* 23.26 Deut. 7. 14.

† 23.27 Heb. neck.

* 23.28 Josh. 24. 12.

* 23.32 ch. 34. 15. Deut. 7. 2.

* 23.33 Deut. 7. 16. Josh. 23. 13. Judg. 2. 3.

* 24.3 ch. 19. 8. &c 24. 3, 7. Deut. 5. 27.

* 24.7 ver. 3.

* 24.8 1 Pet. 1. 2. Heb. 9. 20.

* 24.18 ch. 34. 28. Deut 9 9.

† 25.2 Heb take for me.

† 25.2 Or, heave offering.

* 25.2 ch. 35. 5.

∥ 25.4 Or, silk.

* 25.7 ch. 28. 4.

* 25.7 ch. 28. 15.

* 25.10 ch. 37. 1.

∥ 25.19 Or, of the matter of the mercy seat.

* 25.22 Num. 7. 89.

* 25.23 ch. 37. 10.

∥ 25.29 Or, to pour out withal.

* 25.31 ch. 37. 17.

∥ 25.37 Or, cause to ascend.

† 25.37 Heb. the face of it.

* 25.40 Acts 7. 44. Heb. 8. 5.

† 25.40 Heb. which thou wast caused to see.

† 26.1 Heb. the work of a cunning workman, or, embroiderer.

‡ 26.8 [1611 omits curtains]

∥ 26.11 Or, covering.

† 26.13 Heb. in the remainder, or, surplusage.

† 26.17 Heb. hands.

† 26.24 Heb. twinned.

* 26.30 ch. 25. 9, 40. Acts 7. 44. Heb. 8. 5.

† 27.8 Heb. he shewed.

† 27.18 Heb. fifty by fifty

† 27.20 Heb to ascend up.

∥ 28.8 Or, embroidered.

* 28.11 Wisd. 13. 24.

† 28.17 Heb. fill in it fillings of stone.

∥ 28.17 Or, ruby.

† 28.20 Heb. fillings.

∥ 28.33 Or, skirts.

* 28.35 Ecclus. 45. 9.

† 28.41 Heb. fill their hand.

† 28.42 Heb. flesh of then nakedness.

† 28.42 Heb. be.

* 29.1 Lev 8. 2.

* 29.7 ch. 30. 25.

† 29.9 Heb. bind.

† 29.9 Heb. fill the hand of.

* 29.9 ch. 28. 41.

* 29.10 Lev. 1. 4.

* 29.13 Lev. 3. 3.

∥ 29.13 It seemeth by anatomy, and the Hebrew doctors, to be the midriff

∥ 29.17 Or, upon.

∥ 29.24 Or, shake to and fro.

‡ 29.26 [1611 consecrations]

† 29.30 Heb. he of his sons.

* 29.32 Lev. 8. 31. Matt 12. 4.

* 29.38 Num. 28. 3.

∥ 29.43 Or, Israel.

* 29.45 Lev. 26. 12. 2 Cor. 6. 16.

† 30.3 Heb. the roof and the walls.

† 30.3 Heb. walls.

† 30.4 Heb. ribs.

† 30.7 Heb. incense of spices.

∥ 30.8 Or, setteth up.

† 30.8 Heb. causeth to ascend.

† 30.8 Heb. between the two events.

* 30.12 Num. 1. 2, 5.

† 30.12 Heb. them that are to be numbered.

* 30.13 Lev. 27. 25. Num. 3. 47. Ezek. 45. 12.

† 30.15 Heb. multiply.

† 30.15 Heb. diminish.

* 30.24 ch. 29. 40.

∥ 30.25 Or, perfumer.

† 30.35 Heb salted.

* 31.2 1 Chr. 2. 20.

† 31.7 Heb. vessels.

* 31.14 ch. 20. 8. Deut. 5. 12 Ezek. 20. 12.

† 31.15 Heb. holiness.

* 31.17 Gen. 1. 31. &c 2. 2.

* 31.18 Deut. 9. 10.

* 32.1 Acts 7. 40.

* 32.4 Ps. 106. 19 1 Kings 12. 28.

* 32.6 1 Cor. 10. 7.

* 32.7 Deut. 9. 12.

* 32.8 Deut. 9. 8.

* 32.9 ch. 33 3. Deut. 9. 13.

* 32.11 Ps. 106. 23.

† 32.11 Heb. the face of the Lord.

* 32.12 Num. 14. 13.

* 32.13 Gen. 12. 7. &c 15 7. &c 48. 16.

* 32.16 ch 31. 18.

† 32.18 Heb. weakness.

* 32.20 Deut. 9. 21.

† 32.25 Heb. those that rose up against them.

∥ 32.29 Or, And Moses said, Consecrate yourselves to day to the Lord, because, every man hath been against his son, and against his brother, &c.

† 32.29 Heb. Fill your hands.

* 33.1 Gen. 12. 7.

* 33.2 Deut. 7. 22. Josh 24. 11.

* 33.3 ch. 32. 9. Deut. 9. 13.

* 33.19 Rom. 9. 16.

* 34.1 Deut. 10. 1.

* 34.3 ch. 19. 12.

* 34.7 ch. 20. 5. Deut. 5. 9. Jer. 32. 18.

* 34.10 Deut. 5. 2.

* 34.12 ch. 23. 32 Deut. 7. 2.

† 34.13 Heb statues.

* 34.14 ch. 20. 5.

* 34.16 1 Kings 11. 2

* 34.18 ch 23. 15.

* 34.18 ch 13. 4.

* 34.19 ch. 22. 29 Ezek. 44. 30

∥ 34.20 Or, kid

* 34.20 ch. 23. 15.

* 34.21 ch. 23. 12. Deut 5. 12 Luke 13 14.

* 34.22 ch. 23. 16.

† 34.22 Heb revolution of the year.

* 34.23 ch 23. 14. 17. Deut. 16. 16.

* 34.25 ch 23. 18.

‡ 34.25 [1611 omits the]

* 34.26 ch. 23. 19. Deut. 14. 21.

* 34.27 Deut. 4. 13.

* 34.28 ch. 24. 18. Deut. 9. 9.

† 34.28 Heb. words.

* 34.33 2 Cor. 3. 13.

* 35.2 ch. 20. 9 Lev 23 3. Deut. 5 12 Luke 13. 14.

† 35.2 Heb. holiness.

* 35.5 ch. 25 2

* 35.11 ch. 26. 31.

‡ 35.11 [1611 omits his boards,]

* 35.15 ch. 30. 1.

* 35.16 ch. 27. 1.

* 35.28 ch. 30. 23.

‡ 35.29 [1611 hands]

* 35.30 ch. 31. 2.

* 36.8 ch. 26. 1.

* 36.12 ch. 26. 10.

† 36.29 Heb. twinned.

† 36.30 Heb. two sockets, two sockets under one board.

* 36.31 ch. 25. 28. &c 30. 5.

† 36.37 Heb. the work of a needleworker, or, embroiderer.

* 37.1 ch. 25. 10.

* 37.6 ch. 25. 17.

∥ 37.8 Or, out of, &c.

∥ 37.8 Or, out of, &c.

* 37.16 ch. 25. 29.

∥ 37.16 Or, to pour out withal.

* 37.17 ch. 25. 31.

‡ 37.19 [1611 made he after]

* 37.25 ch. 30. 1.

* 37.29 ch. 30. 35.

* 38.1 ch. 27. 1.

∥ 38.8 Or, brasen glasses.

† 38.8 Heb. assembling by troops.

* 38.20 ch. 27. 19.

† 38.26 Heb. a poll.

* 39.1 ch. 31. 10. &c 35. 19.

* 39.6 ch. 28. 9.

* 39.7 ch. 28. 12.

∥ 39.10 Or, Ruby.

* 39.25 ch. 28. 33.

* 39.28 ch. 28. 42.

* 39.30 ch. 28. 36.

† 39.38 Heb. the incense of sweet spices.

* 40.4 ch. 26. 35.

† 40.4 Heb the order thereof.

† 40.10 Heb. holiness of holinesses.

* 40.17 Num. 7 1.

* 40.21 ch. 35. 12.

* 40.29 ch. 30. 9.

* 40.34 Num. 9 15. 1 Kings &c 10.

† 40.36 Heb. journeyed.

Ezra

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

Ezra

1

1  Now in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, that the word of the LORD [*]by the mouth of Jeremiah might be fulfilled, the LORD stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, that he [†]made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom, and put it also in writing, saying, 2  Thus saith Cyrus king of Persia, The LORD God of heaven hath given me all the kingdoms of the earth; and he hath [*]charged me to build him an house at Jerusalem, which is in Judah. 3 Who is there among you of all his people? his God be with him, and let him go up to Jerusalem, which is in Judah, and build the house of the LORD God of Israel, (he is the God,) which is in Jerusalem. 4  And whosoever remaineth in any place where he sojourneth, let the men of his place [†]help him with silver, and with gold, and with goods, and with beasts, beside the freewill offering for the house of God that is in Jerusalem.

5 ¶ Then rose up the chief of the fathers of Judah and Benjamin, and the priests, and the Levites, with all them whose spirit God had raised, to go up to build the house of the LORD which is in Jerusalem. 6 And all they that were about them [∥]strengthened their hands with vessels of silver, with gold, with goods, and with beasts, and with precious things, beside all that was willingly offered.

7 ¶ Also Cyrus the king brought forth the vessels of the house of the LORD, [*]which Nebuchadnezzar had brought forth out of Jerusalem, and had put them in the house of his gods; 8  Even those did Cyrus king of Persia bring forth by the hand of Mithredath the treasurer, and numbered them unto [*]Sheshbazzar, the prince of Judah. 9 And this is the number of them: thirty chargers of gold, a thousand chargers of silver, nine and twenty knives, 10  Thirty basons of gold, silver basons of a second sort four hundred and ten, and other vessels a thousand. 11  All the vessels of gold and of silver were five thousand and four hundred. All these did Sheshbazzar bring up with them of [†]the captivity that were brought up from Babylon unto Jerusalem.

2

1 Now [*]these are the children of the province that went up out of the captivity, of those which had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away unto Babylon, and came again unto Jerusalem and Judah, every one unto his city; 2  Which came with Zerubbabel: Jeshua, Nehemiah, [∥]Seraiah, Reelaiah, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispar, Bigvai, Rehum, Baanah. The number of the men of the people of Israel: 3  The children of Parosh, two thousand an hundred seventy and two. 4  The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy and two. 5  The children of Arah, seven hundred seventy and five. 6  The children of [*]Pahath-moab, of the children of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand eight hundred and twelve. 7  The children of Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four. 8  The children of Zattu, nine hundred forty and five. 9  The children of Zaccai, seven hundred and threescore. 10  The children of [∥]Bani, six hundred forty and two. 11  The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty and three. 12  The children of Azgad, a thousand two hundred twenty and two. 13  The children of Adonikam, six hundred sixty and six. 14  The children of Bigvai, two thousand fifty and six. 15  The children of Adin, four hundred fifty and four. 16  The children of Ater of Hezekiah, ninety and eight. 17  The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty and three. 18  The children of [∥]Jorah, an hundred and twelve. 19  The children of Hashum, two hundred twenty and three. 20  The children of [∥]Gibbar, ninety and five. 21  The children of Beth-lehem, an hundred twenty and three. 22  The [‡]men of Netophah, fifty and six. 23  The men of Anathoth, an hundred twenty and eight. 24  The children of [∥]Azmaveth, forty and two. 25  The children of Kirjath-arim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred and forty and three. 26  The children of Ramah and Gaba, six hundred twenty and one. 27  The men of Michmas, an hundred twenty and two. 28  The men of Beth-el and Ai, two hundred twenty and three. 29  The children of Nebo, fifty and two. 30  The children of Magbish, an hundred fifty and six. 31  The children of the other [*]Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four. 32  The children of Harim, three hundred and twenty. 33  The children of Lod, [∥]Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty and five. 34  The children of Jericho, three hundred forty and five. 35  The children of Senaah, three thousand and six hundred and thirty.

36 ¶ The priests: the children of [*]Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy and three. 37  The children of [*]Immer, a thousand fifty and two. 38  The children of [*]Pashur, a thousand two hundred forty and seven. 39  The children of [*]Harim, a thousand and seventeen.

40 ¶ The Levites: the children of Jeshua and Kadmiel, of the children of [∥]Hodaviah, seventy and four.

41 ¶ The singers: the children of Asaph, an hundred twenty and eight.

42 ¶ The children of the porters: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, in all an hundred thirty and nine.

43 ¶ The Nethinims: the children of Ziha, the children of Hasupha, the children of Tabbaoth, 44  The children of Keros, the children of Siaha, the children of Padon, 45  The children of Lebanah, the children of Hagabah, the children of Akkub, 46  The children of Hagab, the children of [∥]Shalmai, the children of Hanan, 47  The children of Giddel, the children of Gahar, the children of Reaiah, 48  The children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda, the children of Gazzam, 49  The children of Uzza, the children of Paseah, the children of Besai, 50  The children of Asnah, the children of Mehunim, the children of Nephusim, 51  The children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur, 52  The children of [∥]Bazluth, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha, 53  The children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Thamah, 54  The children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.

55 ¶ The children of Solomon’s servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Sophereth, the children of [∥]Peruda, 56  The children of Jaalah, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel, 57  The children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth of Zebaim, the children of [∥]Ami. 58  All the [*]Nethinims, and the children of [*]Solomon’s servants, were three hundred ninety and two. 59 And these were they which went up from Tel-melah, Tel-harsa, Cherub, Addan, and Immer: but they could not shew their father’s house, and their [∥]seed, whether they were of Israel: 60  The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred fifty and two.

61 ¶ And of the children of the priests: the children of Habaiah, the children of Koz, the children of [*]Barzillai; which took a wife of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite, and was called after their name: 62  These sought their register among those that were reckoned by genealogy, but they were not found: therefore [†]were they, as polluted, put from the priesthood. 63  And the [∥]Tirshatha said unto them, that they should not eat of the most holy things, till there stood up a priest with [*]Urim and with Thummim.

64 ¶ The whole congregation together was forty and two thousand three hundred and threescore, 65  Beside their servants and their maids, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred thirty and seven: and there were among them two hundred singing men and singing women. 66  Their horses were seven hundred thirty and six; their mules, two hundred forty and five; 67  Their camels, four hundred thirty and five; their asses, six thousand seven hundred and twenty.

68 ¶ And some of the chief of the fathers, when they came to the house of the LORD which is at Jerusalem, offered freely for the house of God to set it up in his place: 69  They gave after their ability unto the [*]treasure of the work threescore and one thousand drams of gold, and five thousand pound of silver, and one hundred priests’ garments. 70  So the priests, and the Levites, and some of the people, and the singers, and the porters, and the Nethinims, dwelt in their cities, and all Israel in their cities.

3

1  And when the seventh month was come, and the children of Israel were in the cities, the people gathered themselves together as one man to Jerusalem. 2  Then stood up [∥]Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and his brethren the priests, and [*]Zerubbabel the son of [*]Shealtiel, and his brethren, and builded the altar of the God of Israel, to offer burnt offerings thereon, as it is [*]written in the law of Moses the man of God. 3  And they set the altar upon his bases; for fear was upon them because of the people of those countries: and they offered burnt offerings thereon unto the LORD, even burnt offerings morning and evening. 4  They kept also the feast of tabernacles, [*]as it is written, and [*]offered the daily burnt offerings by number, according to the custom, [†]as the duty of every day required; 5  And afterward offered the continual burnt offering, both of the new moons, and of all the set feasts of the LORD that were consecrated, and of every one that willingly [‡]offered a freewill offering unto the LORD. 6  From the first day of the seventh month began they to offer burnt offerings unto the LORD. But [†]the foundation of the temple of the LORD was not yet laid. 7  They gave money also unto the masons, and to the [∥]carpenters; and meat, and drink, and oil, unto them of Zidon, and to them of Tyre, to bring cedar trees from Lebanon to the sea of [*]Joppa, according to the grant that they had of Cyrus king of Persia.

8 ¶ Now in the second year of their coming unto the house of God at Jerusalem, in the second month, began Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and the remnant of their brethren the priests and the Levites, and all they that were come out of the captivity unto Jerusalem; and appointed the Levites, from twenty years old and upward, to set forward the work of the house of the LORD. 9  Then stood Jeshua with his sons and his brethren, Kadmiel and his sons, the sons of [∥]Judah, [†]together, to set forward the workmen in the house of God: the sons of Henadad, with their sons and their brethren the Levites. 10  And when the builders laid the foundation of the temple of the LORD, they set the priests in their apparel with trumpets, and the Levites the sons of Asaph with cymbals, to praise the LORD, after the [*]ordinance of David king of Israel. 11  And they sang together by course in praising and giving thanks unto the LORD; because he is good, for his mercy endureth for ever toward Israel. And all the people shouted with a great shout, when they praised the LORD, because the foundation of the house of the LORD was laid. 12  But many of the priests and Levites and chief of the fathers, who were ancient men, that had seen the first house, when the foundation of this house was laid before their eyes, wept with a loud voice; and many shouted aloud for joy: 13  So that the people could not discern the noise of the shout of joy from the noise of the weeping of the people: for the people shouted with a loud shout, and the noise was heard afar off.

4

1  Now when the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin heard that [†]the children of the captivity builded the temple unto the LORD God of Israel; 2  Then they came to Zerubbabel, and to the chief of the fathers, and said unto them, Let us build with you: for we seek your God, as ye do; and we do sacrifice unto him since the days of Esar-haddon king of Assur, which brought us up hither. 3  But Zerubbabel, and Jeshua, and the rest of the chief of the fathers of Israel, said unto them, Ye have nothing to do with us to build an house unto our God; but we ourselves together will build unto the LORD God of Israel, as king Cyrus the king of Persia hath commanded us. 4  Then the people of the land weakened the hands of the people of Judah, and troubled them in building, 5  And hired counsellors against them, to frustrate their purpose, all the days of Cyrus king of Persia, even until the reign of Darius king of Persia.

6  And in the reign of [†]Ahasuerus, in the beginning of his reign, wrote they unto him an accusation against the inhabitants of Judah and Jerusalem.

7 ¶ And in the days of Artaxerxes wrote [∥]Bishlam, Mithredath, Tabeel, and the rest of their [†]companions, unto Artaxerxes king of Persia; and the writing of the letter was written in the Syrian tongue, and interpreted in the Syrian tongue. 8  Rehum the chancellor and Shimshai the [∥]scribe wrote a letter against Jerusalem to Artaxerxes the king in this sort: 9  Then wrote Rehum the chancellor, and Shimshai the scribe, and the rest of their [†]companions; the Dinaites, the Apharsathchites, the Tarpelites, the Apharsites, the Archevites, the Babylonians, the Susanchites, the Dehavites, and the Elamites, 10  And the rest of the nations whom the great and noble Asnappar brought over, and set in the cities of Samaria, and the rest that are on this side the river, and [†]at such a time.

11 ¶ This is the copy of the letter that they sent unto him, even unto Artaxerxes the king; Thy servants the men on this side the river, and at such a time. 12  Be it known unto the king, that the Jews which came up from thee to us are come unto Jerusalem, building the rebellious and the bad city, and have [∥]set up the walls thereof, and [†]joined the foundations. 13  Be it known now unto the king, that, if this city be builded, and the walls set up again, then will they not [†]pay toll, tribute, and custom, and so thou shalt endamage the [∥]revenue of the kings. 14  Now because [†]we have maintenance from the king’s palace, and it was not meet for us to see the king’s dishonour, therefore have we sent and certified the king; 15  That search may be made in the book of the records of thy fathers: so shalt thou find in the book of the records, and know that this city is a rebellious city, and hurtful unto kings and provinces, and that they have [†]moved sedition [†]within the same of old time: for which cause was this city destroyed. 16  We certify the king that, if this city be builded again, and the walls thereof set up, by this means thou shalt have no portion on this side the river.

17 ¶ Then sent the king an answer unto Rehum the chancellor, and to Shimshai the scribe, and to the rest of their [†]companions that dwell in Samaria, and unto the rest beyond the river, Peace, and at such a time. 18  The letter which ye sent unto us hath been plainly read before me. 19  And [†]I commanded, and search hath been made, and it is found that this city of old time hath [†]made insurrection against kings, and that rebellion and sedition have been made therein. 20  There have been mighty kings also over Jerusalem, which have ruled over all countries beyond the river; and toll, tribute, and custom, was paid unto them. 21 [†] Give ye now commandment to cause these men to cease, and that this city be not builded, until another commandment shall be given from me. 22  Take heed now that ye fail not to do this: why should damage grow to the hurt of the kings?

23 ¶ Now when the copy of king Artaxerxes’ letter was read before Rehum, and Shimshai the scribe, and their companions, they went up in haste to Jerusalem unto the Jews, and made them to cease [†]by force and power. 24  Then ceased the work of the house [‡]of God which is at Jerusalem. So it ceased unto the second year of the reign of Darius king of Persia.

5

1  Then the prophets, [*]Haggai the prophet, and [*]Zechariah the son of Iddo, prophesied unto the Jews that were in Judah and Jerusalem in the name of the God of Israel, even unto them. 2  Then rose up Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and began to build the house of God which is at Jerusalem: and with them were the prophets of God helping them.

3 ¶ At the same time came to them Tatnai, governor on this side the river, and Shethar-boznai, and their companions, and said thus unto them, Who hath commanded you to build this house, and to make up this wall? 4  Then said we unto them after this manner, What are the names of the men [†]that make this building? 5  But the eye of their God was upon the elders of the Jews, that they could not cause them to cease, till the matter came to Darius: and then they returned answer by letter concerning this matter.

6 ¶ The copy of the letter that Tatnai, governor on this side the river, and Shethar-boznai, and his companions the Apharsachites, which were on this side the river, sent unto Darius the king: 7  They sent a letter unto him, [†]wherein was written thus; Unto Darius the king, all peace. 8  Be it known unto the king, that we went into the province of Judea, to the house of the great God, which is builded with [†]great stones, and timber is laid in the walls, and this work goeth fast on, and prospereth in their hands. 9  Then asked we those elders, and said unto them thus, Who commanded you to build this house, and to make up these walls? 10  We asked their names also, to certify thee, that we might write the names of the men that were the chief of them. 11  And thus they returned us answer, saying, We are the servants of the God of heaven and earth, and build the house that was builded these many years ago, which a great king of Israel builded [*]and set up. 12  But after that our fathers had provoked the God of heaven unto wrath, he gave them into the hand of [*]Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, the Chaldean, who destroyed this house, and carried the people away into Babylon. 13  But in the first year of [*]Cyrus the king of Babylon the same king Cyrus made a decree to build this house of God. 14  And [*]the vessels also of gold and silver of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took out of the temple that was in Jerusalem, and brought them into the temple of Babylon, those did Cyrus the king take out of the temple of Babylon, and they were delivered unto one, whose name was Sheshbazzar, whom he had made [∥]governor; 15  And said unto him, Take these vessels, go, carry them into the temple that is in Jerusalem, and let the house of God be builded in his place. 16  Then came the same Sheshbazzar, and laid the foundation of the house of God which is in Jerusalem: and since that time even until now hath it been in building, and yet it is not finished. 17  Now therefore, if it seem good to the king, let there be search made in the king’s treasure house, which is there at Babylon, whether it be so, that a decree was made of Cyrus the king to build this house of God at Jerusalem, and let the king send his pleasure to us concerning this matter.

6

1  Then Darius the king made a decree, and search was made in the house of the [†]rolls, where the treasures were [†]laid up in Babylon. 2  And there was found at [∥]Achmetha, in the palace that is in the province of the Medes, a roll, and therein was a record thus written: 3  In the first year of Cyrus the king the same Cyrus the king made a decree concerning the house of God at Jerusalem, Let the house be builded, the place where they offered sacrifices, and let the foundations thereof be strongly laid; the height thereof threescore cubits, and the breadth thereof threescore cubits; 4  With three rows of great stones, and a row of new timber: and let the expenses be given out of the king’s house: 5  And also let the golden and silver vessels of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took forth out of the temple which is at Jerusalem, and brought unto Babylon, be restored, and [†]brought again unto the temple which is at Jerusalem, every one to his place, and place them in the house of God. 6  Now therefore, Tatnai, governor beyond the river, Shethar-boznai, and [†]your companions the Apharsachites, which are beyond the river, be ye far from thence: 7  Let the work of this house of God alone; let the governor of the Jews and the elders of the Jews build this house of God in his place. 8  Moreover [†]I make a decree what ye shall do to the elders of these Jews for the building of this house of God: that of the king’s goods, even of the tribute beyond the river, forthwith expenses be given unto these men, that they be not [†]hindered. 9  And that which they have need of, both young bullocks, and rams, and lambs, for the burnt offerings of the God of heaven, wheat, salt, wine, and oil, according to the appointment of the priests which are at Jerusalem, let it be given them day by day without fail: 10  That they may offer sacrifices [†]of sweet savours unto the God of heaven, and pray for the life of the king, and of his sons. 11  Also I have made a decree, that whosoever shall alter this word, let timber be pulled down from his house, and being set up, [†]let him be hanged thereon; and let his house be made a dunghill for this. 12  And the God that hath caused his name to dwell there destroy all kings and people, that shall put to their hand to alter and to destroy this house of God which is at Jerusalem. I Darius have made a decree; let it be done with speed.

13 ¶ Then Tatnai, governor on this side the river, Shethar-boznai, and their companions, according to that which Darius the king had sent, so they did speedily. 14  And the elders of the Jews builded, and they prospered through the prophesying of Haggai the prophet and Zechariah the son of Iddo. And they builded, and finished it, according to the commandment of the God of Israel, and according to the [†]commandment of Cyrus, and Darius, and Artaxerxes king of Persia. 15  And this house was finished on the third day of the month Adar, which was in the sixth year of the reign of Darius the king.

16 ¶ And the children of Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the rest of [†]the children of the captivity, kept the dedication of this house of God with joy, 17  And offered at the dedication of this house of God an hundred bullocks, two hundred rams, four hundred lambs; and for a sin offering for all Israel, twelve he goats, according to the number of the tribes of Israel. 18  And they set the priests in their divisions, and the Levites in their courses, for the service of God, which is at Jerusalem; [†][*]as it is written in the book of Moses. 19  And the children of the captivity kept the passover upon the fourteenth day of the first month. 20  For the priests and the Levites were purified together, all of them were pure, and killed the passover for all the children of the captivity, and for their brethren the priests, and for themselves. 21  And the children of Israel, which were come again out of captivity, and all such as had separated themselves unto them from the filthiness of the heathen of the land, to seek the LORD God of Israel, did eat, 22  And kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days with joy: for the LORD had made them joyful, and turned the heart of the king of Assyria unto them, to strengthen their hands in the work of the house of God, the God of Israel.

7

1  Now after these things, in the reign of Artaxerxes king of Persia, Ezra the son of Seraiah, the son of Azariah, the son of Hilkiah, 2  The son of Shallum, the son of Zadok, the son of Ahitub, 3  The son of Amariah, the son of Azariah, the son of Meraioth, 4  The son of Zerahiah, the son of Uzzi, the son of Bukki, 5  The son of Abishua, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the chief priest: 6  This Ezra went up from Babylon; and he was a ready scribe in the law of Moses, which the LORD God of Israel had given: and the king granted him all his request, according to the hand of the LORD his God upon him. 7  And there went up some of the children of Israel, and of the priests, and the Levites, and the singers, and the porters, and the Nethinims, unto Jerusalem, in the seventh year of Artaxerxes the king. 8  And he came to Jerusalem in the fifth month, which was in the seventh year of the king. 9  For upon the first day of the first month [†]began he to go up from Babylon, and on the first day of the fifth month came he to Jerusalem, according to the good hand of his God upon him. 10  For Ezra had prepared his heart to seek the law of the LORD, and to do it, and to teach in Israel statutes and judgments.

11 ¶ Now this is the copy of the letter that the king Artaxerxes gave unto Ezra the priest, the scribe, even a scribe of the words of the commandments of the LORD, and of his statutes to Israel. 12  Artaxerxes, king of kings, [∥]unto Ezra the priest, a scribe of the law of the God of heaven, perfect peace, and at such a time. 13  I make a decree, that all they of the people of Israel, and of his priests and Levites, in my realm, which are minded of their own freewill to go up to Jerusalem, go with thee. 14  Forasmuch as thou art sent [†]of the king, and of his [*]seven counsellors, to enquire concerning Judah and Jerusalem, according to the law of thy God which is in thine hand; 15  And to carry the silver and gold, which the king and his counsellors have freely offered unto the God of Israel, whose habitation is in Jerusalem, 16 [*] And all the silver and gold that thou canst find in all the province of Babylon, with the freewill offering of the people, and of the priests, offering willingly for the house of their God which is in Jerusalem: 17  That thou mayest buy speedily with this money bullocks, rams, lambs, with their meat offerings and their drink offerings, and offer them upon the altar of the house of your God which is in Jerusalem. 18  And whatsoever shall seem good to thee, and to thy brethren, to do with the rest of the silver and the gold, that do after the will of your God. 19  The vessels also that are given thee for the service of the house of thy God, those deliver thou before the God of Jerusalem. 20  And whatsoever more shall be needful for the house of thy God, which thou shalt have occasion to bestow, bestow it out of the king’s treasure house. 21  And I, even I Artaxerxes the king, do make a decree to all the treasurers which are beyond the river, that whatsoever Ezra the priest, the scribe of the law of the God of heaven, shall require of you, it be done speedily, 22  Unto an hundred talents of silver, and to an hundred [†]measures of wheat, and to an hundred baths of wine, and to an hundred baths of oil, and salt without prescribing how much. 23 [†] Whatsoever is commanded by the God of heaven, let it be diligently done for the house of the God of heaven: for why should there be wrath against the realm of the king and his sons? 24  Also we certify you, that touching any of the priests and Levites, singers, porters, Nethinims, or ministers of this house of God, it shall not be lawful to impose toll, tribute, or custom, upon them. 25  And thou, Ezra, after the wisdom of thy God, that is in thine hand, set magistrates and judges, which may judge all the people that are beyond the river, all such as know the laws of thy God; and teach ye them that know them not. 26  And whosoever will not do the law of thy God, and the law of the king, let judgment be executed speedily upon him, whether it be unto death, or [†]to banishment, or to confiscation of goods, or to imprisonment.

27 ¶ Blessed be the LORD God of our fathers, which hath put such a thing as this in the king’s heart, to beautify the house of the LORD which is in Jerusalem: 28  And hath extended mercy unto me before the king, and his counsellors, and before all the king’s mighty princes. And I was strengthened as the hand of the LORD my God was upon me, and I gathered together out of Israel chief men to go up with me.

8

1 These are now the chief of their fathers, and this is the genealogy of them that went up with me from Babylon, in the reign of Artaxerxes the king. 2  Of the sons of Phinehas; Gershom: of the sons of Ithamar; Daniel: of the sons of David; Hattush. 3  Of the sons of Shechaniah, of the sons of Pharosh; Zechariah: and with him were reckoned by genealogy of the males an hundred and fifty. 4  Of the sons of Pahath-moab; Elihoenai the son of Zerahiah, and with him two hundred males. 5  Of the sons of Shechaniah; the son of Jahaziel, and with him three hundred males. 6  Of the sons also of Adin; Ebed the son of Jonathan, and with him fifty males. 7  And of the sons of Elam; Jeshaiah the son of Athaliah, and with him seventy males. 8  And of the sons of Shephatiah; Zebadiah the son of Michael, and with him fourscore males. 9  Of the sons of Joab; Obadiah the son of Jehiel, and with him two hundred and eighteen males. 10  And of the sons of Shelomith; the son of Josiphiah, and with him an hundred and threescore males. 11  And of the sons of Bebai; Zechariah the son of Bebai, and with him twenty and eight males. 12  And of the sons of Azgad; Johanan [∥]the son of Hakkatan, and with him an hundred and ten males. 13  And of the last sons of Adonikam, whose names are these, Eliphelet, Jeiel, and Shemaiah, and with them threescore males. 14  Of the sons also of Bigvai; Uthai, and [∥]Zabbud, and with them seventy males.

15 ¶ And I gathered them together to the river that runneth to Ahava; and there [∥]abode we in tents three days: and I viewed the people, and the priests, and found there none of the sons of Levi. 16  Then sent I for Eliezer, for Ariel, for Shemaiah, and for Elnathan, and for Jarib, and for Elnathan, and for Nathan, and for Zechariah, and for Meshullam, chief men; also for [‡]Joiarib, and for Elnathan, men of understanding. 17  And I sent them with commandment unto Iddo the chief at the place Casiphia, and [†]I told them what they should say unto Iddo, and to his brethren the Nethinims, at the place Casiphia, that they should bring unto us ministers for the house of our God. 18  And by the good hand of our God upon us they brought us a man of understanding, of the sons of Mahli, the son of Levi, the son of Israel; and Sherebiah, with his sons and his brethren, eighteen; 19  And Hashabiah, and with him Jeshaiah of the sons of Merari, his brethren and their sons, twenty; 20 [*] Also of the Nethinims, whom David and the princes had appointed for the service of the Levites, two hundred and twenty Nethinims: all of them were expressed by name.

21 ¶ Then I proclaimed a fast there, at the river [‡]of Ahava, that we might afflict ourselves before our God, to seek of him a right way for us, and for our little ones, and for all our substance. 22  For I was ashamed to require of the king a band of soldiers and horsemen to help us against the enemy in the way: because we had spoken unto the king, saying, The hand of our God is upon all them for good that seek him; but his power and his wrath is against all them that forsake him. 23  So we fasted and besought our God for this: and he was intreated of us.

24 ¶ Then I separated twelve of the chief of the priests, Sherebiah, Hashabiah, and ten of their brethren with them, 25  And weighed unto them the silver, and the gold, and the vessels, even the offering of the house of our God, which the king, and his counsellors, and his lords, and all Israel there present, had offered: 26  I even weighed unto their hand six hundred and fifty talents of silver, and silver vessels an hundred talents, and of gold an hundred talents; 27  Also twenty basons of gold, of a thousand drams; and two vessels of [†]fine copper, [†]precious as gold. 28  And I said unto them, Ye are holy unto the LORD; the vessels are holy also; and the silver and the gold are a freewill offering unto the LORD God of your fathers. 29  Watch ye, and keep them, until ye weigh them before the chief of the priests and the Levites, and chief of the fathers of Israel, at Jerusalem, in the chambers of the house of the LORD. 30  So took the priests and the Levites the weight of the silver, and the gold, and the vessels, to bring them to Jerusalem unto the house of our God.

31 ¶ Then we departed from the river of Ahava on the twelfth day of the first month, to go unto Jerusalem: and the hand of our God was upon us, and he delivered us from the hand of the enemy, and of such as lay in wait by the way. 32  And we came to Jerusalem, and abode there three days.

33 ¶ Now on the fourth day was the silver and the gold and the vessels weighed in the house of our God by the hand of Meremoth the son of Uriah the priest; and with him was Eleazar the son of Phinehas; and with them was Jozabad the son of Jeshua, and Noadiah the son of Binnui, Levites; 34  By number and by weight of every one: and all the weight was written at that time. 35  Also the children of those that had been carried away, which were come out of the captivity, offered burnt offerings unto the God of Israel, twelve bullocks for all Israel, ninety and six rams, seventy and seven lambs, twelve he goats for a sin offering: all this was a burnt offering unto the LORD.

36 ¶ And they delivered the king’s commissions unto the king’s lieutenants, and to the governors on this side the river: and they furthered the people, and the house of God.

9

1  Now when these things were done, the princes came to me, saying, The people of Israel, and the priests, and the Levites, have not separated themselves from the people of the lands, doing according to their abominations, even of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Jebusites, the Ammonites, the Moabites, the Egyptians, and the Amorites. 2  For they have taken of their daughters for themselves, and for their sons: so that the holy seed have mingled themselves with the people of those lands: yea, the hand of the princes and rulers hath been chief in this trespass. 3  And when I heard this thing, I rent my garment and my mantle, and plucked off the hair of my head and of my beard, and sat down astonied. 4  Then were assembled unto me every one that trembled at the words of the God of Israel, because of the transgression of those that had been carried away; and I sat astonied until the evening sacrifice.

5 ¶ And at the evening sacrifice I arose up from my [∥]heaviness; and having rent my garment and my mantle, I fell upon my knees, and spread out my hands unto the LORD my God, 6  And said, O my God, I am ashamed and blush to lift up my face to thee, my God: for our iniquities are increased over our head, and our [∥]trespass is grown up unto the heavens. 7  Since the days of our fathers have we been in a great trespass unto this day; and for our iniquities have we, our kings, and our priests, been delivered into the hand of the kings of the lands, to the sword, to captivity, and to a spoil, and to confusion of face, as it is this day. 8  And now for a [†]little space grace hath been shewed from the LORD our God, to leave us a remnant to escape, and to give us [∥]a nail in his holy place, that our God may lighten our eyes, and give us a little reviving in our bondage. 9 For we were bondmen; yet our God hath not forsaken us in our bondage, but hath extended mercy unto us in the sight of the kings of Persia, to give us a reviving, to set up the house of our God, and [†]to repair the desolations thereof, and to give us a wall in Judah and in Jerusalem. 10  And now, O our God, what shall we say after this? for we have forsaken thy commandments, 11  Which thou hast commanded [†]by thy servants the prophets, saying, [*]The land, unto which ye go to possess it, is an unclean land with the filthiness of the people of the lands, with their abominations, which have filled it [†]from one end to another with their uncleanness. 12  Now therefore give not your daughters unto their sons, neither take their daughters unto your sons, nor seek their peace or their wealth for ever: that ye may be strong, and eat the good of the land, and leave it for an inheritance to your children for ever. 13  And after all that is come upon us for our evil deeds, and for our great trespass, seeing that thou our God [†]hast punished us less than our iniquities deserve, and hast given us such deliverance as this; 14  Should we again break thy commandments, and join in affinity with the people of these abominations? wouldest not thou be angry with us till thou hadst consumed us, so that there should be no remnant nor escaping? 15  O LORD God of Israel, thou art righteous: for we remain yet escaped, as it is this day: behold, we are before thee in our trespasses: for we cannot stand before thee because of this.

10

1  Now when Ezra had prayed, and when he had confessed, weeping and casting himself down before the house of God, there assembled unto him out of Israel a very great congregation of men and women and children: for the people [†]wept very sore. 2  And Shechaniah the son of Jehiel, one of the sons of Elam, answered and said unto Ezra, We have trespassed against our God, and have taken strange wives of the people of the land: yet now there is hope in Israel concerning this thing. 3  Now therefore let us make a covenant with our God [†]to put away all the wives, and such as are born of them, according to the counsel of my lord, and of those that tremble at the commandment of our God; and let it be done according to the law. 4  Arise; for this matter belongeth unto thee: we also will be with thee: be of good courage, and do it. 5  Then arose Ezra, and made the chief priests, the Levites, and all Israel, to swear that they should do according to this word. And they sware.

6 ¶ Then Ezra rose up from before the house of God, and went into the chamber of Johanan the son of Eliashib: and when he came thither, he did eat no bread, nor drink water: for he mourned because of the transgression of them that had been carried away. 7  And they made proclamation throughout Judah and Jerusalem unto all the children of the captivity, that they should gather themselves together unto Jerusalem; 8  And that whosoever would not come within three days, according to the counsel of the princes and the elders, all his substance should be [†]forfeited, and himself separated from the congregation of those that had been carried away.

9 ¶ Then all the men of Judah and Benjamin gathered themselves together unto Jerusalem within three days. It was the ninth month, on the twentieth day of the month; and all the people sat in the street of the house of God, trembling because of this matter, and for [†]the great rain. 10  And Ezra the priest stood up, and said unto them, Ye have transgressed, and [†]have taken strange wives, to increase the trespass of Israel. 11  Now therefore make confession unto the LORD God of your fathers, and do his pleasure: and separate yourselves from the people of the land, and from the strange wives. 12  Then all the congregation answered and said with a loud voice, As thou hast said, so must we do. 13  But the people are many, and it is a time of much rain, and we are not able to stand without, neither is this a work of one day or two: for [∥]we are many that have transgressed in this thing. 14  Let now our rulers of all the congregation stand, and let all them which have taken strange wives in our cities come at appointed times, and with them the elders of every city, and the judges thereof, until the fierce wrath of our God [∥]for this matter be turned from us.

15 ¶ Only Jonathan the son of Asahel and Jahaziah the son of Tikvah [†]were employed about this matter: and Meshullam and Shabbethai the Levite helped them. 16  And the children of the captivity did so. And Ezra the priest, with certain chief of the fathers, after the house of their fathers, and all of them by their names, were separated, and sat down in the first day of the tenth month to examine the matter. 17  And they made an end with all the men that had taken strange wives by the first day of the first month.

18 ¶ And among the sons of the priests there were found that had taken strange wives: namely, of the sons of Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and his brethren; Maaseiah, and Eliezer, and Jarib, and Gedaliah. 19  And they gave their hands that they would put away their wives; and being guilty, they offered a ram of the flock for their trespass. 20  And of the sons of Immer; Hanani, and Zebadiah. 21  And of the sons of Harim; Maaseiah, and Elijah, and Shemaiah, and Jehiel, and Uzziah. 22  And of the sons of Pashur; Elioenai, Maaseiah, Ishmael, Nethaneel, Jozabad, and Elasah. 23  Also of the Levites; Jozabad, and Shimei, and Kelaiah, (the same is Kelita,) Pethahiah, Judah, and Eliezer. 24  Of the singers also; Eliashib: and of the porters; Shallum, and Telem, and Uri. 25  Moreover of Israel: of the sons of Parosh; Ramiah, and Jeziah, and Malchiah, and Miamin, and Eleazar, and Malchijah, and Benaiah. 26  And of the sons of Elam; Mattaniah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, and Abdi, and Jeremoth, and Eliah. 27  And of the sons of Zattu; Elioenai, Eliashib, Mattaniah, and Jeremoth, and Zabad, and Aziza. 28  Of the sons also of Bebai; Jehohanan, Hananiah, Zabbai, and Athlai. 29  And of the sons of Bani; Meshullam, Malluch, and Adaiah, Jashub, and Sheal, and Ramoth. 30  And of the sons of Pahath-moab; Adna, and Chelal, Benaiah, Maaseiah, Mattaniah, Bezaleel, and Binnui, and Manasseh. 31 And of the sons of Harim; Eliezer, Ishijah, Malchiah, Shemaiah, Shimeon, 32  Benjamin, Malluch, and Shemariah. 33  Of the sons of Hashum; Mattenai, Mattathah, Zabad, Eliphelet, Jeremai, Manasseh, and Shimei. 34  Of the sons of Bani; Maadai, Amram, and Uel, 35  Benaiah, Bedeiah, Chelluh, 36  Vaniah, Meremoth, Eliashib, 37  Mattaniah, Mattenai, and Jaasau, 38  And Bani, and Binnui, Shimei, 39  And Shelemiah, and Nathan, and Adaiah, 40 [∥] Machnadebai, Shashai, Sharai, 41  Azareel, and Shelemiah, Shemariah, 42  Shallum, Amariah, and Joseph. 43  Of the sons of Nebo; Jeiel, Mattithiah, Zabad, Zebina, Jadau, and Joel, Benaiah. 44  All these had taken strange wives: and some of them had wives by whom they had children.

* 1.1 2 Chr. 36. 22. Jer. 25. 12. &c 29. 10.

† 1.1 Heb. caused a voice to pass.

* 1.2 Isai. 44. 28. &c 45. 1, 13.

† 1.4 Heb. lift him up.

∥ 1.6 That is, helped them.

* 1.7 2 Kings 24. 13. 2 Chr. 36. 7.

* 1.8 ch. 5. 14.

† 1.11 Heb. the transportation.

* 2.1 Neh. 7. 6, &c.

∥ 2.2 Neh. 7. 7.

* 2.6 Neh. 7. 11.

∥ 2.10 Neh. 7. 15.

∥ 2.18 Neh. 7. 24.

∥ 2.20 Neh. 7. 25.

‡ 2.22 [1611 children]

∥ 2.24 Neh. 7. 28.

* 2.31 ver. 7.

∥ 2.33 Or, Harid, as it is in some copies.

* 2.36 1 Chr. 24 7.

* 2.37 1 Chr. 24. 14.

* 2.38 1 Chr. 9. 12.

* 2.39 1 Chr. 24. 8.

∥ 2.40 ch 3. 9. called also Hodevah, Neh 7. 43.

∥ 2.46 Or, Shamlai.

∥ 2.52 Neh. 7. 54.

∥ 2.55 Neh. 7. 57.

∥ 2.57 Neh. 7. 59.

* 2.58 Josh. 9. 21, 27. 1 Chr. 9. 2.

* 2.58 1 Kings 9. 21.

∥ 2.59 Or, pedigree.

* 2.61 2 Sam. 17. 27.

† 2.62 Heb. they were polluted from the priesthood.

∥ 2.63 Or, governor.

* 2.63 Ex. 28. 30.

* 2.69 1 Chr. 26. 20.

∥ 3.2 Joshua, Hag. 1. 1.

* 3.2 Matt. 1 12. &c Luke 3 27, called Zorobabel.

* 3.2 Matt. 1. 12. &c Luke 3. 27, called Salathiel.

* 3.2 Deut. 12. 5.

* 3.4 Num. 29. 12.

* 3.4 Ex. 23. 16.

† 3.4 Heb. the matter of the day in his day.

‡ 3.5 [1611 offered, offered]

† 3.6 Heb. the temple of the Lord was not yet founded.

∥ 3.7 Or, workmen.

* 3.7 Acts 9. 36.

∥ 3.9 ch. 2. 40.

† 3.9 Heb. as one.

* 3.10 1 Chr. 6 31. &c 16. 7. &c 25 1.

† 4.1 Heb. the sons of the transportation.

† 4.6 Heb. Ahashverosh.

∥ 4.7 Or, in peace.

† 4.7 Heb. societies.

∥ 4.8 Or, secretary.

† 4.9 Chald. societies.

† 4.10 Chald. Chceneth.

∥ 4.12 Or, finished.

† 4.12 Chald. sewed together.

† 4.13 Chald. give.

∥ 4.13 Or, strength.

† 4.14 Chald. we are salted with the salt of the palace.

† 4.15 Chald. made.

† 4.15 Chald. in the midst thereof.

† 4.17 Chald societies.

† 4.19 Chald. by me a decree is set

† 4.19 Chald. lifted up itself.

† 4.21 Chald. Make a decree.

† 4.23 Chald. by arm and power.

‡ 4.24 [1611 of the God]

* 5.1 Hag. 1. 1.

* 5.1 Zech. 1. 1.

† 5.4 Chald. that build this building?

† 5.7 Chald. in the midst whereof.

† 5.8 Chald. stones of rolling.

* 5.11 1 Kings 6. 1.

* 5.12 2 Kings 24. 2. &c 25. 8.

* 5.13 ch. 1. 1.

* 5.14 ch 1. 8. &c 6. 5.

∥ 5.14 Or, deputy.

† 6.1 Chald. books.

† 6.1 Chald made to descend.

∥ 6.2 Or, Ecbatana, or, in a coffer.

† 6.5 Chald. go.

† 6.6 Chald. their societies.

† 6.8 Chald. by me a decree is made.

† 6.8 Chald. made to cease.

† 6.10 Chald. of rest.

† 6.11 Chald. let him be destroyed.

† 6.14 Chald. decree.

† 6.16 Chald. the sons of the transportation.

† 6.18 Chald. according to the writing.

* 6.18 Num. 3. 6. &c 8. 9.

† 7.9 Heb. was the foundation of the going up.

∥ 7.12 Or, to Ezra the priest, a perfect scribe of the law of the God of heaven, peace, &c.

† 7.14 Chald. from before the king.

* 7.14 Esth. 1. 14.

* 7.16 ch. 8. 25.

† 7.22 Chald. Aramalc

† 7.23 Heb. Whatsoever is of the decree.

† 7.26 Chald. to rooting out.

∥ 8.12 Or, the youngest son.

∥ 8.14 Or, Zaccur, as some read.

∥ 8.15 Or, pitched.

‡ 8.16 [1611 Jarib]

† 8.17 Heb. I put words in their mouth.

* 8.20 ch. 2. 43.

‡ 8.21 [1611 omits of]

† 8.27 Heb. yellow, or, shining brass.

† 8.27 Heb. desirable.

∥ 9.5 Or, afflication.

∥ 9.6 Or, guiltiness

† 9.8 Heb moment.

∥ 9.8 Or, a pin: that is, a constant and sure abode.

† 9.9 Heb. to set up.

† 9.11 Heb. by the hand of thy servants.

* 9.11 Ex. 23. 32. Deut. 7. 3.

† 9.11 Heb. from mouth to mouth.

† 9.13 Heb. hast withheld beneath our iniquities.

† 10.1 Heb. wept a great weeping.

† 10.3 Heb. to bring forth.

† 10.8 Heb. devoted.

† 10.9 Heb. the showers.

† 10.10 Heb. have caused to dwell, or, have brought back.

∥ 10.13 Or, we have greatly offended in this thing.

∥ 10.14 Or, till this matter be dispatched.

† 10.15 Heb. stood.

∥ 10.40 Or, Mabnadebai, according to some copies.

Genesis

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30

31
32
33
34
35
36
37
38
39
40

41
42
43
44
45
46
47
48
49
50

The First Book of Moses, called Genesis

1

1  In the [*]beginning God created the heaven and the earth. 2  And the earth was without form, and void; and darkness was upon the face of the deep. And the Spirit of God moved upon the face of the waters.

3  And God said, [*]Let there be light: and there was light. 4  And God saw the light, that it was good: and God divided [†]the light from the darkness. 5  And God called the light Day, and the darkness he called Night. [†]And the evening and the morning were the first day.

6 ¶ And God said, [*]Let there be a [†]firmament in the midst of the waters, and let it divide the waters from the waters. 7  And God made the firmament, and divided the waters which were under the firmament from the waters which were above the firmament: and it was so. 8  And God called the [*]firmament Heaven. And the evening and the morning were the second day.

9 ¶ And God said, [*]Let the waters under the heaven be gathered together unto one place, and let the dry land appear: and it was so. 10  And God called the dry land Earth; and the gathering together of the waters called he Seas: and God saw that it was good. 11  And God said, Let the earth bring forth [†]grass, the herb yielding seed, and the fruit tree yielding fruit after his kind, whose seed is in itself, upon the earth: and it was so. 12  And the earth brought forth grass, and herb yielding seed after his kind, and the tree yielding fruit, whose seed was in itself, after his kind: and God saw that it was good. 13  And the evening and the morning were the third day.

14 ¶ And God said, Let there be [*]lights in the firmament of the heaven to divide [†]the day from the night; and let them be for signs, and for seasons, and for days, and years: 15  And let them be for lights in the firmament of the heaven to give light upon the earth: and it was so. 16  And God made two great lights; the greater light [†]to rule the day, and the lesser light to rule the night: he made the stars also. 17  And God set them in the firmament of the heaven to give light upon the earth, 18  And to [*]rule over the day and over the night, and to divide the light from the darkness: and God saw that it was good. 19  And the evening and the morning were the fourth day.

20  And God said, [*]Let the waters bring forth abundantly the [∥]moving creature that hath [†]life, and fowl that may fly above the earth in the [†]open firmament of heaven. 21  And God created great whales, and every living creature that moveth, which the waters brought forth abundantly, after their kind, and every winged fowl after his kind: and God saw that it was good. 22  And God blessed them, saying, [*]Be fruitful, and multiply, and fill the waters in the seas, and let fowl multiply in the earth. 23  And the evening and the morning were the fifth day.

24 ¶ And God said, Let the earth bring forth the living creature after his kind, cattle, and creeping thing, and beast of the earth after his kind: and it was so. 25  And God made the beast of the earth after his kind, and cattle after their kind, and every thing that creepeth upon the earth after his kind: and God saw that it was good.

26 ¶ And God said, [*]Let us make man in our image, after our likeness: and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over the cattle, and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth. 27  So God created man in his own image, in the image of God created he him; [*]male and female created he them. 28  And God blessed them, and God said unto them, [*]Be fruitful, and multiply, and replenish the earth, and subdue it: and have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over every living thing that [†]moveth upon the earth.

29 ¶ And God said, Behold, I have given you every herb [†]bearing seed, which is upon the face of all the earth, and every tree, in the which is the fruit of a tree yielding seed; [*]to you it shall be for meat. 30  And to every beast of the earth, and to every fowl of the air, and to every thing that creepeth upon the earth, wherein there is [†]life, I have given every green herb for meat: and it was so. 31  And [*]God saw every thing that he had made, and, behold, it was very good. And the evening and the morning were the sixth day.

2

1  Thus the heavens and the earth were finished, and all the host of them. 2 [*] And on the seventh day God ended his work which he had made; and he rested on the seventh day from all his work which he had made. 3  And God blessed the seventh day, and sanctified it: because that in it he had rested from all his work which God [†]created and made.

4 ¶ These are the generations of the heavens and of the earth when they were created, in the day that the LORD God made the earth and the heavens, 5  And every plant of the field before it was in the earth, and every herb of the field before it grew: for the LORD God had not caused it to rain upon the earth, and there was not a man to till the ground. 6  But [∥]there went up a mist from the earth, and watered the whole face of the ground. 7  And the LORD God formed man [†]of the [*]dust of the ground, and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life; and [*]man became a living soul.

8 ¶ And the LORD God planted a garden eastward in Eden; and there he put the man whom he had formed. 9  And out of the ground made the LORD God to grow every tree that is pleasant to the sight, and good for food; the tree of life also in the midst of the garden, and the tree of knowledge of good and evil. 10  And a river went out of Eden to water the garden; and from thence it was parted, and became into four heads. 11  The name of the first is [*]Pison: that is it which compasseth the whole land of Havilah, where there is gold; 12  And the gold of that land is good: there is bdellium and the onyx stone. 13  And the name of the second river is Gihon: the same is it that compasseth the whole land of [†]Ethiopia. 14  And the name of the third river is Hiddekel: that is it which goeth [∥]toward the east of Assyria. And the fourth river is Euphrates. 15  And the LORD God took [∥]the man, and put him into the garden of Eden to dress it and to keep it.

16  And the LORD God commanded the man, saying, Of every tree of the garden [†]thou mayest freely eat: 17  But of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, thou shalt not eat of it: for in the day that thou eatest thereof [†]thou shalt surely die.

18 ¶ And the LORD God said, It is not good that the man should be alone; I will make [*]him an help [†]meet for him. 19  And out of the ground the LORD God formed every beast of the field, and every fowl of the air; and brought them unto [∥]Adam to see what he would call them: and whatsoever Adam called every living creature, that was the name thereof. 20  And Adam [†]gave names to all cattle, and to the fowl of the air, and to every beast of the field; but for Adam there was not found an help meet for him.

21  And the LORD God caused a deep sleep to fall upon Adam, and he slept: and he took one of his ribs, and closed up the flesh instead thereof; 22  And the rib, which the LORD God had taken from man, [†]made he a woman, and brought her unto the man. 23  And Adam said, This is now bone of my bones, and flesh of my flesh: she shall be called Woman, because she was [*]taken out of Man. 24 [*] Therefore shall a man leave his father and his mother, and shall cleave unto his wife: and they shall be one flesh. 25  And they were both naked, the man and his wife, and were not ashamed.

3

1  Now the serpent was more subtil than any beast of the field which the LORD God had made. And he said unto the woman, [†]Yea, hath God said, Ye shall not eat of every tree of the garden? 2  And the woman said unto the serpent, We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden: 3  But of the fruit of the tree which is in the midst of the garden, God hath said, Ye shall not eat of it, neither shall ye touch it, lest ye die. 4 [*] And the serpent said unto the woman, Ye shall not surely die: 5  For God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, then your eyes shall be opened, and ye shall be as gods, knowing good and evil.

6  And when the woman saw that the tree was good for food, and that it was [†]pleasant to the eyes, and a tree to be desired to make one wise, she took of the fruit thereof, [*]and did eat, and gave also unto her husband with her; and he did eat. 7  And the eyes of them both were opened, and they knew that they were naked; and they sewed fig leaves together, and made themselves [∥]aprons. 8  And they heard the voice of the LORD God walking in the garden in the [†]cool of the day: and Adam and his wife hid themselves from the presence of the LORD God amongst the trees of the garden.

9  And the LORD God called unto Adam, and said unto him, Where art thou? 10  And he said, I heard thy voice in the garden, and I was afraid, because I was naked; and I hid myself.

11  And he said, Who told thee that thou wast naked? Hast thou eaten of the tree, whereof I commanded thee that thou shouldest not eat? 12  And the man said, The woman whom thou gavest to be with me, she gave me of the tree, and I did eat. 13  And the LORD God said unto the woman, What is this that thou hast done? And the woman said, The serpent beguiled me, and I did eat.

14  And the LORD God said unto the serpent, Because thou hast done this, thou art cursed above all cattle, and above every beast of the field; upon thy belly shalt thou go, and dust shalt thou eat all the days of thy life: 15  And I will put enmity between thee and the woman, and between thy seed and her seed; it shall bruise thy head, and thou shalt bruise his heel. 16  Unto the woman he said, I will greatly multiply thy sorrow and thy conception; in sorrow thou shalt bring forth children; and thy desire shall be [∥]to thy husband, and he shall [*]rule over thee.

17  And unto Adam he said, Because thou hast hearkened unto the voice of thy wife, and hast eaten of the tree, of which I commanded thee, saying, Thou shalt not eat of it: cursed is the ground for thy sake; in sorrow shalt thou eat of it all the days of thy life; 18  Thorns also and thistles shall it [†]bring forth to thee; and thou shalt eat the herb of the field; 19  In the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat bread, till thou return unto the ground; for out of it wast thou taken: for dust thou art, and unto dust shalt thou return. 20  And Adam called his wife’s name [†]Eve; because she was the mother of all living. 21  Unto Adam also and to his wife did the LORD God make coats of skins, and clothed them.

22 ¶ And the LORD God said, Behold, the man is become as one of us, to know good and evil: and now, lest he put forth his hand, and take also of the tree of life, and eat, and live for ever: 23  Therefore the LORD God sent him forth from the garden of Eden, to till the ground from whence he was taken. 24  So he drove out the man; and he placed at the east of the garden of Eden Cherubims, and a flaming sword which turned every way, to keep the way of the tree of life.

4

1  And Adam knew Eve his wife; and she conceived, and bare Cain, and said, I have gotten a man from the LORD. 2  And she again bare his brother [†]Abel. And Abel was [†]a keeper of sheep, but Cain was a tiller of the ground.

3  And [†]in process of time it came to pass, that Cain brought of the fruit of the ground an offering unto the LORD. 4  And Abel, he also brought of the firstlings of his [†]flock and of the fat thereof. And the LORD had [*]respect unto Abel and to his offering: 5  But unto Cain and to his offering he had not respect. And Cain was very wroth, and his countenance fell.

6  And the LORD said unto Cain, Why art thou wroth? and why is thy countenance fallen? 7  If thou doest well, shalt thou not [∥]be accepted? and if thou doest not well, sin lieth at the door. And [∥]unto thee shall be his desire, and thou shalt rule over him. 8  And Cain talked with Abel his brother: and it came to pass, when they were in the field, that Cain rose up against Abel his brother, and [*]slew him.

9 ¶ And the LORD said unto Cain, Where is Abel thy brother? And he said, I know not: Am I my brother’s keeper? 10  And he said, What hast thou done? the voice of thy brother’s [†]blood crieth unto me from the ground. 11 And now art thou cursed from the earth, which hath opened her mouth to receive thy brother’s blood from thy hand; 12  When thou tillest the ground, it shall not henceforth yield unto thee her strength; a fugitive and a vagabond shalt thou be in the earth.

13  And Cain said unto the LORD, [∥]My punishment is greater than I can bear. 14  Behold, thou hast driven me out this day from the face of the earth; and from thy face shall I be hid; and I shall be a fugitive and a vagabond in the earth; and it shall come to pass, that every one that findeth me shall slay me. 15  And the LORD said unto him, Therefore whosoever slayeth Cain, vengeance shall be taken on him sevenfold. And the LORD set a mark upon Cain, lest any finding him should kill him.

16 ¶ And Cain went out from the presence of the LORD, and dwelt in the land of Nod, on the east of Eden. 17  And Cain knew his wife; and she conceived, and bare [†]Enoch: and he builded a city, and called the name of the city, after the name of his son, Enoch. 18  And unto Enoch was born Irad: and Irad begat Mehujael: and Mehujael begat Methusael: and Methusael begat [†]Lamech.

19 ¶ And Lamech took unto him two wives: the name of the one was Adah, and the name of the other Zillah. 20  And Adah bare Jabal: he was the father of such as dwell in tents, and of such as have cattle. 21  And his brother’s name was Jubal: he was the father of all such as handle the harp and organ. 22  And Zillah, she also bare Tubal-cain, an [†]instructer of every artificer in brass and iron: and the sister of Tubal-cain was Naamah.

23  And Lamech said unto his wives, Adah and Zillah, Hear my voice; ye wives of Lamech, hearken unto my speech: for [∥]I have slain a man to my wounding, and a young man [∥]to my hurt. 24  If Cain shall be avenged sevenfold, truly Lamech seventy and sevenfold.

25 ¶ And Adam knew his wife again; and she bare a son, and called his name [†]Seth: For God, said she, hath appointed me another seed instead of Abel, whom Cain slew. 26  And to Seth, to him also there was born a son; and he called his name [†]Enos: then began men [∥]to call upon the name of the LORD.

5

1  This is the [*]book of the generations of Adam. In the day that God created man, in the likeness of God made he him; 2 [*] Male and female created he them; and blessed them, and called their name Adam, in the day when they were created.

3 ¶ And Adam lived an hundred and thirty years, and begat a son in his own likeness, after his image; and called his name Seth: 4 [*] And the days of Adam after he had begotten Seth were eight hundred years: and he begat sons and daughters: 5  And all the days that Adam lived were nine hundred and thirty years: and he died.

6  And Seth lived an hundred and five years, and begat [†]Enos: 7  And Seth lived after he begat Enos eight hundred and seven years, and begat sons and daughters: 8  And all the days of Seth were nine hundred and twelve years: and he died.

9 ¶ And Enos lived ninety years, and begat [†]Cainan: 10  And Enos lived after he begat Cainan eight hundred and fifteen years, and begat sons and daughters: 11  And all the days of Enos were nine hundred and five years: and he died.

12 ¶ And Cainan lived seventy years, and begat [†]Mahalaleel: 13  And Cainan lived after he begat Mahalaleel eight hundred and forty years, and begat sons and daughters: 14  And all the days of Cainan were nine hundred and ten years: and he died.

15 ¶ And Mahalaleel lived sixty and five years, and begat [†]Jared: 16  And Mahalaleel lived after he begat Jared eight hundred and thirty years, and begat sons and daughters: 17  And all the days of Mahalaleel were eight hundred ninety and five years: and he died.

18 ¶ And Jared lived an hundred sixty and two years, and he begat Enoch: 19  And Jared lived after he begat Enoch eight hundred years, and begat sons and daughters: 20  And all the days of Jared were nine hundred sixty and two years: and he died.

21 ¶ And Enoch lived sixty and five years, and begat [†]Methuselah: 22  And Enoch walked with God after he begat Methuselah three hundred years, and begat sons and daughters: 23  And all the days of Enoch were three hundred sixty and five years: 24  And [*]Enoch walked with God: and he was not; for God took him.

25  And Methuselah lived an hundred eighty and seven years, and begat [†]Lamech: 26  And Methuselah lived after he begat Lamech seven hundred eighty and two years, and begat sons and daughters: 27  And all the days of Methuselah were nine hundred sixty and nine years: and he died.

28 ¶ And Lamech lived an hundred eighty and two years, and begat a son: 29  And he called his name [†]Noah, saying, This same shall comfort us concerning our work and toil of our hands, because of the ground which the LORD hath cursed. 30  And Lamech lived after he begat Noah five hundred ninety and five years, and begat sons and daughters: 31  And all the days of Lamech were seven hundred seventy and seven years: and he died. 32  And Noah was five hundred years old: and Noah begat Shem, Ham, and Japheth.

6

1  And it came to pass, when men began to multiply on the face of the earth, and daughters were born unto them, 2  That the sons of God saw the daughters of men that they were fair; and they took them wives of all which they chose. 3  And the LORD said, My spirit shall not always strive with man, for that he also is flesh: yet his days shall be an hundred and twenty years.

4  There were giants in the earth in those days; and also after that, when the sons of God came in unto the daughters of men, and they bare children to them, the same became mighty men which were of old, men of renown.

5 ¶ And GOD saw that the wickedness of man was great in the earth, and that [∥]every imagination of the thoughts of his [*]heart was only evil [†]continually.

6  And it repented the LORD that he had made man on the earth, and it grieved him at his heart. 7  And the LORD said, I will destroy man whom I have created from the face of the earth; [†]both man, and beast, and the creeping thing, and the fowls of the air; for it repenteth me that I have made them.

8  But Noah found grace in the eyes of the LORD.

9 ¶ These are the generations of Noah: [*]Noah was a just man and [∥]perfect in his generations, and Noah walked with God. 10  And Noah begat three sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.

11  The earth also was corrupt before God, and the earth was filled with violence. 12  And God looked upon the earth, and, behold, it was corrupt; for all flesh had corrupted his way upon the earth.

13  And God said unto Noah, The end of all flesh is come before me; for the earth is filled with violence through them; and, behold, I will destroy them [∥]with the earth.

14 ¶ Make thee an ark of gopher wood; [†]rooms shalt thou make in the ark, and shalt pitch it within and without with pitch. 15 And this is the fashion which thou shalt make it of: The length of the ark shall be three hundred cubits, the breadth of it fifty cubits, and the height of it thirty cubits. 16  A window shalt thou make to the ark, and in a cubit shalt thou finish it above; and the door of the ark shalt thou set in the side thereof; with lower, second, and third stories shalt thou make it. 17  And, behold, I, even I, do bring a flood of waters upon the earth, to destroy all flesh, wherein is the breath of life, from under heaven; and every thing that is in the earth shall die. 18  But with thee will I establish my covenant; and thou shalt come into the ark, thou, and thy sons, and thy wife, and thy sons’ wives with thee. 19  And of every living thing of all flesh, two of every sort shalt thou bring into the ark, to keep them alive with thee; they shall be male and female. 20  Of fowls after their kind, and of cattle after their kind, of every creeping thing of the earth after his kind, two of every sort shall come unto thee, to keep them alive. 21  And take thou unto thee of all food that is eaten, and thou shalt gather it to thee; and it shall be for food for thee, and for them. 22 [*] Thus did Noah; according to all that God commanded him, so did he.

7

1  And the [*]LORD said unto Noah, Come thou and all thy house into the ark; for thee have I seen righteous before me in this generation. 2  Of every clean beast thou shalt take to thee by [†]sevens, the male and his female: and of beasts that are not clean by two, the male and his female. 3  Of fowls also of the air by sevens, the male and the female; to keep seed alive upon the face of all the earth. 4  For yet seven days, and I will cause it to rain upon the earth forty days and forty nights; and every living substance that I have made will I [†]destroy from off the face of the earth.

5  And Noah did according unto all that the LORD commanded him. 6  And Noah was six hundred years old when the flood of waters was upon the earth.

7 ¶ And Noah went in, and his sons, and his wife, and his sons’ wives with him, into the ark, because of the waters of the flood. 8  Of clean beasts, and of beasts that are not clean, and of fowls, and of every thing that creepeth upon the earth, 9  There went in two and two unto Noah into the ark, the male and the female, as God had commanded Noah. 10  And it came to pass [∥]after seven days, that the waters of the flood were upon the earth.

11 ¶ In the six hundredth year of Noah’s life, in the second month, the seventeenth day of the month, the same day were all the fountains of the great deep broken up, and the [∥]windows of heaven were opened. 12  And the rain was upon the earth forty days and forty nights.

13  In the selfsame day entered Noah, and Shem, and Ham, and Japheth, the sons of Noah, and Noah’s wife, and the three wives of his sons with them, into the ark; 14  They, and every beast after his kind, and all the cattle after their kind, and every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth after his kind, and every fowl after his kind, every bird of every [†]sort. 15  And they went in unto Noah into the ark, two and two of all flesh, wherein is the breath of life. 16  And they that went in, went in male and female of all flesh, as God had commanded him: and the LORD shut him in.

17  And the flood was forty days upon the earth; and the waters increased, and bare up the ark, and it was lift up above the earth. 18  And the waters prevailed, and were increased greatly upon the earth; and the ark went upon the face of the waters. 19  And the waters prevailed exceedingly upon the earth; and all the high hills, that were under the whole heaven, were covered. 20  Fifteen cubits upward did the waters prevail; and the mountains were covered.

21 [*] And all flesh died that moved upon the earth, both of fowl, and of cattle, and of beast, and of every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth, and every man: 22  All in whose nostrils was [†]the breath of life, of all that was in the dry land, died. 23  And every living substance was destroyed which was upon the face of the ground, both man, and cattle, and the creeping things, and the fowl of the heaven; and they were destroyed from the earth: and [*]Noah only remained alive, and they that were with him in the ark. 24  And the waters prevailed upon the earth an hundred and fifty days.

8

1  And God remembered Noah, and every living thing, and all the cattle that was with him in the ark: and God made a wind to pass over the earth, and the waters asswaged; 2  The fountains also of the deep and the windows of heaven were stopped, and the rain from heaven was restrained; 3  And the waters returned from off the earth [†]continually: and after the end of the hundred and fifty days the waters were abated.

4  And the ark rested in the seventh month, on the seventeenth day of the month, upon the mountains of Ararat. 5  And the waters [†]decreased continually until the tenth month: in the tenth month, on the first day of the month, were the tops of the mountains seen.

6 ¶ And it came to pass at the end of forty days, that Noah opened the window of the ark which he had made: 7  And he sent forth a raven, which went forth [†]to and fro, until the waters were dried up from off the earth. 8  Also he sent forth a dove from him, to see if the waters were abated from off the face of the ground; 9  But the dove found no rest for the sole of her foot, and she returned unto him into the ark, for the waters were on the face of the whole earth: then he put forth his hand, and took her, and [†]pulled her in unto him into the ark. 10  And he stayed yet other seven days; and again he sent forth the dove out of the ark; 11  And the dove came in to him in the evening; and, lo, in her mouth was an olive leaf pluckt off: so Noah knew that the waters were abated from off the earth. 12  And he stayed yet other seven days; and sent forth the dove; which returned not again unto him any more.

13 ¶ And it came to pass in the six hundredth and [‡]first year, in the first month, the first day of the month, the waters were dried up from off the earth: and Noah removed the covering of the ark, and looked, and, behold, the face of the ground was dry. 14  And in the second month, on the seven and twentieth day of the month, was the earth dried.

15 ¶ And God spake unto Noah, saying, 16  Go forth of the ark, thou, and thy wife, and thy sons, and thy sons’ wives with thee. 17  Bring forth with thee every living thing that is with thee, of all flesh, both of fowl, and of cattle, and of every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth; that they may breed abundantly in the earth, and be fruitful, and multiply upon the earth. 18  And Noah went forth, and his sons, and his wife, and his sons’ wives with him: 19  Every beast, every creeping thing, and every fowl, and whatsoever creepeth upon the earth, after their [†]kinds, went forth out of the ark.

20 ¶ And Noah builded an altar unto the LORD; and took of every clean beast, and of every clean fowl, and offered burnt offerings on the altar. 21  And the LORD smelled [†]a sweet savour; and the LORD said in his heart, I will not again curse the ground any more for man’s sake; for the [*]imagination of man’s heart is evil from his youth; neither will I again smite any more every thing living, as I have done. 22 [†] While the earth remaineth, seedtime and harvest, and cold and heat, and summer and winter, and day and night shall not cease.

9

1  And God blessed Noah and his sons, and said unto them, [*]Be fruitful, and multiply, and replenish the earth. 2  And the fear of you and the dread of you shall be upon every beast of the earth, and upon every fowl of the air, upon all that moveth upon the earth, and upon all the fishes of the sea; into your hand are they delivered. 3  Every moving thing that liveth shall be meat for you; even as the [*]green herb have I given you all things. 4 [*] But flesh with the life thereof, which is the blood thereof, shall ye not eat. 5  And surely your blood of your lives will I require; at the hand of every beast will I require it, and at the hand of man; at the hand of every man’s brother will I require the life of man. 6 [*] Whoso sheddeth man’s blood, by man shall his blood be shed: [*]for in the image of God made he man. 7  And you, be ye fruitful, and multiply; bring forth abundantly in the earth, and multiply therein.

8 ¶ And God spake unto Noah, and to his sons with him, saying, 9  And I, behold, I establish my covenant with you, and with your seed after you; 10  And with every living creature that is with you, of the fowl, of the cattle, and of every beast of the earth with you; from all that go out of the ark, to every beast of the earth. 11  And [*]I will establish my covenant with you; neither shall all flesh be cut off any more by the waters of a flood; neither shall there any more be a flood to destroy the earth.

12  And God said, This is the token of the covenant which I make between me and you and every living creature that is with you, for perpetual generations: 13  I do set my bow in the cloud, and it shall be for a token of a covenant between me and the earth. 14 [*] And it shall come to pass, when I bring a cloud over the earth, that the bow shall be seen in the cloud: 15  And I will remember my covenant, which is between me and you and every living creature of all flesh; and the waters shall no more become a flood to destroy all flesh. 16  And the bow shall be in the cloud; and I will look upon it, that I may remember the everlasting covenant between God and every living creature of all flesh that is upon the earth. 17  And God said unto Noah, This is the token of the covenant, which I have established between me and all flesh that is upon the earth.

18 ¶ And the sons of Noah, that went forth of the ark, were Shem, and Ham, and Japheth: and Ham is the father of [†]Canaan. 19 These are the three sons of Noah: and of them was the whole earth overspread. 20  And Noah began to be an husbandman, and he planted a vineyard: 21  And he drank of the wine, and was drunken; and he was uncovered within his tent. 22  And Ham, the father of Canaan, saw the nakedness of his father, and told his two brethren without. 23  And Shem and Japheth took a garment, and laid it upon both their shoulders, and went backward, and covered the nakedness of their father; and their faces were backward, and they saw not their father’s nakedness.

24  And Noah awoke from his wine, and knew what his younger son had done unto him. 25  And he said, Cursed be Canaan; a servant of servants shall he be unto his brethren. 26  And he said, Blessed be the LORD God of Shem; and Canaan shall be [∥]his servant. 27  God shall [∥]enlarge Japheth, and he shall dwell in the tents of Shem; and Canaan shall be his servant.

28 ¶ And Noah lived after the flood three hundred and fifty years. 29  And all the days of Noah were nine hundred and fifty years: and he died.

10

1 Now these are the generations of the sons of Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth: and unto them were sons born after the flood. 2 [*] The sons of Japheth; Gomer, and Magog, and Madai, and Javan, and Tubal, and Meshech, and Tiras. 3  And the sons of Gomer; Ashkenaz, and Riphath, and Togarmah. 4  And the sons of Javan; Elishah, and Tarshish, Kittim, and Dodanim. 5  By these were the isles of the Gentiles divided in their lands; every one after his tongue, after their families, in their nations.

6 ¶ [*]And the sons of Ham; Cush, and Mizraim, and Phut, and Canaan. 7  And the sons of Cush; Seba, and Havilah, and Sabtah, and Raamah, and Sabtecha: and the sons of Raamah; Sheba, and Dedan. 8  And Cush begat Nimrod: he began to be a mighty one in the earth. 9  He was a mighty hunter before the LORD: wherefore it is said, Even as Nimrod the mighty hunter before the LORD. 10  And the beginning of his kingdom was [†]Babel, and Erech, and Accad, and Calneh, in the land of Shinar. 11  Out of that land [∥]went forth Asshur, and builded Nineveh, and [∥]the city Rehoboth, and Calah, 12  And Resen between Nineveh and Calah: the same is a great city. 13  And Mizraim begat Ludim, and Anamim, and Lehabim, and Naphtuhim, 14  And Pathrusim, and Casluhim, (out of whom came Philistim,) and Caphtorim.

15 ¶ And Canaan begat [†]Sidon his firstborn, and Heth, 16  And the Jebusite, and the Amorite, and the Girgasite, 17  And the Hivite, and the Arkite, and the Sinite, 18  And the Arvadite, and the Zemarite, and the Hamathite: and afterward were the families of the Canaanites spread abroad. 19  And the border of the Canaanites was from Sidon, as thou comest to Gerar, unto [†]Gaza; as thou goest, unto Sodom, and Gomorrah, and Admah, and Zeboim, even unto Lasha. 20 These are the sons of Ham, after their families, after their tongues, in their countries, and in their nations.

21 ¶ Unto Shem also, the father of all the children of Eber, the brother of Japheth the elder, even to him were children born. 22  The [*]children of Shem; Elam, and Asshur, and [†]Arphaxad, and Lud, and Aram. 23  And the children of Aram; Uz, and Hul, and Gether, and Mash. 24  And Arphaxad begat [†]Salah; and Salah begat Eber. 25 [*] And unto Eber were born two sons: the name of one was Peleg; for in his days was the earth divided; and his brother’s name was Joktan. 26  And Joktan begat Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazarmaveth, and Jerah, 27  And Hadoram, and Uzal, and Diklah, 28  And Obal, and Abimael, and Sheba, 29  And Ophir, and Havilah, and Jobab: all these were the sons of Joktan. 30  And their dwelling was from Mesha, as thou goest unto Sephar a mount of the east. 31 These are the sons of Shem, after their families, after their tongues, in their lands, after their nations. 32 These are the families of the sons of Noah, after their generations, in their nations: and by these were the nations divided in the earth after the flood.

11

1  And [*]the whole earth was of one [†]language, and of one [†]speech. 2  And it came to pass, as they journeyed from the east, that they found a plain in the land of Shinar; and they dwelt there. 3  And [†]they said one to another, Go to, let us make brick, and [†]burn them throughly. And they had brick for stone, and slime had they for morter. 4  And they said, Go to, let us build us a city and a tower, whose top may reach unto heaven; and let us make us a name, lest we be scattered abroad upon the face of the whole earth.

5  And the LORD came down to see the city and the tower, which the children of men builded. 6  And the LORD said, Behold, the people is one, and they have all one language; and this they begin to do: and now nothing will be restrained from them, which they have imagined to do. 7  Go to, let us go down, and there confound their language, that they may not understand one another’s speech. 8  So the LORD scattered them abroad from thence upon the face of all the earth: and they left off to build the city. 9  Therefore is the name of it called [∥]Babel; because the LORD did there confound the language of all the earth: and from thence did the LORD scatter them abroad upon the face of all the earth.

10 ¶ [*]These are the generations of Shem: Shem was an hundred years old, and begat Arphaxad two years after the flood: 11  And Shem lived after he begat Arphaxad five hundred years, and begat sons and daughters. 12  And Arphaxad lived five and thirty years, and begat Salah: 13  And Arphaxad lived after he begat Salah four hundred and three years, and begat sons and daughters. 14  And Salah lived thirty years, and begat Eber: 15  And Salah lived after he begat Eber four hundred and three years, and begat sons and daughters. 16 [*] And Eber lived four and thirty years, and begat [*]Peleg: 17  And Eber lived after he begat Peleg four hundred and thirty years, and begat sons and daughters. 18  And Peleg lived thirty years, and begat Reu: 19  And Peleg lived after he begat Reu two hundred and nine years, and begat sons and daughters. 20  And Reu lived two and thirty years, and begat [*]Serug: 21  And Reu lived after he begat Serug two hundred and seven years, and begat sons and daughters. 22  And Serug lived thirty years, and begat Nahor: 23  And Serug lived after he begat Nahor two hundred years, and begat sons and daughters. 24  And Nahor lived nine and twenty years, and begat [*]Terah: 25  And Nahor lived after he begat Terah an hundred and nineteen years, and begat sons and daughters. 26  And Terah lived seventy years, and [*]begat Abram, Nahor, and Haran.

27 ¶ Now these are the generations of Terah: Terah begat Abram, Nahor, and Haran; and Haran begat Lot. 28  And Haran died before his father Terah in the land of his nativity, in Ur of the Chaldees. 29  And Abram and Nahor took them wives: the name of Abram’s wife was Sarai; and the name of Nahor’s wife, Milcah, the daughter of Haran, the father of Milcah, and the father of Iscah. 30  But Sarai was barren; she had no child. 31  And Terah took Abram his son, and Lot the son of Haran his son’s son, and Sarai his daughter in law, his son Abram’s wife; and they went forth with them from [*]Ur of the Chaldees, to go into the land of Canaan; and they came unto Haran, and dwelt there. 32  And the days of Terah were two hundred and five years: and Terah died in Haran.

12

1  Now the [*]LORD had said unto Abram, Get thee out of thy country, and from thy kindred, and from thy father’s house, unto a land that I will shew thee: 2  And I will make of thee a great nation, and I will bless thee, and make thy name great; and thou shalt be a blessing: 3  And I will bless them that bless thee, and curse him that curseth thee: [*]and in thee shall all families of the earth be blessed.

4  So Abram departed, as the LORD had spoken unto him; and Lot went with him: and Abram was seventy and five years old when he departed out of Haran. 5  And Abram took Sarai his wife, and Lot his brother’s son, and all their substance that they had gathered, and the souls that they had gotten in Haran; and they went forth to go into the land of Canaan; and into the land of Canaan they came.

6 ¶ And Abram passed through the land unto the place of Sichem, unto the plain of Moreh. And the Canaanite was then in the land. 7  And the LORD appeared unto Abram, and said, [*]Unto thy seed will I give this land: and there builded he an [*]altar unto the LORD, who appeared unto him. 8  And he removed from thence unto a mountain on the east of Beth-el, and pitched his tent, having Beth-el on the west, and Hai on the east: and there he builded an altar unto the LORD, and called upon the name of the LORD. 9  And Abram journeyed, [†]going on still toward the south.

10 ¶ And there was a famine in the land: and Abram went down into Egypt to sojourn there; for the famine was grievous in the land. 11  And it came to pass, when he was come near to enter into Egypt, that he said unto Sarai his wife, Behold now, I know that thou art a fair woman to look upon: 12  Therefore it shall come to pass, when the Egyptians shall see thee, that they shall say, This is his wife: and they will kill me, but they will save thee alive. 13  Say, I pray thee, thou art my sister: that it may be well with me for thy sake; and my soul shall live because of thee.

14 ¶ And it came to pass, that, when Abram was come into Egypt, the Egyptians beheld the woman that she was very fair. 15  The princes also of Pharaoh saw her, and commended her before Pharaoh: and the woman was taken into Pharaoh’s house. 16  And he entreated Abram well for her sake: and he had sheep, and oxen, and he asses, and menservants, and maidservants, and she asses, and camels. 17  And the LORD plagued Pharaoh and his house with great plagues because of Sarai Abram’s wife. 18  And Pharaoh called Abram, and said, What is this that thou hast done unto me? why didst thou not tell me that she was thy wife? 19  Why saidst thou, She is my sister? so I might have taken her to me to wife: now therefore behold thy wife, take her, and go thy way. 20  And Pharaoh commanded his men concerning him: and they sent him away, and his wife, and all that he had.

13

1  And Abram went up out of Egypt, he, and his wife, and all that he had, and Lot with him, into the south. 2  And Abram was very rich in cattle, in silver, and in gold. 3  And he went on his journeys from the south even to Beth-el, unto the place where his tent had been at the beginning, between Beth-el and Hai; 4  Unto the [*]place of the altar, which he had made there at the first: and there Abram called on the name of the LORD.

5 ¶ And Lot also, which went with Abram, had flocks, and herds, and tents. 6  And the land was not able to bear them, that they might dwell together: for their substance was great, so that they could not dwell together. 7  And there was a strife between the herdmen of Abram’s cattle and the herdmen of Lot’s cattle: and the Canaanite and the Perizzite dwelled then in the land. 8  And Abram said unto Lot, Let there be no strife, I pray thee, between me and thee, and between my herdmen and thy herdmen; for we be [†]brethren. 9  Is not the whole land before thee? separate thyself, I pray thee, from me: if thou wilt take the left hand, then I will go to the right; or if thou depart to the right hand, then I will go to the left.

10  And Lot lifted up his eyes, and beheld all the plain of Jordan, that it was well watered every where, before the LORD destroyed Sodom and Gomorrah, even as the garden of the LORD, like the land of Egypt, as thou comest unto Zoar. 11  Then Lot chose him all the plain of Jordan; and Lot journeyed east: and they separated themselves the one from the other. 12  Abram dwelled in the land of Canaan, and Lot dwelled in the cities of the plain, and pitched his tent toward Sodom. 13  But the men of Sodom were wicked and sinners before the LORD exceedingly.

14 ¶ And the LORD said unto Abram, after that Lot was separated from him, Lift up now thine eyes, and look from the place where thou art northward, and southward, and eastward, and westward: 15  For all the land which thou seest, [*]to thee will I give it, and to thy seed for ever. 16  And I will make thy seed as the dust of the earth: so that if a man can number the dust of the earth, then shall thy seed also be numbered. 17  Arise, walk through the land in the length of it and in the breadth of it; for I will give it unto thee. 18  Then Abram removed his tent, and came and dwelt in the [†]plain of Mamre, which is in Hebron, and built there an altar unto the LORD.

14

1  And it came to pass in the days of Amraphel king of Shinar, Arioch king of Ellasar, Chedorlaomer king of Elam, and Tidal king of nations; 2  That these made war with Bera king of Sodom, and with Birsha king of Gomorrah, Shinab king of Admah, and Shemeber king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela, which is Zoar. 3  All these were joined together in the vale of Siddim, which is the salt sea. 4  Twelve years they served Chedorlaomer, and in the thirteenth year they rebelled. 5  And in the fourteenth year came Chedorlaomer, and the kings that were with him, and smote the Rephaims in Ashteroth Karnaim, and the Zuzims in Ham, and the Emims in [∥]Shaveh Kiriathaim, 6  And the Horites in their mount Seir, unto [∥]El-paran, which is by the wilderness. 7  And they returned, and came to En-mishpat, which is Kadesh, and smote all the country of the Amalekites, and also the Amorites, that dwelt in Hazezon-tamar. 8  And there went out the king of Sodom, and the king of Gomorrah, and the king of Admah, and the king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela (the same is Zoar;) and they joined battle with them in the vale of Siddim; 9  With Chedorlaomer the king of Elam, and with Tidal king of nations, and Amraphel king of Shinar, and Arioch king of Ellasar; four kings with five. 10  And the vale of Siddim was full of slimepits; and the kings of Sodom and Gomorrah fled, and fell there; and they that remained fled to the mountain. 11  And they took all the goods of Sodom and Gomorrah, and all their victuals, and went their way. 12  And they took Lot, Abram’s brother’s son, who dwelt in Sodom, and his goods, and departed.

13 ¶ And there came one that had escaped, and told Abram the Hebrew; for he dwelt in the plain of Mamre the Amorite, brother of Eshcol, and brother of Aner: and these were confederate with Abram. 14  And when Abram heard that his brother was taken captive, he [∥]armed his [∥]trained servants, born in his own house, three hundred and eighteen, and pursued them unto Dan. 15  And he divided himself against them, he and his servants, by night, and smote them, and pursued them unto Hobah, which is on the left hand of Damascus. 16  And he brought back all the goods, and also brought again his brother Lot, and his goods, and the women also, and the people.

17 ¶ And the king of Sodom went out to meet him after his return from the slaughter of Chedorlaomer, and of the kings that were with him, at the valley of Shaveh, which is the [*]king’s dale. 18  And [*]Melchizedek king of Salem brought forth bread and wine: and he was the priest of the most high God. 19  And he blessed him, and said, Blessed be Abram of the most high God, possessor of heaven and earth: 20  And blessed be the most high God, which hath delivered thine enemies into thy hand. And he gave him [*]tithes of all.

21  And the king of Sodom said unto Abram, Give me the [†]persons, and take the goods to thyself. 22  And Abram said to the king of Sodom, I have lift up mine hand unto the LORD, the most high God, the possessor of heaven and earth, 23  That I will not take from a thread even to a shoelatchet, and that I will not take any thing that is thine, lest thou shouldest say, I have made Abram rich: 24  Save only that which the young men have eaten, and the portion of the men which went with me, Aner, Eshcol, and Mamre; let them take their portion.

15

1  After these things the word of the LORD came unto Abram in a vision, saying, Fear not, Abram: I am thy shield, and thy exceeding [*]great reward.

2  And Abram said, Lord GOD, what wilt thou give me, seeing I go childless, and the steward of my house is this Eliezer of Damascus? 3  And Abram said, Behold, to me thou hast given no seed: and, lo, one born in my house is mine heir. 4  And, behold, the word of the LORD came unto him, saying, This shall not be thine heir; but he that shall come forth out of thine own bowels shall be thine heir. 5  And he brought him forth abroad, and said, Look now toward heaven, and tell the stars, if thou be able to number them: and he said unto him, [*]So shall thy seed be. 6  And he [*]believed in the LORD; and he counted it to him for righteousness.

7  And he said unto him, I am the LORD that brought thee out of Ur of the Chaldees, to give thee this land to inherit it. 8  And he said, Lord GOD, whereby shall I know that I shall inherit it? 9  And he said unto him, Take me an heifer of three years old, and a she goat of three years old, and a ram of three years old, and a turtledove, and a young pigeon. 10  And he took unto him all these, and divided them in the midst, and laid each piece one against another: but the birds divided he not. 11  And when the fowls came down upon the carcases, Abram drove them away.

12  And when the sun was going down, a deep sleep fell upon Abram; and, lo, an horror of great darkness fell upon him. 13  And he said unto Abram, Know of a surety [*]that thy seed shall be a stranger in a land that is not theirs, and shall serve them; and they shall afflict them four hundred years; 14  And also that nation, whom they shall serve, will I judge: and afterward shall they come out with great substance. 15  And thou shalt go to thy fathers in peace; thou shalt be buried in a good old age. 16  But in the fourth generation they shall come hither again: for the iniquity of the Amorites is not yet full.

17  And it came to pass, that, when the sun went down, and it was dark, behold a smoking furnace, and [†]a burning lamp that passed between those pieces. 18  In the same day the LORD made a covenant with Abram, saying, [*]Unto thy seed have I given this land, from the river of Egypt unto the great river, the river Euphrates: 19  The Kenites, and the Kenizzites, and the Kadmonites, 20  And the Hittites, and the Perizzites, and the Rephaims, 21  And the Amorites, and the Canaanites, and the Girgashites, and the Jebusites.

16

1  Now Sarai Abram’s wife bare him no children: and she had an handmaid, an Egyptian, whose name was Hagar. 2  And Sarai said unto Abram, Behold now, the LORD hath restrained me from bearing: I pray thee, go in unto my maid; it may be that I may [†]obtain children by her. And Abram hearkened to the voice of Sarai. 3  And Sarai Abram’s wife took Hagar her maid the Egyptian, after Abram had dwelt ten years in the land of Canaan, and gave her to her husband Abram to be his wife.

4 ¶ And he went in unto Hagar, and she conceived: and when she saw that she had conceived, her mistress was despised in her eyes. 5  And Sarai said unto Abram, My wrong be upon thee: I have given my maid into thy bosom; and when she saw that she had conceived, I was despised in her eyes: the LORD judge between me and thee. 6  But Abram said unto Sarai, Behold, thy maid is in thy hand; do to her [†]as it pleaseth thee. And when Sarai [†]dealt hardly with her, she fled from her face.

7 ¶ And the angel of the LORD found her by a fountain of water in the wilderness, by the fountain in the way to Shur. 8  And he said, Hagar, Sarai’s maid, whence camest thou? and whither wilt thou go? And she said, I flee from the face of my mistress Sarai. 9  And the angel of the LORD said unto her, Return to thy mistress, and submit thyself under her hands.

10  And the angel of the LORD said unto her, I will multiply thy seed exceedingly, that it shall not be numbered for multitude. 11  And the angel of the LORD said unto her, Behold, thou art with child, and shalt bear a son, and shalt call his name [∥]Ishmael; because the LORD hath heard thy affliction. 12  And he will be a wild man; his hand will be against every man, and every man’s hand against him; [*]and he shall dwell in the presence of all his brethren. 13  And she called the name of the LORD that spake unto her, Thou God seest me: for she said, Have I also here looked after him that seeth me? 14  Wherefore the well was called [*][∥]Beer-lahai-roi; behold, it is between Kadesh and Bered.

15 ¶ And Hagar bare Abram a son: and Abram called his son’s name, which Hagar bare, Ishmael. 16  And Abram was fourscore and six years old, when Hagar bare Ishmael to Abram.

17

1  And when Abram was ninety years old and nine, the LORD appeared to Abram, and said unto him, I am the Almighty God; [*]walk before me, and be thou [∥]perfect. 2  And I will make my covenant between me and thee, and will multiply thee exceedingly. 3  And Abram fell on his face: and God talked with him, saying,

4  As for me, behold, my covenant is with thee, and thou shalt be a father of [†]many nations. 5  Neither shall thy name any more be called Abram, but thy name shall be Abraham; [*]for a father of many nations have I made thee. 6  And I will make thee exceeding fruitful, and I will make nations of thee, and kings shall come out of thee.

7  And I will establish my covenant between me and thee and thy seed after thee in their generations for an everlasting covenant, to be a God unto thee, and to thy seed after thee. 8  And I will give unto thee, and to thy seed after thee, the land [†]wherein thou art a stranger, all the land of Canaan, for an everlasting possession; and I will be their God.

9 ¶ And God said unto Abraham, Thou shalt keep my covenant therefore, thou, and thy seed after thee in their generations. 10 This is my covenant, which ye shall keep, between me and you and thy seed after thee; [*]Every man child among you shall be circumcised. 11  And ye shall circumcise the flesh of your foreskin; and it shall be [*]a token of the covenant betwixt me and you. 12  And [†]he that is eight days old [*]shall be circumcised among you, every man child in your generations, he that is born in the house, or bought with money of any stranger, which is not of thy seed. 13  He that is born in thy house, and he that is bought with thy money, must needs be circumcised: and my covenant shall be in your flesh for an everlasting covenant. 14  And the uncircumcised man child whose flesh of his foreskin is not circumcised, that soul shall be cut off from his people; he hath broken my covenant.

15 ¶ And God said unto Abraham, As for Sarai thy wife, thou shalt not call her name Sarai, but Sarah shall her name be. 16  And I will bless her, and give thee a son also of her: yea, I will bless her, and [†]she shall be a mother of nations; kings of people shall be of her. 17  Then Abraham fell upon his face, and laughed, and said in his heart, Shall a child be born unto him that is an hundred years old? and shall Sarah, that is ninety years old, bear? 18  And Abraham said unto God, O that Ishmael might live before thee! 19  And God said, [*]Sarah thy wife shall bear thee a son indeed; and thou shalt call his name Isaac: and I will establish my covenant with him for an everlasting covenant, and with his seed after him. 20  And as for Ishmael, I have heard thee: Behold, I have blessed him, and will make him fruitful, and will multiply him exceedingly; [*]twelve princes shall he beget, and I will make him a great nation. 21  But my covenant will I establish with Isaac, which Sarah shall bear unto thee at this set time in the next year. 22  And he left off talking with him, and God went up from Abraham.

23 ¶ And Abraham took Ishmael his son, and all that were born in his house, and all that were bought with his money, every male among the men of Abraham’s house; and circumcised the flesh of their foreskin in the selfsame day, as God had said unto him. 24  And Abraham was ninety years old and nine, when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin. 25  And Ishmael his son was thirteen years old, when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin. 26  In the selfsame day was Abraham circumcised, and Ishmael his son. 27  And all the men of his house, born in the house, and bought with money of the stranger, were circumcised with him.

18

1  And the LORD appeared unto him in the plains of Mamre: and he sat in the tent door in the heat of the day; 2 [*] And he lift up his eyes and looked, and, lo, three men stood by him: and when he saw them, he ran to meet them from the tent door, and bowed himself toward the ground, 3  And said, My Lord, if now I have found favour in thy sight, pass not away, I pray thee, from thy servant: 4  Let a little water, I pray you, be fetched, and wash your feet, and rest yourselves under the tree: 5  And I will fetch a morsel of bread, and [†]comfort ye your hearts; after that ye shall pass on: for therefore [†]are ye come to your servant. And they said, So do, as thou hast said. 6  And Abraham hastened into the tent unto Sarah, and said, [†]Make ready quickly three measures of fine meal, knead it, and make cakes upon the hearth. 7  And Abraham ran unto the herd, and fetcht a calf tender and good, and gave it unto a young man; and he hasted to dress it. 8  And he took butter, and milk, and the calf which he had dressed, and set it before them; and he stood by them under the tree, and they did eat.

9 ¶ And they said unto him, Where is Sarah thy wife? And he said, Behold, in the tent. 10  And he said, I will certainly return unto thee according to the time of life; and, lo, [*]Sarah thy wife shall have a son. And Sarah heard it in the tent door, which was behind him. 11  Now Abraham and Sarah were old and well stricken in age; and it ceased to be with Sarah after the manner of women. 12  Therefore Sarah laughed within herself, saying, After I am waxed old shall I have pleasure, my [*]lord being old also? 13  And the LORD said unto Abraham, Wherefore did Sarah laugh, saying, Shall I of a surety bear a child, which am old? 14  Is any thing too hard for the LORD? At the time appointed I will return unto thee, according to the time of life, and Sarah shall have a son. 15  Then Sarah denied, saying, I laughed not; for she was afraid. And he said, Nay; but thou didst laugh.

16 ¶ And the men rose up from thence, and looked toward Sodom: and Abraham went with them to bring them on the way. 17  And the LORD said, Shall I hide from Abraham that thing which I do; 18  Seeing that Abraham shall surely become a great and mighty nation, and all the nations of the earth shall be [*]blessed in him? 19  For I know him, that he will command his children and his household after him, and they shall keep the way of the LORD, to do justice and judgment; that the LORD may bring upon Abraham that which he hath spoken of him. 20  And the LORD said, Because the cry of Sodom and Gomorrah is great, and because their sin is very grievous; 21  I will go down now, and see whether they have done altogether according to the cry of it, which is come unto me; and if not, I will know. 22  And the men turned their faces from thence, and went toward Sodom: but Abraham stood yet before the LORD.

23 ¶ And Abraham drew near, and said, Wilt thou also destroy the righteous with the wicked? 24  Peradventure there be fifty righteous within the city: wilt thou also destroy and not spare the place for the fifty righteous that are therein? 25  That be far from thee to do after this manner, to slay the righteous with the wicked: and that the righteous should be as the wicked, that be far from thee: Shall not the Judge of all the earth do right? 26  And the LORD said, If I find in Sodom fifty righteous within the city, then I will spare all the place for their sakes. 27  And Abraham answered and said, Behold now, I have taken upon me to speak unto the Lord, which am but dust and ashes: 28  Peradventure there shall lack five of the fifty righteous: wilt thou destroy all the city for lack of five? And he said, If I find there forty and five, I will not destroy it. 29  And he spake unto him yet again, and said, Peradventure there shall be forty found there. And he said, I will not do it for forty’s sake. 30  And he said unto him, Oh let not the Lord be angry, and I will speak: Peradventure there shall thirty be found there. And he said, I will not do it, if I find thirty there. 31  And he said, Behold now, I have taken upon me to speak unto the Lord: Peradventure there shall be twenty found there. And he said, I will not destroy it for twenty’s sake. 32  And he said, Oh let not the Lord be angry, and I will speak yet but this once: Peradventure ten shall be found there. And he said, I will not destroy it for ten’s sake. 33  And the LORD went his way, as soon as he had left communing with Abraham: and Abraham returned unto his place.

19

1  And there came two angels to Sodom at even; and Lot sat in the gate of Sodom: and Lot seeing them rose up to meet them; and he bowed himself with his face toward the ground; 2  And he said, Behold now, my lords, turn in, I pray you, into your servant’s house, and tarry all night, and [*]wash your feet, and ye shall rise up early, and go on your ways. And they said, Nay; but we will abide in the street all night. 3  And he pressed upon them greatly; and they turned in unto him, and entered into his house; and he made them a feast, and did bake unleavened bread, and they did eat.

4 ¶ But before they lay down, the men of the city, even the men of Sodom, compassed the house round, both old and young, all the people from every quarter: 5  And they called unto Lot, and said unto him, Where are the men which came in to thee this night? bring them out unto us, that we may know them. 6  And Lot went out at the door unto them, and shut the door after him, 7  And said, I pray you, brethren, do not so wickedly. 8  Behold now, I have two daughters which have not known man; let me, I pray you, bring them out unto you, and do ye to them as is good in your eyes: only unto these men do nothing; for therefore came they under the shadow of my roof. 9  And they said, Stand back. And they said again, This one fellow came in to sojourn, and he will needs be a judge: now will we deal worse with thee, than with them. And they pressed sore upon the man, even Lot, and came near to break the door. 10  But the men put forth their hand, and pulled Lot into the house to them, and shut to the door. 11  And they smote the men [*]that were at the door of the house with blindness, both small and great: so that they wearied themselves to find the door.

12 ¶ And the men said unto Lot, Hast thou here any besides? son in law, and thy sons, and thy daughters, and whatsoever thou hast in the city, bring them out of this place: 13  For we will destroy this place, because the [*]cry of them is waxen great before the face of the LORD; and the LORD hath sent us to destroy it. 14  And Lot went out, and spake unto his sons in law, which married his daughters, and said, Up, get you out of this place; for the LORD will destroy this city. But he seemed as one that mocked unto his sons in law.

15 ¶ And when the morning arose, then the angels hastened Lot, saying, Arise, take thy wife, and thy two daughters, which [†]are here; lest thou be consumed in the [∥]iniquity of the city. 16  And [*]while he lingered, the men laid hold upon his hand, and upon the hand of his wife, and upon the hand of his two daughters; the LORD being merciful unto him: and they brought him forth, and set him without the city.

17 ¶ And it came to pass, when they had brought them forth abroad, that he said, Escape for thy life; look not behind thee, neither stay thou in all the plain; escape to the mountain, lest thou be consumed. 18  And Lot said unto them, Oh, not so, my Lord: 19  Behold now, thy servant hath found grace in thy sight, and thou hast magnified thy mercy, which thou hast shewed unto me in saving my life; and I cannot escape to the mountain, lest some evil take me, and I die: 20  Behold now, this city is near to flee unto, and it is a little one: Oh, let me escape thither, (is it not a little one?) and my soul shall live. 21  And he said unto him, See, I have accepted [†]thee concerning this thing [‡]also, that I will not overthrow this city, for the which thou hast spoken. 22  Haste thee, escape thither; for I cannot do any thing till thou be come thither. Therefore the name of the city was called Zoar.

23 ¶ The sun was [†]risen upon the earth when Lot entered into Zoar.

24  Then [*]the LORD rained upon Sodom and upon Gomorrah brimstone and fire from the LORD out of heaven; 25  And he overthrew those cities, and all the plain, and all the inhabitants of the cities, and that which grew upon the ground.

26 ¶ But his wife looked back from behind him, and she became a pillar of salt.

27 ¶ And Abraham gat up early in the morning to the place where he stood before the LORD: 28  And he looked toward Sodom and Gomorrah, and toward all the land of the plain, and beheld, and, lo, the smoke of the country went up as the smoke of a furnace.

29 ¶ And it came to pass, when God destroyed the cities of the plain, that God remembered Abraham, and sent Lot out of the midst of the overthrow, when he overthrew the cities in the which Lot dwelt.

30 ¶ And Lot went up out of Zoar, and dwelt in the mountain, and his two daughters with him; for he feared to dwell in Zoar: and he dwelt in a cave, he and his two daughters. 31  And the firstborn said unto the younger, Our father is old, and there is not a man in the earth to come in unto us after the manner of all the earth: 32  Come, let us make our father drink wine, and we will lie with him, that we may preserve seed of our father. 33  And they made their father drink wine that night: and the firstborn went in, and lay with her father; and he perceived not when she lay down, nor when she arose. 34  And it came to pass on the morrow, that the firstborn said unto the younger, Behold, I lay yesternight with my father: let us make him drink wine this night also; and go thou in, and lie with him, that we may preserve seed of our father. 35  And they made their father drink wine that night also: and the younger arose, and lay with him; and he perceived not when she lay down, nor when she arose. 36  Thus were both the daughters of Lot with child by their father. 37  And the firstborn bare a son, and called his name Moab: the same is the father of the Moabites unto this day. 38  And the younger, she also bare a son, and called his name Ben-ammi: the same is the father of the children of Ammon unto this day.

20

1  And Abraham journeyed from thence toward the south country, and dwelled between Kadesh and Shur, and sojourned in Gerar. 2  And Abraham said of Sarah his wife, She is my sister: and Abimelech king of Gerar sent, and took Sarah.

3  But God came to Abimelech in a dream by night, and said to him, Behold, thou art but a dead man, for the woman which thou hast taken; for she is [†]a man’s wife. 4  But Abimelech had not come near her: and he said, Lord, wilt thou slay also a righteous nation? 5  Said he not unto me, She is my sister? and she, even she herself said, He is my brother: in the [∥]integrity of my heart and innocency of my hands have I done this. 6  And God said unto him in a dream, Yea, I know that thou didst this in the integrity of thy heart; for I also withheld thee from sinning against me: therefore suffered I thee not to touch her. 7  Now therefore restore the man his wife; for he is a prophet, and he shall pray for thee, and thou shalt live: and if thou restore her not, know thou that thou shalt surely die, thou, and all that are thine.

8  Therefore Abimelech rose early in the morning, and called all his servants, and told all these things in their ears: and the men were sore afraid. 9  Then Abimelech called Abraham, and said unto him, What hast thou done unto us? and what have I offended thee, that thou hast brought on me and on my kingdom a great sin? thou hast done deeds unto me that ought not to be done. 10  And Abimelech said unto Abraham, What sawest thou, that thou hast done this thing? 11  And Abraham said, Because I thought, Surely the fear of God is not in this place; and they will slay me for my wife’s sake. 12  And yet indeed she is my sister; she is the daughter of my father, but not the daughter of my mother; and she became my wife. 13  And it came to pass, when God caused me to wander from my father’s house, that I said unto her, This is thy kindness which thou shalt shew unto me; at every place whither we shall come, [*]say of me, He is my brother.

14  And Abimelech took sheep, and oxen, and menservants, and womenservants, and gave them unto Abraham, and restored him Sarah his wife. 15  And Abimelech said, Behold, my land is before thee: dwell [†]where it pleaseth thee. 16  And unto Sarah he said, Behold, I have given thy brother a thousand pieces of silver: behold, he is to thee a covering of the eyes, unto all that are with thee, and with all other: thus she was reproved.

17 ¶ So Abraham prayed unto God: and God healed Abimelech, and his wife, and his maidservants; and they bare children. 18  For the LORD had fast closed up all the wombs of the house of Abimelech, because of Sarah Abraham’s wife.

21

1  And the LORD visited Sarah as he had said, and the LORD did unto Sarah [*]as he had spoken. 2  For Sarah [*]conceived, and bare Abraham a son in his old age, at the set time of which God had spoken to him. 3  And Abraham called the name of his son that was born unto him, whom Sarah bare to him, Isaac. 4  And Abraham circumcised his son Isaac being eight days old, [*]as God had commanded him. 5  And Abraham was an hundred years old, when his son Isaac was born unto him.

6 ¶ And Sarah said, God hath made me to laugh, so that all that hear will laugh with me. 7  And she said, Who would have said unto Abraham, that Sarah should have given children suck? for I have born him a son in his old age. 8  And the child grew, and was weaned: and Abraham made a great feast the same day that Isaac was weaned.

9 ¶ And Sarah saw the son of Hagar the Egyptian, which she had born unto Abraham, mocking. 10  Wherefore she said unto Abraham, [*]Cast out this bondwoman and her son: for the son of this bondwoman shall not be heir with my son, even with Isaac. 11  And the thing was very grievous in Abraham’s sight because of his son.

12 ¶ And God said unto Abraham, Let it not be grievous in thy sight because of the lad, and because of thy bondwoman; in all that Sarah hath said unto thee, hearken unto her voice; for in Isaac shall thy seed be called. 13  And also of the son of the bondwoman will I make a nation, because he is thy seed.

14  And Abraham rose up early in the morning, and took bread, and a bottle of water, and gave it unto Hagar, putting it on her shoulder, and the child, and sent her away: and she departed, and wandered in the wilderness of Beer-sheba. 15  And the water was spent in the bottle, and she cast the child under one of the shrubs. 16  And she went, and sat her down over against him a good way off, as it were a bowshot: for she said, Let me not see the death of the child. And she sat over against him, and lift up her voice, and wept. 17  And God heard the voice of the lad; and the angel of God called to Hagar out of heaven, and said unto her, What aileth thee, Hagar? fear not; for God hath heard the voice of the lad where he is. 18  Arise, lift up the lad, and hold him in thine hand; for I will make him a great nation. 19  And God opened her eyes, and she saw a well of water; and she went, and filled the bottle with water, and gave the lad drink. 20  And God was with the lad; and he grew, and dwelt in the wilderness, and became an archer. 21  And he dwelt in the wilderness of Paran: and his mother took him a wife out of the land of Egypt.

22 ¶ And it came to pass at that time, that Abimelech and Phichol the chief captain of his host spake unto Abraham, saying, God is with thee in all that thou doest: 23  Now therefore swear unto me here by God [†]that thou wilt not deal falsely with me, nor with my son, nor with my son’s son: but according to the kindness that I have done unto thee, thou shalt do unto me, and to the land wherein thou hast sojourned. 24  And Abraham said, I will swear. 25  And Abraham reproved Abimelech because of a well of water, which Abimelech’s servants had violently taken away. 26  And Abimelech said, I wot not who hath done this thing: neither didst thou tell me, neither yet heard I of it, but to day. 27  And Abraham took sheep and oxen, and gave them unto Abimelech; and both of them made a covenant. 28  And Abraham set seven ewe lambs of the flock by themselves. 29  And Abimelech said unto Abraham, What mean these seven ewe lambs which thou hast set by themselves? 30  And he said, For these seven ewe lambs shalt thou take of my hand, that they may be a witness unto me, that I have digged this well. 31  Wherefore he called that place [∥]Beer-sheba; because there they sware both of them. 32  Thus they made a covenant at Beer-sheba: then Abimelech rose up, and Phichol the chief captain of his host, and they returned into the land of the Philistines.

33 ¶ And Abraham planted a [∥]grove in Beer-sheba, and called there on the name of the LORD, the everlasting God. 34  And Abraham sojourned in the Philistines’ land many days.

22

1  And it came to pass after these things, that [*]God did tempt Abraham, and said unto him, Abraham: and he said, [†]Behold, here I am. 2  And he said, Take now thy son, thine only son Isaac, whom thou lovest, and get thee into the land of Moriah; and offer him there for a burnt offering upon one of the mountains which I will tell thee of.

3 ¶ And Abraham rose up early in the morning, and saddled his ass, and took two of his young men with him, and Isaac his son, and clave the wood for the burnt offering, and rose up, and went unto the place of which God had told him. 4  Then on the third day Abraham lifted up his eyes, and saw the place afar off. 5  And Abraham said unto his young men, Abide ye here with the ass; and I and the lad will go yonder and worship, and come again to you. 6  And Abraham took the wood of the burnt offering, and laid it upon Isaac his son; and he took the fire in his hand, and a knife; and they went both of them together. 7  And Isaac spake unto Abraham his father, and said, My father: and he said, [†]Here am I, my son. And he said, Behold the fire and [‡]the wood: but where is the [∥]lamb for a burnt offering? 8  And Abraham said, My son, God will provide himself a lamb for a burnt offering: so they went both of them together. 9  And they came to the place which God had told him of; and Abraham built an altar there, and laid the wood in order, and bound Isaac his son, and [*]laid him on the altar upon the wood. 10  And Abraham stretched forth his hand, and took the knife to slay his son.

11  And the angel of the LORD called unto him out of heaven, and said, Abraham, Abraham: and he said, Here am I. 12  And he said, Lay not thine hand upon the lad, neither do thou any thing unto him: for now I know that thou fearest God, seeing thou hast not withheld thy son, thine only son from me. 13  And Abraham lifted up his eyes, and looked, and behold behind him a ram caught in a thicket by his horns: and Abraham went and took the ram, and offered him up for a burnt offering in the stead of his son. 14  And Abraham called the name of that place [∥]Jehovah-jireh: as it is said to this day, In the mount of the LORD it shall be seen.

15 ¶ And the angel of the LORD called unto Abraham out of heaven the second time, 16  And said, [*]By myself have I sworn, saith the LORD, for because thou hast done this thing, and hast not withheld thy son, thine only son: 17  That in blessing I will bless thee, and in multiplying I will multiply thy seed as the stars of the heaven, and as the sand which is upon the sea [†]shore; and thy seed shall possess the gate of his enemies; 18 [*] And in thy seed shall all the nations of the earth be blessed; because thou hast obeyed my voice. 19  So Abraham returned unto his young men, and they rose up and went together to Beer-sheba; and Abraham dwelt at Beer-sheba.

20 ¶ And it came to pass after these things, that it was told Abraham, saying, Behold, Milcah, she hath also born children unto thy brother Nahor; 21  Huz his firstborn, and Buz his brother, and Kemuel the father of Aram, 22  And Chesed, and Hazo, and Pildash, and Jidlaph, and Bethuel. 23  And Bethuel begat [*]Rebekah: these eight Milcah did bear to Nahor, Abraham’s brother. 24  And his concubine, whose name was Reumah, she bare also Tebah, and Gaham, and Thahash, and Maachah.

23

1  And Sarah was an hundred and seven and twenty years old: these were the years of the life of Sarah. 2  And Sarah died in Kirjath-arba; the same is Hebron in the land of Canaan: and Abraham came to mourn for Sarah, and to weep for her.

3 ¶ And Abraham stood up from before his dead, and spake unto the sons of Heth, saying, 4 I am a stranger and a sojourner with you: give me a possession of a buryingplace with you, that I may bury my dead out of my sight. 5  And the children of Heth answered Abraham, saying unto him, 6  Hear us, my lord: thou art [†]a mighty prince among us: in the choice of our sepulchres bury thy dead; none of us shall withhold from thee his sepulchre, but that thou mayest bury thy dead. 7  And Abraham stood up, and bowed himself to the people of the land, even to the children of Heth. 8  And he communed with them, saying, If it be your mind that I should bury my dead out of my sight; hear me, and intreat for me to Ephron the son of Zohar, 9  That he may give me the cave of Machpelah, which he hath, which is in the end of his field; for [†]as much money as it is worth he shall give it me for a possession of a buryingplace amongst you. 10  And Ephron dwelt among the children of Heth: and Ephron the Hittite answered Abraham in the [†]audience of the children of Heth, even of all that went in at the [‡]gate of his city, saying, 11  Nay, my lord, hear me: the field give I thee, and the cave that is therein, I give it thee; in the presence of the sons of my people give I it thee: bury thy dead. 12  And Abraham bowed down himself before the people of the land. 13  And he spake unto Ephron in the audience of the people of the land, saying, But if thou wilt give it, I pray thee, hear me: I will give thee money for the field; take it of me, and I will bury my dead there. 14  And Ephron answered Abraham, saying unto him, 15  My lord, hearken unto me: the land is worth four hundred shekels of silver; what is that betwixt me and thee? bury therefore thy dead.

16  And Abraham hearkened unto Ephron; and Abraham weighed to Ephron the silver, which he had named in the audience of the sons of Heth, four hundred shekels of silver, current money with the merchant.

17 ¶ And the field of Ephron, which was in Machpelah, which was before Mamre, the field, and the cave which was therein, and all the trees that were in the field, that were in all the borders round about, were made sure 18  Unto Abraham for a possession in the presence of the children of Heth, before all that went in at the gate of his city. 19  And after this, Abraham buried Sarah his wife in the cave of the field of Machpelah before Mamre: the same is Hebron in the land of Canaan. 20  And the field, and the cave that is therein, were made sure unto Abraham for a possession of a buryingplace by the sons of Heth.

24

1  And Abraham was old, and [†]well stricken in age: and the LORD had blessed Abraham in all things. 2  And Abraham said unto his eldest servant of his house, that ruled over all that he had, [*]Put, I pray thee, thy hand under my thigh: 3  And I will make thee swear by the LORD, the God of heaven, and the God of the earth, that thou shalt not take a wife unto my son of the daughters of the Canaanites, among whom I dwell: 4  But thou shalt go unto my country, and to my kindred, and take a wife unto my son Isaac. 5  And the servant said unto him, Peradventure the woman will not be willing to follow me unto this land: must I needs bring thy son again unto the land from whence thou camest? 6  And Abraham said unto him, Beware thou that thou bring not my son thither again.

7 ¶ The LORD God of heaven, which took me from my father’s house, and from the land of my kindred, and which spake unto me, and that sware unto me, saying, [*]Unto thy seed will I give this land; he shall send his angel before thee, and thou shalt take a wife unto my son from thence. 8  And if the woman will not be willing to follow thee, then thou shalt be clear from this my oath: only bring not my son thither again. 9  And the servant put his hand under the thigh of Abraham his master, and sware to him concerning that matter.

10 ¶ And the servant took ten camels of the camels of his master, and departed; [∥]for all the goods of his master were in his hand: and he arose, and went to Mesopotamia, unto the city of Nahor. 11  And he made his camels to kneel down without the city by a well of water at the time of the evening, even the time [†]that women go out to draw water. 12  And he said, O LORD God of my master Abraham, I pray thee, send me good speed this day, and shew kindness unto my master Abraham. 13  Behold, [*]I stand here by the well of water; and the daughters of the men of the city come out to draw water: 14  And let it come to pass, that the damsel to whom I shall say, Let down thy pitcher, I pray thee, that I may drink; and she shall say, Drink, and I will give thy camels drink also: let the same be she that thou hast appointed for thy servant Isaac; and thereby shall I know that thou hast shewed kindness unto my master.

15 ¶ And it came to pass, before he had done speaking, that, behold, Rebekah came out, who was born to Bethuel, son of Milcah, the wife of Nahor, Abraham’s brother, with her pitcher upon her shoulder. 16  And the damsel was [†]very fair to look upon, a virgin, neither had any man known her: and she went down to the well, and filled her pitcher, and came up. 17  And the servant ran to meet her, and said, Let me, I pray thee, drink a little water of thy pitcher. 18  And she said, Drink, my lord: and she hasted, and let down her pitcher upon her hand, and gave him drink. 19  And when she had done giving him drink, she said, I will draw water for thy camels also, until they have done drinking. 20  And she hasted, and emptied her pitcher into the trough, and ran again unto the well to draw water, and drew for all his camels. 21  And the man wondering at her held his peace, to wit whether the LORD had made his journey prosperous or not. 22  And it came to pass, as the camels had done drinking, that the man took a golden [∥]earring of half a shekel weight, and two bracelets for her hands of ten shekels weight of gold; 23  And said, Whose daughter art thou? tell me, I pray thee: is there room in thy father’s house for us to lodge in? 24  And she said unto him, I am the daughter of Bethuel the son of Milcah, which she bare unto Nahor. 25  She said moreover unto him, We have both straw and provender enough, and room to lodge in. 26  And the man bowed down his head, and worshipped the LORD. 27  And he said, Blessed be the LORD God of my master Abraham, who hath not left destitute my master of his mercy and his truth: I being in the way, the LORD led me to the house of my master’s brethren. 28  And the damsel ran, and told them of her mother’s house these things.

29 ¶ And Rebekah had a brother, and his name was Laban: and Laban ran out unto the man, unto the well. 30  And it came to pass, when he saw the earring and bracelets upon his sister’s hands, and when he heard the words of Rebekah his sister, saying, Thus spake the man unto me; that he came unto the man; and, behold, he stood by the camels at the well. 31  And he said, Come in, thou blessed of the LORD; wherefore standest thou without? for I have prepared the house, and room for the camels.

32 ¶ And the man came into the house: and he ungirded his camels, and gave straw and provender for the camels, and water to wash his feet, and the men’s feet that were with him. 33  And there was set meat before him to eat: but he said, I will not eat, until I have told mine errand. And he said, Speak on. 34  And he said, I am Abraham’s servant. 35  And the LORD hath blessed my master greatly; and he is become great: and he hath given him flocks, and herds, and silver, and gold, and menservants, and maidservants, and camels, and asses. 36  And Sarah my master’s wife bare a son to my master when she was old: and unto him hath he given all that he hath. 37  And my master made me swear, saying, Thou shalt not take a wife to my son of the daughters of the Canaanites, in whose land I dwell: 38  But thou shalt go unto my father’s house, and to my kindred, and take a wife unto my son. 39  And I said unto my master, Peradventure the woman will not follow me. 40  And he said unto me, The LORD, before whom I walk, will send his angel with thee, and prosper thy way; and thou shalt take a wife for my son of my kindred, and of my father’s house: 41  Then shalt thou be clear from this my oath, when thou comest to my kindred; and if they give not thee one, thou shalt be clear from my oath. 42  And I came this day unto the well, and said, O LORD God of my master Abraham, if now thou do prosper my way which I go: 43 [*] Behold, I stand by the well of water; and it shall come to pass, that when the virgin cometh forth to draw water, and I say to her, Give me, I pray thee, a little water of thy pitcher to drink; 44  And she say to me, Both drink thou, and I will also draw for thy camels: let the same be the woman whom the LORD hath appointed out for my master’s son. 45  And before I had done speaking in mine heart, behold, Rebekah came forth with her pitcher on her shoulder; and she went down unto the well, and drew water: and I said unto her, Let me drink, I pray thee. 46  And she made haste, and let down her pitcher from her shoulder, and said, Drink, and I will give thy camels drink also: so I drank, and she made the camels drink also. 47  And I asked her, and said, Whose daughter art thou? And she said, The daughter of Bethuel, Nahor’s son, whom Milcah bare unto him: and I put the earring upon her face, and the bracelets upon her hands. 48  And I bowed down my head, and worshipped the LORD, and blessed the LORD God of my master Abraham, which had led me in the right way to take my master’s brother’s daughter unto his son. 49  And now if ye will deal kindly and truly with my master, tell me: and if not, tell me; that I may turn to the right hand, or to the left. 50  Then Laban and Bethuel answered and said, The thing proceedeth from the LORD: we cannot speak unto thee bad or good. 51  Behold, Rebekah is before thee, take her, and go, and let her be thy master’s son’s wife, as the LORD hath spoken. 52  And it came to pass, that, when Abraham’s servant heard their words, he worshipped the LORD, bowing himself to the earth. 53  And the servant brought forth [†]jewels of silver, and jewels of gold, and raiment, and gave them to Rebekah: he gave also to her brother and to her mother precious things.

54  And they did eat and drink, he and the men that were with him, and tarried all night; and they rose up in the morning, and he said, [*]Send me away unto my master. 55  And her brother and her mother said, Let the damsel abide with us [∥]a few days, at the least ten; after that she shall go. 56  And he said unto them, Hinder me not, seeing the LORD hath prospered my way; send me away that I may go to my master. 57  And they said, We will call the damsel, and enquire at her mouth. 58  And they called Rebekah, and said unto her, Wilt thou go with this man? And she said, I will go. 59  And they sent away Rebekah their sister, and her nurse, and Abraham’s servant, and his men. 60  And they blessed Rebekah, and said unto her, Thou art our sister, be thou the mother of thousands of millions, and let thy seed possess the gate of those which hate them.

61 ¶ And Rebekah arose, and her damsels, and they rode upon the camels, and followed the man: and the servant took Rebekah, and went his way.

62  And Isaac came from the way of the [*]well Lahai-roi; for he dwelt in the south country. 63  And Isaac went out [∥]to meditate in the field at the eventide: and he lifted up his eyes, and saw, and, behold, the camels were coming. 64  And Rebekah lifted up her eyes, and when she saw Isaac, she lighted off the camel. 65 For she had said unto the servant, What man is this that walketh in the field to meet us? And the servant had said, It is my master: therefore she took a vail, and covered herself. 66  And the servant told Isaac all things that he had done. 67  And Isaac brought her into his mother Sarah’s tent, and took Rebekah, and she became his wife; and he loved her: and Isaac was comforted after his mother’s death.

25

1  Then again Abraham took a wife, and her name was Keturah. 2  And [*]she bare him Zimran, and Jokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah. 3  And Jokshan begat Sheba, and Dedan. And the sons of Dedan were Asshurim, and Letushim, and Leummim. 4  And the sons of Midian; Ephah, and Epher, and Hanoch, and Abidah, and Eldaah. All these were the children of Keturah.

5 ¶ And Abraham gave all that he had unto Isaac. 6  But unto the sons of the concubines, which Abraham had, Abraham gave gifts, and sent them away from Isaac his son, while he yet lived, eastward, unto the east country. 7 And these are the days of the years of Abraham’s life which he lived, an hundred threescore and fifteen years. 8  Then Abraham gave up the ghost, and died in a good old age, an old man, and full of years; and was gathered to his people. 9  And his sons Isaac and Ishmael buried him in the cave of Machpelah, in the field of Ephron the son of Zohar the Hittite, which is before Mamre; 10 [*] The field which Abraham purchased of the sons of Heth: there was Abraham buried, and Sarah his wife.

11 ¶ And it came to pass after the death of Abraham, that God blessed his son Isaac; and Isaac dwelt by the [*]well Lahai-roi.

12 ¶ Now these are the generations of Ishmael, Abraham’s son, whom Hagar the Egyptian, Sarah’s handmaid, bare unto Abraham: 13 And [*]these are the names of the sons of Ishmael, by their names, according to their generations: the firstborn of Ishmael, Nebajoth; and Kedar, and Adbeel, and Mibsam, 14  And Mishma, and Dumah, and Massa, 15  Hadar, and Tema, Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah: 16 These are the sons of Ishmael, and these are their names, by their towns, and by their castles; twelve princes according to their nations. 17 And these are the years of the life of Ishmael, an hundred and thirty and seven years: and he gave up the ghost and died; and was gathered unto his people. 18  And they dwelt from Havilah unto Shur, that is before Egypt, as thou goest toward Assyria: and he [†]died in the presence of all his brethren.

19 ¶ And these are the generations of Isaac, Abraham’s son: Abraham begat Isaac: 20  And Isaac was forty years old when he took Rebekah to wife, the daughter of Bethuel the Syrian of Padan-aram, the sister to Laban the Syrian. 21  And Isaac intreated the LORD for his wife, because she was barren: and the LORD was intreated of him, and Rebekah his wife conceived. 22  And the children struggled together within her; and she said, If it be so, why am I thus? And she went to enquire of the LORD. 23  And the LORD said unto her, Two nations are in thy womb, and two manner of people shall be separated from thy bowels; and the one people shall be stronger than the other people; and [*]the elder shall serve the younger.

24 ¶ And when her days to be delivered were fulfilled, behold, there were twins in her womb. 25  And the first came out red, all over like an hairy garment; and they called his name Esau. 26  And after that came his brother out, and [*]his hand took hold on Esau’s heel; and his name was called Jacob: and Isaac was threescore years old when she bare them. 27  And the boys grew: and Esau was a cunning hunter, a man of the field; and Jacob was a plain man, dwelling in tents. 28  And Isaac loved Esau, because [†]he did eat of his venison: but Rebekah loved Jacob.

29 ¶ And Jacob sod pottage: and Esau came from the field, and he was faint: 30  And Esau said to Jacob, Feed me, I pray thee, [†]with that same red pottage; for I am faint: therefore was his name called Edom. 31  And Jacob said, Sell me this day thy birthright. 32  And Esau said, Behold, I am [†]at the point to die: and what profit shall this birthright do to me? 33  And Jacob said, Swear to me this day; and he sware unto him: and [*]he sold his birthright unto Jacob. 34  Then Jacob gave Esau bread and pottage of lentiles; and he did eat and drink, and rose up, and went his way: thus Esau despised his birthright.

26

1  And there was a famine in the land, beside the first famine that was in the days of Abraham. And Isaac went unto Abimelech king of the Philistines unto Gerar. 2  And the LORD appeared unto him, and said, Go not down into Egypt; dwell in the land which I shall tell thee of: 3  Sojourn in this land, and I will be with thee, and will bless thee; for unto thee, and unto thy seed, [*]I will give all these countries, and I will perform the oath which I sware unto Abraham thy father; 4  And I will make thy seed to multiply as the stars of heaven, and will give unto thy seed all these countries; and in thy seed shall all the nations of the earth be [*]blessed; 5  Because that Abraham obeyed my voice, and kept my charge, my commandments, my statutes, and my laws.

6 ¶ And Isaac dwelt in Gerar: 7  And the men of the place asked him of his wife; and he said, She is my sister: for he feared to say, She is my wife; lest, said he, the men of the place should kill me for Rebekah; because she was fair to look upon. 8  And it came to pass, when he had been there a long time, that Abimelech king of the Philistines looked out at a window, and saw, and, behold, Isaac was sporting with Rebekah his wife. 9  And Abimelech called Isaac, and said, Behold, of a surety she is thy wife: and how saidst thou, She is my sister? And Isaac said unto him, Because I said, Lest I die for her. 10  And Abimelech said, What is this thou hast done unto us? one of the people might lightly have lien with thy wife, and thou shouldest have brought guiltiness upon us. 11  And Abimelech charged all his people, saying, He that toucheth this man or his wife shall surely be put to death.

12  Then Isaac sowed in that land, and [†]received in the same year an hundredfold: and the LORD blessed him. 13  And the man waxed great, and [†]went forward, and grew until he became very great: 14  For he had possession of flocks, and possession of herds, and great store of [∥]servants: and the Philistines envied him. 15  For all the wells which his father’s servants had digged in the days of Abraham his father, the Philistines had stopped them, and filled them with earth. 16  And Abimelech said unto Isaac, Go from us; for thou art much mightier than we.

17 ¶ And Isaac departed thence, and pitched his tent in the valley of Gerar, and dwelt there. 18  And Isaac digged again the wells of water, which they had digged in the days of Abraham his father; for the Philistines had stopped them after the death of Abraham: and he called their names after the names by which his father had called them. 19  And Isaac’s servants digged in the valley, and found there a well of [†]springing water. 20  And the herdmen of Gerar did strive with Isaac’s herdmen, saying, The water is ours: and he called the name of the well [∥]Esek; because they strove with him. 21  And they digged another well, and strove for that also: and he called the name of it [∥]Sitnah. 22  And he removed from thence, and digged another well; and for that they strove not: and he called the name of it [∥]Rehoboth; and he said, For now the LORD hath made room for us, and we shall be fruitful in the land. 23  And he went up from thence to Beer-sheba. 24  And the LORD appeared unto him the same night, and said, I am the God of Abraham thy father: fear not, for I am with thee, and will bless thee, and multiply thy seed for my servant Abraham’s sake. 25  And he builded an altar there, and called upon the name of the LORD, and pitched his tent there: and there Isaac’s servants digged a well.

26 ¶ Then Abimelech went to him from Gerar, and Ahuzzath one of his friends, and Phichol the chief captain of his army. 27  And Isaac said unto them, Wherefore come ye to me, seeing ye hate me, and have sent me away from you? 28  And they said, [†]We saw certainly that the LORD was with thee: and we said, Let there be now an oath betwixt us, even betwixt us and thee, and let us make a covenant with thee; 29 [†] That thou wilt do us no hurt, as we have not touched thee, and as we have done unto thee nothing but good, and have sent thee away in peace: thou art now the blessed of the LORD. 30  And he made them a feast, and they did eat and drink. 31  And they rose up betimes in the morning, and sware one to another: and Isaac sent them away, and they departed from him in peace. 32  And it came to pass the same day, that Isaac’s servants came, and told him concerning the well which they had digged, and said unto him, We have found water. 33  And he called it [∥]Shebah: therefore the name of the city is [∥]Beer-sheba unto this day.

34 ¶ And Esau was forty years old when he took to wife Judith the daughter of Beeri the Hittite, and Bashemath the daughter of Elon the Hittite: 35  Which [*]were [†]a grief of mind unto Isaac and to Rebekah.

27

1  And it came to pass, that when Isaac was old, and his eyes were dim, so that he could not see, he called Esau his eldest son, and said unto him, My son: and he said unto him, Behold, here am I. 2  And he said, Behold now, I am old, I know not the day of my death: 3  Now therefore take, I pray thee, thy weapons, thy quiver and thy bow, and go out to the field, and [†]take me some venison; 4  And make me savoury meat, such as I love, and bring it to me, that I may eat; that my soul may bless thee before I die. 5  And Rebekah heard when Isaac spake to Esau his son. And Esau went to the field to hunt for venison, and to bring it.

6 ¶ And Rebekah spake unto Jacob her son, saying, Behold, I heard thy father speak unto Esau thy brother, saying, 7  Bring me venison, and make me savoury meat, that I may eat, and bless thee before the LORD before my death. 8  Now therefore, my son, obey my voice according to that which I command thee. 9  Go now to the flock, and fetch me from thence two good kids of the goats; and I will make them savoury meat for thy father, such as he loveth: 10  And thou shalt bring it to thy father, that he may eat, and that he may bless thee before his death. 11  And Jacob said to Rebekah his mother, Behold, Esau my brother is a hairy man, and I am a smooth man: 12  My father peradventure will feel me, and I shall seem to him as a deceiver; and I shall bring a curse upon me, and not a blessing. 13  And his mother said unto him, Upon me be thy curse, my son: only obey my voice, and go fetch me them. 14  And he went, and fetched, and brought them to his mother: and his mother made savoury meat, such as his father loved. 15  And Rebekah took [†]goodly raiment of her eldest son Esau, which were with her in the house, and put them upon Jacob her younger son: 16  And she put the skins of the kids of the goats upon his hands, and upon the smooth of his neck: 17  And she gave the savoury meat and the bread, which she had prepared, into the hand of her son Jacob.

18 ¶ And he came unto his father, and said, My father: and he said, Here am I; who art thou, my son? 19  And Jacob said unto his father, I am Esau thy firstborn; I have done according as thou badest me: arise, I pray thee, sit and eat of my venison, that thy soul may bless me. 20  And Isaac said unto his son, How is it that thou hast found it so quickly, my son? And he said, Because the LORD thy God brought it [†]to me. 21  And Isaac said unto Jacob, Come near, I pray thee, that I may feel thee, my son, whether thou be my very son Esau or not. 22  And Jacob went near unto Isaac his father; and he felt him, and said, The voice is Jacob’s voice, but the hands are the hands of Esau. 23  And he discerned him not, because his hands were hairy, as his brother Esau’s hands: so he blessed him. 24  And he said, Art thou my very son Esau? And he said, I am. 25  And he said, Bring it near to me, and I will eat of my son’s venison, that my soul may bless thee. And he brought it near to him, and he did eat: and he brought him wine, and he drank. 26  And his father Isaac said unto him, Come near now, and kiss me, my son. 27  And he came near, and kissed him: and he smelled the smell of his raiment, and blessed him, and said, See, the smell of my son is as the smell of a field which the LORD hath blessed: 28  Therefore [*]God give thee of the dew of heaven, and the fatness of the earth, and plenty of corn and wine: 29  Let people serve thee, and nations bow down to thee: be lord over thy brethren, and let thy mother’s sons bow down to thee: cursed be every one that curseth thee, and blessed be he that blesseth thee.

30 ¶ And it came to pass, as soon as Isaac had made an end of blessing Jacob, and Jacob was yet scarce gone out from the presence of Isaac his father, that Esau his brother came in from his hunting. 31  And he also had made savoury meat, and brought it unto his father, and said unto his father, Let my father arise, and eat of his son’s venison, that thy soul may bless me. 32  And Isaac his father said unto him, Who art thou? And he said, I am thy son, thy firstborn Esau. 33  And Isaac [†]trembled very exceedingly, and said, Who? where is he that hath [†]taken venison, and brought it me, and I have eaten of all before thou camest, and have blessed him? yea, and he shall be blessed. 34  And when Esau heard the words of his father, he cried with a great and exceeding bitter cry, and said unto his father, Bless me, even me also, O my father. 35  And he said, Thy brother came with subtilty, and hath taken away thy blessing. 36  And he said, Is not he rightly named [∥]Jacob? for he hath supplanted me these two times: he took away my birthright; and, behold, now he hath taken away my blessing. And he said, Hast thou not reserved a blessing for me? 37  And Isaac answered and said unto Esau, Behold, I have made him thy lord, and all his brethren have I given to him for servants; and with corn and wine have I [∥]sustained him: and what shall I do now unto thee, my son? 38  And Esau said unto his father, Hast thou but one blessing, my father? bless me, even me also, O my father. And Esau lifted up his voice, [*]and wept. 39  And Isaac his father answered and said unto him, Behold, [*]thy dwelling shall be [∥]the fatness of the earth, and of the dew of heaven from above; 40  And by thy sword shalt thou live, and shalt serve thy brother; and it shall come to pass when thou shalt have the dominion, that thou shalt break his yoke from off thy neck.

41 ¶ And Esau hated Jacob because of the blessing wherewith his father blessed him: and Esau said in his heart, The days of mourning for my father are at hand; [*]then will I slay my brother Jacob. 42  And these words of Esau her elder son were told to Rebekah: and she sent and called Jacob her younger son, and said unto him, Behold, thy brother Esau, as touching thee, doth comfort himself, purposing to kill thee. 43  Now therefore, my son, obey my voice; and arise, flee thou to Laban my brother to Haran; 44  And tarry with him a few days, until thy brother’s fury turn away; 45  Until thy brother’s anger turn away from thee, and he forget that which thou hast done to him: then I will send, and fetch thee from thence: why should I be deprived also of you both in one day? 46  And Rebekah said to Isaac, [*]I am weary of my life because of the daughters of Heth: if Jacob take a wife of the daughters of Heth, such as these which are of the daughters of the land, what good shall my life do me?

28

1  And Isaac called Jacob, and blessed him, and charged him, and said unto him, Thou shalt not take a wife of the daughters of Canaan. 2 [*] Arise, go to Padan-aram, to the house of Bethuel thy mother’s father; and take thee a wife from thence of the daughters of Laban thy mother’s brother. 3  And God Almighty bless thee, and make thee fruitful, and multiply thee, that thou mayest be [†]a multitude of people; 4  And give thee the blessing of Abraham, to thee, and to thy seed with thee; that thou mayest inherit the land [†]wherein thou art a stranger, which God gave unto Abraham. 5  And Isaac sent away Jacob: and he went to Padan-aram unto Laban, son of Bethuel the Syrian, the brother of Rebekah, Jacob’s and Esau’s mother.

6 ¶ When Esau saw that Isaac had blessed Jacob, and sent him away to Padan-aram, to take him a wife from thence; and that as he blessed him he gave him a charge, saying, Thou shalt not take a wife of the daughters of Canaan; 7  And that Jacob obeyed his father and his mother, and was gone to Padan-aram; 8  And Esau seeing that the daughters of Canaan [†]pleased not Isaac his father; 9  Then went Esau unto Ishmael, and took unto the wives which he had Mahalath the daughter of Ishmael Abraham’s son, the sister of Nebajoth, to be his wife.

10 ¶ And Jacob went out from Beer-sheba, and went toward [*]Haran. 11  And he lighted upon a certain place, and tarried there all night, because the sun was set; and he took of the stones of that place, and put them for his pillows, and lay down in that place to sleep. 12  And he dreamed, and behold a ladder set up on the earth, and the top of it reached to heaven: and behold the angels of God ascending and descending on it. 13 [*] And, behold, the LORD stood above it, and said, I am the LORD God of Abraham thy father, and the God of Isaac: the land whereon thou liest, to thee will I give it, and to thy seed; 14  And thy seed shall be as the dust of the earth, and thou shalt [†]spread abroad [*]to the west, and to the east, and to the north, and to the south: and in thee and [*]in thy seed shall all the families of the earth be blessed. 15 And, behold, I am with thee, and will keep thee in all places whither thou goest, and will bring thee again into this land; for I will not leave thee, until I have done that which I have spoken to thee of.

16 ¶ And Jacob awaked out of his sleep, and he said, Surely the LORD is in this place; and I knew it not. 17  And he was afraid, and said, How dreadful is this place! this is none other but the house of God, and this is the gate of heaven. 18  And Jacob rose up early in the morning, and took the stone that he had put for his pillows, and set it up for a pillar, and poured oil upon the top of it. 19  And he called the name of that place [∥]Beth-el: but the name of that city was called Luz at the first. 20  And Jacob vowed a vow, saying, If God will be with me, and will keep me in this way that I go, and will give me bread to eat, and raiment to put on, 21  So that I come again to my father’s house in peace; then shall the LORD be my God: 22  And this stone, which I have set for a pillar, shall be God’s house: and of all that thou shalt give me I will surely give the tenth unto thee.

29

1  Then Jacob [†]went on his journey, and came into the land of the [†]people of the east. 2  And he looked, and behold a well in the field, and, lo, there were three flocks of sheep lying by it; for out of that well they watered the flocks: and a great stone was upon the well’s mouth. 3  And thither were all the flocks gathered: and they rolled the stone from the well’s mouth, and watered the sheep, and put the stone again upon the well’s mouth in his place. 4  And Jacob said unto them, My brethren, whence be ye? And they said, Of Haran are we. 5  And he said unto them, Know ye Laban the son of Nahor? And they said, We know him. 6  And he said unto them, [†]Is he well? And they said, He is well: and, behold, Rachel his daughter cometh with the sheep. 7  And he said, Lo, [†]it is yet high day, neither is it time that the cattle should be gathered together: water ye the sheep, and go and feed them. 8  And they said, We cannot, until all the flocks be gathered together, and till they roll the stone from the well’s mouth; then we water the sheep.

9 ¶ And while he yet spake with them, Rachel came with her father’s sheep: for she kept them. 10  And it came to pass, when Jacob saw Rachel the daughter of Laban his mother’s brother, and the sheep of Laban his mother’s brother, that Jacob went near, and rolled the stone from the well’s mouth, and watered the flock of Laban his mother’s brother. 11  And Jacob kissed Rachel, and lifted up his voice, and wept. 12  And Jacob told Rachel that he was her father’s brother, and that he was Rebekah’s son: and she ran and told her father. 13  And it came to pass, when Laban heard the [†]tidings of Jacob his sister’s son, that he ran to meet him, and embraced him, and kissed him, and brought him to his house. And he told Laban all these things. 14  And Laban said to him, Surely thou art my bone and my flesh. And he abode with him [†]the space of a month.

15 ¶ And Laban said unto Jacob, Because thou art my brother, shouldest thou therefore serve me for nought? tell me, what shall thy wages be? 16  And Laban had two daughters: the name of the elder was Leah, and the name of the younger was Rachel. 17  Leah was tender eyed; but Rachel was beautiful and well favoured. 18  And Jacob loved Rachel; and said, I will serve thee seven years for Rachel thy younger daughter. 19  And Laban said, It is better that I give her to thee, than that I should give her to another man: abide with me. 20  And Jacob served seven years for Rachel; and they seemed unto him but a few days, for the love he had to her.

21 ¶ And Jacob said unto Laban, Give me my wife, for my days are fulfilled, that I may go in unto her. 22  And Laban gathered together all the men of the place, and made a feast. 23  And it came to pass in the evening, that he took Leah his daughter, and brought her to him; and he went in unto her. 24  And Laban gave unto his daughter Leah Zilpah his maid for an handmaid. 25  And it came to pass, that in the morning, behold, it was Leah: and he said to Laban, What is this thou hast done unto me? did not I serve with thee for Rachel? wherefore then hast thou beguiled me? 26  And Laban said, It must not be so done in our [†]country, to give the younger before the firstborn. 27  Fulfil her week, and we will give thee this also for the service which thou shalt serve with me yet seven other years. 28  And Jacob did so, and fulfilled her week: and he gave him Rachel his daughter to wife also. 29  And Laban gave to Rachel his daughter Bilhah his handmaid to be her maid. 30  And he went in also unto Rachel, and he loved also Rachel more than Leah, and served with him yet seven other years.

31 ¶ And when the LORD saw that Leah was hated, he opened her womb: but Rachel was barren. 32  And Leah conceived, and bare a son, and she called his name [∥]Reuben: for she said, Surely the LORD hath looked upon my affliction; now therefore my husband will love me. 33  And she conceived again, and bare a son; and said, Because the LORD hath heard that I was hated, he hath therefore given me this son also: and she called his name [∥]Simeon. 34  And she conceived again, and bare a son; and said, Now this time will my husband be joined unto me, because I have born him three sons: therefore was his name called [∥]Levi. 35  And she conceived again, and bare a son: and she said, Now will I praise the LORD: therefore she called his name [*][∥]Judah; and [†]left bearing.

30

1  And when Rachel saw that she bare Jacob no children, Rachel envied her sister; and said unto Jacob, Give me children, or else I die. 2  And Jacob’s anger was kindled against Rachel: and he said, Am I in God’s stead, who hath withheld from thee the fruit of the womb? 3  And she said, Behold my maid Bilhah, go in unto her; and she shall bear upon my knees, that I may also [†]have children by her. 4  And she gave him Bilhah her handmaid to wife: and Jacob went in unto her. 5  And Bilhah conceived, and bare Jacob a son. 6  And Rachel said, God hath judged me, and hath also heard my voice, and hath given me a son: therefore called she his name [∥]Dan. 7  And Bilhah Rachel’s maid conceived again, and bare Jacob a second son. 8  And Rachel said, With [†]great wrestlings have I wrestled with my sister, and I have prevailed: and she called his name [∥][*]Naphtali. 9  When Leah saw that she had left bearing, she took Zilpah her maid, and gave her Jacob to wife. 10  And Zilpah Leah’s maid bare Jacob a son. 11  And Leah said, A troop cometh: and she called his name [∥]Gad. 12  And Zilpah Leah’s maid bare Jacob a second son. 13  And Leah said, [†]Happy am I, for the daughters will call me blessed: and she called his name [∥]Asher.

14 ¶ And Reuben went in the days of wheat harvest, and found mandrakes in the field, and brought them unto his mother Leah. Then Rachel said to Leah, Give me, I pray thee, of thy son’s mandrakes. 15  And she said unto her, Is it a small matter that thou hast taken my husband? and wouldest thou take away my son’s mandrakes also? And Rachel said, Therefore he shall lie with thee to night for thy son’s mandrakes. 16  And Jacob came out of the field in the evening, and Leah went out to meet him, and said, Thou must come in unto me; for surely I have hired thee with my son’s mandrakes. And he lay with her that night. 17  And God hearkened unto Leah, and she conceived, and bare Jacob the fifth son. 18  And Leah said, God hath given me my hire, because I have given my maiden to my husband: and she called his name [∥]Issachar. 19  And Leah conceived again, and bare Jacob the sixth son. 20  And Leah said, God hath endued me with a good dowry; now will my husband dwell with me, because I have born him six sons: and she called his name [∥][*]Zebulun. 21  And afterwards she bare a daughter, and called her name [∥]Dinah.

22 ¶ And God remembered Rachel, and God hearkened to her, and opened her womb. 23  And she conceived, and bare a son; and said, God hath taken away my reproach: 24  And she called his name [∥]Joseph; and said, The LORD shall add to me another son.

25 ¶ And it came to pass, when Rachel had born Joseph, that Jacob said unto Laban, Send me away, that I may go unto mine own place, and to my country. 26  Give me my wives and my children, for whom I have served thee, and let me go: for thou knowest my service which I have done thee. 27  And Laban said unto him, I pray thee, if I have found favour in thine eyes, tarry: for I have learned by experience that the LORD hath blessed me for thy sake. 28  And he said, Appoint me thy wages, and I will give it. 29  And he said unto him, Thou knowest how I have served thee, and how thy cattle was with me. 30 For it was little which thou hadst before I came, and it is now [†]increased unto a multitude; and the LORD hath blessed thee [†]since my coming: and now when shall I provide for mine own house also? 31  And he said, What shall I give thee? And Jacob said, Thou shalt not give me any thing: if thou wilt do this thing for me, I will again feed and keep thy flock: 32  I will pass through all thy flock to day, removing from thence all the speckled and spotted cattle, and all the brown cattle among the sheep, and the spotted and speckled among the goats: and of such shall be my hire. 33  So shall my righteousness answer for me [†]in time to come, when it shall come for my hire before thy face: every one that is not speckled and spotted among the goats, and brown among the sheep, that shall be counted stolen with me. 34  And Laban said, Behold, I would it might be according to thy word. 35  And he removed that day the he goats that were ringstraked and spotted, and all the she goats that were speckled and spotted, and every one that had some white in it, and all the brown among the sheep, and gave them into the hand of his sons. 36  And he set three days’ journey betwixt himself and Jacob: and Jacob fed the rest of Laban’s flocks.

37 ¶ And Jacob took him rods of green poplar, and of the hazel and chesnut tree; and pilled white strakes in them, and made the white appear which was in the rods. 38  And he set the rods which he had pilled before the flocks in the gutters in the watering troughs when the flocks came to drink, that they should conceive when they came to drink. 39  And the flocks conceived before the rods, and brought forth cattle ringstraked, speckled, and spotted. 40  And Jacob did separate the lambs, and set the faces of the flocks toward the ringstraked, and all the brown in the flock of Laban; and he put his own flocks by themselves, and put them not unto Laban’s cattle. 41  And it came to pass, whensoever the stronger cattle did conceive, that Jacob laid the rods before the eyes of the cattle in the gutters, that they might conceive among the rods. 42  But when the cattle were feeble, he put them not in: so the feebler were Laban’s, and the stronger Jacob’s. 43  And the man increased exceedingly, and had much cattle, and maidservants, and menservants, and camels, and asses.

31

1  And he heard the words of Laban’s sons, saying, Jacob hath taken away all that was our father’s; and of that which [‡]was our father’s hath he gotten all this glory. 2  And Jacob beheld the countenance of Laban, and, behold, it was not toward him [†]as before. 3  And the LORD said unto Jacob, Return unto the land of thy fathers, and to thy kindred; and I will be with thee. 4  And Jacob sent and called Rachel and Leah to the field unto his flock, 5  And said unto them, I see your father’s countenance, that it is not toward me as before; but the God of my father hath been with me. 6  And ye know that with all my power I have served your father. 7  And your father hath deceived me, and changed my wages ten times; but God suffered him not to hurt me. 8  If he said thus, The speckled shall be thy wages; then all the cattle bare speckled: and if he said thus, The ringstraked shall be thy hire; then bare all the cattle ringstraked. 9  Thus God hath taken away the cattle of your father, and given them to me. 10  And it came to pass at the time that the cattle conceived, that I lifted up mine eyes, and saw in a dream, and, behold, the [∥]rams which leaped upon the cattle were ringstraked, speckled, and grisled. 11  And the angel of God spake unto me in a dream, saying, Jacob: And I said, Here am I. 12  And he said, Lift up now thine eyes, and see, all the rams which leap upon the cattle are ringstraked, speckled, and grisled: for I have seen all that Laban doeth unto thee. 13 I am the God of Beth-el, [*]where thou anointedst the pillar, and where thou vowedst a vow unto me: now arise, get thee out from this land, and return unto the land of thy kindred. 14  And Rachel and Leah answered and said unto him, Is there yet any portion or inheritance for us in our father’s house? 15  Are we not counted of him strangers? for he hath sold us, and hath quite devoured also our money. 16  For all the riches which God hath taken from our father, that is ours, and our children’s: now then, whatsoever God hath said unto thee, do.

17 ¶ Then Jacob rose up, and set his sons and his wives upon camels; 18  And he carried away all his cattle, and all his goods which he had gotten, the cattle of his getting, which he had gotten in Padan-aram, for to go to Isaac his father in the land of Canaan. 19  And Laban went to shear his sheep: and Rachel had stolen the [†]images that were her father’s. 20  And Jacob stole away [†]unawares to Laban the Syrian, in that he told him not that he fled. 21  So he fled with all that he had; and he rose up, and passed over the river, and set his face toward the mount Gilead. 22  And it was told Laban on the third day that Jacob was fled. 23  And he took his brethren with him, and pursued after him seven days’ journey; and they overtook him in the mount Gilead. 24  And God came to Laban the Syrian in a dream by night, and said unto him, Take heed that thou speak not to Jacob [†]either good or bad.

25 ¶ Then Laban overtook Jacob. Now Jacob had pitched his tent in the mount: and Laban with his brethren pitched in the mount of Gilead. 26  And Laban said to Jacob, What hast thou done, that thou hast stolen away unawares to me, and carried away my daughters, as captives taken with the sword? 27  Wherefore didst thou flee away secretly, and [†]steal away from me; and didst not tell me, that I might have sent thee away with mirth, and with songs, with tabret, and with harp? 28  And hast not suffered me to kiss my sons and my daughters? thou hast now done foolishly in so doing. 29  It is in the power of my hand to do you hurt: but the God of your father spake unto me yesternight, saying, Take thou heed that thou speak not to Jacob either good or bad. 30 And now, though thou wouldest needs be gone, because thou sore longedst after thy father’s house, yet wherefore hast thou stolen my gods? 31  And Jacob answered and said to Laban, Because I was afraid: for I said, Peradventure thou wouldest take by force thy daughters from me. 32  With whomsoever thou findest thy gods, let him not live: before our brethren discern thou what is thine with me, and take it to thee. For Jacob knew not that Rachel had stolen them. 33  And Laban went into Jacob’s tent, and into Leah’s tent, and into the two maidservants’ tents; but he found them not. Then went he out of Leah’s tent, and entered into Rachel’s tent. 34  Now Rachel had taken the images, and put them in the camel’s furniture, and sat upon them. And Laban [†]searched all the tent, but found them not. 35  And she said to her father, Let it not displease my lord that I cannot rise up before thee; for the custom of women is upon me. And he searched, but found not the images.

36 ¶ And Jacob was wroth, and chode with Laban: and Jacob answered and said to Laban, What is my trespass? what is my sin, that thou hast so hotly pursued after me? 37  Whereas thou hast [†]searched all my stuff, what hast thou found of all thy household stuff? set it here before my brethren and thy brethren, that they may judge betwixt us both. 38  This twenty years have I been with thee; thy ewes and thy she goats have not cast their young, and the rams of thy flock have I not eaten. 39  That which was torn of beasts I brought not unto thee; I bare the loss of it; of [*]my hand didst thou require it, whether stolen by day, or stolen by night. 40  Thus I was; in the day the drought consumed me, and the frost by night; and my sleep departed from mine eyes. 41  Thus have I been twenty years in thy house; I served thee fourteen years for thy two daughters, and six years for thy cattle: and thou hast changed my wages ten times. 42  Except the God of my father, the God of Abraham, and the fear of Isaac, had been with me, surely thou hadst sent me away now empty. God hath seen mine affliction and the labour of my hands, and rebuked thee yesternight.

43 ¶ And Laban answered and said unto Jacob, These daughters are my daughters, and these children are my children, and these cattle are my cattle, and all that thou seest is mine: and what can I do this day unto these my daughters, or unto their children which they have born? 44  Now therefore come thou, let us make a covenant, I and thou; and let it be for a witness between me and thee. 45  And Jacob took a stone, and set it up for a pillar. 46  And Jacob said unto his brethren, Gather stones; and they took stones, and made an heap: and they did eat there upon the heap. 47  And Laban called it [∥]Jegar-sahadutha: but Jacob called it Galeed. 48  And Laban said, This heap is a witness between me and thee this day. Therefore was the name of it called Galeed; 49  And [∥]Mizpah; for he said, The LORD watch between me and thee, when we are absent one from another. 50  If thou shalt afflict my daughters, or if thou shalt take other wives beside my daughters, no man is with us; see, God is witness betwixt me and thee. 51  And Laban said to Jacob, Behold this heap, and behold this pillar, which I have cast betwixt me and thee; 52  This heap be witness, and this pillar be witness, that I will not pass over this heap to thee, and that thou shalt not pass over this heap and this pillar unto me, for harm. 53  The God of Abraham, and the God of Nahor, the God of their father, judge betwixt us. And Jacob sware by the fear of his father Isaac. 54  Then Jacob [∥]offered sacrifice upon the mount, and called his brethren to eat bread: and they did eat bread, and tarried all night in the mount. 55  And early in the morning Laban rose up, and kissed his sons and his daughters, and blessed them: and Laban departed, and returned unto his place.

32

1  And Jacob went on his way, and the angels of God met him. 2  And when Jacob saw them, he said, This is God’s host: and he called the name of that place [∥]Mahanaim.

3  And Jacob sent messengers before him to Esau his brother unto the land of Seir, the [†]country of Edom. 4  And he commanded them, saying, Thus shall ye speak unto my lord Esau; Thy servant Jacob saith thus, I have sojourned with Laban, and stayed there until now: 5  And I have oxen, and asses, flocks, and menservants, and womenservants: and I have sent to tell my lord, that I may find grace in thy sight.

6 ¶ And the messengers returned to Jacob, saying, We came to thy brother Esau, and also he cometh to meet thee, and four hundred men with him. 7  Then Jacob was greatly afraid and distressed: and he divided the people that was with him, and the flocks, and herds, and the camels, into two bands; 8  And said, If Esau come to the one company, and smite it, then the other company which is left shall escape.

9 ¶ And Jacob said, O God of my father Abraham, and God of my father Isaac, the LORD which saidst unto me, [*]Return unto thy country, and to thy kindred, and I will deal well with thee: 10 [†] I am not worthy of the least of all the mercies, and of all the truth, which thou hast shewed unto thy servant; for with my staff I passed over this Jordan; and now I am become two bands. 11  Deliver me, I pray thee, from the hand of my brother, from the hand of Esau: for I fear him, lest he will come and smite me, and the mother [†]with the children. 12  And thou saidst, I will surely do thee good, and make thy seed as the sand of the sea, which cannot be numbered for multitude.

13 ¶ And he lodged there that same night; and took of that which came to his hand a present for Esau his brother; 14  Two hundred she goats, and twenty he goats, two hundred ewes, and twenty rams, 15  Thirty milch camels with their colts, forty kine, and ten bulls, twenty she asses, and ten foals. 16  And he delivered them into the hand of his servants, every drove by themselves; and said unto his servants, Pass over before me, and put a space betwixt drove and drove. 17  And he commanded the foremost, saying, When Esau my brother meeteth thee, and asketh thee, saying, Whose art thou? and whither goest thou? and whose are these before thee? 18  Then thou shalt say, They be thy servant Jacob’s; it is a present sent unto my lord Esau: and, behold, also he is behind us. 19  And so commanded he the second, and the third, and all that followed the droves, saying, On this manner shall ye speak unto Esau, when ye find him. 20  And say ye moreover, Behold, thy servant Jacob is behind us. For he said, I will appease him with the present that goeth before me, and afterward I will see his face; peradventure he will accept [†]of me. 21  So went the present over before him: and himself lodged that night in the company. 22  And he rose up that night, and took his two wives, and his two womenservants, and his eleven sons, and passed over the ford Jabbok. 23  And he took them, and [†]sent them over the brook, and sent over that he had.

24 ¶ And Jacob was left alone; and there wrestled a man with him until the [†]breaking of the day. 25  And when he saw that he prevailed not against him, he touched the hollow of his thigh; and the hollow of Jacob’s thigh was out of joint, as he wrestled with him. 26  And he said, Let me go, for the day breaketh. And he said, [*]I will not let thee go, except thou bless me. 27  And he said unto him, What is thy name? And he said, Jacob. 28  And he said, [*]Thy name shall be called no more Jacob, but Israel: for as a prince hast thou power with God and with men, and hast prevailed. 29  And Jacob asked him, and said, Tell me, I pray thee, thy name. And he said, Wherefore is it that thou dost ask after my name? And he blessed him there. 30  And Jacob called the name of the place [∥]Peniel: for I have seen God face to face, and my life is preserved. 31  And as he passed over Penuel the sun rose upon him, and he halted upon his thigh. 32  Therefore the children of Israel eat not of the sinew which shrank, which is upon the hollow of the thigh, unto this day: because he touched the hollow of Jacob’s thigh in the sinew that shrank.

33

1  And Jacob lifted up his eyes, and looked, and, behold, Esau came, and with him four hundred men. And he divided the children unto Leah, and unto Rachel, and unto the two handmaids. 2  And he put the handmaids and their children foremost, and Leah and her children after, and Rachel and Joseph hindermost. 3  And he passed over before them, and bowed himself to the ground seven times, until he came near to his brother. 4  And Esau ran to meet him, and embraced him, and fell on his neck, and kissed him: and they wept.

5  And he lifted up his eyes, and saw the women and the children; and said, Who are those [†]with thee? And he said, The children which God hath graciously given thy servant. 6  Then the handmaidens came near, they and their children, and they bowed themselves. 7  And Leah also with her children came near, and bowed themselves: and after came Joseph near and Rachel, and they bowed themselves. 8  And he said, [†]What meanest thou by all this drove which I met? And he said, These are to find grace in the sight of my lord. 9  And Esau said, I have enough, my brother; [†]keep that thou hast unto thyself. 10  And Jacob said, Nay, I pray thee, if now I have found grace in thy sight, then receive my present at my hand: for therefore I have seen thy face, as though I had seen the face of God, and thou wast pleased with me. 11  Take, I pray thee, my blessing that is brought to thee; because God hath dealt graciously with me, and because I have enough. And he urged him, and he took it. 12  And he said, Let us take our journey, and let us go, and I will go before thee. 13  And he said unto him, My lord knoweth that the children are tender, and the flocks and herds with young are with me: and if men should overdrive them one day, all the flock will die. 14  Let my lord, I pray thee, pass over before his servant: and I will lead on softly, [†]according as the cattle that goeth before me and the children be able to endure, until I come unto my lord unto Seir. 15  And Esau said, Let me now [†]leave with thee some of the folk that are with me. And he said, [†]What needeth it? let me find grace in the sight of my lord.

16 ¶ So Esau returned that day on his way unto Seir. 17  And Jacob journeyed to Succoth, and built him an house, and made booths for his cattle: therefore the name of the place is called [∥]Succoth.

18 ¶ And Jacob came to Shalem, a city of [*]Shechem, which is in the land of Canaan, when he came from Padan-aram; and pitched his tent before the city. 19  And he bought a parcel of a field, where he had spread his tent, at the hand of the children of [*]Hamor, Shechem’s father, for an hundred [∥]pieces of money. 20  And he erected there an altar, and called it [∥]El-elohe-Israel.

34

1  And Dinah the daughter of Leah, which she bare unto Jacob, went out to see the daughters of the land. 2  And when Shechem the son of Hamor the Hivite, prince of the country, saw her, he took her, and lay with her, and [†]defiled her. 3  And his soul clave unto Dinah the daughter of Jacob, and he loved the damsel, and spake [†]kindly unto the damsel. 4  And Shechem spake unto his father Hamor, saying, Get me this damsel to wife. 5  And Jacob heard that he had defiled Dinah his daughter: now his sons were with his cattle in the field: and Jacob held his peace until they were come.

6 ¶ And Hamor the father of Shechem went out unto Jacob to commune with him. 7  And the sons of Jacob came out of the field when they heard it: and the men were grieved, and they were very wroth, because he had wrought folly in Israel in lying with Jacob’s daughter; which thing ought not to be done. 8  And Hamor communed with them, saying, The soul of my son Shechem longeth for your daughter: I pray you give her him to wife. 9  And make ye marriages with us, and give your daughters unto us, and take our daughters unto you. 10  And ye shall dwell with us: and the land shall be before you; dwell and trade ye therein, and get you possessions therein. 11  And Shechem said unto her father and unto her brethren, Let me find grace in your eyes, and what ye shall say unto me I will give. 12  Ask me never so much dowry and gift, and I will give according as ye shall say unto me: but give me the damsel to wife. 13  And the sons of Jacob answered Shechem and Hamor his father deceitfully, and said, because he had defiled Dinah their sister: 14  And they said unto them, We cannot do this thing, to give our sister to one that is uncircumcised; for that were a reproach unto us: 15  But in this will we consent unto you: If ye will be as we be, that every male of you be circumcised; 16  Then will we give our daughters unto you, and we will take your daughters to us, and we will dwell with you, and we will become one people. 17  But if ye will not hearken unto us, to be circumcised; then will we take our daughter, and we will be gone.

18  And their words pleased Hamor, and Shechem Hamor’s son. 19  And the young man deferred not to do the thing, because he had delight in Jacob’s daughter: and he was more honourable than all the house of his father.

20 ¶ And Hamor and Shechem his son came unto the gate of their city, and communed with the men of their city, saying, 21  These men are peaceable with us; therefore let them dwell in the land, and trade therein; for the land, behold, it is large enough for them; let us take their daughters to us for wives, and let us give them our daughters. 22  Only herein will the men consent unto us for to dwell with us, to be one people, if every male among us be circumcised, as they are circumcised. 23  Shall not their cattle and their substance and every beast of theirs be ours? only let us consent unto them, and they will dwell with us. 24  And unto Hamor and unto Shechem his son hearkened all that went out of the gate of his city; and every male was circumcised, all that went out of the gate of his city.

25 ¶ And it came to pass on the third day, when they were sore, that two of the sons of Jacob, Simeon and Levi, Dinah’s brethren, took each man his sword, and came upon the city boldly, and [*]slew all the males. 26  And they slew Hamor and Shechem his son with the [†]edge of the sword, and took Dinah out of Shechem’s house, and went out. 27  The sons of Jacob came upon the slain, and spoiled the city, because they had defiled their sister. 28  They took their sheep, and their oxen, and their asses, and that which was in the city, and that which was in the field, 29  And all their wealth, and all their little ones, and their wives took they captive, and spoiled even all that was in the house. 30  And Jacob said to Simeon and Levi, Ye have troubled me to make me to stink among the inhabitants of the land, among the Canaanites and the Perizzites: and I being few in number, they shall gather themselves together against me, and slay me; and I shall be destroyed, I and my house. 31  And they said, Should he deal with our sister as with an harlot?

35

1  And God said unto Jacob, Arise, go up to Beth-el, and dwell there: and make there an altar unto God, that appeared unto thee [*]when thou fleddest from the face of Esau thy brother. 2  Then Jacob said unto his household, and to all that were with him, Put away the strange gods that are among you, and be clean, and change your garments: 3  And let us arise, and go up to Beth-el; and I will make there an altar unto God, who answered me in the day of my distress, and was with me in the way which I went. 4  And they gave unto Jacob all the strange gods which were in their hand, and all their earrings which were in their ears; and Jacob hid them under the oak which was by Shechem. 5  And they journeyed: and the terror of God was upon the cities that were round about them, and they did not pursue after the sons of Jacob.

6 ¶ So Jacob came to Luz, which is in the land of Canaan, that is, Beth-el, he and all the people that were with him. 7  And he built there an altar, and [*]called the place [∥]El-beth-el: because there God appeared unto him, when he fled from the face of his brother. 8  But Deborah Rebekah’s nurse died, and she was buried beneath Beth-el under an oak: and the name of it was called [∥]Allon-bachuth.

9 ¶ And God appeared unto Jacob again, when he came out of Padan-aram, and blessed him. 10  And God said unto him, Thy name is Jacob: thy name shall not be called any more Jacob, [*]but Israel shall be thy name: and he called his name Israel. 11  And God said unto him, I am God Almighty: be fruitful and multiply; a nation and a company of nations shall be of thee, and kings shall come out of thy loins; 12  And the land which I gave Abraham and Isaac, to thee I will give it, and to thy seed after thee will I give the land. 13  And God went up from him in the place where he talked with him. 14  And Jacob set up a pillar in the place where he talked with him, even a pillar of stone: and he poured a drink offering thereon, and he poured oil thereon. 15  And Jacob called the name of the place where God spake with him, Beth-el.

16 ¶ And they journeyed from Beth-el; and there was but [†]a little way to come to Ephrath: and Rachel travailed, and she had hard labour. 17  And it came to pass, when she was in hard labour, that the midwife said unto her, Fear not; thou shalt have this son also. 18  And it came to pass, as her soul was in departing, (for she died) that she called his name [∥]Ben-oni: but his father called him [∥]Benjamin. 19  And Rachel died, and was buried in the way to Ephrath, which is Beth-lehem. 20  And Jacob set a pillar upon her grave: that is the pillar of Rachel’s grave unto this day.

21 ¶ And Israel journeyed, and spread his tent beyond the tower of Edar. 22  And it came to pass, when Israel dwelt in that land, that Reuben went and [*]lay with Bilhah his father’s concubine: and Israel heard it. Now the sons of Jacob were twelve: 23  The sons of Leah; Reuben, Jacob’s firstborn, and Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Zebulun: 24  The sons of Rachel; Joseph, and Benjamin: 25  And the sons of Bilhah, Rachel’s handmaid; Dan, and Naphtali: 26  And the sons of Zilpah, Leah’s handmaid; Gad, and Asher: these are the sons of Jacob, which were born to him in Padan-aram.

27 ¶ And Jacob came unto Isaac his father unto Mamre, unto the city of Arbah, which is Hebron, where Abraham and Isaac sojourned. 28  And the days of Isaac were an hundred and fourscore years. 29  And Isaac gave up the ghost, and died, and [*]was gathered unto his people, being old and full of days: and his sons Esau and Jacob buried him.

36

1 Now these are the generations of Esau, who is Edom. 2  Esau took his wives of the daughters of Canaan; Adah the daughter of Elon the Hittite, and Aholibamah the daughter of Anah the daughter of Zibeon the Hivite; 3  And Bashemath Ishmael’s daughter, sister of Nebajoth. 4  And [*]Adah bare to Esau Eliphaz; and Bashemath bare Reuel; 5  And Aholibamah bare Jeush, and Jaalam, and Korah: these are the sons of Esau, which were born unto him in the land of Canaan. 6  And Esau took his wives, and his sons, and his daughters, and all the [†]persons of his house, and his cattle, and all his beasts, and all his substance, which he had got in the land of Canaan; and went into the country from the face of his brother Jacob. 7  For their riches were more than that they might dwell together; and the land wherein they were strangers could not bear them because of their cattle. 8  Thus dwelt Esau in [*]mount Seir: Esau is Edom.

9 ¶ And these are the generations of Esau the father of [†]the Edomites in mount Seir: 10 These are the names of Esau’s sons; [*]Eliphaz the son of Adah the wife of Esau, Reuel the son of Bashemath the wife of Esau. 11  And the sons of Eliphaz were Teman, Omar, Zepho, and Gatam, and Kenaz. 12  And Timna was concubine to Eliphaz Esau’s son; and she bare to Eliphaz Amalek: these were the sons of Adah Esau’s wife. 13 And these are the sons of Reuel; Nahath, and Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah: these were the sons of Bashemath Esau’s wife.

14 ¶ And these were the sons of Aholibamah, the daughter of Anah [‡]the daughter of Zibeon, Esau’s wife: and she bare to Esau Jeush, and Jaalam, and Korah.

15 ¶ These were dukes of the sons of Esau: the sons of Eliphaz the firstborn son of Esau; duke Teman, duke Omar, duke Zepho, duke Kenaz, 16  Duke Korah, duke Gatam, and duke Amalek: these are the dukes that came of Eliphaz in the land of Edom; these were the sons of Adah.

17 ¶ And these are the sons of Reuel Esau’s son; duke Nahath, duke Zerah, duke Shammah, duke Mizzah: these are the dukes that came of Reuel in the land of Edom; these are the sons of Bashemath Esau’s wife.

18 ¶ And these are the sons of Aholibamah Esau’s wife; duke Jeush, duke Jaalam, duke Korah: these were the dukes that came of Aholibamah the daughter of Anah, Esau’s wife. 19 These are the sons of Esau, who is Edom, and these are their dukes.

20 ¶ [*]These are the sons of Seir the Horite, who inhabited the land; Lotan, and Shobal, and Zibeon, and Anah, 21  And Dishon, and Ezer, and Dishan: these are the dukes of the Horites, the children of Seir in the land of Edom. 22  And the children of Lotan were Hori and Hemam; and Lotan’s sister was Timna. 23  And the children of Shobal were these; Alvan, and Manahath, and Ebal, Shepho, and Onam. 24 And these are the children of Zibeon; both Ajah, and Anah: this was that Anah that found the mules in the wilderness, as he fed the asses of Zibeon his father. 25  And the children of Anah were these; Dishon, and Aholibamah the daughter of Anah. 26 And these are the children of Dishon; Hemdan, and Eshban, and Ithran, and Cheran. 27  The children of Ezer are these; Bilhan, and Zaavan, and Akan. 28  The children of Dishan are these; Uz, and Aran. 29 These are the dukes that came of the Horites; duke Lotan, duke Shobal, duke Zibeon, duke Anah, 30  Duke Dishon, duke Ezer, duke Dishan: these are the dukes that came of Hori, among their dukes in the land of Seir.

31 ¶ And these are the kings that reigned in the land of Edom, before there reigned any king over the children of Israel. 32  And Bela the son of Beor reigned in Edom: and the name of his city was Dinhabah. 33  And Bela died, and Jobab the son of Zerah of Bozrah reigned in his stead. 34  And Jobab died, and Husham of the land of Temani reigned in his stead. 35  And Husham died, and Hadad the son of Bedad, who smote Midian in the field of Moab, reigned in his stead: and the name of his city was Avith. 36  And Hadad died, and Samlah of Masrekah reigned in his stead. 37  And Samlah died, and Saul of Rehoboth by the river reigned in his stead. 38  And Saul died, and Baal-hanan the son of Achbor reigned in his stead. 39  And Baal-hanan the son of Achbor died, and Hadar reigned in his stead: and the name of his city was Pau; and his wife’s name was Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, the daughter of Mezahab. 40 And these are the names of the dukes that came of Esau, according to their families, after their places, by their names; duke Timnah, duke Alvah, duke Jetheth, 41  Duke Aholibamah, duke Elah, duke Pinon, 42  Duke Kenaz, duke Teman, duke Mibzar, 43  Duke Magdiel, duke Iram: these be the dukes of Edom, according to their habitations in the land of their possession: he is Esau the father of [†]the Edomites.

37

1  And Jacob dwelt in the land [†]wherein his father was a stranger, in the land of Canaan. 2 These are the generations of Jacob. Joseph, being seventeen years old, was feeding the flock with his brethren; and the lad was with the sons of Bilhah, and with the sons of Zilpah, his father’s wives: and Joseph brought unto his father their evil report. 3  Now Israel loved Joseph more than all his children, because he was the son of his old age: and he made him a coat of many [∥]colours. 4  And when his brethren saw that their father loved him more than all his brethren, they hated him, and could not speak peaceably unto him.

5 ¶ And Joseph dreamed a dream, and he told it his brethren: and they hated him yet the more. 6  And he said unto them, Hear, I pray you, this dream which I have dreamed: 7 For, behold, we were binding sheaves in the field, and, lo, my sheaf arose, and also stood upright; and, behold, your sheaves stood round about, and made obeisance to my sheaf. 8  And his brethren said to him, Shalt thou indeed reign over us? or shalt thou indeed have dominion over us? And they hated him yet the more for his dreams, and for his words.

9 ¶ And he dreamed yet another dream, and told it his brethren, and said, Behold, I have dreamed a dream more; and, behold, the sun and the moon and the eleven stars made obeisance to me. 10  And he told it to his father, and to his brethren: and his father rebuked him, and said unto him, What is this dream that thou hast dreamed? Shall I and thy mother and thy brethren indeed come to bow down ourselves to thee to the earth? 11  And his brethren envied him; but his father observed the saying.

12 ¶ And his brethren went to feed their father’s flock in Shechem. 13  And Israel said unto Joseph, Do not thy brethren feed the flock in Shechem? come, and I will send thee unto them. And he said to him, Here am I. 14  And he said to him, Go, I pray thee, [†]see whether it be well with thy brethren, and well with the flocks; and bring me word again. So he sent him out of the vale of Hebron, and he came to Shechem.

15 ¶ And a certain man found him, and, behold, he was wandering in the field: and the man asked him, saying, What seekest thou? 16  And he said, I seek my brethren: tell me, I pray thee, where they feed their flocks. 17  And the man said, They are departed hence; for I heard them say, Let us go to Dothan. And Joseph went after his brethren, and found them in Dothan. 18  And when they saw him afar off, even before he came near unto them, they conspired against him to slay him. 19  And they said one to another, Behold, this [†]dreamer cometh. 20  Come now therefore, and let us slay him, and cast him into some pit, and we will say, Some evil beast hath devoured him: and we shall see what will become of his dreams. 21  And [*]Reuben heard it, and he delivered him out of their hands; and said, Let us not kill him. 22  And Reuben said unto them, Shed no blood, but cast him into this pit that is in the wilderness, and lay no hand upon him; that he might rid him out of their hands, to deliver him to his father again.

23 ¶ And it came to pass, when Joseph was come unto his brethren, that they stript Joseph out of his coat, his coat of many [∥]colours that was on him; 24  And they took him, and cast him into a pit: and the pit was empty, there was no water in it. 25  And they sat down to eat bread: and they lifted up their eyes and looked, and, behold, a company of Ishmeelites came from Gilead with their camels bearing spicery and balm and myrrh, going to carry it down to Egypt. 26  And Judah said unto his brethren, What profit is it if we slay our brother, and conceal his blood? 27  Come, and let us sell him to the Ishmeelites, and let not our hand be upon him; for he is our brother and our flesh. And his brethren [†]were content. 28  Then there passed by Midianites merchantmen; and they drew and lifted up Joseph out of the pit, [*]and sold Joseph to the Ishmeelites for twenty pieces of silver: and they brought Joseph into Egypt.

29 ¶ And Reuben returned unto the pit; and, behold, Joseph was not in the pit; and he rent his clothes. 30  And he returned unto his brethren, and said, The child is not; and I, whither shall I go?

31  And they took Joseph’s coat, and killed a kid of the goats, and dipped the coat in the blood; 32  And they sent the coat of many colours, and they brought it to their father; and said, This have we found: know now whether it be thy son’s coat or no. 33  And he knew it, and said, It is my son’s coat; an [*]evil beast hath devoured him; Joseph is without doubt rent in pieces. 34  And Jacob rent his clothes, and put sackcloth upon his loins, and mourned for his son many days. 35  And all his sons and all his daughters rose up to comfort him; but he refused to be comforted; and he said, For I will go down into the grave unto my son mourning. Thus his father wept for him. 36  And the [‡]Midianites sold him into Egypt unto Potiphar, an [†]officer of Pharaoh’s, and [†][∥]captain of the guard.

38

1  And it came to pass at that time, that Judah went down from his brethren, and turned in to a certain Adullamite, whose name was Hirah. 2  And Judah saw there a daughter of a certain Canaanite, whose name was [*]Shuah; and he took her, and went in unto her. 3  And she conceived, and bare a son; and he called his name Er. 4 [*] And she conceived again, and bare a son; and she called his name Onan. 5  And she yet again conceived, and bare a son; and called his name Shelah: and he was at Chezib, when she bare him. 6  And Judah took a wife for Er his firstborn, whose name was Tamar. 7  And [*]Er, Judah’s firstborn, was wicked in the sight of the LORD; and the LORD slew him. 8  And Judah said unto Onan, Go in unto thy brother’s wife, and marry her, and raise up seed to thy brother. 9  And Onan knew that the seed should not be his; and it came to pass, when he went in unto his brother’s wife, that he spilled it on the ground, lest that he should give seed to his brother. 10  And the thing which he did [†]displeased the LORD: wherefore he slew him also. 11  Then said Judah to Tamar his daughter in law, Remain a widow at thy father’s house, till Shelah my son be grown: for he said, Lest peradventure he die also, as his brethren did. And Tamar went and dwelt in her father’s house.

12 ¶ And [†]in process of time the daughter of Shuah Judah’s wife died; and Judah was comforted, and went up unto his sheepshearers to Timnath, he and his friend Hirah the Adullamite. 13  And it was told Tamar, saying, Behold thy father in law goeth up to Timnath to shear his sheep. 14  And she put her widow’s garments off from her, and covered her with a vail, and wrapped herself, and sat in an [†]open place, which is by the way to Timnath; for she saw that Shelah was grown, and she was not given unto him to wife. 15  When Judah saw her, he thought her to be an harlot; because she had covered her face. 16  And he turned unto her by the way, and said, Go to, I pray thee, let me come in unto thee; (for he knew not that she was his daughter in law.) And she said, What wilt thou give me, that thou mayest come in unto me? 17  And he said, I will send thee [†]a kid from the flock. And she said, Wilt thou give me a pledge, till thou send it? 18  And he said, What pledge shall I give thee? And she said, Thy signet, and thy bracelets, and thy staff that is in thine hand. And he gave it her, and came in unto her, and she conceived by him. 19  And she arose, and went away, and laid by her vail from her, and put on the garments of her widowhood. 20  And Judah sent the kid by the hand of his friend the Adullamite, to receive his pledge from the woman’s hand: but he found her not. 21  Then he asked the men of that place, saying, Where is the harlot, that was [∥]openly by the way side? And they said, There was no harlot in this place. 22  And he returned to Judah, and said, I cannot find her; and also the men of the place said, that there was no harlot in this place. 23  And Judah said, Let her take it to her, lest we [†]be shamed: behold, I sent this kid, and thou hast not found her.

24 ¶ And it came to pass about three months after, that it was told Judah, saying, Tamar thy daughter in law hath played the harlot; and also, behold, she is with child by whoredom. And Judah said, Bring her forth, and let her be burnt. 25 When she was brought forth, she sent to her father in law, saying, By the man, whose these are, am I with child: and she said, Discern, I pray thee, whose are these, the signet, and bracelets, and staff. 26  And Judah acknowledged them, and said, She hath been more righteous than I; because that I gave her not to Shelah my son. And he knew her again no more.

27 ¶ And it came to pass in the time of her travail, that, behold, twins were in her womb. 28  And it came to pass, when she travailed, that the one put out his hand: and the midwife took and bound upon his hand a scarlet thread, saying, This came out first. 29  And it came to pass, as he drew back his hand, that, behold, his brother came out: and she said, [∥]How hast thou broken forth? this breach be upon thee: therefore his name was called [∥][*]Pharez. 30  And afterward came out his brother, that had the scarlet thread upon his hand: and his name was called Zarah.

39

1  And Joseph was brought down to Egypt; and Potiphar, an officer of Pharaoh, captain of the guard, an Egyptian, bought him of the [‡]hands of the Ishmeelites, which had brought him down thither. 2  And the LORD was with Joseph, and he was a prosperous man; and he was in the house of his master the Egyptian. 3  And his master saw that the LORD was with him, and that the LORD made all that he did to prosper in his hand. 4  And Joseph found grace in his sight, and he served him: and he made him overseer over his house, and all that he had he put into his hand. 5  And it came to pass from the time that he had made him overseer in his house, and over all that he had, that the LORD blessed the Egyptian’s house for Joseph’s sake; and the blessing of the LORD was upon all that he had in the house, and in the field. 6  And he left all that he had in Joseph’s hand; and he knew not ought he had, save the bread which he did eat. And Joseph was a goodly person, and well favoured.

7 ¶ And it came to pass after these things, that his master’s wife cast her eyes upon Joseph; and she said, Lie with me. 8  But he refused, and said unto his master’s wife, Behold, my master wotteth not what is with me in the house, and he hath committed all that he hath to my hand; 9  There is none greater in this house than I; neither hath he kept back any thing from me but thee, because thou art his wife: how then can I do this great wickedness, and sin against God? 10  And it came to pass, as she spake to Joseph day by day, that he hearkened not unto her, to lie by her, or to be with her. 11  And it came to pass about this time, that Joseph went into the house to do his business; and there was none of the men of the house there within. 12  And she caught him by his garment, saying, Lie with me: and he left his garment in her hand, and fled, and got him out.

13  And it came to pass, when she saw that he had left his garment in her hand, and was fled forth, 14  That she called unto the men of her house, and spake unto them, saying, See, he hath brought in an Hebrew unto us to mock us; he came in unto me to lie with me, and I cried with a [†]loud voice: 15  And it came to pass, when he heard that I lifted up my voice and cried, that he left his garment with me, and fled, and got him out. 16  And she laid up his garment by her, until [‡]his lord came home. 17  And she spake unto him according to these words, saying, The Hebrew servant, which thou hast brought unto us, came in unto me to mock me: 18  And it came to pass, as I lifted up my voice and cried, that he left his garment with me, and fled out.

19  And it came to pass, when his master heard the words of his wife, which she spake unto him, saying, After this manner did thy servant to me; that his wrath was kindled. 20  And Joseph’s master took him, and put him into the prison, a place where the king’s prisoners were bound: and he was there in the prison.

21 ¶ But the LORD was with Joseph, and [†]shewed him mercy, and gave him favour in the sight of the keeper of the prison. 22  And the keeper of the prison committed to Joseph’s hand all the prisoners that were in the prison; and whatsoever they did there, he was the doer of it. 23  The keeper of the prison looked not to any thing that was under his hand; because the LORD was with him, and that which he did, the LORD made it to prosper.

40

1  And it came to pass after these things, that the butler of the king of Egypt and his baker had offended their lord the king of Egypt. 2  And Pharaoh was wroth against two of his officers, against the chief of the butlers, and against the chief of the bakers. 3  And he put them in ward in the house of the captain of the guard, into the prison, the place where Joseph was bound. 4  And the captain of the guard charged Joseph with them, and he served them: and they continued a season in ward.

5 ¶ And they dreamed a dream both of them, each man his dream in one night, each man according to the interpretation of his dream, the butler and the baker of the king of Egypt, which were bound in the prison. 6  And Joseph came in unto them in the morning, and looked upon them, and, behold, they were sad. 7  And he asked Pharaoh’s officers that were with him in the ward of his lord’s house, saying, Wherefore [†]look ye so sadly to day? 8  And they said unto him, We have dreamed a dream, and there is no interpreter of it. And Joseph said unto them, Do not interpretations belong to God? tell me them, I pray you. 9  And the chief butler told his dream to Joseph, and said to him, In my dream, behold, a vine was before me; 10  And in the vine were three branches: and it was as though it budded, and her blossoms shot forth; and the clusters thereof brought forth ripe grapes: 11  And Pharaoh’s cup was in my hand: and I took the grapes, and pressed them into Pharaoh’s cup, and I gave the cup into Pharaoh’s hand. 12  And Joseph said unto him, This is the interpretation of it: The three branches are three days: 13  Yet within three days shall Pharaoh [∥]lift up thine head, and restore thee unto thy place: and thou shalt deliver Pharaoh’s cup into his hand, after the former manner when thou wast his butler. 14  But [†]think on me when it shall be well with thee, and shew kindness, I pray thee, unto me, and make mention of me unto Pharaoh, and bring me out of this house: 15  For indeed I was stolen away out of the land of the Hebrews: and here also have I done nothing that they should put me into the dungeon. 16  When the chief baker saw that the interpretation was good, he said unto Joseph, I also was in my dream, and, behold, I had three [∥]white baskets on my head: 17  And in the uppermost basket there was of all manner [†]of bakemeats for Pharaoh; and the birds did eat them out of the basket upon my head. 18  And Joseph answered and said, This is the interpretation thereof: The three baskets are three days: 19  Yet within three days shall Pharaoh [∥]lift up thy head from off thee, and shall hang thee on a tree; and the birds shall eat thy flesh from off thee.

20 ¶ And it came to pass the third day, which was Pharaoh’s birthday, that he made a feast unto all his servants: and he [∥]lifted up the head of the chief butler and of the chief baker among his servants. 21  And he restored the chief butler unto his butlership again; and he gave the cup into Pharaoh’s hand: 22  But he hanged the chief baker: as Joseph had interpreted to them. 23  Yet did not the chief butler remember Joseph, but forgat him.

41

1  And it came to pass at the end of two full years, that Pharaoh dreamed: and, behold, he stood by the river. 2  And, behold, there came up out of the river seven well favoured kine and fatfleshed; and they fed in a meadow. 3  And, behold, seven other kine came up after them out of the river, ill favoured and leanfleshed; and stood by the other kine upon the brink of the river. 4  And the ill favoured and leanfleshed kine did eat up the seven well favoured and fat kine. So Pharaoh awoke. 5  And he slept and dreamed the second time: and, behold, seven ears of corn came up upon one stalk, [†]rank and good. 6  And, behold, seven thin ears and blasted with the east wind sprung up after them. 7  And the seven thin ears devoured the seven rank and full ears. And Pharaoh awoke, and, behold, it was a dream. 8  And it came to pass in the morning that his spirit was troubled; and he sent and called for all the magicians of Egypt, and all the wise men thereof: and Pharaoh told them his dream; but there was none that could interpret them unto Pharaoh.

9 ¶ Then spake the chief butler unto Pharaoh, saying, I do remember my faults this day: 10  Pharaoh was wroth with his servants, and put me in ward in the captain of the guard’s house, both me and the chief baker: 11  And we dreamed a dream in one night, I and he; we dreamed each man according to the interpretation of his dream. 12 And there was there with us a young man, an Hebrew, servant to the captain of the guard; and we told him, and he [*]interpreted to us our dreams; to each man according to his dream he did interpret. 13  And it came to pass, as he interpreted to us, so it was; me he restored unto mine office, and him he hanged.

14 ¶ [*]Then Pharaoh sent and called Joseph, and they [†]brought him hastily out of the dungeon: and he shaved himself, and changed his raiment, and came in unto Pharaoh. 15  And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, I have dreamed a dream, and there is none that can interpret it: and I have heard say of thee, that [∥]thou canst understand a dream to interpret it. 16  And Joseph answered Pharaoh, saying, It is not in me: God shall give Pharaoh an answer of peace.

17  And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, In my dream, behold, I stood upon the bank of the river: 18  And, behold, there came up out of the river seven kine, fatfleshed and well favoured; and they fed in a meadow: 19  And, behold, seven other kine came up after them, poor and very ill favoured and leanfleshed, such as I never saw in all the land of Egypt for badness: 20  And the lean and the ill favoured kine did eat up the first seven fat kine: 21  And when they had [†]eaten them up, it could not be known that they had eaten them; but they were still ill favoured, as at the beginning. So I awoke. 22  And I saw in my dream, and, behold, seven ears came up in one stalk, full and good: 23  And, behold, seven ears, [∥]withered, thin, and blasted with the east wind, sprung up after them: 24  And the thin ears devoured the seven good ears: and I told this unto the magicians; but there was none that could declare it to me.

25 ¶ And Joseph said unto Pharaoh, The dream of Pharaoh is one: God hath shewed Pharaoh what he is about to do. 26  The seven good kine are seven years; and the seven good ears are seven years: the dream is one. 27  And the seven thin and ill favoured kine that came up after them are seven years; and the seven empty ears blasted with the east wind shall be seven years of famine. 28 This is the thing which I have spoken unto Pharaoh: What God is about to do he sheweth unto Pharaoh. 29  Behold, there come seven years of great plenty throughout all the land of Egypt: 30  And there shall arise after them seven years of famine; and all the plenty shall be forgotten in the land of Egypt; and the famine shall consume the land; 31  And the plenty shall not be known in the land by reason of that famine following; for it shall be very [†]grievous. 32  And for that the dream was doubled unto Pharaoh twice; it is because the thing is [∥]established by God, and God will shortly bring it to pass.

33  Now therefore let Pharaoh look out a man discreet and wise, and set him over the land of Egypt. 34  Let Pharaoh do this, and let him appoint [∥]officers over the land, and take up the fifth part of the land of Egypt in the seven plenteous years. 35  And let them gather all the food of those good years that come, and lay up corn under the hand of Pharaoh, and let them keep food in the cities. 36  And that food shall be for store to the land against the seven years of famine, which shall be in the land of Egypt; that the land [†]perish not through the famine.

37 ¶ And the thing was good in the eyes of Pharaoh, and in the eyes of all his servants. 38  And Pharaoh said unto his servants, Can we find such a one as this is, a man in whom the Spirit of God is? 39  And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, Forasmuch as God hath shewed thee all this, there is none so discreet and wise as thou art: 40 [*] Thou shalt be over my house, and according unto thy word shall all my people be [†]ruled: only in the throne will I be greater than thou. 41  And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, See, I have set thee over all the land of Egypt. 42  And Pharaoh took off his ring from his hand, and put it upon Joseph’s hand, and arrayed him in vestures of [∥]fine linen, and put a gold chain about his neck; 43  And he made him to ride in the second chariot which he had; and they cried before him, [∥][†]Bow the knee: and he made him ruler over all the land of Egypt. 44  And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, I am Pharaoh, and without thee shall no man lift up his hand or foot in all the land of Egypt. 45  And Pharaoh called Joseph’s name Zaphnath-paaneah; and he gave him to wife Asenath the daughter of Poti-pherah [∥]priest of On. And Joseph went out over all the land of Egypt.

46 ¶ And Joseph was thirty years old when he stood before Pharaoh king of Egypt. And Joseph went out from the presence of Pharaoh, and went throughout all the land of Egypt. 47  And in the seven plenteous years the earth brought forth by handfuls. 48  And he gathered up all the food of the seven years, which were in the land of Egypt, and laid up the food in the cities: the food of the field, which was round about every city, laid he up in the same. 49  And Joseph gathered corn as the sand of the sea, very much, until he left numbering; for it was without number. 50 [*] And unto Joseph were born two sons before the years of famine came, which Asenath the daughter of Poti-pherah [∥]priest of On bare unto him. 51  And Joseph called the name of the firstborn [∥]Manasseh: For God, said he, hath made me forget all my toil, and all my father’s house. 52  And the name of the second called he [∥]Ephraim: For God hath caused me to be fruitful in the land of my affliction.

53 ¶ And the seven years of plenteousness, that was in the land of Egypt, were ended. 54 [*] And the seven years of dearth began to come, according as Joseph had said: and the dearth was in all lands; but in all the land of Egypt there was bread. 55  And when all the land of Egypt was famished, the people cried to Pharaoh for bread: and Pharaoh said unto all the Egyptians, Go unto Joseph; what he saith to you, do. 56  And the famine was over all the face of the earth: and Joseph opened [†]all the storehouses, and sold unto the Egyptians; and the famine waxed sore in the land of Egypt. 57  And all countries came into Egypt to Joseph for to buy corn; because that the famine was so sore in all lands.

42

1  Now when [*]Jacob saw that there was corn in Egypt, Jacob said unto his sons, Why do ye look one upon another? 2  And he said, Behold, I have heard that there is corn in Egypt: get you down thither, and buy for us from thence; that we may live, and not die.

3 ¶ And Joseph’s ten brethren went down to buy corn in Egypt. 4  But Benjamin, Joseph’s brother, Jacob sent not with his brethren; for he said, Lest peradventure mischief befall him. 5  And the sons of Israel came to buy corn among those that came: for the famine was in the land of Canaan. 6  And Joseph was the governor over the land, and he it was that sold to all the people of the land: and Joseph’s brethren came, and bowed down themselves before him with their faces to the earth.

7  And Joseph saw his brethren, and he knew them, but made himself strange unto them, and spake [†]roughly unto them; and he said unto them, Whence come ye? And they said, From the land of Canaan to buy food. 8  And Joseph knew his brethren, but they knew not him. 9  And Joseph [*]remembered the dreams which he dreamed of them, and said unto them, Ye are spies; to see the nakedness of the land ye are come. 10  And they said unto him, Nay, my lord, but to buy food are thy servants come. 11  We are all one man’s sons; we are true men, thy servants are no spies. 12  And he said unto them, Nay, but to see the nakedness of the land ye are come. 13  And they said, Thy servants are twelve brethren, the sons of one man in the land of Canaan; and, behold, the youngest is this day with our father, and one is not. 14  And Joseph said unto them, That is it that I spake unto you, saying, Ye are spies: 15  Hereby ye shall be proved: By the life of Pharaoh ye shall not go forth hence, except your youngest brother come hither. 16  Send one of you, and let him fetch your brother, and ye shall be [†]kept in prison, that your words may be proved, whether there be any truth in you: or else by the life of Pharaoh surely ye are spies. 17  And he [†]put them all together into ward three days. 18  And Joseph said unto them the third day, This do, and live; for I fear God: 19 If ye be true men, let one of your brethren be bound in the house of your prison: go ye, carry corn for the famine of your houses: 20  But [*]bring your youngest brother unto me; so shall your words be verified, and ye shall not die. And they did so.

21 ¶ And they said one to another, We are verily guilty concerning our brother, in that we saw the anguish of his soul, when he besought us, and we would not hear; therefore is this distress come upon us. 22  And Reuben answered them, saying, [*]Spake I not unto you, saying, Do not sin against the child; and ye would not hear? therefore, behold, also his blood is required. 23  And they knew not that Joseph understood them; for [†]he spake unto them by an interpreter. 24  And he turned himself about from them, and wept; and returned to them again, and communed with them, and took from them Simeon, and bound him before their eyes.

25 ¶ Then Joseph commanded to fill their sacks with corn, and to restore every man’s money into his sack, and to give them provision for the way: and thus did he unto them. 26  And they laded their asses with the corn, and departed thence. 27  And as one of them opened his sack to give his ass provender in the inn, he espied his money; for, behold, it was in his sack’s mouth. 28  And he said unto his brethren, My money is restored; and, lo, it is even in my sack: and their heart [†]failed them, and they were afraid, saying one to another, What is this that God hath done unto us?

29 ¶ And they came unto Jacob their father unto the land of Canaan, and told him all that befell unto them; saying, 30  The man, who is the lord of the land, spake [†]roughly to us, and took us for spies of the country. 31  And we said unto him, We are true men; we are no spies: 32 We be twelve brethren, sons of our father; one is not, and the youngest is this day with our father in the land of Canaan. 33  And the man, the lord of the country, said unto us, Hereby shall I know that ye are true men; leave one of your brethren here with me, and take food for the famine of your households, and be gone: 34  And bring your youngest brother unto me: then shall I know that ye are no spies, but that ye are true men: so will I deliver you your brother, and ye shall traffick in the land.

35 ¶ And it came to pass as they emptied their sacks, that, behold, every man’s bundle of money was in his sack: and when both they and their father saw the bundles of money, they were afraid. 36  And Jacob their father said unto them, Me have ye bereaved of my children: Joseph is not, and Simeon is not, and ye will take Benjamin away: all these things are against me. 37  And Reuben spake unto his father, saying, Slay my two sons, if I bring him not to thee: deliver him into my hand, and I will bring him to thee again. 38  And he said, My son shall not go down with you; for his brother is dead, and he is left alone: if mischief befall him by the way in the which ye go, then shall ye bring down my gray hairs with sorrow to the grave.

43

1  And the famine was sore in the land. 2  And it came to pass, when they had eaten up the corn which they had brought out of Egypt, their father said unto them, Go again, buy us a little food. 3  And Judah spake unto him, saying, The man [†]did solemnly protest unto us, saying, Ye shall not see my face, except your [*]brother be with you. 4  If thou wilt send our brother with us, we will go down and buy thee food: 5  But if thou wilt not send him, we will not go down: for the man said unto us, Ye shall not see my face, except your brother be with you. 6  And Israel said, Wherefore dealt ye so ill with me, as to tell the man whether ye had yet a brother? 7  And they said, The man [†]asked us straitly of our state, and of our kindred, saying, Is your father yet alive? have ye another brother? and we told him according to the [†]tenor of these words: [†]could we certainly know that he would say, Bring your brother down? 8  And Judah said unto Israel his father, Send the lad with me, and we will arise and go; that we may live, and not die, both we, and thou, and also our little ones. 9  I will be surety for him; of my hand shalt thou require him: [*]if I bring him not unto thee, and set him before thee, then let me bear the blame for ever: 10  For except we had lingered, surely now we had returned [∥]this second time.

11  And their father Israel said unto them, If it must be so now, do this; take of the best fruits in the land in your vessels, and carry down the man a present, a little balm, and a little honey, spices, and myrrh, nuts, and almonds: 12  And take double money in your hand; and the money that was brought again in the mouth of your sacks, carry it again in your hand; peradventure it was an oversight: 13  Take also your brother, and arise, go again unto the man: 14  And God Almighty give you mercy before the man, that he may send away your other brother, and Benjamin. [∥]If I be bereaved of my children, I am bereaved.

15 ¶ And the men took that present, and they took double money in their hand, and Benjamin; and rose up, and went down to Egypt, and stood before Joseph. 16  And when Joseph saw Benjamin with them, he said to the ruler of his house, Bring these men home, and [†]slay, and make ready; for these men shall [†]dine with me at noon. 17  And the man did as Joseph bade; and the man brought the men into Joseph’s house. 18  And the men were afraid, because they were brought into Joseph’s house; and they said, Because of the money that was returned in our sacks at the first time are we brought in; that he may [†]seek occasion against us, and fall upon us, and take us for bondmen, and our asses. 19  And they came near to the steward of Joseph’s house, and they communed with him at the door of the house, 20  And said, O sir, [*][†]we came indeed down at the first time to buy food: 21  And it came to pass, when we came to the inn, that we opened our sacks, and, behold, every man’s money was in the mouth of his sack, our money in full weight: and we have brought it again in our hand. 22  And other money have we brought down in our hands to buy food: we cannot tell who put our money in our sacks. 23  And he said, Peace be to you, fear not: your God, and the God of your father, hath given you treasure in your sacks: [†]I had your money. And he brought Simeon out unto them. 24  And the man brought the men into Joseph’s house, and [*]gave them water, and they washed their feet; and he gave their asses provender. 25  And they made ready the present against Joseph came at noon: for they heard that they should eat bread there.

26 ¶ And when Joseph came home, they brought him the present which was in their hand into the house, and bowed themselves to him to the earth. 27  And he asked them of their [†]welfare, and said, [†]Is your father well, the old man of whom ye spake? Is he yet alive? 28  And they answered, Thy servant our father is in good health, he is yet alive. And they bowed down their heads, and made obeisance. 29  And he lifted up his eyes, and saw his brother Benjamin, his mother’s son, and said, Is this your younger brother, of whom ye spake unto me? And he said, God be gracious unto thee, my son. 30  And Joseph made haste; for his bowels did yearn upon his brother: and he sought where to weep; and he entered into his chamber, and wept there. 31  And he washed his face, and went out, and refrained himself, and said, Set on bread. 32  And they set on for him by himself, and for them by themselves, and for the Egyptians, which did eat with him, by themselves: because the Egyptians might not eat bread with the Hebrews; for that is an abomination unto the Egyptians. 33  And they sat before him, the firstborn according to his birthright, and the youngest according to his youth: and the men marvelled one at another. 34  And he took and sent messes unto them from before him: but Benjamin’s mess was five times so much as any of theirs. And they drank, and [†]were merry with him.

44

1  And he commanded [†]the steward of his house, saying, Fill the men’s sacks with food, as much as they can carry, and put every man’s money in his sack’s mouth. 2  And put my cup, the silver cup, in the sack’s mouth of the youngest, and his corn money. And he did according to the word that Joseph had spoken. 3  As soon as the morning was light, the men were sent away, they and their asses. 4  And when they were gone out of the city, and not yet far off, Joseph said unto his steward, Up, follow after the men; and when thou dost overtake them, say unto them, Wherefore have ye rewarded evil for good? 5  Is not this it in which my lord drinketh, and whereby indeed he [∥]divineth? ye have done evil in so doing.

6 ¶ And he overtook them, and he spake unto them these same words. 7  And they said unto him, Wherefore saith my lord these words? God forbid that thy servants should do according to this thing: 8  Behold, the money, which we found in our sacks’ mouths, we brought again unto thee out of the land of Canaan: how then should we steal out of thy lord’s house silver or gold? 9  With whomsoever of thy servants it be found, both let him die, and we also will be my lord’s bondmen. 10  And he said, Now also let it be according unto your words: he with whom it is found shall be my servant; and ye shall be blameless. 11  Then they speedily took down every man his sack to the ground, and opened every man his sack. 12  And he searched, and began at the eldest, and left at the youngest: and the cup was found in Benjamin’s sack. 13  Then they rent their clothes, and laded every man his ass, and returned to the city.

14 ¶ And Judah and his brethren came to Joseph’s house; for he was yet there: and they fell before him on the ground. 15  And Joseph said unto them, What deed is this that ye have done? wot ye not that such a man as I can certainly [∥]divine? 16  And Judah said, What shall we say unto my lord? what shall we speak? or how shall we clear ourselves? God hath found out the iniquity of thy servants: behold, we are my lord’s servants, both we, and he also with whom the cup is found. 17  And he said, God forbid that I should do so: but the man in whose hand the cup is found, he shall be my servant; and as for you, get you up in peace unto your father.

18 ¶ Then Judah came near unto him, and said, Oh my lord, let thy servant, I pray thee, speak a word in my lord’s ears, and let not thine anger burn against thy servant: for thou art even as Pharaoh. 19  My lord asked his servants, saying, Have ye a father, or a brother? 20  And we said unto my lord, We have a father, an old man, and a child of his old age, a little one; and his brother is dead, and he alone is left of his mother, and his father loveth him. 21  And thou saidst unto thy servants, Bring him down unto me, that I may set mine eyes upon him. 22  And we said unto my lord, The lad cannot leave his father: for if he should leave his father, his father would die. 23  And thou saidst unto thy servants, [*]Except your youngest brother come down with you, ye shall see my face no more. 24  And it came to pass when we came up unto thy servant my father, we told him the words of my lord. 25  And our father said, Go again, and buy us a little food. 26  And we said, We cannot go down: if our youngest brother be with us, then will we go down: for we may not see the man’s face, except our youngest brother be with us. 27  And thy servant my father said unto us, Ye know that my wife bare me two sons: 28  And the one went out from me, and I said, [*]Surely he is torn in pieces; and I saw him not since: 29  And if ye take this also from me, and mischief befall him, ye shall bring down my gray hairs with sorrow to the grave. 30  Now therefore when I come to thy servant my father, and the lad be not with us; seeing that his life is bound up in the lad’s life; 31  It shall come to pass, when he seeth that the lad is not with us, that he will die: and thy servants shall bring down the gray hairs of thy servant our father with sorrow to the grave. 32  For thy servant became surety for the lad unto my father, saying, [*]If I bring him not unto thee, then I shall bear the blame to my father for ever. 33  Now therefore, I pray thee, let thy servant abide instead of the lad a bondman to my lord; and let the lad go up with his brethren. 34  For how shall I go up to my father, and the lad be not with me? lest peradventure I see the evil that shall [†]come on my father.

45

1  Then Joseph could not refrain himself before all them that stood by him; and he cried, Cause every man to go out from me. And there stood no man with him, while Joseph made himself known unto his brethren. 2  And he [†]wept aloud: and the Egyptians and the house of Pharaoh heard. 3  And Joseph said unto his brethren, [*]I am Joseph; doth my father yet live? And his brethren could not answer him; for they were [∥]troubled at his presence. 4  And Joseph said unto his brethren, Come near to me, I pray you. And they came near. And he said, I am Joseph your brother, whom ye sold into Egypt. 5  Now therefore be not grieved, [†]nor angry with yourselves, that ye sold me hither: [*]for God did send me before you to preserve life. 6  For these two years hath the famine been in the land: and yet there are five years, in the which there shall neither be earing nor harvest. 7  And God sent me before you [†]to preserve you a posterity in the earth, and to save your lives by a great deliverance. 8 So now it was not you that sent me hither, but God: and he hath made me a father to Pharaoh, and lord of all his house, and a ruler throughout all the land of Egypt. 9  Haste ye, and go up to my father, and say unto him, Thus saith thy son Joseph, God hath made me lord of all Egypt: come down unto me, tarry not: 10  And thou shalt dwell in the land of Goshen, and thou shalt be near unto me, thou, and thy children, and thy children’s children, and thy flocks, and thy herds, and all that thou hast: 11  And there will I nourish thee; for yet there are five years of famine; lest thou, and thy household, and all that thou hast, come to poverty. 12  And, behold, your eyes see, and the eyes of my brother Benjamin, that it is my mouth that speaketh unto you. 13  And ye shall tell my father of all my glory in Egypt, and of all that ye have seen; and ye shall haste and bring down my father hither. 14  And he fell upon his brother Benjamin’s neck, and wept; and Benjamin wept upon his neck. 15  Moreover he kissed all his brethren, and wept upon them: and after that his brethren talked with him.

16 ¶ And the fame thereof was heard in Pharaoh’s house, saying, Joseph’s brethren are come: and it [†]pleased Pharaoh well, and his servants. 17  And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, Say unto thy brethren, This do ye; lade your beasts, and go, get you unto the land of Canaan; 18  And take your father and your households, and come unto me: and I will give you the good of the land of Egypt, and ye shall eat the fat of the land. 19  Now thou art commanded, this do ye; take you wagons out of the land of Egypt for your little ones, and for your wives, and bring your father, and come. 20  Also [†]regard not your stuff; for the good of all the land of Egypt is yours. 21  And the children of Israel did so: and Joseph gave them wagons, according to the [†]commandment of Pharaoh, and gave them provision for the way. 22  To all of them he gave each man changes of raiment; but to Benjamin he gave three hundred pieces of silver, and five changes of raiment. 23  And to his father he sent after this manner; ten asses [†]laden with the good things of Egypt, and ten she asses laden with corn and bread and meat for his father by the way. 24  So he sent his brethren away, and they departed: and he said unto them, See that ye fall not out by the way.

25 ¶ And they went up out of Egypt, and came into the land of Canaan unto Jacob their father, 26  And told him, saying, Joseph is yet alive, and he is governor over all the land of Egypt. And [†]Jacob’s heart fainted, for he believed them not. 27  And they told him all the words of Joseph, which he had said unto them: and when he saw the wagons which Joseph had sent to carry him, the spirit of Jacob their father revived: 28  And Israel said, It is enough; Joseph my son is yet alive: I will go and see him before I die.

46

1  And Israel took his journey with all that he had, and came to Beer-sheba, and offered sacrifices unto the God of his father Isaac. 2  And God spake unto Israel in the visions of the night, and said, Jacob, Jacob. And he said, Here am I. 3  And he said, I am God, the God of thy father: fear not to go down into Egypt; for I will there make of thee a great nation: 4  I will go down with thee into Egypt; and I will also surely bring thee up again: and Joseph shall put his hand upon thine eyes.

5  And Jacob rose up from Beer-sheba: and the sons of Israel carried Jacob their father, and their little ones, and their wives, in the wagons which Pharaoh had sent to carry him. 6  And they took their cattle, and their goods, which they had gotten in the land of Canaan, and came into Egypt, [*]Jacob, and all his seed with him: 7  His sons, and his sons’ sons with him, his daughters, and his sons’ daughters, and all his seed brought he with him into Egypt.

8 ¶ And [*]these are the names of the children of Israel, which came into Egypt, Jacob and his sons: [*]Reuben, Jacob’s firstborn. 9  And the sons of Reuben; Hanoch, and Phallu, and Hezron, and Carmi.

10 ¶ And [*]the sons of Simeon; Jemuel, and Jamin, and Ohad, and Jachin, and Zohar, and Shaul the son of a Canaanitish woman.

11 ¶ And the sons of [*]Levi; Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.

12 ¶ And the sons of [*]Judah; Er, and Onan, and Shelah, and Pharez, and Zerah: but Er and Onan died in the land of Canaan. And the sons of Pharez were Hezron and Hamul.

13 ¶ [*]And the sons of Issachar; Tola, and Phuvah, and Job, and Shimron.

14 ¶ And the sons of Zebulun; Sered, and Elon, and Jahleel. 15 These be the sons of Leah, which she bare unto Jacob in Padan-aram, with his daughter Dinah: all the souls of his sons and his daughters were thirty and three.

16 ¶ And the sons of Gad; Ziphion, and Haggi, Shuni, and Ezbon, Eri, and Arodi, and Areli.

17 ¶ [*]And the sons of Asher; Jimnah, and Ishuah, and Isui, and Beriah, and Serah their sister: and the sons of Beriah; Heber, and Malchiel. 18 These are the sons of Zilpah, whom Laban gave to Leah his daughter, and these she bare unto Jacob, even sixteen souls. 19  The sons of Rachel Jacob’s wife; Joseph, and Benjamin.

20 ¶ And unto Joseph in the land of Egypt were born Manasseh and Ephraim, [*]which Asenath the daughter of Poti-pherah [∥]priest of On bare unto him.

21 ¶ [*]And the sons of Benjamin were Belah, and Becher, and Ashbel, Gera, and Naaman, Ehi, and Rosh, Muppim, and Huppim, and Ard. 22 These are the sons of Rachel, which were born to Jacob: all the souls were fourteen.

23 ¶ And the sons of Dan; Hushim.

24 ¶ And the sons of Naphtali; Jahzeel, and Guni, and Jezer, and Shillem. 25 These are the sons of Bilhah, which Laban gave unto Rachel his daughter, and she bare these unto Jacob: all the souls were seven. 26 [*] All the souls that came with Jacob into Egypt, which came out of his [†]loins, besides Jacob’s sons’ wives, all the souls were threescore and six; 27  And the sons of Joseph, which were born him in Egypt, were two souls: all the souls of the house of Jacob, which came into Egypt, were threescore and ten.

28 ¶ And he sent Judah before him unto Joseph, to direct his face unto Goshen; and they came into the land of Goshen. 29  And Joseph made ready his chariot, and went up to meet Israel his father, to Goshen, and presented himself unto him; and he fell on his neck, and wept on his neck a good while. 30  And Israel said unto Joseph, Now let me die, since I have seen thy face, because thou art yet alive. 31  And Joseph said unto his brethren, and unto his father’s house, I will go up, and shew Pharaoh, and say unto him, My brethren, and my father’s house, which were in the land of Canaan, are come unto me; 32  And the men are shepherds, for [†]their trade hath been to feed cattle; and they have brought their flocks, and their herds, and all that they have. 33  And it shall come to pass, when Pharaoh shall call you, and shall say, What is your occupation? 34  That ye shall say, Thy servants’ trade hath been about cattle from our youth even until now, both we, and also our fathers: that ye may dwell in the land of Goshen; for every shepherd is an abomination unto the Egyptians.

47

1  Then Joseph came and told Pharaoh, and said, My father and my brethren, and their flocks, and their herds, and all that they have, are come out of the land of Canaan; and, behold, they are in the land of Goshen. 2  And he took some of his brethren, even five men, and presented them unto Pharaoh. 3  And Pharaoh said unto his brethren, What is your occupation? And they said unto Pharaoh, Thy servants are shepherds, both we, and also our fathers. 4  They said moreover unto Pharaoh, For to sojourn in the land are we come; for thy servants have no pasture for their flocks; for the famine is sore in the land of Canaan: now therefore, we pray thee, let thy servants dwell in the land of Goshen. 5  And Pharaoh spake unto Joseph, saying, Thy father and thy brethren are come unto thee: 6  The land of Egypt is before thee; in the best of the land make thy father and brethren to dwell; in the land of Goshen let them dwell: and if thou knowest [‡]any men of activity among them, then make them rulers over my cattle. 7  And Joseph brought in Jacob his father, and set him before Pharaoh: and Jacob blessed Pharaoh. 8  And Pharaoh said unto Jacob, [†]How old art thou? 9  And Jacob said unto Pharaoh, [*]The days of the years of my pilgrimage are an hundred and thirty years: few and evil have the days of the years of my life been, and have not attained unto the days of the years of the life of my fathers in the days of their pilgrimage. 10  And Jacob blessed Pharaoh, and went out from before Pharaoh.

11 ¶ And Joseph placed his father and his brethren, and gave them a possession in the land of Egypt, in the best of the land, in the land of Rameses, as Pharaoh had commanded. 12  And Joseph nourished his father, and his brethren, and all his father’s household, with bread, [∥][†]according to their families.

13 ¶ And there was no bread in all the land; for the famine was very sore, so that the land of Egypt and all the land of Canaan fainted by reason of the famine. 14  And Joseph gathered up all the money that was found in the land of Egypt, and in the land of Canaan, for the corn which they bought: and Joseph brought the money into Pharaoh’s house. 15  And when money failed in the land of Egypt, and in the land of Canaan, all the Egyptians came unto Joseph, and said, Give us bread: for why should we die in thy presence? for the money faileth. 16  And Joseph said, Give your cattle; and I will give you for your cattle, if money fail. 17  And they brought their cattle unto Joseph: and Joseph gave them bread in exchange for horses, and for the flocks, and for the cattle of the herds, and for the asses: and he [†]fed them with bread for all their cattle for that year. 18  When that year was ended, they came unto him the second year, and said unto him, We will not hide it from my lord, how that our money is spent; my lord also [‡]hath our herds of cattle; there is not ought left in the sight of my lord, but our bodies, and our lands: 19  Wherefore shall we die before thine eyes, both we and our land? buy us and our land for bread, and we and our land will be servants unto Pharaoh: and give us seed, that we may live, and not die, that the land be not desolate. 20  And Joseph bought all the land of Egypt for Pharaoh; for the Egyptians sold every man his field, because the famine prevailed over them: so the land became Pharaoh’s. 21  And as for the people, he removed them to cities from one end of the borders of Egypt even to the other end thereof. 22  Only the land of the [∥]priests bought he not; for the priests had a portion assigned them of Pharaoh, and did eat their portion which Pharaoh gave them: wherefore they sold not their lands. 23  Then Joseph said unto the people, Behold, I have bought you this day and your land for Pharaoh: lo, here is seed for you, and ye shall sow the land. 24  And it shall come to pass in the increase, that ye shall give the fifth part unto Pharaoh, and four parts shall be your own, for seed of the field, and for your food, and for them of your households, and for food for your little ones. 25  And they said, Thou hast saved our lives: let us find grace in the sight of my lord, and we will be Pharaoh’s servants. 26  And Joseph made it a law over the land of Egypt unto this day, that Pharaoh should have the fifth part; except the land of the [∥]priests only, which became not Pharaoh’s.

27 ¶ And Israel dwelt in the land of Egypt, in the country of Goshen; and they had possessions therein, and grew, and multiplied exceedingly. 28  And Jacob lived in the land of Egypt seventeen years: so [†]the whole age of Jacob was an hundred forty and seven years. 29  And the time drew nigh that Israel must die: and he called his son Joseph, and said unto him, If now I have found grace in thy sight, [*]put, I pray thee, thy hand under my thigh, and deal kindly and truly with me; bury me not, I pray thee, in Egypt: 30  But I will lie with my fathers, and thou shalt carry me out of Egypt, and bury me in their buryingplace. And he said, I will do as thou hast said. 31  And he said, Swear unto me. And he sware unto him. And [*]Israel bowed himself upon the bed’s head.

48

1  And it came to pass after these things, that one told Joseph, Behold, thy father is sick: and he took with him his two sons, Manasseh and Ephraim. 2 And one told Jacob, and said, Behold, thy son Joseph cometh unto thee: and Israel strengthened himself, and sat upon the bed. 3  And Jacob said unto Joseph, God Almighty appeared unto me at [*]Luz in the land of Canaan, and blessed me, 4  And said unto me, Behold, I will make thee fruitful, and multiply thee, and I will make of thee a multitude of people; and will give this land to thy seed after thee for an everlasting possession.

5 ¶ And now thy [*]two sons, Ephraim and Manasseh, which were born unto thee in the land of Egypt before I came unto thee into Egypt, are mine; as Reuben and Simeon, they shall be mine. 6  And thy issue, which thou begettest after them, shall be thine, and shall be called after the name of their brethren in their inheritance. 7  And as for me, when I came from Padan, [*]Rachel died by me in the land of Canaan in the way, when yet there was but a little way to come unto Ephrath: and I buried her there in the way of Ephrath; the same is Beth-lehem.

8  And Israel beheld Joseph’s sons, and said, Who are these? 9  And Joseph said unto his father, They are my sons, whom God hath given me in this place. And he said, Bring them, I pray thee, unto me, and I will bless them. 10  Now the eyes of Israel were [†]dim for age, so that he could not see. And he brought them near unto him; and he kissed them, and embraced them. 11  And Israel said unto Joseph, I had not thought to see thy face: and, lo, God hath shewed me also thy seed. 12  And Joseph brought them out from between his knees, and he bowed himself with his face to the earth. 13  And Joseph took them both, Ephraim in his right hand toward Israel’s left hand, and Manasseh in his left hand toward Israel’s right hand, and brought them near unto him. 14  And Israel stretched out his right hand, and laid it upon Ephraim’s head, who was the younger, and his left hand upon Manasseh’s head, guiding his hands wittingly; for Manasseh was the firstborn.

15 ¶ And [*]he blessed Joseph, and said, God, before whom my fathers Abraham and Isaac did walk, the God which fed me all my life long unto this day, 16  The Angel which redeemed me from all evil, bless the lads; and let my name be named on them, and the name of my fathers Abraham and Isaac; and let them [†]grow into a multitude in the midst of the earth. 17  And when Joseph saw that his father laid his right hand upon the head of Ephraim, it displeased him: and he held up his father’s hand, to remove it from Ephraim’s head unto Manasseh’s head. 18  And Joseph said unto his father, Not so, my father: for this is the firstborn; put thy right hand upon his head. 19  And his father refused, and said, I know it, my son, I know it: he also shall become a people, and he also shall be great: but truly his younger brother shall be greater than he, and his seed shall become a [†]multitude of nations. 20  And he blessed them that day, saying, In thee shall Israel bless, saying, God make thee as Ephraim and as Manasseh: and he set Ephraim before Manasseh. 21  And Israel said unto Joseph, Behold, I die: but God shall be with you, and bring you again unto the land of your fathers. 22  Moreover I have given to thee one portion above thy brethren, which I took out of the hand of the Amorite with my sword and with my bow.

49

1  And Jacob called unto his sons, and said, Gather yourselves together, that I may tell you that which shall befall you in the last days. 2  Gather yourselves together, and hear, ye sons of Jacob; and hearken unto Israel your father.

3 ¶ Reuben, thou art my firstborn, my might, and the beginning of my strength, the excellency of dignity, and the excellency of power: 4  Unstable as water, [†]thou shalt not excel; because thou [*]wentest up to thy father’s bed; then defiledst thou it: [∥]he went up to my couch.

5 ¶ Simeon and Levi are brethren; [∥]instruments of cruelty are in their habitations. 6  O my soul, come not thou into their secret; unto their assembly, mine honour, be not thou united: for in their anger they slew a man, and in their selfwill they [∥]digged down a wall. 7  Cursed be their anger, for it was fierce; and their wrath, for it was cruel: I will divide them in Jacob, and scatter them in Israel.

8 ¶ Judah, thou art he whom thy brethren shall praise: thy hand shall be in the neck of thine enemies; thy father’s children shall bow down before thee. 9  Judah is a lion’s whelp: from the prey, my son, thou art gone up: he stooped down, he couched as a lion, and as an old lion; who shall rouse him up? 10  The sceptre shall not depart from Judah, nor a lawgiver from between his feet, until Shiloh come; and unto him shall the gathering of the people be. 11  Binding his foal unto the vine, and his ass’s colt unto the choice vine; he washed his garments in wine, and his clothes in the blood of grapes: 12  His eyes shall be red with wine, and his teeth white with milk.

13 ¶ Zebulun shall dwell at the haven of the sea; and he shall be for an haven of ships; and his border shall be unto Zidon.

14 ¶ Issachar is a strong ass couching down between two burdens: 15  And he saw that rest was good, and the land that it was pleasant; and bowed his shoulder to bear, and became a servant unto tribute.

16 ¶ Dan shall judge his people, as one of the tribes of Israel. 17  Dan shall be a serpent by the way, [†]an adder in the path, that biteth the horse heels, so that his rider shall fall backward. 18  I have waited for thy salvation, O LORD.

19 ¶ Gad, a troop shall overcome him: but he shall overcome at the last.

20 ¶ Out of Asher his bread shall be fat, and he shall yield royal dainties.

21 ¶ Naphtali is a hind let loose: he giveth goodly words.

22 ¶ Joseph is a fruitful bough, even a fruitful bough by a well; whose [†]branches run over the wall: 23  The archers have sorely grieved him, and shot at him, and hated him: 24  But his bow abode in strength, and the arms of his hands were made strong by the hands of the mighty God of Jacob; (from thence is the shepherd, the stone of Israel:) 25  Even by the God of thy father, who shall help thee; and by the Almighty, who shall bless thee with blessings of heaven above, blessings of the deep that lieth under, blessings of the breasts, and of the womb: 26  The blessings of thy father have prevailed above the blessings of my progenitors unto the utmost bound of the everlasting hills: they shall be on the head of Joseph, and on the crown of the head of him that was separate from his brethren.

27 ¶ Benjamin shall ravin as a wolf: in the morning he shall devour the prey, and at night he shall divide the spoil.

28 ¶ All these are the twelve tribes of Israel: and this is it that their father spake unto them, and blessed them; every one according to his blessing he blessed them. 29  And he charged them, and said unto them, I am to be gathered unto my people: [*]bury me with my fathers in the cave that is in the field of Ephron the Hittite, 30  In the cave that is in the field of Machpelah, which is before Mamre, in the land of Canaan, [*]which Abraham bought with the field of Ephron the Hittite for a possession of a buryingplace. 31  There they buried Abraham and Sarah his wife; there they buried Isaac and Rebekah his wife; and there I buried Leah. 32  The purchase of the field and of the cave that is therein was from the children of Heth. 33  And when Jacob had made an end of commanding his sons, he gathered up his feet into the bed, and yielded up the ghost, and was gathered unto his people.

50

1  And Joseph fell upon his father’s face, and wept upon him, and kissed him. 2  And Joseph commanded his servants the physicians to embalm his father: and the physicians embalmed Israel. 3  And forty days were fulfilled for him; for so are fulfilled the days of those which are embalmed: and the Egyptians [†]mourned for him threescore and ten days. 4  And when the days of his mourning were past, Joseph spake unto the house of Pharaoh, saying, If now I have found grace in your eyes, speak, I pray you, in the ears of Pharaoh, saying, 5 [*] My father made me swear, saying, Lo, I die: in my grave which I have digged for me in the land of Canaan, there shalt thou bury me. Now therefore let me go up, I pray thee, and bury my father, and I will come again. 6  And Pharaoh said, Go up, and bury thy father, according as he made thee swear.

7 ¶ And Joseph went up to bury his father: and with him went up all the servants of Pharaoh, the elders of his house, and all the elders of the land of Egypt, 8  And all the house of Joseph, and his brethren, and his father’s house: only their little ones, and their flocks, and their herds, they left in the land of Goshen. 9  And there went up with him both chariots and horsemen: and it was a very great company. 10  And they came to the threshingfloor of Atad, which is beyond Jordan, and there they mourned with a great and very sore lamentation: and he made a mourning for his father seven days. 11  And when the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, saw the mourning in the floor of Atad, they said, This is a grievous mourning to the Egyptians: wherefore the name of it was called [∥]Abel-mizraim, which is beyond Jordan. 12  And his sons did unto him according as he commanded them: 13  For [*]his sons carried him into the land of Canaan, and buried him in the cave of the field of Machpelah, which Abraham [*]bought with the field for a possession of a buryingplace of Ephron the Hittite, before Mamre.

14 ¶ And Joseph returned into Egypt, he, and his brethren, and all that went up with him to bury his father, after he had buried his father.

15 ¶ And when Joseph’s brethren saw that their father was dead, they said, Joseph will peradventure hate us, and will certainly requite us all the evil which we did unto him. 16  And they [†]sent a messenger unto Joseph, saying, Thy father did command before he died, saying, 17  So shall ye say unto Joseph, Forgive, I pray thee now, the trespass of thy brethren, and their sin; for they did unto thee evil: and now, we pray thee, forgive the trespass of the servants of the God of thy father. And Joseph wept when they spake unto him. 18  And his brethren also went and fell down before his face; and they said, Behold, we be thy servants. 19  And Joseph said unto them, [*]Fear not: for am I in the place of God? 20  But as for you, ye thought evil against me; but God meant it unto good, to bring to pass, as it is this day, to save much people alive. 21  Now therefore fear ye not: I will nourish you, and your little ones. And he comforted them, and spake [†]kindly unto them.

22 ¶ And Joseph dwelt in Egypt, he, and his father’s house: and Joseph lived an hundred and ten years. 23  And Joseph saw Ephraim’s children of the third generation: [*]the children also of Machir the son of Manasseh were [†]brought up upon Joseph’s knees. 24  And Joseph said unto his brethren, I die: and [*]God will surely visit you, and bring you out of this land unto the land which he sware to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob. 25  And [*]Joseph took an oath of the children of Israel, saying, God will surely visit you, and ye shall carry up my bones from hence. 26  So Joseph died, being an hundred and ten years old: and they embalmed him, and he was put in a coffin in Egypt.

* 1.1 Ps. 33. 6. &c 136. 5. Acts 14. 15. &c 17. 24. Heb. 11. 3.

* 1.3 2 Cor. 4. 6.

† 1.4 Heb. between the light and between the darkness.

† 1.5 Heb. And the evening was, and the morning was, &c.

* 1.6 Ps. 136. 5. Jer. 10. 12. &c 51. 15.

† 1.6 Heb. expansion.

* 1.8 Jer. 51. 15.

* 1.9 Ps. 33. 7. &c 136. 6. Job 38. 8.

† 1.11 Heb. tender grass.

* 1.14 Deut. 4. 19. Ps. 136. 7.

† 1.14 Heb. between the day and between the night.

† 1.16 Heb. for the rule of the day, &c.

* 1.18 Jer. 31. 35.

* 1.20 2 Esd. 6. 47.

∥ 1.20 Or, creeping.

† 1.20 Heb. soul.

† 1.20 Heb. face of the firmament of heaven.

* 1.22 ch. 8. 17. &c 9. 1.

* 1.26 ch. 5. 1. &c 9. 6. 1 Cor. 11. 7. Eph. 4. 24. Col. 3. 10.

* 1.27 Matt. 19. 4. Wisd. 2. 23.

* 1.28 ch. 9. 1.

† 1.28 Heb creepeth.

† 1.29 Heb. seeding seed.

* 1.29 ch. 9. 3.

† 1.30 Heb. a living soul.

* 1.31 Ecclus 39. 16.

* 2.2 Ex. 20. 11. &c 31. 17. Deut. 5. 14. Heb. 4. 4.

† 2.3 Heb. created to make.

∥ 2.6 Or, a mist which went up from, &c.

† 2.7 Heb. dust of the ground.

* 2.7 1 Cor. 15. 47.

* 2.7 1 Cor. 15. 45.

* 2.11 Ecclus. 24. 25.

† 2.13 Heb. Cush.

∥ 2.14 Or, eastward to Assyria.

∥ 2.15 Or, Adam.

† 2.16 Heb. eating thou shalt eat.

† 2.17 Heb. dying thou shalt die.

* 2.18 Ecclus. 36. 24.

† 2.18 Heb as before him.

∥ 2.19 Or, the man.

† 2.20 Heb. called.

† 2.22 Heb. builded.

* 2.23 1 Cor. 11. 8.

* 2.24 Matt. 19. 5. Mark 10. 7. 1 Cor. 6. 16. Eph. 5. 31.

† 3.1 Heb. Yea, because, &c.

* 3.4 2 Cor. 11. 3. 1 Tim. 2. 14.

† 3.6 Heb. a desire.

* 3.6 Ecclus. 25. 24. 1 Tim. 2. 14.

∥ 3.7 Or, things to gird about.

† 3.8 Heb. wind.

∥ 3.16 Or, subject to thy husband.

* 3.16 1 Cor. 14. 34.

† 3.18 Heb cause to bud.

† 3.20 Heb. Chavah.

† 4.2 Heb. Hebel.

† 4.2 Heb. a feeder.

† 4.3 Heb. at the end of days.

† 4.4 Heb. sheep, or, goats.

* 4.4 Heb. 11. 4.

∥ 4.7 Or, have the excellency?

∥ 4.7 Or, subject unto thee.

* 4.8 Wisd. 10. 3. Matt. 23. 35. 1 John 3. 12. Jude 11.

† 4.10 Heb. bloods.

∥ 4.13 Or, My iniquity is greater than that it may be forgiven

† 4.17 Heb. Chanoch.

† 4.18 Heb Lemech.

† 4.22 Heb. whetter.

∥ 4.23 Or, I would slay a man in my wound, &c.

∥ 4.23 Or, in my hurt.

† 4.25 Heb. Sheth.

† 4.26 Heb. Enosh

∥ 4.26 Or, to call themselves by the name of the Lord

* 5.1 1 Chr. 1. 1.

* 5.2 Wisd. 2. 23.

* 5.4 1 Chr. 1. 1, &c.

† 5.6 Heb. Enosh.

† 5.9 Heb. Kenan.

† 5.12 Gr. Maleleel.

† 5.15 Heb. Jered.

† 5.21 Gr. Mathusala.

* 5.24 Ecclus. 44. 16. Heb. 11. 5.

† 5.25 Heb. Lemech.

† 5.29 Gr. Noe.

∥ 6.5 Or, the whole imagination. The Hebrew word signifieth not only the imagination, but also the purposes and desires.

* 6.5 ch. 8. 21. Matt. 15. 19.

† 6.5 Heb. every day.

† 6.7 Heb. from man unto beast.

* 6.9 Ecclus. 44. 17. 2 Pet. 2. 5.

∥ 6.9 Or, upright.

∥ 6.13 Or, from the earth.

† 6.14 Heb. nests.

* 6.22 Heb. 11 7.

* 7.1 2 Pet 2. 5

† 7.2 Heb. seven seven.

† 7.4 Heb blot out.

∥ 7.10 Or, on the seventh day.

∥ 7.11 Or, floodgates.

† 7.14 Heb. wing.

* 7.21 Wisd. 10. 4.

† 7.22 Heb the breath of the spirit of life.

* 7.23 Wisd. 10 4. 2 Pet. 2. 5.

† 8.3 Heb. in going and returning.

† 8.5 Heb were in going and decreasing.

† 8.7 Heb. in going forth and returning.

† 8.9 Heb. caused her to come.

‡ 8.13 [1611 one]

† 8.19 Heb. families.

† 8.21 Heb. a savour of rest.

* 8.21 ch. 6. 5. Matt. 15. 19.

† 8.22 Heb. As yet all the days of the earth.

* 9.1 ch. 1. 28. &c 8. 17.

* 9.3 ch. 1. 29.

* 9.4 Lev. 17. 14.

* 9.6 Matt. 26. 52. Rev. 13. 10.

* 9.6 ch. 1. 27.

* 9.11 Is. 54. 9.

* 9.14 Ecclus 43. 11, 12.

† 9.18 Heb. Chenaan.

∥ 9.26 Or, servant to them.

∥ 9.27 Or, persuade.

* 10.2 1 Chr. 1. 5.

* 10.6 1 Chr. 1. 8.

† 10.10 Gr. Babylon.

∥ 10.11 Or, he went out into Assyria.

∥ 10.11 Or, the streets of the city.

† 10.15 Heb. Tzidon.

† 10.19 Heb. Azzah.

* 10.22 1 Chr. 1. 17.

† 10.22 Heb. Arpachshad.

† 10.24 Heb. Shelah.

* 10.25 1 Chr. 1. 19.

* 11.1 Wisd. 10. 5.

† 11.1 Heb. lip.

† 11.1 Heb. words.

† 11.3 Heb. a man said to his neighbour.

† 11.3 Heb. burn them to a burning.

∥ 11.9 That is, Confusion.

* 11.10 1 Chr. 1. 17.

* 11.16 1 Chr. 1. 19.

* 11.16 Luke 3. 35, Phalec.

* 11.20 Luke 3. 35, Saruch.

* 11.24 Luke 3 34, Thara.

* 11.26 Josh. 24 2. 1 Chr. 1. 26.

* 11.31 Neh. 9. 7. Judith 5. 7. Acts 7. 4.

* 12.1 Acts 7. 3.

* 12.3 ch. 18. 18. &c 22. 18. Acts 3. 25. Gal. 3. 8.

* 12.7 ch. 13. 15.

* 12.7 ch. 13. 4.

† 12.9 Heb. in going and journeying.

* 13.4 ch. 12. 7

† 13.8 Heb. men brethren.

* 13.15 ch. 12. 7. &c 26. 4. Deut. 34. 4.

† 13.18 Heb. plains.

∥ 14.5 Or, the plain of Kiriathaim.

∥ 14.6 Or, the plain of Paran.

∥ 14.14 Or, led forth.

∥ 14.14 Or, instructed.

* 14.17 2 Sam. 18. 18.

* 14.18 Heb. 7. 1.

* 14.20 Heb. 7. 4.

† 14.21 Heb. souls.

* 15.1 Ps. 16. 5.

* 15.5 Rom. 4. 18.

* 15.6 Rom. 4. 3. Gal. 3. 6. James 2. 23.

* 15.13 Acts 7. 6.

† 15.17 Heb. a lamp of fire.

* 15.18 ch. 12. 7. &c 13 15. &c 26. 4. Deut. 34. 4.

† 16.2 Heb. be builded by her.

† 16.6 Heb. that which is good in thy eyes.

† 16.6 Heb. afflicted her.

∥ 16.11 That is, God shall hear.

* 16.12 ch. 25. 18.

* 16.14 ch. 24 62

∥ 16.14 That is, The well of him that liveth and seeth me.

* 17.1 ch. 5. 22.

∥ 17.1 Or, upright, or, sincere.

† 17.4 Heb. multitude of nations.

* 17.5 Rom. 4. 17.

† 17.8 Heb. of thy sojournings.

* 17.10 Acts 7. 8.

* 17.11 Acts 7. 8. Rom. 4. 11.

† 17.12 Heb. a son of eight days.

* 17.12 Lev. 12. 8. Luke 2. 21. John 7. 22.

† 17.16 Heb. she shall became nations.

* 17.19 ch. 18. 10 &c 21. 2.

* 17.20 ch. 25. 12.

* 18.2 Heb. 13. 2.

† 18.5 Heb. stay.

† 18.5 Heb. you have passed.

† 18.6 Heb. Hasten.

* 18.10 ch. 17. 19. &c 21. 2.

* 18.12 1 Pet. 3. 6.

* 18.18 ch. 12. 3. &c 22. 18. Acts 3. 25. Gal. 3. 3.

* 19.2 ch. 18. 4.

* 19.11 Wisd. 19. 17.

* 19.13 ch. 18. 20.

† 19.15 Heb. are found.

∥ 19.15 Or, punishment.

* 19.16 Wisd. 10. 6.

† 19.21 Heb. thy face.

‡ 19.21 [1611 omits also]

† 19.23 Heb. gone forth.

* 19.24 Deut. 29. 23. Isai. 13. 19. Jer. 50. 40. Amos 4. 11. Luke 17. 29. Jude 7.

† 20.3 Heb. married to an husband.

∥ 20.5 Or, simplicity, or, sincerity.

* 20.13 ch. 12. 13.

† 20.15 Heb. as is good in thine eyes.

* 21.1 ch. 17. 19. &c 18. 10.

* 21.2 Acts 7. 8 Gal. 4. 22. Heb. 11. 11.

* 21.4 ch. 17. 12.

* 21.10 Gal. 4. 30.

† 21.23 Heb. if thou shalt he unto me.

∥ 21.31 That is. The well of the oath.

∥ 21.33 Or, tree.

* 22.1 Heb. 11. 17.

† 22.1 Heb. Behold me.

† 22.7 Heb. Behold me.

‡ 22.7 [1611 omits the]

∥ 22.7 Or, kid.

* 22.9 Jam. 2. 21.

∥ 22.14 That is, The Lord will see, or, provide.

* 22.16 Ps. 105. 9. Ecclus. 44. 21 Luke 1. 73 Heb. 6. 13.

† 22.17 Heb. lip.

* 22.18 ch. 12. 3. &c 18. 18. Ecclus. 44. 22. Acts 3. 25. Gal. 3. 8.

* 22.23 Rom. 9. 10, Rebecca.

† 23.6 Heb. a prince of God.

† 23.9 Heb. full money.

† 23.10 Heb. ears.

‡ 23.10 [1611 gates]

† 24.1 Heb. gone into days.

* 24.2 ch. 47. 29.

* 24.7 ch. 12. 7. &c 13. 15. &c 15. 18. &c 26. 4.

∥ 24.10 Or, and.

† 24.11 Heb. that women which draw water go forth.

* 24.13 ver. 43.

† 24.16 Heb. good of countenance.

∥ 24.22 Or, jewel for the forehead.

* 24.43 ver 13

† 24.53 Heb. vessels.

* 24.54 ver. 56. &c 59.

∥ 24.55 Or, a full year, or, ten months.

* 24.62 ch. 16. 14. &c 25. 11.

∥ 24.63 Or, to pray.

* 25.2 1 Chr. 1. 32.

* 25.10 ch 23. 16.

* 25.11 ch. 16. 14. &c 24. 62.

* 25.13 1 Chr. 1. 29.

† 25.18 Heb. fell.

* 25.23 Rom. 9. 12.

* 25.26 Hos. 12. 3.

† 25.28 Heb. venison was in his mouth.

† 25.30 Heb. with that red, with that red pottage.

† 25.32 Heb. going to die.

* 25.33 Heb. 12. 16.

* 26.3 ch. 13. 15. &c 15. 18.

* 26.4 ch. 12. 3. &c 15. 18. &c 22. 18.

† 26.12 Heb. found.

† 26.13 Heb. went going.

∥ 26.14 Or, husbandry.

† 26.19 Heb. living.

∥ 26.20 That is, Contention.

∥ 26.21 That is, Hatred.

∥ 26.22 That is, Room.

† 26.28 Heb. Seeing we saw.

† 26.29 Heb. If thou shall, &c.

∥ 26.33 That is, An oath.

∥ 26.33 That is, The well of the oath.

* 26.35 ch. 27. 46.

† 26.35 Heb. bitterness of spirit.

† 27.3 Heb. hunt.

† 27.15 Heb. desirable.

† 27.20 Heb. before me.

* 27.28 Heb. 11. 20.

† 27.33 Heb. trembled with a great trembling greatly.

† 27.33 Heb. hunted.

∥ 27.36 That is, A supplanter.

∥ 27.37 Or, supported.

* 27.38 Heb. 12. 17.

* 27.39 ver. 28.

∥ 27.39 Or, of the fatness.

* 27.41 Obad. 10.

* 27.46 ch. 26. 35.

* 28.2 Hos. 12. 12.

† 28.3 Heb. an assembly of people.

† 28.4 Heb. of thy sojournings.

† 28.8 Heb. were evil in the eyes, &c.

* 28.10 Acts 7. 2, Charran.

* 28.13 ch. 35. 1 &c 48. 3.

† 28.14 Heb. break forth.

* 28.14 Deut. 12. 20.

* 28.14 ch. 12. 3. &c 18. 18. &c 22. 18. &c 26. 4.

∥ 28.19 That is, The house of God.

† 29.1 Heb. lift up his feet.

† 29.1 Heb. children.

† 29.6 Heb. Is there peace to him?

† 29.7 Heb. yet the day is great.

† 29.13 Heb. hearing.

† 29.14 Heb. a month of days.

† 29.26 Heb. place.

∥ 29.32 That is, See a son.

∥ 29.33 That is, Hearing.

∥ 29.34 That is, Joined.

* 29.35 Matt. 1. 2.

∥ 29.35 That is, Praise.

† 29.35 Heb. stood from bearing.

† 30.3 Heb. be built by her.

∥ 30.6 That is, Judging.

† 30.8 Heb. wrestlings of God.

∥ 30.8 That is, My wrestling.

* 30.8 Matt. 4. 13, Nephthalim.

∥ 30.11 That is, A troop, or, company.

† 30.13 Heb. In my happiness.

∥ 30.13 That is, Happy.

∥ 30.18 That is, An hire.

∥ 30.20 That is, Dwelling.

* 30.20 Matt. 4. 13, Zabulan.

∥ 30.21 That is, Judgment.

∥ 30.24 That is, Adding.

† 30.30 Heb. broken forth.

† 30.30 Heb at my foot.

† 30.33 Heb. to morrow.

‡ 31.1 [1611 was of our father's]

† 31.2 Heb. as yesterday and the day before.

∥ 31.10 Or, he goats.

* 31.13 ch. 28. 18.

† 31.19 Heb. teraphim

† 31.20 Heb. the heart of Laban.

† 31.24 Heb. from good to bad.

† 31.27 Heb. hast stolen me.

† 31.34 Heb. felt.

† 31.37 Heb. felt.

* 31.39 Ex. 22. 12.

∥ 31.47 That is, The heap of witness.

∥ 31.49 That is, A beacon, or, watch-tower.

∥ 31.54 Or, killed beasts.

∥ 32.2 That is, Two hosts, or, camps.

† 32.3 Heb. field.

* 32.9 ch. 31. 13.

† 32.10 Heb I am less than all, &c.

† 32.11 Heb. upon.

† 32.20 Heb. my face.

† 32.23 Heb. caused to pass.

† 32.24 Heb. ascending of the morning.

* 32.26 Hos. 12. 4.

* 32.28 ch. 35. 10.

∥ 32.30 That is, The face of God.

† 33.5 Heb. to thee.

† 33.8 Heb. What is all this band to thee?

† 33.9 Heb. be that to thee that is thine.

† 33.14 Heb. according to the foot of the work, &c. and according to the foot of the children.

† 33.15 Heb. set, or, place.

† 33.15 Heb. Wherefore is this?

∥ 33.17 That is, Booths.

* 33.18 Acts 7. 16, Sychem.

* 33.19 Acts 7. 16, Emmor.

∥ 33.19 Or, lambs

∥ 33.20 That is, God the God of Israel.

† 34.2 Heb humbled her.

† 34.3 Heb. to her heart.

* 34.25 ch. 49. 6.

† 34.26 Heb. mouth.

* 35.1 ch. 27. 43.

* 35.7 ch. 28. 19.

∥ 35.7 That is, The God of Beth-el.

∥ 35.8 That is, The oak of weeping.

* 35.10 ch. 32. 28.

† 35.16 Heb. a little piece of ground.

∥ 35.18 That is, The son of my sorrow.

∥ 35.18 That is, The son of the right hand.

* 35.22 ch. 49. 4.

* 35.29 ch. 25. 8.

* 36.4 1 Chr. 1. 35.

† 36.6 Heb. souls.

* 36.8 Josh. 24. 4.

† 36.9 Heb. Edom.

* 36.10 1 Chr. 1. 35, &c.

‡ 36.14 [1611 omits the]

* 36.20 1 Chr. 1. 38.

† 36.43 Heb. Edom.

† 37.1 Heb. of his father's sojournings.

∥ 37.3 Or, pieces.

† 37.14 Heb. see the peace of thy brethren, &c.

† 37.19 Heb. master of dreams.

* 37.21 ch. 42. 22.

∥ 37.23 Or, pieces.

† 37.27 Heb. hearkened.

* 37.28 Ps. 105. 17. Wisd. 10. 13. Acts 7. 9.

* 37.33 ch. 44. 28

‡ 37.36 [1611 Medanites]

† 37.36 Heb. eunuch But the word doth signify not only eunuchs, but also chamberlains, courtiers, and officers.

† 37.36 Heb. chief of the slaughtermen, or, executioners.

∥ 37.36 Or, chief marshal.

* 38.2 1 Chr. 2. 8.

* 38.4 Num. 26. 19.

* 38.7 Num. 26. 19.

† 38.10 Heb. was evil in the eyes of the Lord.

† 38.12 Heb. the days were multiplied.

† 38.14 Heb. the door of eyes, or, of Enajim.

† 38.17 Heb. a kid of the goats.

∥ 38.21 Or, in Enajim.

† 38.23 Heb. become a contempt.

∥ 38.29 Or, Wherefore hast thou made this breach against thee?

∥ 38.29 That is, A breach.

* 38.29 1 Chr. 2. 4. Matt. 1. 3.

‡ 39.1 [1611 hand]

† 39.14 Heb. great.

‡ 39.16 [1611 her]

† 39.21 Heb. extended kindness unto him.

† 40.7 Heb. are your faces evil?

∥ 40.13 Or, reckon.

† 40.14 Heb. remember me with thee.

∥ 40.16 Or, full of holes.

† 40.17 Heb. meat of Pharaoh, the work of a baker, or, cook.

∥ 40.19 Or, reckon thee, and take thy office from thee.

∥ 40.20 Or, reckoned.

† 41.5 Heb. fat.

* 41.12 ch. 40. 12, &c.

* 41.14 Ps. 105 20.

† 41.14 Heb. made him run.

∥ 41.15 Or, when thou hearest a dream, thou canst interpret it.

† 41.21 Heb. come to the inward parts of them.

∥ 41.23 Or, small.

† 41.31 Heb. heavy.

∥ 41.32 Or, prepared of God.

∥ 41.34 Or, overseers.

† 41.36 Heb. be not cut off.

* 41.40 Ps. 105. 21. 1 Mac 2. 53. Acts 7. 10.

† 41.40 Heb. armed, or, kiss.

∥ 41.42 Or, silk.

∥ 41.43 Or, Tender father.

† 41.43 Heb. Abrech.

∥ 41.45 Or, prince.

* 41.50 ch. 46. 20. &c 48. 5.

∥ 41.50 Or, prince.

∥ 41.51 That is, Forgetting.

∥ 41.52 That is, Fruitful.

* 41.54 Ps. 105. 16.

† 41.56 Heb. all wherein was.

* 42.1 Acts 7. 12.

† 42.7 Heb. hard things with them.

* 42.9 ch. 37. 5.

† 42.16 Heb. bound.

† 42.17 Heb. gathered.

* 42.20 ch. 43. 5.

* 42.22 ch. 37. 21.

† 42.23 Heb. an interpreter was between them.

† 42.28 Heb. went forth.

† 42.30 Heb with us hard things.

† 43.3 Heb. protesting he protested.

* 43.3 ch. 42. 20.

† 43.7 Heb. asking he asked us.

† 43.7 Heb. mouth.

† 43.7 Heb. knowing could we know.

* 43.9 ch. 44. 32.

∥ 43.10 Or, twice by this.

∥ 43.14 Or, And I, as I have been, &c.

† 43.16 Heb. kill a killing.

† 43.16 Heb. eat.

† 43.18 Heb. roll himself upon us.

* 43.20 ch 42. 3.

† 43.20 Heb. coming down we came down.

† 43.23 Heb. your money came to me.

* 43.24 ch. 18. 4. &c 24. 32.

† 43.27 Heb. peace.

† 43.27 Heb. Is there peace to your father?

† 43.34 Heb. they drank largely.

† 44.1 Heb. him that was over his house.

∥ 44.5 Or, maketh trial?

∥ 44.15 Or, make trial?

* 44.23 ch. 43. 3.

* 44.28 ch. 37. 33.

* 44.32 ch. 43. 9.

† 44.34 Heb. find my father.

† 45.2 Heb. gave forth his voice in weeping.

* 45.3 Acts 7. 13.

∥ 45.3 Or, terrified.

† 45.5 Heb. neither let there be anger in your eyes.

* 45.5 ch. 50. 20.

† 45.7 Heb. to put for you a remnant.

† 45.16 Heb. was good in the eyes of Pharaoh.

† 45.20 Heb let not your eye spare, &c.

† 45.21 Heb. mouth.

† 45.23 Heb carrying.

† 45.26 Heb. his.

* 46.6 Josh. 24. 4. Ps. 105. 23. Isal. 52. 4.

* 46.8 Ex. 1.1 &c 6. 14 Num. 26. 8. 1 Chr. 5. 1.

* 46.8 Num. 26. 5.

* 46.10 Ex. 6. 15. 1 Chr. 4. 24.

* 46.11 1 Chr. 6. 1.

* 46.12 1 Chr. 2. 3. &c 4. 21. ch. 38. 3.

* 46.13 1 Chr. 7. 1.

* 46.17 1 Chr 7. 30.

* 46.20 ch. 41. 50

∥ 46.20 Or, prince.

* 46.21 1 Chr. 7. 6. &c 8. 1.

* 46.26 Deut. 10. 22.

† 46.26 Heb. thigh.

† 46.32 Heb. they are men of cattle.

‡ 47.6 [1611 any man]

† 47.8 Heb. How many are the days of the years of thy life?

* 47.9 Heb. 11. 9, 13.

∥ 47.12 Or, as a little child is nourished.

† 47.12 Heb. according to the little ones.

† 47.17 Heb. led them.

‡ 47.18 [1611 had]

∥ 47.22 Or, princes.

∥ 47.26 Or, princes.

† 47.28 Heb. the days of the years of his life.

* 47.29 ch. 24. 2.

* 47.31 Heb. 11. 21.

* 48.3 ch. 28. 13 &c 35. 6.

* 48.5 ch. 41. 50. Josh. 13. 7.

* 48.7 ch. 35. 19.

† 48.10 Heb. heavy.

* 48.15 Heb. 11. 21.

† 48.16 Heb. as fishes do increase.

† 48.19 Heb. fulness.

† 49.4 Heb do not thou excel.

* 49.4 ch. 35. 22. 1 Chr. 5. 1.

∥ 49.4 Or, my couch is gone.

∥ 49.5 Or, their swords are weapons of violence.

∥ 49.6 Or, houghed oxen.

† 49.17 Heb. an arrow-snake.

† 49.22 Heb. daughters.

* 49.29 ch. 47. 30.

* 49.30 ch. 23. 16.

† 50.3 Heb. wept.

* 50.5 ch. 47. 29.

∥ 50.11 That is, The mourning of the Egyptians.

* 50.13 Acts 7. 16.

* 50.13 ch. 23. 16.

† 50.16 Heb. charged.

* 50.19 ch. 45. 5.

† 50.21 Heb. to their hearts.

* 50.23 Num. 32. 39.

† 50.23 Heb. borne.

* 50.24 Heb. 11. 22.

* 50.25 Ex. 13. 19.

Habakkuk

1
2
3

Habakkuk

1

1  The burden which Habakkuk the prophet did see. 2  O LORD, how long shall I cry, and thou wilt not hear! even cry out unto thee of violence, and thou wilt not save! 3  Why dost thou shew me iniquity, and cause me to behold grievance? for spoiling and violence are before me: and there are that raise up strife and contention. 4  Therefore the law is slacked, and judgment doth never go forth: for the [*]wicked doth compass about the righteous; therefore [∥]wrong judgment proceedeth.

5 ¶ [*]Behold ye among the heathen, and regard, and wonder marvellously: for I will work a work in your days, which ye will not believe, though it be told you. 6  For, lo, I raise up the Chaldeans, that bitter and hasty nation, which shall march through the [†]breadth of the land, to possess the dwellingplaces that are not theirs. 7 They are terrible and dreadful: [∥]their judgment and their dignity shall proceed of themselves. 8  Their horses also are swifter than the leopards, and are more [†]fierce than the [*]evening wolves: and their horsemen shall spread themselves, and their horsemen shall come from far; they shall fly as the eagle that hasteth to eat. 9  They shall come all for violence: [∥][†]their faces shall sup up as the east wind, and they shall gather the captivity as the sand. 10  And they shall scoff at the kings, and the princes shall be a scorn unto them: they shall deride every strong hold; for they shall heap dust, and take it. 11 Then shall his mind change, and he shall pass over, and offend, imputing this his power unto his god.

12 ¶ Art thou not from everlasting, O LORD my God, mine Holy One? we shall not die. O LORD, thou hast ordained them for judgment; and, O [†]mighty God, thou hast [†]established them for correction. 13  Thou art of purer eyes than to behold evil, and canst not look on [∥]iniquity: wherefore lookest thou upon them that deal treacherously, and holdest thy tongue when the wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous than he? 14  And makest men as the fishes of the sea, as the [∥]creeping things, that have no ruler over them? 15  They take up all of them with the angle, they catch them in their net, and gather them in their [∥]drag: therefore they rejoice and are glad. 16  Therefore they sacrifice unto their net, and burn incense unto their drag; because by them their portion is fat, and their meat [∥][†]plenteous. 17  Shall they therefore empty their net, and not spare continually to slay the nations?

2

1  I will [*]stand upon my watch, and set me upon the [†]tower, and will watch to see what he will say [∥]unto me, and what I shall answer [∥][†]when I am reproved. 2  And the LORD answered me, and said, Write the vision, and make it plain upon tables, that he may run that readeth it. 3  For the vision is yet for an appointed time, but at the end it shall speak, and not lie: though it tarry, wait for it; because it will [*]surely come, it will not tarry. 4  Behold, his soul which is lifted up is not upright in him: but the [*]just shall live by his faith.

5 ¶ [∥]Yea also, because he transgresseth by wine, he is a proud man, neither keepeth at home, who enlargeth his desire as hell, and is as death, and cannot be satisfied, but gathereth unto him all nations, and heapeth unto him all people: 6  Shall not all these take up a parable against him, and a taunting proverb against him, and say, [∥]Woe to him that increaseth that which is not his! how long? and to him that ladeth himself with thick clay! 7  Shall they not rise up suddenly that shall bite thee, and awake that shall vex thee, and thou shalt be for booties unto them? 8  Because thou hast spoiled many nations, all the remnant of the people shall spoil thee; because of men’s [†]blood, and for the violence of the land, of the city, and of all that dwell therein.

9 ¶ Woe to him that [*][∥]coveteth an evil covetousness to his house, that he may set his nest on high, that he may be delivered from the [†]power of evil! 10  Thou hast consulted shame to thy house by cutting off many people, and hast sinned against thy soul. 11  For the stone shall cry out of the wall, and the [∥]beam out of the timber shall [∥]answer it.

12 ¶ Woe to him that buildeth a town with [*][†]blood, and stablisheth a city by iniquity! 13 Behold, is it not of the LORD of hosts that the people shall labour in the very fire, and the people shall weary themselves [∥]for very vanity? 14  For the earth shall be filled [∥]with the [*]knowledge of the glory of the LORD, as the waters cover the sea.

15 ¶ Woe unto him that giveth his neighbour drink, that puttest thy bottle to him, and makest him drunken also, that thou mayest look on their nakedness! 16  Thou art filled [∥]with shame for glory: [*]drink thou also, and let thy foreskin be uncovered: the cup of the LORD’s right hand shall be turned unto thee, and shameful spewing shall be on thy glory. 17  For the violence of Lebanon shall cover thee, and the spoil of beasts, which made them afraid, because of men’s blood, and for the violence of the land, of the city, and of all that dwell therein.

18 ¶ What profiteth the graven image that the maker thereof hath graven it; the molten image, and a [*]teacher of lies, that [†]the maker of his work trusteth therein, to make dumb idols? 19  Woe unto him that saith to the wood, Awake; to the dumb stone, Arise, it shall teach! Behold, it is laid over with gold and silver, and there is no breath at all in the midst of it. 20  But [*]the LORD is in his holy temple: [†]let all the earth keep silence before him.

3

1  A prayer of Habakkuk the prophet [∥]upon Shigionoth. 2  O LORD, I have heard [†]thy speech, and was afraid: O LORD, [∥]revive thy work in the midst of the years, in the midst of the years make known; in wrath remember mercy.

3  God came from [∥]Teman, and the Holy One from mount Paran. Selah. His glory covered the heavens, and the earth was full of his praise. 4 And his brightness was as the light; he had [∥]horns coming out of his hand: and there was the hiding of his power. 5  Before him went the pestilence, and [∥]burning coals went forth at his feet. 6  He stood, and measured the earth: he beheld, and drove asunder the nations; and the everlasting mountains were scattered, the perpetual hills did bow: his ways are everlasting. 7  I saw the tents of [∥]Cushan [∥]in affliction: and the curtains of the land of Midian did tremble. 8  Was the LORD displeased against the rivers? was thine anger against the rivers? was thy wrath against the sea, that thou didst ride upon thine horses and [∥]thy chariots of salvation? 9  Thy bow was made quite naked, according to the oaths of the tribes, even thy word. Selah. [∥]Thou didst cleave the earth with rivers. 10  The mountains saw thee, and they trembled: the overflowing of the water passed by: the deep uttered his voice, and lifted up his hands on high. 11  The sun and moon [*]stood still in their habitation: [∥]at the light of thine [*]arrows they went, and at the shining of thy glittering spear. 12  Thou didst march through the land in indignation, thou didst thresh the heathen in anger. 13  Thou wentest forth for the salvation of thy people, even for salvation with thine anointed; thou woundedst the head out of the house of the wicked, [†]by discovering the foundation unto the neck. Selah. 14  Thou didst strike through with his staves the head of his villages: they [†]came out as a whirlwind to scatter me: their rejoicing was as to devour the poor secretly. 15  Thou didst walk through the sea with thine horses, through the [∥]heap of great waters.

16  When I heard, my belly trembled; my lips quivered at the voice: rottenness entered into my bones, and I trembled in myself, that I might rest in the day of trouble: when he cometh up unto the people, he will [∥]invade them with his troops.

17 ¶ Although the fig tree shall not blossom, neither shall fruit be in the vines; the labour of the olive shall [†]fail, and the fields shall yield no meat; the flock shall be cut off from the fold, and there shall be no herd in the stalls: 18  Yet I will rejoice in the LORD, I will joy in the God of my salvation. 19  The LORD God is my strength, and he will make my feet like [*]hinds’ feet, and he will make me to walk upon mine high places. To the chief singer on my [†]stringed instruments.

* 1.4 Job 21 7. Jer. 12. 1.

∥ 1.4 Or, wrested.

* 1.5 Acts 13. 41.

† 1.6 Heb breadths.

∥ 1.7 Or, from them shall proceed the judgment of these, and the captivity of these.

† 1.8 Heb sharp.

* 1.8 Zeph. 3. 3.

∥ 1.9 Or, the supping up of their faces, &c. or, their faces shall look toward the east.

† 1.9 Heb. the opposition of their faces toward the east

† 1.12 Heb. rock.

† 1.12 Heb. founded.

∥ 1.13 Or, grievance.

∥ 1.14 Or, moving.

∥ 1.15 Or, flue net.

∥ 1.16 Or, dainty.

† 1.16 Heb. fat.

* 2.1 Is. 21. 8.

† 2.1 Heb. fenced place.

∥ 2.1 Or, in me.

∥ 2.1 Or, when I am argued with.

† 2.1 Heb. upon my reproof, or, arguing.

* 2.3 Heb. 10. 37.

* 2.4 John 3. 36. Rom. 1. 17. Gal. 3. 11. Heb. 10. 38.

∥ 2.5 Or, How much more.

∥ 2.6 Or, Ho, he.

† 2.8 Heb. bloods.

* 2.9 Jer. 22. 13.

∥ 2.9 Or, gaineth an evil gain.

† 2.9 Heb. palm of the hand.

∥ 2.11 Or, piece, or, fastening.

∥ 2.11 Or, witness against it.

* 2.12 Ezek. 24. 9. Nah. 8. 1.

† 2.12 Heb. bloods.

∥ 2.13 Or, in vain?

∥ 2.14 Or, by knowing the glory of the Lord.

* 2.14 Is. 11. 9.

∥ 2.16 Or, more with shame than with glory.

* 2.16 Jer. 25. 26.

* 2.18 Jer. 10. 8, 14. Zech. 10. 2.

† 2.18 Heb. the fashioner of his fashion.

* 2.20 Ps. 11. 4.

† 2.20 Heb. be silent all the earth before him.

∥ 3.1 Or, according to variable songs, or, tunes, called in Hebrew, Shigionoth.

† 3.2 Heb. thy report, or, thy hearing.

∥ 3.2 Or, preserve alive.

∥ 3.3 Or, the south.

∥ 3.4 Or, bright beams out of his side.

∥ 3.5 Or, burning diseases.

∥ 3.7 Or, Ethiopia.

∥ 3.7 Or, under affliction, or, vanity

∥ 3.8 Or, thy chariots were salvation?

∥ 3.9 Or, Thou didst cleave the rivers of the earth.

* 3.11 Josh. 10. 12.

∥ 3.11 Or, thine arrows walked in the light, &c.

* 3.11 Josh. 10. 11.

† 3.13 Heb. making naked.

† 3.14 Heb. were tempestuous.

∥ 3.15 Or, mud.

∥ 3.16 Or, cut them in pieces.

† 3.17 Heb. lie.

* 3.19 2 Sam. 22 34. Ps 18. 33.

† 3.19 Heb. neginoth.

Haggai

1
2

Haggai

1

1  In the second year of Darius the king, in the sixth month, in the first day of the month, came the word of the LORD [†]by Haggai the prophet unto Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, [∥]governor of Judah, and to [‡]Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest, saying, 2  Thus speaketh the LORD of hosts, saying, This people say, The time is not come, the time that the LORD’s house should be built. 3  Then came the word of the LORD by Haggai the prophet, saying, 4  Is it time for you, O ye, to dwell in your cieled houses, and this house lie waste? 5  Now therefore thus saith the LORD of hosts; [†]Consider your ways. 6  Ye have [*]sown much, and bring in little; ye eat, but ye have not enough; ye drink, but ye are not filled with drink; ye clothe you, but there is none warm; and he that earneth wages earneth wages to put it into a bag [†]with holes.

7 ¶ Thus saith the LORD of hosts; Consider your ways. 8  Go up to the mountain, and bring wood, and build the house; and I will take pleasure in it, and I will be glorified, saith the LORD. 9  Ye looked for much, and, lo, it came to little; and when ye brought it home, I did [∥]blow upon it. Why? saith the LORD of hosts. Because of mine house that is waste, and ye run every man unto his own house. 10  Therefore [*]the heaven over you is stayed from dew, and the earth is stayed from her fruit. 11  And I called for a drought upon the land, and upon the mountains, and upon the corn, and upon the new wine, and upon the oil, and upon that which the ground bringeth forth, and upon men, and upon cattle, and upon all the labour of the hands.

12 ¶ Then Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest, with all the remnant of the people, obeyed the voice of the LORD their God, and the words of Haggai the prophet, as the LORD their God had sent him, and the people did fear before the LORD. 13  Then spake Haggai the LORD’s messenger in the LORD’s message unto the people, saying, I am with you, saith the LORD. 14  And the LORD stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people; and they came and did work in the house of the LORD of hosts, their God, 15  In the four and twentieth day of the sixth month, in the second year of Darius the king.

2

1  In the seventh month, in the one and twentieth day of the month, came the word of the LORD [†]by the prophet Haggai, saying, 2  Speak now to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest, and to the residue of the people, saying, 3 Who is left among you that saw this house in her first glory? and how do ye see it now? is it not in your eyes in comparison of it as nothing? 4  Yet now be strong, O Zerubbabel, saith the LORD; and be strong, O Joshua, son of Josedech, the high priest; and be strong, all ye people of the land, saith the LORD, and work: for I am with you, saith the LORD of hosts: 5  According to the word that I covenanted with you when ye came out of Egypt, so my spirit remaineth among you: fear ye not. 6  For thus saith the LORD of hosts; [*]Yet once, it is a little while, and I will shake the heavens, and the earth, and the sea, and the dry land; 7  And I will shake all nations, and the desire of all nations shall come: and I will fill this house with glory, saith the LORD of hosts. 8  The silver is mine, and the gold is mine, saith the LORD of hosts. 9  The glory of this latter house shall be greater than of the former, saith the LORD of hosts: and in this place will I give peace, saith the LORD of hosts.

10 ¶ In the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, in the second year of Darius, came the word of the LORD by Haggai the prophet, saying, 11  Thus saith the LORD of hosts; Ask now the priests concerning the law, saying, 12  If one bear holy flesh in the skirt of his garment, and with his skirt do touch bread, or pottage, or wine, or oil, or any meat, shall it be holy? And the priests answered and said, No. 13  Then said Haggai, If one that is unclean by a dead body touch any of these, shall it be unclean? And the priests answered and said, It shall be unclean. 14  Then answered Haggai, and said, So is this people, and so is this nation before me, saith the LORD; and so is every work of their hands; and that which they offer there is unclean. 15  And now, I pray you, consider from this day and upward, from before a stone was laid upon a stone in the temple of the LORD: 16 Since those days were, when one came to an heap of twenty measures, there were but ten: when one came to the pressfat for to draw out fifty vessels out of the press, there were but twenty. 17  I smote you [*]with blasting and with mildew and with hail in all the labours of your hands; yet ye turned not to me, saith the LORD. 18  Consider now from this day and upward, from the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, even from the day that the foundation of the LORD’s temple was laid, consider it. 19  Is the seed yet in the barn? yea, as yet the vine, and the fig tree, and the pomegranate, and the olive tree, hath not brought forth: from this day will I bless you.

20 ¶ And again the word of the LORD came unto Haggai in the four and twentieth day of the month, saying, 21  Speak to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah, saying, I will shake the heavens and the earth; 22  And I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms, and I will destroy the strength of the kingdoms of the heathen; and I will overthrow the chariots, and those that ride in them; and the horses and their riders shall come down, every one by the sword of his brother. 23  In that day, saith the LORD of hosts, will I take thee, O Zerubbabel, my servant, the son of Shealtiel, saith the LORD, and will make thee as a signet: for I have chosen thee, saith the LORD of hosts.

† 1.1 Heb. by the hand of Haggai.

∥ 1.1 Or, captain

‡ 1.1 [1611 Josuah]

† 1.5 Heb. Set your heart on your ways.

* 1.6 Deut. 28 38. Mic. 6. 14. 15.

† 1.6 Heb. pierced through.

∥ 1.9 Or, blow it away.

* 1.10 Deut. 28. 23.

† 2.1 Heb. by the hand of.

* 2.6 Heb 12. 26.

* 2.17 Amos 4. 9.

Hosea

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14

Hosea

1

1  The word of the LORD that came unto Hosea, the son of Beeri, in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash, king of Israel.

2  The beginning of the word of the LORD by Hosea. And the LORD said to Hosea, Go, take unto thee a wife of whoredoms and children of whoredoms: for the land hath committed great whoredom, departing from the LORD. 3  So he went and took Gomer the daughter of Diblaim; which conceived, and bare him a son. 4  And the LORD said unto him, Call his name Jezreel; for yet a little while, and I will [†]avenge the blood of Jezreel upon the house of Jehu, and will cause to cease the kingdom of the house of Israel. 5  And it shall come to pass at that day, that I will break the bow of Israel in the valley of Jezreel.

6 ¶ And she conceived again, and bare a daughter. And God said unto him, Call her name [∥]Lo-ruhamah: for [†]I will no more have mercy upon the house of Israel; [∥]but I will utterly take them away. 7  But I will have mercy upon the house of Judah, and will save them by the LORD their God, and will not save them by bow, nor by sword, nor by battle, by horses, nor by horsemen.

8 ¶ Now when she had weaned Lo-ruhamah, she conceived, and bare a son. 9  Then said God, Call his name [∥]Lo-ammi: for ye are not my people, and I will not be your God.

10 ¶ Yet the number of the children of Israel shall be as the sand of the sea, which cannot be measured nor numbered; [*]and it shall come to pass, that [∥]in the place where it was said unto them, Ye are not my people, there it shall be said unto them, Ye are the sons of the living God. 11 [*] Then shall the children of Judah and the children of Israel be gathered together, and appoint themselves one head, and they shall come up out of the land: for great shall be the day of Jezreel.

2

1  Say ye unto your brethren, [∥]Ammi; and to your sisters, [∥]Ru-hamah. 2  Plead with your mother, plead: for [*]she is not my wife, neither am I her husband: let her therefore put away her [*]whoredoms out of her sight, and her adulteries from between her breasts; 3  Lest I strip her naked, and set her as in the day that she was [*]born, and make her as a wilderness, and set her like a dry land, and slay her with thirst. 4  And I will not have mercy upon her children; for they be the children of whoredoms. 5  For their mother hath played the harlot: she that conceived them hath done shamefully: for she said, I will go after my lovers, that give me my bread and my water, my wool and my flax, mine oil and my [†]drink.

6 ¶ Therefore, behold, I will hedge up thy way with thorns, and [†]make a wall, that she shall not find her paths. 7  And she shall follow after her lovers, but she shall not overtake them; and she shall seek them, but shall not find them: then shall she say, I will go and return to my first husband; for then was it better with me than now. 8  For she did not know that I gave her corn, and [†]wine, and oil, and multiplied her silver and gold, [∥]which they prepared for Baal. 9  Therefore will I return, and take away my corn in the time thereof, and my wine in the season thereof, and will [∥]recover my wool and my flax given to cover her nakedness. 10  And now will I discover her [†]lewdness in the sight of her lovers, and none shall deliver her out of mine hand. 11  I will also cause all her mirth to cease, her feast days, her new moons, and her sabbaths, and all her solemn feasts. 12  And I will [†]destroy her vines and her fig trees, whereof she hath said, These are my rewards that my lovers have given me: and I will make them a forest, and the beasts of the field shall eat them. 13  And I will visit upon her the days of Baalim, wherein she burned incense to them, and she decked herself with her earrings and her jewels, and she went after her lovers, and forgat me, saith the LORD.

14 ¶ Therefore, behold, I will allure her, and bring her into the wilderness, and speak [∥][†]comfortably unto her. 15  And I will give her her vineyards from thence, and the valley of Achor for a door of hope: and she shall sing there, as in the days of her youth, and as in the day when she came up out of the land of Egypt. 16  And it shall be at that day, saith the LORD, that thou shalt call me [∥]Ishi; and shalt call me no more [∥]Baali. 17  For I will take away the names of Baalim out of her mouth, and they shall no more be remembered by their name. 18  And in that day will I make a [*]covenant for them with the beasts of the field, and with the fowls of heaven, and with the creeping things of the ground: and I will break the bow and the sword and the battle out of the earth, and will make them to lie down safely. 19  And I will betroth thee unto me for ever; yea, I will betroth thee unto me in righteousness, and in judgment, and in lovingkindness, and in mercies. 20  I will even betroth thee unto me in faithfulness: and thou shalt know the LORD. 21  And it shall come to pass in that day, I will hear, saith the LORD, I will hear the heavens, and they shall hear the earth; 22  And the earth shall hear the corn, and the wine, and the oil; and they shall hear Jezreel. 23  And I will sow her unto me in the earth; and I will have mercy upon her that had not obtained mercy; and I [*]will say to them which were not my people, Thou art my people; and they shall say, Thou art my God.

3

1  Then said the LORD unto me, Go yet, love a woman beloved of her friend, yet an adulteress, according to the love of the LORD toward the children of Israel, who look to other gods, and love flagons [†]of wine. 2  So I bought her to me for fifteen pieces of silver, and for an homer of barley, and an [†]half homer of barley: 3  And I said unto her, Thou shalt [*]abide for me many days; thou shalt not play the harlot, and thou shalt not be for another man: so will I also be for thee. 4  For the children of Israel shall abide many days without a king, and without a prince, and without a sacrifice, and without [†]an image, and without an ephod, and without teraphim: 5  Afterward shall the children of Israel return, and seek the LORD their God, and [*]David their king; and shall fear the LORD and his goodness in the [*]latter days.

4

1  Hear the word of the LORD, ye children of Israel: for the LORD hath a [*]controversy with the inhabitants of the land, because there is no truth, nor mercy, nor knowledge of God in the land. 2  By swearing, and lying, and killing, and stealing, and committing adultery, they break out, and [†]blood toucheth blood. 3  Therefore shall the land mourn, and every one that dwelleth therein shall languish, with the beasts of the field, and with the fowls of heaven; yea, the fishes of the sea also shall be taken away. 4  Yet let no man strive, nor reprove another: for [‡]thy people are as they that strive with the priest. 5  Therefore shalt thou fall in the day, and the prophet also shall fall with thee in the night, and I will [†]destroy thy mother.

6 ¶ My people are [†]destroyed for lack of knowledge: because thou hast rejected knowledge, I will also reject thee, that thou shalt be no priest to me: seeing thou hast forgotten the law of thy God, I will also forget thy children. 7  As they were increased, so they sinned against me: therefore will I change their glory into shame. 8  They eat up the sin of my people, and they [†]set their heart on their iniquity. 9  And there shall be, [*]like people, like priest: and I will [†]punish them for their ways, and [†]reward them their doings. 10  For they shall eat, and not have enough: they shall commit whoredom, and shall not increase: because they have left off to take heed to the LORD. 11  Whoredom and wine and new wine take away the heart.

12 ¶ My people ask counsel at their stocks, and their staff declareth unto them: for the spirit of whoredoms hath caused them to err, and they have gone a whoring from under their God. 13  They sacrifice upon the tops of the mountains, and burn incense upon the hills, under oaks and poplars and elms, because the shadow thereof is good: therefore your daughters shall commit whoredom, and your spouses shall commit adultery. 14 [∥] I will not punish your daughters when they commit whoredom, nor your spouses when they commit adultery: for themselves are separated with whores, and they sacrifice with harlots: therefore the people that doth not understand shall [∥]fall.

15 ¶ Though thou, Israel, play the harlot, yet let not Judah offend; and come not ye unto Gilgal, neither go ye up to [*]Beth-aven, nor swear, The LORD liveth. 16  For Israel slideth back as a backsliding heifer: now the LORD will feed them as a lamb in a large place. 17  Ephraim is joined to idols: let him alone. 18  Their drink [†]is sour: they have committed whoredom continually: her [†]rulers with shame do love, Give ye. 19  The wind hath bound her up in her wings, and they shall be ashamed because of their sacrifices.

5

1  Hear ye this, O priests; and hearken, ye house of Israel; and give ye ear, O house of the king; for judgment is toward you, because ye have been a snare on Mizpah, and a net spread upon Tabor. 2  And the revolters are profound to make slaughter, [∥]though I have been [†]a rebuker of them all. 3  I know Ephraim, and Israel is not hid from me: for now, O Ephraim, thou committest whoredom, and Israel is defiled. 4 [†][∥] They will not frame their doings to turn unto their God: for the spirit of whoredoms is in the midst of them, and they have not known the LORD. 5  And the pride of Israel doth testify to his face: therefore shall Israel and Ephraim fall in their iniquity; Judah also shall fall with them. 6  They shall go with their flocks and with their herds to seek the LORD; but they shall not find him; he hath withdrawn himself from them. 7  They have dealt treacherously against the LORD: for they have begotten strange children: now shall a month devour them with their portions.

8  Blow ye the cornet in Gibeah, and the trumpet in Ramah: cry aloud at Beth-aven, after thee, O Benjamin. 9  Ephraim shall be desolate in the day of rebuke: among the tribes of Israel have I made known that which shall surely be. 10  The princes of Judah were like them that remove the bound: therefore I will pour out my wrath upon them like water. 11  Ephraim is oppressed and broken in judgment, because he willingly walked after the commandment. 12 Therefore will I be unto Ephraim as a moth, and to the house of Judah as [∥]rottenness. 13  When Ephraim saw his sickness, and Judah saw his wound, then went Ephraim to the Assyrian, and sent [∥]to king Jareb: yet could he not heal you, nor cure you of your wound. 14 For I will be unto Ephraim as a lion, and as a young lion to the house of Judah: I, even I, will tear and go away; I will take away, and none shall rescue him.

15 ¶ I will go and return to my place, [†]till they acknowledge their offence, and seek my face: in their affliction they will seek me early.

6

1  Come, and let us return unto the LORD: for he hath torn, and he will heal us; he hath smitten, and he will bind us up. 2 [*] After two days will he revive us: in the third day he will raise us up, and we shall live in his sight. 3  Then shall we know, if we follow on to know the LORD: his going forth is prepared as the morning; and he shall come unto us as the rain, as the latter and former rain unto the earth.

4 ¶ O Ephraim, what shall I do unto thee? O Judah, what shall I do unto thee? for your [∥]goodness is as a morning cloud, and as the early dew it goeth away. 5  Therefore have I hewed them by the prophets; I have slain them by the words of my mouth: [∥]and thy judgments are as the light that goeth forth. 6  For I desired [*]mercy, and not sacrifice; and the knowledge of God more than burnt offerings. 7  But they [∥]like men have transgressed the covenant: there have they dealt treacherously against me. 8  Gilead is a city of them that work iniquity, and is [∥]polluted with blood. 9  And as troops of robbers wait for a man, so the company of priests murder in the way [†]by consent: for they commit [∥]lewdness. 10  I have seen an horrible thing in the house of Israel: there is the whoredom of Ephraim, Israel is defiled. 11  Also, O Judah, he hath set an harvest for thee, when I returned the captivity of my people.

7

1  When I would have healed Israel, then the iniquity of Ephraim was discovered, and the [†]wickedness of Samaria: for they commit falsehood; and the thief cometh in, and the troop of robbers [†]spoileth without. 2  And they [†]consider not in their hearts that I remember all their wickedness: now their own doings have beset them about; they are before my face. 3  They make the king glad with their wickedness, and the princes with their lies. 4 They are all adulterers, as an oven heated by the baker, [∥]who ceaseth [∥]from raising after he hath kneaded the dough, until it be leavened. 5  In the day of our king the princes have made him sick [∥]with bottles of wine; he stretched out his hand with scorners. 6  For they have [∥]made ready their heart like an oven, whiles they lie in wait: their baker sleepeth all the night; in the morning it burneth as a flaming fire. 7  They are all hot as an oven, and have devoured their judges; all their kings are fallen: there is none among them that calleth unto me.

8  Ephraim, he hath mixed himself among the people; Ephraim is a cake not turned. 9  Strangers have devoured his strength, and he knoweth it not: yea, gray hairs are [†]here and there upon him, yet he knoweth not. 10  And the [*]pride of Israel testifieth to his face: and they do not return to the LORD their God, nor seek him for all this.

11 ¶ Ephraim also is like a silly dove without heart: they call to Egypt, they go to Assyria. 12  When they shall go, I will spread my net upon them; I will bring them down as the fowls of the heaven; I will chastise them, as their congregation hath heard. 13  Woe unto them! for they have fled from me: [†]destruction unto them! because they have transgressed against me: though I have redeemed them, yet they have spoken lies against me. 14  And they have not cried unto me with their heart, when they howled upon their beds: they assemble themselves for corn and wine, and they rebel against me. 15  Though I [∥]have bound and strengthened their arms, yet do they imagine mischief against me. 16  They return, but not to the most High: they are like a deceitful bow: their princes shall fall by the sword for the [*]rage of their tongue: this shall be their derision in the land of Egypt.

8

1  Set the trumpet to [†]thy mouth. He shall come as an eagle against the house of the LORD, because they have transgressed my covenant, and trespassed against my law. 2  Israel shall cry unto me, My God, we know thee. 3  Israel hath cast off the thing that is good: the enemy shall pursue him. 4  They have set up kings, but not by me: they have made princes, and I knew it not: of their silver and their gold have they made them idols, that they may be cut off.

5 ¶ Thy calf, O Samaria, hath cast thee off; mine anger is kindled against them: how long will it be ere they attain to innocency? 6  For from Israel was it also: the workman made it; therefore it is not God: but the calf of Samaria shall be broken in pieces. 7  For they have sown the wind, and they shall reap the whirlwind: it hath no [∥]stalk: the bud shall yield no meal: if so be it yield, the strangers shall swallow it up.

8  Israel is swallowed up: now shall they be among the Gentiles as a vessel wherein is no pleasure. 9  For they are gone up to Assyria, a wild ass alone by himself: Ephraim hath hired [†]lovers. 10  Yea, though they have hired among the nations, now will I gather them, and they shall [∥]sorrow a little for the burden of the king of princes. 11  Because Ephraim hath made many altars to sin, altars shall be unto him to sin. 12  I have written to him the great things of my law, but they were counted as a strange thing. 13 [∥] They sacrifice flesh for the sacrifices of mine offerings, and eat it; but the LORD accepteth them not; now will he remember their iniquity, and visit their sins: they shall return to Egypt. 14  For Israel hath forgotten his Maker, and buildeth temples; and Judah hath multiplied fenced cities: but I will send a fire upon his cities, and it shall devour the palaces thereof.

9

1  Rejoice not, O Israel, for joy, as other people: for thou hast gone a whoring from thy God, thou hast loved a [*]reward [∥]upon every cornfloor. 2  The floor and the [∥]winepress shall not feed them, and the new wine shall fail in her. 3  They shall not dwell in the LORD’s land; but Ephraim shall return to Egypt, and they shall eat unclean things in Assyria. 4  They shall not offer wine offerings to the LORD, neither shall they be pleasing unto him: their sacrifices shall be unto them as the bread of mourners; all that eat thereof shall be polluted: for their bread for their soul shall not come into the house of the LORD. 5  What will ye do in the solemn day, and in the day of the feast of the LORD? 6  For, lo, they are gone because of [†]destruction: Egypt shall gather them up, Memphis shall bury them: [∥][†]the pleasant places for their silver, nettles shall possess them: thorns shall be in their tabernacles.

7  The days of visitation are come, the days of recompence are come; Israel shall know it: the prophet is a fool, the [†]spiritual man is mad, for the multitude of thine iniquity, and the great hatred. 8  The watchman of Ephraim was with my God: but the prophet is a snare of a fowler in all his ways, and hatred [∥]in the house of his God. 9  They have deeply corrupted themselves, as in the days of [*]Gibeah: therefore he will remember their iniquity, he will visit their sins. 10  I found Israel like grapes in the wilderness; I saw your fathers as the firstripe in the fig tree at her first time: but they went to [*]Baal-peor, and separated themselves unto that shame; and their abominations were according as they loved.

11  As for Ephraim, their glory shall [‡]fly away like a bird, from the birth, and from the womb, and from the conception. 12  Though they bring up their children, yet will I bereave them, that there shall not be a man left: yea, woe also to them when I depart from them! 13  Ephraim, as I saw Tyrus, is planted in a pleasant place: but Ephraim shall bring forth his children to the murderer. 14  Give them, O LORD: what wilt thou give? give them a [†]miscarrying womb and dry breasts. 15  All their wickedness [*]is in Gilgal: for there I hated them: for the wickedness of their doings I will drive them out of mine house, I will love them no more: all their princes are revolters. 16  Ephraim is smitten, their root is dried up, they shall bear no fruit: yea, though they bring forth, yet will I slay even [†]the beloved fruit of their womb. 17  My God will cast them away, because they did not hearken unto him: and they shall be wanderers among the nations.

10

1  Israel is [∥]an empty vine, he bringeth forth fruit unto himself: according to the multitude of his fruit he hath increased the altars; according to the goodness of his land they have made goodly [†]images. 2 [∥] Their heart is divided; now shall they be found faulty: he shall [†]break down their altars, he shall spoil their images. 3  For now they shall say, We have no king, because we feared not the LORD; what then should a king do to us? 4  They have spoken words, swearing falsely in making a covenant: thus judgment springeth up as hemlock in the furrows of the field. 5  The inhabitants of Samaria shall fear because of the calves of Beth-aven: for the people thereof shall mourn over it, and [∥]the priests thereof that rejoiced on it, for the glory thereof, because it is departed from it. 6  It shall be also carried unto Assyria for a present to [*]king Jareb: Ephraim shall receive shame, and Israel shall be ashamed of his own counsel. 7  As for Samaria, her king is cut off as the foam upon [†]the water. 8  The high places also of Aven, the sin of Israel, shall be destroyed: the thorn and the thistle shall come up on their altars; [*]and they shall say to the mountains, Cover us; and to the hills, Fall on us.

9  O Israel, thou hast sinned from the days of Gibeah: there they stood: the battle in Gibeah against the children of iniquity did not overtake them. 10  It is in my desire that I should chastise them; and the people shall be gathered against them, [∥]when they shall bind themselves in their two furrows. 11  And Ephraim is as an heifer that is taught, and loveth to tread out the corn; but I passed over upon [†]her fair neck: I will make Ephraim to ride; Judah shall plow, and Jacob shall break his clods. 12  Sow to yourselves in righteousness, reap in mercy; [*]break up your fallow ground: for it is time to seek the LORD, till he come and rain righteousness upon you. 13  Ye have plowed wickedness, ye have reaped iniquity; ye have eaten the fruit of lies: because thou didst trust in thy way, in the multitude of thy mighty men. 14  Therefore shall a tumult arise among thy people, and all thy fortresses shall be spoiled, as Shalman spoiled [*]Beth-arbel in the day of battle: the mother was dashed in pieces upon her children. 15  So shall Beth-el do unto you because of [†]your great wickedness: in a morning shall the king of Israel utterly be cut off.

11

1  When Israel was a child, then I loved him, and [*]called my son out of Egypt. 2  As they called them, so they went from them: they sacrificed unto Baalim, and burned incense to graven images. 3  I taught Ephraim also to go, taking them by their arms; but they knew not that I healed them. 4  I drew them with cords of a man, with bands of love: and I was to them as they that [†]take off the yoke on their jaws, and I laid meat unto them.

5 ¶ He shall not return into the land of Egypt, but the Assyrian shall be his king, because they refused to return. 6  And the sword shall abide on his cities, and shall consume his branches, and devour them, because of their own counsels. 7  And my people are bent to backsliding from me: though they called them to the most High, [†]none at all would exalt him.

8  How shall I give thee up, Ephraim? how shall I deliver thee, Israel? how shall I make thee as [*]Admah? how shall I set thee as Zeboim? mine heart is turned within me, my repentings are kindled together. 9  I will not execute the fierceness of mine anger, I will not return to destroy Ephraim: for I am God, and not man; the Holy One in the midst of thee: and I will not enter into the city. 10  They shall walk after the LORD: he shall roar like a lion: when he shall roar, then the children shall tremble from the west. 11  They shall tremble as a bird out of Egypt, and as a dove out of the land of Assyria: and I will place them in their houses, saith the LORD. 12  Ephraim compasseth me about with lies, and the house of Israel with deceit: but Judah yet ruleth with God, and is faithful [∥]with the saints.

12

1  Ephraim feedeth on wind, and followeth after the east wind: he daily increaseth lies and desolation; and they do make a covenant with the Assyrians, and oil is carried into Egypt. 2  The LORD hath also a controversy with Judah, and will [†]punish Jacob according to his ways; according to his doings will he recompense him.

3 ¶ He took his brother [*]by the heel in the womb, and by his strength he [†][*]had power with God: 4  Yea, he had power over the angel, and prevailed: he wept, and made supplication unto him: he found him in [*]Beth-el, and there he spake with us; 5  Even the LORD God of hosts; the LORD is his [*]memorial. 6  Therefore turn thou to thy God: keep mercy and judgment, and wait on thy God continually.

7 ¶ He is [∥]a merchant, the balances of deceit are in his hand: he loveth to [∥]oppress. 8  And Ephraim said, Yet I am become rich, I have found me out substance: [∥]in all my labours they shall find none iniquity in me [†]that were sin. 9 And I that am the LORD thy God from the land of Egypt will yet make thee to dwell in tabernacles, as in the days of the solemn feast. 10  I have also spoken by the prophets, and I have multiplied visions, and used similitudes, [†]by the ministry of the prophets. 11  Is there iniquity in Gilead? surely they are vanity: they sacrifice bullocks in [*]Gilgal; yea, their altars are as heaps in the furrows of the fields. 12  And Jacob [*]fled into the country of Syria, and Israel [*]served for a wife, and for a wife he kept sheep. 13 [*] And by a prophet the LORD brought Israel out of Egypt, and by a prophet was he preserved. 14  Ephraim provoked him to anger [†]most bitterly: therefore shall he leave his [†]blood upon him, and his reproach shall his Lord return unto him.

13

1  When Ephraim spake trembling, he exalted himself in Israel; but when he offended in Baal, he died. 2  And now [†]they sin more and more, and have made them molten images of their silver, and idols according to their own understanding, all of it the work of the craftsmen: they say of them, Let [∥]the men that sacrifice kiss the calves. 3  Therefore they shall be as the morning cloud, and as the early dew [‡]that passeth away, as the chaff that is driven with the whirlwind out of the floor, and as the smoke out of the chimney. 4 Yet [*]I am the LORD thy God from the land of Egypt, and thou shalt know no god but me: for there is no saviour beside me.

5 ¶ I did know thee in the wilderness, in the land of [†]great drought. 6  According to their pasture, so were they filled; they were filled, and their heart was exalted; therefore have they forgotten me. 7  Therefore I will be unto them as a lion: as a leopard by the way will I observe them: 8  I will meet them as a bear that is bereaved of her whelps, and will rend the caul of their heart, and there will I devour them like a lion: [†]the wild beast shall tear them.

9 ¶ O Israel, thou hast destroyed thyself; but in me [†]is thine help. 10  I will be thy king: where is any other that may save thee in all thy cities? and thy judges of whom thou saidst, Give me a king and princes? 11  I gave thee a [*]king in mine anger, and took him away in my wrath. 12  The iniquity of Ephraim is bound up; his sin is hid. 13  The sorrows of a travailing woman shall come upon him: he is an unwise son; for he should not stay [†]long in the place of the breaking forth of children. 14  I will ransom them from [†]the power of the grave; I will redeem them from death: [*]O death, I will be thy plagues; O grave, I will be thy destruction: repentance shall be hid from mine eyes.

15 ¶ Though he be fruitful among his brethren, [*]an east wind shall come, the wind of the LORD shall come up from the wilderness, and his spring shall become dry, and his fountain shall be dried up: he shall spoil the treasure of all [†]pleasant vessels. 16  Samaria shall become desolate; for she hath rebelled against her God: they shall fall by the sword: their infants shall be dashed in pieces, and their women with child shall be ripped up.

14

1  O Israel, return unto the LORD thy God; for thou hast fallen by thine iniquity. 2  Take with you words, and turn to the LORD: say unto him, Take away all iniquity, and [∥]receive us graciously: so will we render the [*]calves of our lips. 3  Asshur shall not save us; we will not ride upon horses: neither will we say any more to the work of our hands, Ye are our gods: for in thee the fatherless findeth mercy.

4 ¶ I will heal their backsliding, I will love them freely: for mine anger is turned away from him. 5  I will be as the dew unto Israel: he shall [∥]grow as the lily, and [†]cast forth his roots as Lebanon. 6  His branches [†]shall spread, and his beauty shall be as the olive tree, and his smell as Lebanon. 7  They that dwell under his shadow shall return; they shall revive as the corn, and [∥]grow as the vine: the [∥]scent thereof shall be as the wine of Lebanon.

8  Ephraim shall say, What have I to do any more with idols? I have heard him, and observed him: I am like a green fir tree. From me is thy fruit found. 9 Who is wise, and he shall understand these things? prudent, and he shall know them? for the ways of the LORD are right, and the just shall walk in them: but the transgressors shall fall therein.

† 1.4 Heb. visit.

∥ 1.6 That is, Not having obtained mercy

† 1.6 Heb. I will not add any more to.

∥ 1.6 Or, that I should altogether pardon them.

∥ 1.9 That is, Not my people.

* 1.10 Rom. 9. 25, 26.

∥ 1.10 Or, instead of that

* 1.11 Jer. 3. 18. Ezek. 34. &c 37.

∥ 2.1 That is, My people.

∥ 2.1 That is, Having obtained mercy.

* 2.2 Is 50 1.

* 2.2 Ezek. 16. 25.

* 2.3 Ezek. 16. 4.

† 2.5 Heb. drinks.

† 2.6 Heb. wall a wall.

† 2.8 Heb. new wine.

∥ 2.8 Or, wherewith they made Baal.

∥ 2.9 Or, take away.

† 2.10 Heb. folly, or, villany.

† 2.12 Heb. make desolate.

∥ 2.14 Or, friendly.

† 2.14 Heb. to her heart.

∥ 2.16 That is, My husband.

∥ 2.16 That is, My lord.

* 2.18 Job 5. 23.

* 2.23 Rom. 9. 26 1 Pet. 2. 10.

† 3.1 Heb of grapes.

† 3.2 Heb. lethech.

* 3.3 Deut 21. 13.

† 3.4 Heb. a standing. or, statue.

* 3.5 Jer 30. 9. Ezek. 34. 23.

* 3.5 Is. 2 2.

* 4.1 Mic. 6. 2.

† 4.2 Heb. bloods.

‡ 4.4 [1611 this]

† 4.5 Heb cut off.

† 4.6 Heb. cut off.

† 4.8 Heb. lift up their soul to their iniquity.

* 4.9 Is 24 2.

† 4.9 Heb. visit upon.

† 4.9 Heb. cause to return.

∥ 4.14 Or, Shall I not, &c.

∥ 4.14 Or, be punished

* 4.15 1 Kin. 12. 29.

† 4.18 Heb. is gone.

† 4.18 Heb. shields.

∥ 5.2 Or, and, &c.

† 5.2 Heb. a correction.

† 5.4 Heb. They will not give.

∥ 5.4 Or, Their doings will not suffer them.

∥ 5.12 Or, a worm.

∥ 5.13 Or, to the king of Jareb: or, to the king that should plead.

† 5.15 Heb. till they be guilty.

* 6.2 1 Cor. 15. 4.

∥ 6.4 Or, mercy, or, kindness.

∥ 6.5 Or, that thy judgments might be, &c.

* 6.6 1 Sam. 15 22 Eccles 5 1. Matt 9. 13 &c 12. 7

∥ 6.7 Or, like Adam.

∥ 6.8 Or, cunning for blood.

† 6.9 Heb. with one shoulder, or, to Shechem.

∥ 6.9 Or, enormity

† 7.1 Heb. evils

† 7.1 Heb. strippeth.

† 7.2 Heb. say not to.

∥ 7.4 Or, the raiser will cease.

∥ 7.4 Or, from waking.

∥ 7.5 Or, with heat through wine.

∥ 7.6 Or, applied.

† 7.9 Heb. sprinkled.

* 7.10 ch. 5. 5.

† 7.13 Heb. spoil.

∥ 7.15 Or, chastened.

* 7.16 Ps. 73. 9.

† 8.1 Heb. the roof of thy mouth.

∥ 8.7 Or, standing corn.

† 8.9 Heb. loves

∥ 8.10 Or, begin.

∥ 8.13 Or, In the sacrifices of mine offerings they, &c.

* 9.1 Jer. 44. 17.

∥ 9.1 Or, in, &c.

∥ 9.2 Or, winefat.

† 9.6 Heb. spoil.

∥ 9.6 Or, their silver shall be desired, the nettle, &c.

† 9.6 Heb. the desire.

† 9.7 Heb. man of the spirit.

∥ 9.8 Or, against.

* 9.9 Judg. 19. 18.

* 9.10 Num. 25 3.

‡ 9.11 [1611 flee]

† 9.14 Heb. that casteth the fruit.

* 9.15 ch. 12. 11.

† 9.16 Heb. the desires.

∥ 10.1 Or, a vine emptying the fruit which it giveth.

† 10.1 Heb. statues, or, standing images.

∥ 10.2 Or, He hath divided their heart.

† 10.2 Heb. behead.

∥ 10.5 Or, Chemarim.

* 10.6 ch. 5. 13.

† 10.7 Heb. the face of the water.

* 10.8 Is. 2 19 Luke 23. 30. Rev. 6. 16. &c 9. 6.

∥ 10.10 Or, when I shall bind them for their two transgressions, or, in their two habitations.

† 10.11 Heb. the beauty of her neck.

* 10.12 Jer. 4. 3.

* 10.14 2 Kin. 18 34. &c 19. 13.

† 10.15 Heb. the evil of your evil.

* 11.1 Matt. 2. 15.

† 11.4 Heb. lift up.

† 11.7 Heb together they exalted not.

* 11.8 Gen 19. 24. Amos 4. 11.

∥ 11.12 Or, with the most holy.

† 12.2 Heb. visit upon.

* 12.3 Gen. 25. 26.

† 12.3 Heb was a prince, or, behaved himself princely

* 12.3 Gen. 32. 24.

* 12.4 Gen. 35. 9, 10.

* 12.5 Ex. 3. 15.

∥ 12.7 Or, Canaan

∥ 12.7 Or, deceive.

∥ 12.8 Or, all my labours suffice me not: he shall have punishment of iniquity in whom is sin.

† 12.8 Heb. which.

† 12.10 Heb. by the hand.

* 12.11 ch 4 15. &c 9 15.

* 12.12 Gen. 28. 5.

* 12.12 Gen. 29. 20, 28.

* 12.13 Ex. 12. 50, 51. &c 13. 3.

† 12.14 Heb. with bitternesses.

† 12.14 Heb. bloods.

† 13.2 Heb. they add to sin.

∥ 13.2 Or, the sacrificers of men.

‡ 13.3 [1611 it]

* 13.4 Is 43. 11 ch. 12. 9.

† 13.5 Heb. droughts.

† 13.8 Heb the beast of the field.

† 13.9 Heb in thy help

* 13.11 1 Sam. 8. 5 &c 15. 23. &c 16. 1.

† 13.13 Heb. a time

† 13.14 Heb. the hand.

* 13.14 1 Cor. 15. 55.

* 13.15 Ezek. 19. 12.

† 13.15 Heb. vessels of desire.

∥ 14.2 Or, give good.

* 14.2 Heb. 13. 15.

∥ 14.5 Or, blossom.

† 14.5 Heb. strike.

† 14.6 Heb. shall go.

∥ 14.7 Or, blossom.

∥ 14.7 Or, memorial.

Isaiah

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30

31
32
33
34
35
36
37
38
39
40

41
42
43
44
45
46
47
48
49
50

51
52
53
54
55
56
57
58
59
60

61
62
63
64
65
66

The Book of the Prophet Isaiah

1

1  The vision of Isaiah the son of Amoz, which he saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah.

2 [*] Hear, O heavens, and give ear, O earth: for the LORD hath spoken, I have nourished and brought up children, and they have rebelled against me. 3 [*] The ox knoweth his owner, and the ass his master’s crib: but Israel doth not know, my people doth not consider. 4  Ah sinful nation, a people [†]laden with iniquity, a seed of evildoers, children that are corrupters: they have forsaken the LORD, they have provoked the Holy One of Israel unto anger, they are [†]gone away backward.

5 ¶ Why should ye be stricken any more? ye will [†]revolt more and more: the whole head is sick, and the whole heart faint. 6  From the sole of the foot even unto the head there is no soundness in it; but wounds, and bruises, and putrifying sores: they have not been closed, neither bound up, neither mollified with [∥]ointment. 7 [*] Your country is desolate, your cities are burned with fire: your land, strangers devour it in your presence, and it is desolate, [†]as overthrown by strangers. 8  And the daughter of Zion is left as a cottage in a vineyard, as a lodge in a garden of cucumbers, as a besieged city. 9 [*] Except the LORD of hosts had left unto us a very small remnant, we should have been as [*]Sodom, and we should have been like unto Gomorrah.

10 ¶ Hear the word of the LORD, ye rulers of Sodom; give ear unto the law of our God, ye people of Gomorrah. 11  To what purpose is the multitude of your [*]sacrifices unto me? saith the LORD: I am full of the burnt offerings of rams, and the fat of fed beasts; and I delight not in the blood of bullocks, or of lambs, or of [†]he goats. 12  When ye come [†]to appear before me, who hath required this at your hand, to tread my courts? 13  Bring no more vain oblations; incense is an abomination unto me; the new moons and sabbaths, the calling of assemblies, I cannot away with; it is [∥]iniquity, even the solemn meeting. 14  Your new moons and your appointed feasts my soul hateth: they are a trouble unto me; I am weary to bear them. 15  And [*]when ye spread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you: yea, when ye [†]make many prayers, I will not hear: your hands are full of [*][†]blood.

16 ¶ Wash you, make you clean; put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes; [*]cease to do evil; 17  Learn to do well; seek judgment, [∥]relieve the oppressed, judge the fatherless, plead for the widow. 18  Come now, and let us reason together, saith the LORD: though your sins be as scarlet, they shall be as white as snow; though they be red like crimson, they shall be as wool. 19  If ye be willing and obedient, ye shall eat the good of the land: 20  But if ye refuse and rebel, ye shall be devoured with the sword: for the mouth of the LORD hath spoken it.

21 ¶ How is the faithful city become an harlot! it was full of judgment; righteousness lodged in it; but now murderers. 22  Thy silver is become dross, thy wine mixed with water: 23  Thy princes are rebellious, and companions of thieves: every one loveth gifts, and followeth after rewards: they [*]judge not the fatherless, neither doth the cause of the widow come unto them. 24  Therefore saith the Lord, the LORD of hosts, the mighty One of Israel, Ah, I will ease me of mine adversaries, and avenge me of mine enemies:

25 ¶ And I will turn my hand upon thee, and [†]purely purge away thy dross, and take away all thy tin: 26  And I will restore thy judges as at the first, and thy counsellors as at the beginning: afterward thou shalt be called, The city of righteousness, the faithful city. 27  Zion shall be redeemed with judgment, and [∥]her converts with righteousness.

28 ¶ And the [*][†]destruction of the transgressors and of the sinners shall be together, and they that forsake the LORD shall be consumed. 29  For they shall be ashamed of the oaks which ye have desired, and ye shall be confounded for the gardens that ye have chosen. 30  For ye shall be as an oak whose leaf fadeth, and as a garden that hath no water. 31  And the strong shall be as tow, [∥]and the maker of it as a spark, and they shall both burn together, and none shall quench them.

2

1  The word that Isaiah the son of Amoz saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem. 2  And [*]it shall come to pass in the last days, that the mountain of the LORD’s house shall be [∥]established in the top of the mountains, and shall be exalted above the hills; and all nations shall flow unto it. 3  And many people shall go and say, Come ye, and let us go up to the mountain of the LORD, to the house of the God of Jacob; and he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in his paths: for out of Zion shall go forth the law, and the word of the LORD from Jerusalem. 4  And he shall judge among the nations, and shall rebuke many people: and they shall beat their swords into plowshares, and their spears into [∥]pruninghooks: nation shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall they learn war any more. 5  O house of Jacob, come ye, and let us walk in the light of the LORD.

6 ¶ Therefore thou hast forsaken thy people the house of Jacob, because they be replenished [∥]from the east, and are soothsayers like the Philistines, and they [∥]please themselves in the children of strangers. 7  Their land also is full of silver and gold, neither is there any end of their treasures; their land is also full of horses, neither is there any end of their chariots: 8  Their land also is full of idols; they worship the work of their own hands, that which their own fingers have made: 9  And the mean man boweth down, and the great man humbleth himself: therefore forgive them not.

10 ¶ Enter into the rock, and hide thee in the dust, for fear of the LORD, and for the glory of his majesty. 11  The [*]lofty looks of man shall be humbled, and the haughtiness of men shall be bowed down, and the LORD alone shall be exalted in that day. 12  For the day of the LORD of hosts shall be upon every one that is proud and lofty, and upon every one that is lifted up; and he shall be brought low: 13  And upon all the cedars of Lebanon, that are high and lifted up, and upon all the oaks of Bashan, 14  And upon all the high mountains, and upon all the hills that are lifted up, 15  And upon every high tower, and upon every fenced wall, 16  And upon all the ships of Tarshish, and upon all [†]pleasant pictures. 17  And the loftiness of man shall be bowed down, and the haughtiness of men shall be made low: and the LORD alone shall be exalted in that day. 18  And [∥]the idols he shall utterly abolish. 19  And they shall go into the [*]holes of the rocks, and into the caves of [†]the earth, for fear of the LORD, and for the glory of his majesty, when he ariseth to shake terribly the earth. 20  In that day a man shall cast [†]his idols of silver, and his idols of gold, [∥]which they made each one for himself to worship, to the moles and to the bats; 21  To go into the clefts of the rocks, and into the tops of the ragged rocks, for fear of the LORD, and for the glory of his majesty, when he ariseth to shake terribly the earth. 22  Cease ye from man, whose breath is in his nostrils: for wherein is he to be accounted of?

3

1  For, behold, the Lord, the LORD of hosts, doth take away from Jerusalem and from Judah the stay and the staff, the whole stay of bread, and the whole stay of water, 2  The mighty man, and the man of war, the judge, and the prophet, and the prudent, and the ancient, 3  The captain of fifty, and [†]the honourable man, and the counsellor, and the cunning artificer, and the [∥]eloquent orator. 4  And I will give [*]children to be their princes, and babes shall rule over them. 5  And the people shall be oppressed, every one by another, and every one by his neighbour: the child shall behave himself proudly against the ancient, and the base against the honourable. 6  When a man shall take hold of his brother of the house of his father, saying, Thou hast clothing, be thou our ruler, and let this ruin be under thy hand: 7  In that day shall he [†]swear, saying, I will not be an [†]healer; for in my house is neither bread nor clothing: make me not a ruler of the people. 8  For Jerusalem is ruined, and Judah is fallen: because their tongue and their doings are against the LORD, to provoke the eyes of his glory.

9 ¶ The shew of their countenance doth witness against them; and they declare their sin as [*]Sodom, they hide it not. Woe unto their soul! for they have rewarded evil unto themselves. 10  Say ye to the righteous, that it shall be well with him: for they shall eat the fruit of their doings. 11  Woe unto the wicked! it shall be ill with him: for the reward of his hands shall be [†]given him.

12 ¶ As for my people, children are their oppressors, and women rule over them. O my people, [∥]they which lead thee cause thee to err, and [†]destroy the way of thy paths. 13  The LORD standeth up to plead, and standeth to judge the people. 14  The LORD will enter into judgment with the ancients of his people, and the princes thereof: for ye have [∥]eaten up the vineyard; the spoil of the poor is in your houses. 15 What mean ye that ye beat my people to pieces, and grind the faces of the poor? saith the Lord GOD of hosts.

16 ¶ Moreover the LORD saith, Because the daughters of Zion are haughty, and walk with stretched forth necks and [†]wanton eyes, walking and [∥]mincing as they go, and making a tinkling with their feet: 17  Therefore the Lord will smite with a scab the crown of the head of the daughters of Zion, and the LORD will [†]discover their secret parts. 18  In that day the Lord will take away the bravery of their tinkling ornaments about their feet, and their [∥]cauls, and their round tires like the moon, 19  The [∥]chains, and the bracelets, and the [∥]mufflers, 20  The bonnets, and the ornaments of the legs, and the headbands, and the [†]tablets, and the earrings, 21  The rings, and nose jewels, 22  The changeable suits of apparel, and the mantles, and the wimples, and the crisping pins, 23  The glasses, and the fine linen, and the hoods, and the vails. 24 And it shall come to pass, that instead of sweet smell there shall be stink; and instead of a girdle a rent; and instead of well set hair baldness; and instead of a stomacher a girding of sackcloth; and burning instead of beauty. 25  Thy men shall fall by the sword, and thy [†]mighty in the war. 26  And her gates shall lament and mourn; and she being [∥][†]desolate shall sit upon the ground.

4

1  And in that day seven women shall take hold of one man, saying, We will eat our own bread, and wear our own apparel: only [†]let us be called by thy name, [∥]to take away our reproach.

2  In that day shall the branch of the LORD be [†]beautiful and glorious, and the fruit of the earth shall be excellent and comely [†]for them that are escaped of Israel. 3 And it shall come to pass, that he that is left in Zion, and he that remaineth in Jerusalem, shall be called holy, even every one that is written [∥]among the living in Jerusalem: 4  When the Lord shall have washed away the filth of the daughters of Zion, and shall have purged the blood of Jerusalem from the midst thereof by the spirit of judgment, and by the spirit of burning. 5  And the LORD will create upon every dwelling place of mount Zion, and upon her assemblies, a [*]cloud and smoke by day, and the shining of a flaming fire by night: for [∥]upon all the glory shall be [†]a defence. 6  And there shall be a tabernacle for a shadow in the daytime from the heat, and for a place of refuge, and for a covert from storm and from rain.

5

1  Now will I sing to my wellbeloved a song of my beloved touching his vineyard. My wellbeloved hath a [*]vineyard in [†]a very fruitful hill: 2  And he [∥]fenced it, and gathered out the stones thereof, and planted it with the choicest vine, and built a tower in the midst of it, and also [†]made a winepress therein: and he looked that it should bring forth grapes, and it brought forth wild grapes. 3  And now, O inhabitants of Jerusalem, and men of Judah, judge, I pray you, betwixt me and my vineyard. 4  What could have been done more to my vineyard, that I have not done in it? wherefore, when I looked that it should bring forth grapes, brought it forth wild grapes? 5  And now go to; I will tell you what I will do to my vineyard: I will take away the hedge thereof, and it shall be eaten up; and break down the wall thereof, and it shall be [†]trodden down: 6  And I will lay it waste: it shall not be pruned, nor digged; but there shall come up briers and thorns: I will also command the clouds that they rain no rain upon it. 7  For the vineyard of the LORD of hosts is the house of Israel, and the men of Judah [†]his pleasant plant: and he looked for judgment, but behold [†]oppression; for righteousness, but behold a cry.

8 ¶ Woe unto them that join [*]house to house, that lay field to field, till there be no place, that they may be placed alone in the midst of the earth! 9 [∥] In mine ears said the LORD of hosts, [†]Of a truth many houses shall be desolate, even great and fair, without inhabitant. 10  Yea, ten acres of vineyard shall yield one bath, and the seed of an homer shall yield an ephah.

11 ¶ [*]Woe unto them that rise up early in the morning, that they may follow strong drink; that continue until night, till wine [∥]inflame them! 12  And the harp, and the viol, the tabret, and pipe, and wine, are in their feasts: but they regard not the work of the LORD, neither consider the operation of his hands.

13 ¶ Therefore my people are gone into captivity, because they have no knowledge: and [†]their honourable men are famished, and their multitude dried up with thirst. 14  Therefore hell hath enlarged herself, and opened her mouth without measure: and their glory, and their multitude, and their pomp, and he that rejoiceth, shall descend into it. 15  And [*]the mean man shall be brought down, and the mighty man shall be humbled, and the eyes of the lofty shall be humbled: 16  But the LORD of hosts shall be exalted in judgment, and [∥][†]God that is holy shall be sanctified in righteousness. 17  Then shall the lambs feed after their manner, and the waste places of the fat ones shall strangers eat.

18  Woe unto them that draw iniquity with cords of vanity, and sin as it were with a cart rope: 19  That say, Let him make speed, and hasten his work, that we may see it: and let the counsel of the Holy One of Israel draw nigh and come, that we may know it!

20 ¶ Woe unto them [†]that call evil good, and good evil; that put darkness for light, and light for darkness; that put bitter for sweet, and sweet for bitter! 21  Woe unto them that are [*]wise in their own eyes, and prudent [†]in their own sight! 22  Woe unto them that are mighty to drink wine, and men of strength to mingle strong drink: 23  Which [*]justify the wicked for reward, and take away the righteousness of the righteous from him! 24  Therefore as [†]the fire devoureth the stubble, and the flame consumeth the chaff, so their root shall be as rottenness, and their blossom shall go up as dust: because they have cast away the law of the LORD of hosts, and despised the word of the Holy One of Israel. 25  Therefore is the anger of the LORD kindled against his people, and he hath stretched forth his hand against them, and hath smitten them: and the hills did tremble, and their carcases were [∥]torn in the midst of the streets. [*]For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still.

26 ¶ And he will lift up an ensign to the nations from far, and will hiss unto them from the end of the earth: and, behold, they shall come with speed swiftly: 27  None shall be weary nor stumble among them; none shall slumber nor sleep; neither shall the girdle of their loins be loosed, nor the latchet of their shoes be broken: 28  Whose arrows are sharp, and all their bows bent, their horses’ hoofs shall be counted like flint, and their wheels like a whirlwind: 29  Their roaring shall be like a lion, they shall roar like young lions: yea, they shall roar, and lay hold of the prey, and shall carry it away safe, and none shall deliver it. 30  And in that day they shall roar against them like the roaring of the sea: and if one look unto the land, behold darkness and [∥]sorrow, [∥]and the light is darkened in the heavens thereof.

6

1  In the year that king Uzziah died I [*]saw also the Lord sitting upon a throne, high and lifted up, and [∥]his train filled the temple. 2  Above it stood the seraphims: each one had six wings; with twain he covered his face, and with twain he covered his feet, and with twain he did fly. 3  And [†]one cried unto another, and said, [*]Holy, holy, holy, is the LORD of hosts: [†]the whole earth is full of his glory. 4  And the posts of the [†]door moved at the voice of him that cried, and the house was filled with smoke.

5 ¶ Then said I, Woe is me! for I am [†]undone; because I am a man of unclean lips, and I dwell in the midst of a people of unclean lips: for mine eyes have seen the King, the LORD of hosts. 6  Then flew one of the seraphims unto me, [†]having a live coal in his hand, which he had taken with the tongs from off the altar: 7  And he [†]laid it upon my mouth, and said, Lo, this hath touched thy lips; and thine iniquity is taken away, and thy sin purged. 8  Also I heard the voice of the Lord, saying, Whom shall I send, and who will go for [*]us? Then [‡]said I, [†]Here am I; send me.

9 ¶ And he said, Go, and tell this people, [*]Hear ye [∥][†]indeed, but understand not; and see ye indeed, but perceive not. 10  Make the heart of this people fat, and make their ears heavy, and shut their eyes; lest they see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their heart, and convert, and be healed. 11  Then said I, Lord, how long? And he answered, Until the cities be wasted without inhabitant, and the houses without man, and the land be [†]utterly desolate, 12  And the LORD have removed men far away, and there be a great forsaking in the midst of the land.

13 ¶ But yet in it shall be a tenth, [∥]and it shall return, and shall be eaten: as a teil tree, and as an oak, whose [∥]substance is in them, when they cast their leaves: so the holy seed shall be the substance thereof.

7

1  And it came to pass in the days of [*]Ahaz the son of Jotham, the son of Uzziah, king of Judah, that Rezin the king of Syria, and Pekah the son of Remaliah, king of Israel, went up toward Jerusalem to war against it, but could not prevail against it. 2  And it was told the house of David, saying, Syria [†]is confederate with Ephraim. And his heart was moved, and the heart of his people, as the trees of the wood are moved with the wind. 3  Then said the LORD unto Isaiah, Go forth now to meet Ahaz, thou, and [∥]Shear-jashub thy son, at the end of the [*]conduit of the upper pool in the [∥]highway of the fuller’s field; 4  And say unto him, Take heed, and be quiet; fear not, [†]neither be fainthearted for the two tails of these smoking firebrands, for the fierce anger of Rezin with Syria, and of the son of Remaliah. 5  Because Syria, Ephraim, and the son of Remaliah, have taken evil counsel against thee, saying, 6  Let us go up against Judah, and [∥]vex it, and let us make a breach therein for us, and set a king in the midst of it, even the son of Tabeal: 7  Thus saith the Lord GOD, It shall not stand, neither shall it come to pass. 8  For the head of Syria is Damascus, and the head of Damascus is Rezin; and within threescore and five years shall Ephraim be broken, [†]that it be not a people. 9  And the head of Ephraim is Samaria, and the head of Samaria is Remaliah’s son. [∥]If ye will not believe, surely ye shall not be established.

10 ¶ [†]Moreover the LORD spake again unto Ahaz, saying, 11  Ask thee a sign of the LORD thy God; [∥]ask it either in the depth, or in the height above. 12  But Ahaz said, I will not ask, neither will I tempt the LORD. 13  And he said, Hear ye now, O house of David; Is it a small thing for you to weary men, but will ye weary my God also? 14  Therefore the Lord himself shall give you a sign; [*]Behold, a virgin shall conceive, and bear a son, and [∥]shall call his name Immanuel. 15  Butter and honey shall he eat, that he may know to refuse the evil, and choose the good. 16  For before the child shall know to refuse the evil, and choose the good, the land that thou abhorrest shall be forsaken of both her kings.

17 ¶ The LORD shall bring upon thee, and upon thy people, and upon thy father’s house, days that have not come, from the day that Ephraim departed from Judah; even the king of Assyria. 18  And it shall come to pass in that day, that the LORD shall hiss for the fly that is in the uttermost part of the rivers of Egypt, and for the bee that is in the land of Assyria. 19  And they shall come, and shall rest all of them in the desolate valleys, and in the holes of the rocks, and upon all thorns, and upon all [∥]bushes. 20  In the same day shall the Lord shave with a [*]razor that is hired, namely, by them beyond the river, by the king of Assyria, the head, and the hair of the feet: and it shall also consume the beard. 21  And it shall come to pass in that day, that a man shall nourish a young cow, and two sheep; 22  And it shall come to pass, for the abundance of milk that they shall give he shall eat butter: for butter and honey shall every one eat that is left [†]in the land. 23  And it shall come to pass in that day, that every place shall be, where there were a thousand vines at a thousand silverlings, it shall even be for briers and thorns. 24  With arrows and with bows shall men come thither; because all the land shall become briers and thorns. 25 And on all hills that shall be digged with the mattock, there shall not come thither the fear of briers and thorns: but it shall be for the sending forth of oxen, and for the treading of lesser cattle.

8

1  Moreover the LORD said unto me, Take thee a great roll, and write in it with a man’s pen concerning [†]Maher-shalal-hash-baz. 2  And I took unto me faithful witnesses to record, Uriah the priest, and Zechariah the son of Jeberechiah. 3  And I [†]went unto the prophetess; and she conceived, and bare a son. Then said the LORD to me, Call his name Maher-shalal-hash-baz. 4  For before the child shall have knowledge to cry, My father, and my mother, [∥]the riches of Damascus and the spoil of Samaria shall be taken away before the king of Assyria.

5 ¶ The LORD spake also unto me again, saying, 6  Forasmuch as this people refuseth the waters of Shiloah that go softly, and rejoice in Rezin and Remaliah’s son; 7  Now therefore, behold, the Lord bringeth up upon them the waters of the river, strong and many, even the king of Assyria, and all his glory: and he shall come up over all his channels, and go over all his banks: 8  And he shall pass through Judah; he shall overflow and go over, he shall reach even to the neck; and [†]the stretching out of his wings shall fill the breadth of thy land, O Immanuel.

9 ¶ Associate yourselves, O ye people, [∥]and ye shall be broken in pieces; and give ear, all ye of far countries: gird yourselves, and ye shall be broken in pieces; gird yourselves, and ye shall be broken in pieces. 10  Take counsel together, and it shall come to nought; speak the word, and it shall not stand: for God is with us.

11 ¶ For the LORD spake thus to me [†]with a strong hand, and instructed me that I should not walk in the way of this people, saying, 12  Say ye not, A confederacy, to all them to whom this people shall say, A confederacy; neither fear ye their fear, nor be afraid. 13  Sanctify the LORD of hosts himself; and let him be your fear, and let him be your dread. 14  And he shall be for a sanctuary; but for [*]a stone of stumbling and for a rock of offence to both the houses of Israel, for a gin and for a snare to the inhabitants of Jerusalem. 15  And many among them shall [*]stumble, and fall, and be broken, and be snared, and be taken.

16  Bind up the testimony, seal the law among my disciples. 17  And I will wait upon the LORD, that hideth his face from the house of Jacob, and I will look for him. 18 [*] Behold, I and the children whom the LORD hath given me are for signs and for wonders in Israel from the LORD of hosts, which dwelleth in mount Zion.

19 ¶ And when they shall say unto you, Seek unto them that have familiar spirits, and unto wizards that peep, and that mutter: should not a people seek unto their God? for the living to the dead? 20 [*] To the law and to the testimony: if they speak not according to this word, it is because there is [†]no light in them. 21  And they shall pass through it, hardly bestead and hungry: and it shall come to pass, that when they shall be hungry, they shall fret themselves, and curse their king and their God, and look upward. 22  And they shall look unto the earth; and behold trouble and darkness, dimness of anguish; and they shall be driven to darkness.

9

1  Nevertheless the dimness shall not be such as was in her vexation, when at the first he lightly afflicted the land of Zebulun and the land of Naphtali, and afterward did more grievously afflict her by the way of the sea, beyond Jordan, in Galilee [∥]of the nations. 2 [*] The people that walked in darkness have seen a great light: they that dwell in the land of the shadow of death, upon them hath the light shined. 3  Thou hast multiplied the nation, and [∥]not increased the joy: they joy before thee according to the joy in harvest, and as men rejoice when they divide the spoil. 4 [∥] For thou hast broken the yoke of his burden, and the staff of his shoulder, the rod of his oppressor, as in the day of [*]Midian. 5 [∥] For every battle of the warrior is with confused noise, and garments rolled in blood; [∥]but this shall be with burning and [†]fuel of fire. 6  For unto us a child is born, unto us a [*]son is given: and the government shall be upon his shoulder: and his name shall be called Wonderful, Counsellor, The mighty God, The everlasting Father, The Prince of Peace. 7  Of the increase of his government and peace [*]there shall be no end, upon the throne of David, and upon his kingdom, to order it, and to establish it with judgment and with justice from henceforth even for ever. The [*]zeal of the LORD of hosts will perform this.

8 ¶ The Lord sent a word into Jacob, and it hath lighted upon Israel. 9  And all the people shall know, even Ephraim and the inhabitant of Samaria, that say in the pride and stoutness of heart, 10  The bricks are fallen down, but we will build with hewn stones: the sycomores are cut down, but we will change them into cedars. 11  Therefore the LORD shall set up the adversaries of Rezin against him, and [†]join his enemies together; 12  The Syrians before, and the Philistines behind; and they shall devour Israel [†]with open mouth. [*]For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still.

13 ¶ For the people turneth not unto him that smiteth them, neither do they seek the LORD of hosts. 14  Therefore the LORD will cut off from Israel head and tail, branch and rush, in one day. 15  The ancient and honourable, he is the head; and the prophet that teacheth lies, he is the tail. 16  For [∥]the leaders of this people cause them to err; and [∥]they that are led of them are [†]destroyed. 17  Therefore the Lord shall have no joy in their young men, neither shall have mercy on their fatherless and widows: for every one is an hypocrite and an evildoer, and every mouth speaketh [∥]folly. For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still.

18 ¶ For wickedness burneth as the fire: it shall devour the briers and thorns, and shall kindle in the thickets of the forest, and they shall mount up like the lifting up of smoke. 19  Through the wrath of the LORD of hosts is the land darkened, and the people shall be as the [†]fuel of the fire: no man shall spare his brother. 20  And he shall [†]snatch on the right hand, and be hungry; and he shall eat on the left hand, and they shall not be satisfied: they shall eat every man the flesh of his own arm: 21  Manasseh, Ephraim; and Ephraim, Manasseh: and they together shall be against Judah. For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still.

10

1  Woe unto them that decree unrighteous decrees, and [∥]that write grievousness which they have prescribed; 2  To turn aside the needy from judgment, and to take away the right from the poor of my people, that widows may be their prey, and that they may rob the fatherless! 3  And what will ye do in the day of visitation, and in the desolation which shall come from far? to whom will ye flee for help? and where will ye leave your glory? 4  Without me they shall bow down under the prisoners, and they shall fall under the slain. [*]For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still.

5 ¶ [∥]O [†]Assyrian, the rod of mine anger, [∥]and the staff in their hand is mine indignation. 6  I will send him against an hypocritical nation, and against the people of my wrath will I give him a charge, to take the spoil, and to take the prey, and [†]to tread them down like the mire of the streets. 7  Howbeit he meaneth not so, neither doth his heart think so; but it is in his heart to destroy and cut off nations not a few. 8 [*] For he saith, Are not my princes altogether kings? 9  Is not Calno as Carchemish? is not Hamath as Arpad? is not Samaria as Damascus? 10  As my hand hath found the kingdoms of the idols, and whose graven images did excel them of Jerusalem and of Samaria; 11  Shall I not, as I have done unto Samaria and her idols, so do to Jerusalem and her idols? 12 Wherefore it shall come to pass, that when the Lord hath performed his whole work [*]upon mount Zion and on Jerusalem, I will [†]punish the fruit [†]of the stout heart of the king of Assyria, and the glory of his high looks. 13  For he saith, By the strength of my hand I have done it, and by my wisdom; for I am prudent: and I have removed the bounds of the people, and have robbed their treasures, and I have put down the inhabitants [∥]like a valiant man: 14  And my hand hath found as a nest the riches of the people: and as one gathereth eggs that are left, have I gathered all the earth; and there was none that moved the wing, or opened the mouth, or peeped. 15  Shall the axe boast itself against him that heweth therewith? or shall the saw magnify itself against him that shaketh it? [∥]as if the rod should shake itself against them that lift it up, or as if the staff should lift up [∥]itself, as if it were no wood. 16  Therefore shall the Lord, the Lord of hosts, send among his fat ones leanness; and under his glory he shall kindle a burning like the burning of a fire. 17  And the light of Israel shall be for a fire, and his Holy One for a flame: and it shall burn and devour his thorns and his briers in one day; 18  And shall consume the glory of his forest, and of his fruitful field, [†]both soul and body: and they shall be as when a standardbearer fainteth. 19  And the rest of the trees of his forest shall be [†]few, that a child may write them.

20 ¶ And it shall come to pass in that day, that the remnant of Israel, and such as are escaped of the house of Jacob, shall no more again stay upon him that smote them; but shall stay upon the LORD, the Holy One of Israel, in truth. 21  The remnant shall return, even the remnant of Jacob, unto the mighty God. 22 [*] For though thy people Israel be as the sand of the sea, yet a remnant [†]of them shall return: [*]the consumption decreed shall overflow [∥]with righteousness. 23 [*] For the Lord GOD of hosts shall make a consumption, even determined, in the midst of all the land.

24 ¶ Therefore thus saith the Lord GOD of hosts, O my people that dwellest in Zion, be not afraid of the Assyrian: he shall smite thee with a rod, [∥]and shall lift up his staff against thee, after the manner of [*]Egypt. 25  For yet a very little while, and the indignation shall cease, and mine anger in their destruction. 26  And the LORD of hosts shall stir up a scourge for him according to the slaughter of [*]Midian at the rock of Oreb: and as his rod was upon the sea, so shall he lift it up after the manner of Egypt. 27  And it shall come to pass in that day, that his burden [†]shall be taken away from off thy shoulder, and his yoke from off thy neck, and the yoke shall be destroyed because of the anointing. 28  He is come to Aiath, he is passed to Migron; at Michmash he hath laid up his carriages: 29  They are gone over the passage: they have taken up their lodging at Geba; Ramah is afraid; Gibeah of Saul is fled. 30 [†] Lift up thy voice, O daughter of Gallim: cause it to be heard unto Laish, O poor Anathoth. 31  Madmenah is removed; the inhabitants of Gebim gather themselves to flee. 32  As yet shall he remain at Nob that day: he shall shake his hand against the mount of the daughter of Zion, the hill of Jerusalem. 33  Behold, the Lord, the LORD of hosts, shall lop the bough with terror: and the high ones of stature shall be hewn down, and the haughty shall be humbled. 34  And he shall cut down the thickets of the [‡]forest with iron, and Lebanon shall fall [∥]by a mighty one.

11

1  And there shall come forth a rod out of the stem of [*]Jesse, and a Branch shall grow out of his roots: 2  And the spirit of the LORD shall rest upon him, the spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of counsel and might, the spirit of knowledge and of the fear of the LORD; 3  And shall make him of [†]quick understanding in the fear of the LORD: and he shall not judge after the sight of his eyes, neither reprove after the hearing of his ears: 4  But with righteousness shall he judge the poor, and [∥]reprove with equity for the meek of the earth: and he shall [*]smite the earth with the rod of his mouth, and with the breath of his lips shall he slay the wicked. 5  And righteousness shall be the girdle of his loins, and faithfulness the girdle of his reins. 6 [*] The wolf also shall dwell with the lamb, and the leopard shall lie down with the kid; and the calf and the young lion and the fatling together; and a little child shall lead them. 7  And the cow and the bear shall feed; their young ones shall lie down together: and the lion shall eat straw like the ox. 8  And the sucking child shall play on the hole of the asp, and the weaned child shall put his hand on the [∥]cockatrice’ den. 9  They shall not hurt nor destroy in all my holy mountain: for the earth shall be full of the knowledge of the LORD, as the waters cover the sea.

10 ¶ And in that day there shall be a root of Jesse, which shall stand for an ensign of the people; to it shall the [*]Gentiles seek: and his rest shall be [†]glorious. 11  And it shall come to pass in that day, that the Lord shall set his hand again the second time to recover the remnant of his people, which shall be left, from Assyria, and from Egypt, and from Pathros, and from Cush, and from Elam, and from Shinar, and from Hamath, and from the islands of the sea. 12  And he shall set up an ensign for the nations, and shall assemble the outcasts of Israel, and gather together the dispersed of Judah from the four [†]corners of the earth. 13  The envy also of Ephraim shall depart, and the adversaries of Judah shall be cut off: Ephraim shall not envy Judah, and Judah shall not vex Ephraim. 14  But they shall fly upon the shoulders of the Philistines toward the west; they shall spoil [†]them of the east together: [†]they shall lay their hand upon Edom and Moab; [†]and the children of Ammon shall obey them. 15  And the LORD shall utterly destroy the tongue of the Egyptian sea; and with his mighty wind shall he shake his hand over the river, and shall smite it in the seven streams, and make men go over [†]dryshod. 16  And there shall be an highway for the remnant of his people, which shall be left, from Assyria; [*]like as it was to Israel in the day that he came up out of the land of Egypt.

12

1  And in that day thou shalt say, O LORD, I will praise thee: though thou wast angry with me, thine anger is turned away, and thou comfortedst me. 2  Behold, God is my salvation; I will trust, and not be afraid: for the LORD JEHOVAH is my [*]strength and my song; he also is become my salvation. 3  Therefore with joy shall ye draw water out of the wells of salvation.

4  And in that day shall ye say, [*]Praise the LORD, [∥]call upon his name, declare his doings among the people, make mention that his name is exalted. 5  Sing unto the LORD; for he hath done excellent things: this is known in all the earth. 6  Cry out and shout, thou [†]inhabitant of Zion: for great is the Holy One of Israel in the midst of thee.

13

1  The burden of Babylon, which Isaiah the son of Amoz did see. 2  Lift ye up a banner upon the high mountain, exalt the voice unto them, shake the hand, that they may go into the gates of the nobles. 3  I have commanded my sanctified ones, I have also called my mighty ones for mine anger, even them that rejoice in my highness. 4  The noise of a multitude in the mountains, [†]like as of a great people; a tumultuous noise of the kingdoms of nations gathered together: the LORD of hosts mustereth the host of the battle. 5  They come from a far country, from the end of heaven, even the LORD, and the weapons of his indignation, to destroy the whole land.

6 ¶ Howl ye; for the day of the LORD is at hand; it shall come as a destruction from the Almighty. 7  Therefore shall all hands [∥]be faint, and every man’s heart shall melt: 8  And they shall be afraid: pangs and sorrows shall take hold of them; they shall be in pain as a woman that travaileth: they shall [†]be amazed [†]one at another; their faces shall be as [†]flames. 9  Behold, the day of the LORD cometh, cruel both with wrath and fierce anger, to lay the land desolate: and he shall destroy the sinners thereof out of it. 10  For the stars of heaven and the constellations thereof shall not give their light: the sun shall be [*]darkened in his going forth, and the moon shall not cause her light to shine. 11  And I will punish the world for their evil, and the wicked for their iniquity; and I will cause the arrogancy of the proud to cease, and will lay low the haughtiness of the terrible. 12  I will make a man more precious than fine gold; even a man than the golden wedge of Ophir. 13  Therefore I will shake the heavens, and the earth shall remove out of her place, in the wrath of the LORD of hosts, and in the day of his fierce anger. 14  And it shall be as the chased roe, and as a sheep that no man taketh up: they shall every man turn to his own people, and flee every one into his own land. 15  Every one that is found shall be thrust through; and every one that is joined unto them shall fall by the sword. 16  Their children also shall be [*]dashed to pieces before their eyes; their houses shall be spoiled, and their wives ravished. 17  Behold, I will stir up the Medes against them, which shall not regard silver; and as for gold, they shall not delight in it. 18  Their bows also shall dash the young men to pieces; and they shall have no pity on the fruit of the womb; their eye shall not spare children.

19 ¶ And Babylon, the glory of kingdoms, the beauty of the Chaldees’ excellency, shall be [†]as when God overthrew [*]Sodom and Gomorrah. 20  It shall never be inhabited, neither shall it be dwelt in from generation to generation: neither shall the Arabian pitch tent there; neither shall the shepherds make their fold there. 21  But [†]wild beasts of the desert shall lie there; and their houses shall be full of [†]doleful creatures; and [∥][†]owls shall dwell there, and satyrs shall dance there. 22  And [†]the wild beasts of the islands shall cry in their [∥]desolate houses, and dragons in their pleasant palaces: and her time is near to come, and her days shall not be prolonged.

14

1  For the LORD will have mercy on Jacob, and will yet choose Israel, and set them in their own land: and the strangers shall be joined with them, and they shall cleave to the house of Jacob. 2  And the people shall take them, and bring them to their place: and the house of Israel shall possess them in the land of the LORD for servants and handmaids: and they shall take them captives, [†]whose captives they were; and they shall rule over their oppressors. 3  And it shall come to pass in the day that the LORD shall give thee rest from thy sorrow, and from thy fear, and from the hard bondage wherein thou wast made to serve,

4 ¶ That thou shalt take up this [∥]proverb against the king of Babylon, and say, How hath the oppressor ceased! the [∥]golden city ceased! 5  The LORD hath broken the staff of the wicked, and the sceptre of the rulers. 6  He who smote the people in wrath with [†]a continual stroke, he that ruled the nations in anger, is persecuted, and none hindereth. 7  The whole earth is at rest, and is quiet: they break forth into singing. 8  Yea, the fir trees rejoice at thee, and the cedars of Lebanon, saying, Since thou art laid down, no feller is come up against us. 9 [∥] Hell from beneath is moved for thee to meet thee at thy coming: it stirreth up the dead for thee, even all the [†][∥]chief ones of the earth; it hath raised up from their thrones all the kings of the nations. 10  All they shall speak and say unto thee, Art thou also become weak as we? art thou become like unto us? 11  Thy pomp is brought down to the grave, and the noise of thy viols: the worm is spread under thee, and the worms cover thee. 12  How art thou fallen from heaven, [∥]O Lucifer, son of the morning! how art thou cut down to the ground, which didst weaken the nations! 13  For thou hast said in thine heart, I will ascend into heaven, I will exalt my throne above the stars of God: I will sit also upon the mount of the congregation, in the sides of the north: 14  I will ascend above the heights of the clouds; I will be like the most High. 15  Yet thou shalt be brought down to hell, to the sides of the pit. 16  They that see thee shall narrowly look upon thee, and consider thee, saying, Is this the man that made the earth to tremble, that did shake kingdoms; 17  That made the world as a wilderness, and destroyed the cities thereof; that [∥]opened not the house of his prisoners? 18  All the kings of the nations, even all of them, lie in glory, every one in his own house. 19  But thou art cast out of thy grave like an abominable branch, and as the raiment of those that are slain, thrust through with a sword, that go down to the stones of the pit; as a carcase trodden under feet. 20  Thou shalt not be joined with them in burial, because thou hast destroyed thy land, and slain thy people: [*]the seed of evildoers shall never be renowned. 21  Prepare slaughter for his children [*]for the iniquity of their fathers; that they do not rise, nor possess the land, nor fill the face of the world with cities. 22  For I will rise up against them, saith the LORD of hosts, and cut off from Babylon the name, and remnant, and son, and nephew, saith the LORD. 23  I will also make it a possession for the bittern, and pools of water: and I will sweep it with the besom of destruction, saith the LORD of hosts.

24 ¶ The LORD of hosts hath sworn, saying, Surely as I have thought, so shall it come to pass; and as I have purposed, so shall it stand: 25  That I will break the Assyrian in my land, and upon my mountains tread him under foot: then shall his yoke depart from off them, and his burden depart from off their shoulders. 26 This is the purpose that is purposed upon the whole earth: and this is the hand that is stretched out upon all the nations. 27  For the LORD of hosts hath [*]purposed, and who shall disannul it? and his hand is stretched out, and who shall turn it back? 28  In the year that king Ahaz died was this burden.

29 ¶ Rejoice not thou, whole Palestina, because the rod of him that smote thee is broken: for out of the serpent’s root shall come forth a [∥]cockatrice, and his fruit shall be a fiery flying serpent. 30  And the firstborn of the poor shall feed, and the needy shall lie down in safety: and I will kill thy root with famine, and he shall slay thy remnant. 31  Howl, O gate; cry, O city; thou, whole Palestina, art dissolved: for there shall come from the north a smoke, and [∥]none shall be alone in his [∥]appointed times. 32 What shall one then answer the messengers of the nation? That [*]the LORD hath founded Zion, and the poor of his people shall [∥]trust in it.

15

1  The burden of Moab. Because in the night Ar of Moab is laid waste, and [∥]brought to silence; because in the night Kir of Moab is laid waste, and brought to silence; 2  He is gone up to Bajith, and to Dibon, the high places, to weep: Moab shall howl over Nebo, and over Medeba: [*]on all their heads shall be baldness, and every beard cut off. 3  In their streets they shall gird themselves with sackcloth: on the tops of their houses, and in their streets, every one shall howl, [†]weeping abundantly. 4  And Heshbon shall cry, and Elealeh: their voice shall be heard even unto Jahaz: therefore the armed soldiers of Moab shall cry out; his life shall be grievous unto him. 5  My heart shall cry out for Moab; [∥]his fugitives shall flee unto Zoar, an [*]heifer of three years old: for by the mounting up of Luhith with weeping shall they go it up; for in the way of Horonaim they shall raise up a cry of [†]destruction.

6  For the waters of Nimrim shall be [†]desolate: for the hay is withered away, the grass faileth, there is no green thing. 7  Therefore the abundance they have gotten, and that which they have laid up, shall they carry away to the [∥]brook of the willows. 8  For the cry is gone round about the borders of Moab; the howling thereof unto Eglaim, and the howling thereof unto Beer-elim. 9  For the waters of Dimon shall be full of blood: for I will bring [†]more upon Dimon, lions upon him that escapeth of Moab, and upon the remnant of the land.

16

1  Send ye the lamb to the ruler of the land from [∥][†]Sela to the wilderness, unto the mount of the daughter of Zion. 2 For it shall be, that, as a wandering bird [∥]cast out of the nest, so the daughters of Moab shall be at the fords of Arnon. 3 [†] Take counsel, execute judgment; make thy shadow as the night in the midst of the noonday; hide the outcasts; bewray not him that wandereth. 4  Let mine outcasts dwell with thee, Moab; be thou a covert to them from the face of the spoiler: for the [†]extortioner is at an end, the spoiler ceaseth, [†]the oppressors are consumed out of the land. 5  And in mercy [*]shall the throne be [∥]established: and he shall sit upon it in truth in the tabernacle of David, judging, and seeking judgment, and hasting righteousness.

6 ¶ We have heard of the [*]pride of Moab; he is very proud: even of his haughtiness, and his pride, and his wrath: but his lies shall not be so. 7  Therefore shall Moab [*]howl for Moab, every one shall howl: for the foundations of Kir-hareseth shall ye [∥]mourn; surely they are stricken. 8  For the fields of Heshbon languish, and the vine of Sibmah: the lords of the heathen have broken down the principal plants thereof, they are come even unto Jazer, they wandered through the wilderness: her branches are [∥]stretched out, they are gone over the sea.

9 ¶ Therefore I will bewail with the weeping of Jazer the vine of Sibmah: I will water thee with my tears, O Heshbon, and Elealeh: for [∥]the shouting for thy summer fruits and for thy harvest is fallen. 10  And [*]gladness is taken away, and joy out of the plentiful field; and in the vineyards there shall be no singing, neither shall there be shouting: the treaders shall tread out no wine in their presses; I have made their vintage shouting to cease. 11  Wherefore my bowels shall sound like an harp for Moab, and mine inward parts for Kir-haresh.

12 ¶ And it shall come to pass, when it is seen that Moab is weary on the high place, that he shall come to his sanctuary to pray; but he shall not prevail. 13 This is the word that the LORD hath spoken concerning Moab since that time. 14  But now the LORD hath spoken, saying, Within three years, as the years of an hireling, and the glory of Moab shall be contemned, with all that great multitude; and the remnant shall be very small and [∥]feeble.

17

1  The burden of Damascus. Behold, Damascus is taken away from being a city, and it shall be a ruinous heap. 2  The cities of Aroer are forsaken: they shall be for flocks, which shall lie down, and none shall make them afraid. 3  The fortress also shall cease from Ephraim, and the kingdom from Damascus, and the remnant of Syria: they shall be as the glory of the children of Israel, saith the LORD of hosts. 4  And in that day it shall come to pass, that the glory of Jacob shall be made thin, and the fatness of his flesh shall wax lean. 5  And it shall be as when the harvestman gathereth the corn, and reapeth the ears with his arm; and it shall be as he that gathereth ears in the valley of Rephaim.

6 ¶ Yet gleaning grapes shall be left in it, as the shaking of an olive tree, two or three berries in the top of the uppermost bough, four or five in the outmost fruitful branches thereof, saith the LORD God of Israel. 7  At that day shall a man look to his Maker, and his eyes shall have respect to the Holy One of Israel. 8  And he shall not look to the altars, the work of his hands, neither shall respect that which his fingers have made, either the groves, or the [∥]images.

9 ¶ In that day shall his strong cities be as a forsaken bough, and an uppermost branch, which they left because of the children of Israel: and there shall be desolation. 10  Because thou hast forgotten the God of thy salvation, and hast not been mindful of the rock of thy strength, therefore shalt thou plant pleasant plants, and shalt set it with strange slips: 11  In the day shalt thou make thy plant to grow, and in the morning shalt thou make thy seed to flourish: but the harvest shall be a [∥]heap in the day of grief and of desperate sorrow.

12 ¶ Woe to the [∥]multitude of many people, which make a noise like the noise of the seas; and to the rushing of nations, that make a rushing like the rushing of [∥]mighty waters! 13  The nations shall rush like the rushing of many waters: but God shall rebuke them, and they shall flee far off, and shall be chased as the chaff of the mountains before the wind, and like [∥]a rolling thing before the whirlwind. 14  And behold at eveningtide trouble; and before the morning he is not. This is the portion of them that spoil us, and the lot of them that rob us.

18

1  Woe to the land shadowing with wings, which is beyond the rivers of Ethiopia: 2  That sendeth ambassadors by the sea, even in vessels of bulrushes upon the waters, saying, Go, ye swift messengers, to a nation [∥]scattered and peeled, to a people terrible from their beginning hitherto; [∥][†]a nation meted out and trodden down, [∥]whose land the rivers have spoiled! 3  All ye inhabitants of the world, and dwellers on the earth, see ye, when he lifteth up an ensign on the mountains; and when he bloweth a trumpet, hear ye. 4  For so the LORD said unto me, I will take my rest, and I will [∥]consider in my dwelling place like a clear heat [∥]upon herbs, and like a cloud of dew in the heat of harvest. 5  For afore the harvest, when the bud is perfect, and the sour grape is ripening in the flower, he shall both cut off the sprigs with pruning hooks, and take away and cut down the branches. 6  They shall be left together unto the fowls of the mountains, and to the beasts of the earth: and the fowls shall summer upon them, and all the beasts of the earth shall winter upon them.

7 ¶ In that time shall the present be brought unto the LORD of hosts of a people [∥]scattered and peeled, and from a people terrible from their beginning hitherto; a nation meted out and trodden under foot, whose land the rivers have spoiled, to the place of the name of the LORD of hosts, the mount Zion.

19

1  The burden of Egypt. Behold, the LORD rideth upon a swift cloud, and shall come into Egypt: and the idols of Egypt shall be moved at his presence, and the heart of Egypt shall melt in the midst of it. 2  And I will [†]set the Egyptians against the Egyptians: and they shall fight every one against his brother, and every one against his neighbour; city against city, and kingdom against kingdom. 3  And the spirit of Egypt [†]shall fail in the midst thereof; and I will [†]destroy the counsel thereof: and they shall seek to the idols, and to the charmers, and to them that have familiar spirits, and to the wizards. 4  And the Egyptians will I [∥]give over into the hand of a cruel lord; and a fierce king shall rule over them, saith the Lord, the LORD of hosts. 5  And the waters shall fail from the sea, and the river shall be wasted and dried up. 6  And they shall turn the rivers far away; and the brooks of defence shall be emptied and dried up: the reeds and flags shall wither. 7  The paper reeds by the brooks, by the mouth of the brooks, and every thing sown by the brooks, shall wither, be driven away, [†]and be no more. 8  The fishers also shall mourn, and all they that cast angle into the brooks shall lament, and they that spread nets upon the waters shall languish. 9  Moreover they that work in fine flax, and they that weave [∥]networks, shall be confounded. 10  And they shall be broken in the [†]purposes thereof, all that make sluices and ponds [†]for fish.

11 ¶ Surely the princes of Zoan are fools, the counsel of the wise counsellors of Pharaoh is become brutish: how say ye unto Pharaoh, I am the son of the wise, the son of ancient kings? 12  Where are they? where are thy wise men? and let them tell thee now, and let them know what the LORD of hosts hath purposed upon Egypt. 13  The princes of Zoan are become fools, the princes of Noph are deceived; they have also seduced Egypt, even [∥][†]they that are the stay of the tribes thereof. 14  The LORD hath mingled [†]a perverse spirit in the midst thereof: and they have caused Egypt to err in every work thereof, as a drunken man staggereth in his vomit. 15 Neither shall there be any work for Egypt, which the head or tail, branch or rush, may do. 16  In that day shall Egypt be like unto women: and it shall be afraid and fear because of the shaking of the hand of the LORD of hosts, which he shaketh over it. 17  And the land of Judah shall be a terror unto Egypt, every one that maketh mention thereof shall be afraid in himself, because of the counsel of the LORD of hosts, which he hath determined against it.

18 ¶ In that day shall five cities in the land of Egypt speak [†]the language of Canaan, and swear to the LORD of hosts; one shall be called, The city [∥]of destruction. 19  In that day shall there be an altar to the LORD in the midst of the land of Egypt, and a pillar at the border thereof to the LORD. 20  And it shall be for a sign and for a witness unto the LORD of hosts in the land of Egypt: for they shall cry unto the LORD because of the oppressors, and he shall send them a saviour, and a great one, and he shall deliver them. 21  And the LORD shall be known to Egypt, and the Egyptians shall know the LORD in that day, and shall do sacrifice and oblation; yea, they shall vow a vow unto the LORD, and perform it. 22  And the LORD shall smite Egypt: he shall smite and heal it: and they shall return even to the LORD, and he shall be intreated of them, and shall heal them.

23 ¶ In that day shall there be a highway out of Egypt to Assyria, and the Assyrian shall come into Egypt, and the Egyptian into Assyria, and the Egyptians shall serve with the Assyrians. 24  In that day shall Israel be the third with Egypt and with Assyria, even a blessing in the midst of the land: 25  Whom the LORD of hosts shall bless, saying, Blessed be Egypt my people, and Assyria the work of my hands, and Israel mine inheritance.

20

1  In the year that Tartan came unto Ashdod, (when Sargon the king of Assyria sent him,) and fought against Ashdod, and took it; 2  At the same time spake the LORD [†]by Isaiah the son of Amoz, saying, Go and loose the sackcloth from off thy loins, and put off thy shoe from thy foot. And he did so, walking naked and barefoot. 3  And the LORD said, Like as my servant Isaiah hath walked naked and barefoot three years for a sign and wonder upon Egypt and upon Ethiopia; 4  So shall the king of Assyria lead away [†]the Egyptians prisoners, and the Ethiopians captives, young and old, naked and barefoot, even with their buttocks uncovered, to the [†]shame of Egypt. 5  And they shall be afraid and ashamed of Ethiopia their expectation, and of Egypt their glory. 6  And the inhabitant of this [∥]isle shall say in that day, Behold, such is our expectation, whither we flee for help to be delivered from the king of Assyria: and how shall we escape?

21

1  The burden of the desert of the sea. As whirlwinds in the south pass through; so it cometh from the desert, from a terrible land. 2  A [†]grievous vision is declared unto me; the treacherous dealer dealeth treacherously, and the spoiler spoileth. Go up, O Elam: besiege, O Media; all the sighing thereof have I made to cease. 3  Therefore are my loins filled with pain: pangs have taken hold upon me, as the pangs of a woman that travaileth: I was bowed down at the hearing of it; I was dismayed at the seeing of it. 4 [∥] My heart panted, fearfulness affrighted me: the night of my pleasure hath he [†]turned into fear unto me. 5  Prepare the table, watch in the watchtower, eat, drink: arise, ye princes, and anoint the shield. 6  For thus hath the Lord said unto me, Go, set a watchman, let him declare what he seeth. 7  And he saw a chariot with a couple of horsemen, a chariot of asses, and a chariot of camels; and he hearkened diligently with much heed: 8  And [∥]he cried, A lion: My lord, I stand continually upon the [*]watchtower in the daytime, and I am set in my ward [∥]whole nights: 9  And, behold, here cometh a chariot of men, with a couple of horsemen. And he answered and said, [*]Babylon is fallen, is fallen; and all the graven images of her gods he hath broken unto the ground. 10  O my threshing, and the [†]corn of my floor: that which I have heard of the LORD of hosts, the God of Israel, have I declared unto you.

11 ¶ The burden of Dumah. He calleth to me out of Seir, Watchman, what of the night? Watchman, what of the night? 12  The watchman said, The morning cometh, and also the night: if ye will enquire, enquire ye: return, come.

13 ¶ The burden upon Arabia. In the forest in Arabia shall ye lodge, O ye travelling companies of Dedanim. 14  The inhabitants of the land of Tema [∥]brought water to him that was thirsty, they prevented with their bread him that fled. 15  For they fled [∥][†]from the swords, from the drawn sword, and from the bent bow, and from the grievousness of war. 16  For thus hath the Lord said unto me, Within a year, according to the years of an hireling, and all the glory of Kedar shall fail: 17  And the residue of the number of [†]archers, the mighty men of the children of Kedar, shall be diminished: for the LORD God of Israel hath spoken it.

22

1  The burden of the valley of vision. What aileth thee now, that thou art wholly gone up to the housetops? 2  Thou that art full of stirs, a tumultuous city, a joyous city: thy slain men are not slain with the sword, nor dead in battle. 3  All thy rulers are fled together, they are bound [†]by the archers: all that are found in thee are bound together, which have fled from far. 4  Therefore said I, [*]Look away from me; [†]I will weep bitterly, labour not to comfort me, because of the spoiling of the daughter of my people. 5 For it is a day of trouble, and of treading down, and of perplexity by the Lord GOD of hosts in the valley of vision, breaking down the walls, and of crying to the mountains. 6  And Elam bare the quiver with chariots of men and horsemen, and Kir [†]uncovered the shield. 7 And it shall come to pass, that [†]thy choicest valleys shall be full of chariots, and the horsemen shall set themselves in array [∥]at the gate.

8 ¶ And he discovered the covering of Judah, and thou didst look in that day to the armour of the house of the forest. 9  Ye have seen also the breaches of the city of David, that they are many: and ye gathered together the waters of the lower pool. 10  And ye have numbered the houses of Jerusalem, and the houses have ye broken down to fortify the wall. 11  Ye made also a ditch between the two walls for the water of the old pool: but ye have not looked unto the maker thereof, neither had respect unto him that fashioned it long ago. 12  And in that day did the Lord GOD of hosts call to weeping, and to mourning, and to baldness, and to girding with sackcloth: 13  And behold joy and gladness, slaying oxen, and killing sheep, eating flesh, and drinking wine: [*]let us eat and drink; for to morrow we shall die. 14  And it was revealed in mine ears by the LORD of hosts, Surely this iniquity shall not be purged from you till ye die, saith the Lord GOD of hosts.

15 ¶ Thus saith the Lord GOD of hosts, Go, get thee unto this treasurer, even unto Shebna, which is over the house, and say, 16  What hast thou here? and whom hast thou here, that thou hast hewed thee out a sepulchre here, [∥]as he that heweth him out a sepulchre on high, and that graveth an habitation for himself in a rock? 17  Behold, [∥]the LORD will carry thee away with [†]a mighty captivity, and will surely cover thee. 18  He will surely violently turn and toss thee like a ball into a [†]large country: there shalt thou die, and there the chariots of thy glory shall be the shame of thy lord’s house. 19  And I will drive thee from thy station, and from thy state shall he pull thee down.

20 ¶ And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will call my servant Eliakim the son of Hilkiah: 21  And I will clothe him with thy robe, and strengthen him with thy girdle, and I will commit thy government into his hand: and he shall be a father to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and to the house of Judah. 22  And the key of the house of David will I lay upon his shoulder; so he shall [*]open, and none shall shut; and he shall shut, and none shall open. 23  And I will fasten him as a nail in a sure place; and he shall be for a glorious throne to his father’s house. 24  And they shall hang upon him all the glory of his father’s house, the offspring and the issue, all vessels of small quantity, from the vessels of cups, even to all the [∥]vessels of flagons. 25  In that day, saith the LORD of hosts, shall the nail that is fastened in the sure place be removed, and be cut down, and fall; and the burden that was upon it shall be cut off: for the LORD hath spoken it.

23

1  The burden of Tyre. Howl, ye ships of Tarshish; for it is laid waste, so that there is no house, no entering in: from the land of Chittim it is revealed to them. 2  Be [†]still, ye inhabitants of the isle; thou whom the merchants of Zidon, that pass over the sea, have replenished. 3  And by great waters the seed of Sihor, the harvest of the river, is her revenue; and she is a mart of nations. 4  Be thou ashamed, O Zidon: for the sea hath spoken, even the strength of the sea, saying, I travail not, nor bring forth children, neither do I nourish up young men, nor bring up virgins. 5  As at the report concerning Egypt, so shall they be sorely pained at the report of Tyre. 6  Pass ye over to Tarshish; howl, ye inhabitants of the isle. 7  Is this your joyous city, whose antiquity is of ancient days? her own feet shall carry her [†]afar off to sojourn. 8  Who hath taken this counsel against Tyre, the crowning city, whose merchants are princes, whose traffickers are the honourable of the earth? 9  The LORD of hosts hath purposed it, [†]to stain the pride of all glory, and to bring into contempt all the honourable of the earth. 10  Pass through thy land as a river, O daughter of Tarshish: there is no more [†]strength. 11  He stretched out his hand over the sea, he shook the kingdoms: the LORD hath given a commandment [∥]against [†]the merchant city, to destroy the [∥]strong holds thereof. 12  And he said, Thou shalt no more rejoice, O thou oppressed virgin, daughter of Zidon: arise, pass over to Chittim; there also shalt thou have no rest. 13  Behold the land of the Chaldeans; this people was not, till the Assyrian founded it for them that dwell in the wilderness: they set up the towers thereof, they raised up the palaces thereof; and he brought it to ruin. 14  Howl, ye ships of Tarshish: for your strength is laid waste.

15  And it shall come to pass in that day, that Tyre shall be forgotten seventy years, according to the days of one king: after the end of seventy years [†]shall Tyre sing as an harlot. 16  Take an harp, go about the city, thou harlot that hast been forgotten; make sweet melody, sing many songs, that thou mayest be remembered.

17 ¶ And it shall come to pass after the end of seventy years, that the LORD will visit Tyre, and she shall turn to her hire, and shall commit fornication with all the kingdoms of the world upon the face of the earth. 18  And her merchandise and her hire shall be holiness to the LORD: it shall not be treasured nor laid up; for her merchandise shall be for them that dwell before the LORD, to eat sufficiently, and for [†]durable clothing.

24

1  Behold, the LORD maketh the earth empty, and maketh it waste, and [†]turneth it upside down, and scattereth abroad the inhabitants thereof. 2  And it shall be, as with the people, so with the [∥][*]priest; as with the servant, so with his master; as with the maid, so with her mistress; as with the buyer, so with the seller; as with the lender, so with the borrower; as with the taker of usury, so with the giver of usury to him. 3  The land shall be utterly emptied, and utterly spoiled: for the LORD hath spoken this word. 4  The earth mourneth and fadeth away, the world languisheth and fadeth away, [†]the haughty people of the earth do languish. 5  The earth also is defiled under the inhabitants thereof; because they have transgressed the laws, changed the ordinance, broken the everlasting covenant. 6  Therefore hath the curse devoured the earth, and they that dwell therein are desolate: therefore the inhabitants of the earth are burned, and few men left. 7  The new wine mourneth, the vine languisheth, all the merryhearted do sigh. 8  The mirth [*]of tabrets ceaseth, the noise of them that rejoice endeth, the joy of the harp ceaseth. 9  They shall not drink wine with a song; strong drink shall be bitter to them that drink it. 10  The city of confusion is broken down: every house is shut up, that no man may come in. 11  There is a crying for wine in the streets; all joy is darkened, the mirth of the land is gone. 12  In the city is left desolation, and the gate is smitten with destruction.

13 ¶ When thus it shall be in the midst of the land among the people, there shall be as the shaking of an olive tree, and as the gleaning grapes when the vintage is done. 14  They shall lift up their voice, they shall sing for the majesty of the LORD, they shall cry aloud from the sea. 15  Wherefore glorify ye the LORD in the [∥]fires, even the name of the LORD God of Israel in the isles of the sea.

16 ¶ From the [†]uttermost part of the earth have we heard songs, even glory to the righteous. But I said, [†]My leanness, my leanness, woe unto me! the treacherous dealers have dealt treacherously; yea, the treacherous dealers have dealt very treacherously. 17 [*] Fear, and the pit, and the snare, are upon thee, O inhabitant of the earth. 18 And it shall come to pass, that he who fleeth from the noise of the fear shall fall into the pit; and he that cometh up out of the midst of the pit shall be taken in the snare: for the windows from on high are open, and the foundations of the earth do shake. 19  The earth is utterly broken down, the earth is clean dissolved, the earth is moved exceedingly. 20  The earth shall reel to and fro like a drunkard, and shall be removed like a cottage; and the transgression thereof shall be heavy upon it; and it shall fall, and not rise again. 21  And it shall come to pass in that day, that the LORD shall [†]punish the host of the high ones that are on high, and the kings of the earth upon the earth. 22  And they shall be gathered together, [†]as prisoners are gathered in the [∥]pit, and shall be shut up in the prison, and after many days shall they be [∥]visited. 23  Then the [*]moon shall be confounded, and the sun ashamed, when the LORD of hosts shall reign in mount Zion, and in Jerusalem, and [∥]before his ancients gloriously.

25

1  O LORD, thou art my God; I will exalt thee, I will praise thy name; for thou hast done wonderful things; thy counsels of old are faithfulness and truth. 2  For thou hast made of a city an heap; of a defenced city a ruin: a palace of strangers to be no city; it shall never be built. 3  Therefore shall the strong people glorify thee, the city of the terrible nations shall fear thee. 4  For thou hast been a strength to the poor, a strength to the needy in his distress, a refuge from the storm, a shadow from the heat, when the blast of the terrible ones is as a storm against the wall. 5  Thou shalt bring down the noise of strangers, as the heat in a dry place; even the heat with the shadow of a cloud: the branch of the terrible ones shall be brought low.

6 ¶ And in this mountain shall the LORD of hosts make unto all people a feast of fat things, a feast of wines on the lees, of fat things full of marrow, of wines on the lees well refined. 7  And he will [†]destroy in this mountain the face of the covering [†]cast over all people, and the vail that is spread over all nations. 8  He will [*]swallow up death in victory; and the Lord GOD will [*]wipe away tears from off all faces; and the rebuke of his people shall he take away from off all the earth: for the LORD hath spoken it.

9 ¶ And it shall be said in that day, Lo, this is our God; we have waited for him, and he will save us: this is the LORD; we have waited for him, we will be glad and rejoice in his salvation. 10  For in this mountain shall the hand of the LORD rest, and Moab shall be [∥]trodden down under him, even as straw is [∥]trodden down for the dunghill. 11  And he shall spread forth his hands in the midst of them, as he that swimmeth spreadeth forth his hands to swim: and he shall bring down their pride together with the spoils of their hands. 12  And the fortress of the high fort of thy walls shall he bring down, lay low, and bring to the ground, even to the dust.

26

1  In that day shall this song be sung in the land of Judah; We have a strong city; salvation will God appoint for walls and bulwarks. 2  Open ye the gates, that the righteous nation which keepeth the [†]truth may enter in. 3  Thou wilt keep him in [†]perfect peace, whose [∥]mind is stayed on thee: because he trusteth in thee. 4  Trust ye in the LORD for ever: for in the LORD JEHOVAH is [†]everlasting strength:

5 ¶ For he bringeth down them that dwell on high; the lofty city, he layeth it low; he layeth it low, even to the ground; he bringeth it even to the dust. 6  The foot shall tread it down, even the feet of the poor, and the steps of the needy. 7  The way of the just is uprightness: thou, most upright, dost weigh the path of the just. 8  Yea, in the way of thy judgments, O LORD, have we waited for thee; the desire of our soul is to thy name, and to the remembrance of thee. 9  With my soul have I desired thee in the night; yea, with my spirit within me will I seek thee early: for when thy judgments are in the earth, the inhabitants of the world will learn righteousness. 10  Let favour be shewed to the wicked, yet will he not learn righteousness: in the land of uprightness will he deal unjustly, and will not behold the majesty of the LORD. 11  LORD, when thy hand is lifted up, they will not see: but they shall see, and be ashamed for their envy [∥]at the people; yea, the fire of thine enemies shall devour them.

12 ¶ LORD, thou wilt ordain peace for us: for thou also hast wrought all our works [∥]in us. 13  O LORD our God, other lords beside thee have had dominion over us: but by thee only will we make mention of thy name. 14  They are dead, they shall not live; they are deceased, they shall not rise: therefore hast thou visited and destroyed them, and made all their memory to perish. 15  Thou hast increased the nation, O LORD, thou hast increased the nation: thou art glorified: thou hadst removed it far unto all the ends of the earth. 16  LORD, in trouble have they visited thee, they poured out a [†]prayer when thy chastening was upon them. 17  Like as a woman with child, that draweth near the time of her delivery, is in pain, and crieth out in her pangs; so have we been in thy sight, O LORD. 18  We have been with child, we have been in pain, we have as it were brought forth wind; we have not wrought any deliverance in the earth; neither have the inhabitants of the world fallen. 19  Thy dead men shall live, together with my dead body shall they arise. Awake and sing, ye that dwell in dust: for thy dew is as the dew of herbs, and the earth shall cast out the dead.

20 ¶ Come, my people, enter thou into thy chambers, and shut thy doors about thee: hide thyself as it were for a little moment, until the indignation be overpast. 21  For, behold, the LORD [*]cometh out of his place to punish the inhabitants of the earth for their iniquity: the earth also shall disclose her [†]blood, and shall no more cover her slain.

27

1  In that day the LORD with his sore and great and strong sword shall punish leviathan the [∥]piercing serpent, even leviathan that crooked serpent; and he shall slay the dragon that is in the sea. 2  In that day sing ye unto her, A vineyard of red wine. 3  I the LORD do keep it; I will water it every moment: lest any hurt it, I will keep it night and day. 4  Fury is not in me: who would set the briers and thorns against me in battle? I would [∥]go through them, I would burn them together. 5  Or let him take hold of my strength, that he may make peace with me; and he shall make peace with me. 6  He shall cause them that come of Jacob to take root: Israel shall blossom and bud, and fill the face of the world with fruit.

7 ¶ Hath he smitten him, [†]as he smote those that smote him? or is he slain according to the slaughter of them that are slain by him? 8  In measure, [∥]when it shooteth forth, thou wilt debate with it: [∥]he stayeth his rough wind in the day of the east wind. 9  By this therefore shall the iniquity of Jacob be purged; and this is all the fruit to take away his sin; when he maketh all the stones of the altar as chalkstones that are beaten in sunder, the groves and [∥]images shall not stand up. 10  Yet the defenced city shall be desolate, and the habitation forsaken, and left like a wilderness: there shall the calf feed, and there shall he lie down, and consume the branches thereof. 11  When the boughs thereof are withered, they shall be broken off: the women come, and set them on fire: for it is a people of no understanding: therefore he that made them will not have mercy on them, and he that formed them will shew them no favour.

12 ¶ And it shall come to pass in that day, that the LORD shall beat off from the channel of the river unto the stream of Egypt, and ye shall be gathered one by one, O ye children of Israel. 13  And it shall come to pass in that day, that the great trumpet shall be blown, and they shall come which were ready to perish in the land of Assyria, and the outcasts in the land of Egypt, and shall worship the LORD in the holy mount at Jerusalem.

28

1  Woe to the crown of pride, to the drunkards of Ephraim, whose glorious beauty is a fading flower, which are on the head of the fat valleys of them that are [†]overcome with wine! 2  Behold, the Lord hath a mighty and strong one, which as a tempest of hail and a destroying storm, as a flood of mighty waters overflowing, shall cast down to the earth with the hand. 3  The crown of pride, the drunkards of Ephraim, shall be trodden [†]under feet: 4  And the glorious beauty, which is on the head of the fat valley, shall be a fading flower, and as the hasty fruit before the summer; which when he that looketh upon it [‡]seeth, while it is yet in his hand he [†]eateth it up.

5 ¶ In that day shall the LORD of hosts be for a crown of glory, and for a diadem of beauty, unto the residue of his people, 6  And for a spirit of judgment to him that sitteth in judgment, and for strength to them that turn the battle to the gate.

7 ¶ But they also have erred through wine, and through strong drink are out of the way; the priest and the prophet have erred through strong drink, they are swallowed up of wine, they are out of the way through strong drink; they err in vision, they stumble in judgment. 8  For all tables are full of vomit and filthiness, so that there is no place clean.

9 ¶ Whom shall he teach knowledge? and whom shall he make to understand [†]doctrine? them that are weaned from the milk, and drawn from the breasts. 10  For precept [∥]must be upon precept, precept upon precept; line upon line, line upon line; here a little, and there a little: 11  For with [†][*]stammering lips and another tongue [∥]will he speak to this people. 12  To whom he said, This is the rest wherewith ye may cause the weary to rest; and this is the refreshing: yet they would not hear. 13  But the word of the LORD was unto them precept upon precept, precept upon precept; line upon line, line upon line; here a little, and there a little; that they might go, and fall backward, and be broken, and snared, and taken.

14 ¶ Wherefore hear the word of the LORD, ye scornful men, that rule this people which is in Jerusalem. 15  Because ye have said, We have made a covenant with death, and with hell are we at agreement; when the overflowing scourge shall pass through, it shall not come unto us: for we have made lies our refuge, and under falsehood have we hid ourselves:

16 ¶ Therefore thus saith the Lord GOD, Behold, I lay in Zion for a foundation [*]a stone, a tried stone, a precious corner stone, a sure foundation: he that believeth shall not make haste. 17  Judgment also will I lay to the line, and righteousness to the plummet: and the hail shall sweep away the refuge of lies, and the waters shall overflow the hiding place.

18 ¶ And your covenant with death shall be disannulled, and your agreement with hell shall not stand; when the overflowing scourge shall pass through, then ye shall be [†]trodden down by it. 19  From the time that it goeth forth it shall take you: for morning by morning shall it pass over, by day and by night: and it shall be a vexation only [∥]to understand the report. 20  For the bed is shorter than that a man can stretch himself on it: and the covering narrower than that he can wrap himself in it. 21  For the LORD shall rise up as in mount [*]Perazim, he shall be wroth as in the valley of [*]Gibeon, that he may do his work, his strange work; and bring to pass his act, his strange act. 22  Now therefore be ye not mockers, lest your bands be made strong: for I have heard from the Lord GOD of hosts a consumption, even determined upon the whole earth.

23 ¶ Give ye ear, and hear my voice; hearken, and hear my speech. 24  Doth the plowman plow all day to sow? doth he open and break the clods of his ground? 25  When he hath made plain the face thereof, doth he not cast abroad the fitches, and scatter the cummin, and cast in [∥]the principal wheat and the appointed barley and the [∥]rie in their [†]place? 26 [∥] For his God doth instruct him to discretion, and doth teach him. 27  For the fitches are not threshed with a threshing instrument, neither is a cart wheel turned about upon the cummin; but the fitches are beaten out with a staff, and the cummin with a rod. 28  Bread corn is bruised; because he will not ever be threshing it, nor break it with the wheel of his cart, nor bruise it with his horsemen. 29  This also cometh forth from the LORD of hosts, which is wonderful in counsel, and excellent in working.

29

1  Woe [∥]to Ariel, to Ariel, [∥]the city where David dwelt! add ye year to year; let them [†]kill sacrifices. 2  Yet I will distress Ariel, and there shall be heaviness and sorrow: and it shall be unto me as Ariel. 3  And I will camp against thee round about, and will lay siege against thee with a mount, and I will raise forts against thee. 4  And thou shalt be brought down, and shalt speak out of the ground, and thy speech shall be low out of the dust, and thy voice shall be, as of one that hath a familiar spirit, out of the ground, and thy speech shall [†]whisper out of the dust. 5  Moreover the multitude of thy strangers shall be like small dust, and the multitude of the terrible ones shall be as chaff that passeth away: yea, it shall be at an instant suddenly. 6  Thou shalt be visited of the LORD of hosts with thunder, and with earthquake, and great noise, with storm and tempest, and the flame of devouring fire.

7 ¶ And the multitude of all the nations that fight against Ariel, even all that fight against her and her munition, and that distress her, shall be as a dream of a night vision. 8  It shall even be as when an hungry man dreameth, and, behold, he eateth; but he awaketh, and his soul is empty: or as when a thirsty man dreameth, and, behold, he drinketh; but he awaketh, and, behold, he is faint, and his soul hath appetite: so shall the multitude of all the nations be, that fight against mount Zion.

9 ¶ Stay yourselves, and wonder; [∥]cry ye out, and cry: they are drunken, but not with wine; they stagger, but not with strong drink. 10  For the LORD hath poured out upon you the spirit of deep sleep, and hath closed your eyes: the prophets and your [†]rulers, the seers hath he covered. 11  And the vision of all is become unto you as the words of a [∥]book that is sealed, which men deliver to one that is learned, saying, Read this, I pray thee: and he saith, I cannot; for it is sealed: 12  And the book is delivered to him that is not learned, saying, Read this, I pray thee: and he saith, I am not learned.

13 ¶ Wherefore the Lord said, [*]Forasmuch as this people draw near me with their mouth, and with their lips do honour me, but have removed their heart far from me, and their fear toward me is taught by the precept of men: 14  Therefore, behold, [†]I will proceed to do a marvellous work among this people, even a marvellous work and a wonder: [*]for the wisdom of their wise men shall perish, and the understanding of their prudent men shall be hid. 15  Woe unto them that seek deep to hide their counsel from the LORD, and their works are in the dark, and they say, [*]Who seeth us? and who knoweth us? 16  Surely your turning of things upside down shall be esteemed as the potter’s clay: for shall the [*]work say of him that made it, He made me not? or shall the thing framed say of him that framed it, He had no understanding?

17  Is it not yet a very little while, and Lebanon shall be turned into a fruitful field, and the fruitful field shall be esteemed as a forest?

18 ¶ And in that day shall the deaf hear the words of the book, and the eyes of the blind shall see out of obscurity, and out of darkness. 19  The meek also [†]shall increase their joy in the LORD, and the poor among men shall rejoice in the Holy One of Israel. 20  For the terrible one is brought to nought, and the scorner is consumed, and all that watch for iniquity are cut off: 21  That make a man an offender for a word, and lay a snare for him that reproveth in the gate, and turn aside the just for a thing of nought. 22  Therefore thus saith the LORD, who redeemed Abraham, concerning the house of Jacob, Jacob shall not now be ashamed, neither shall his face now wax pale. 23  But when he seeth his children, the work of mine hands, in the midst of him, they shall sanctify my name, and sanctify the Holy One of Jacob, and shall fear the God of Israel. 24  They also that erred in spirit [†]shall come to understanding, and they that murmured shall learn doctrine.

30

1  Woe to the rebellious children, saith the LORD, that take counsel, but not of me; and that cover with a covering, but not of my spirit, that they may add sin to sin: 2  That walk to go down into Egypt, and have not asked at my mouth; to strengthen themselves in the strength of Pharaoh, and to trust in the shadow of Egypt! 3  Therefore shall the strength of Pharaoh be your shame, and the trust in the shadow of Egypt your confusion. 4  For his princes were at Zoan, and his ambassadors came to Hanes. 5  They were all ashamed of a people that could not profit them, nor be an help nor profit, but a shame, and also a reproach. 6  The burden of the beasts of the south: into the land of trouble and anguish, from whence come the young and old lion, the viper and fiery flying serpent, they will carry their riches upon the shoulders of young asses, and their treasures upon the bunches of camels, to a people that shall not profit them. 7  For the Egyptians shall help in vain, and to no purpose: therefore have I cried [∥]concerning this, Their strength is to sit still.

8 ¶ Now go, write it before them in a table, and note it in a book, that it may be for [†]the time to come for ever and ever: 9 That this is a rebellious people, lying children, children that will not hear the law of the LORD: 10  Which say to the seers, See not; and to the prophets, Prophesy not unto us right things, speak unto us smooth things, prophesy deceits: 11  Get you out of the way, turn aside out of the path, cause the Holy One of Israel to cease from before us. 12  Wherefore thus saith the Holy One of Israel, Because ye despise this word, and trust in [∥]oppression and perverseness, and stay thereon: 13  Therefore this iniquity shall be to you as a breach ready to fall, swelling out in a high wall, whose breaking cometh suddenly at an instant. 14  And he shall break it as the breaking of [†]the potters’ vessel that is broken in pieces; he shall not spare: so that there shall not be found in the bursting of it a sherd to take fire from the hearth, or to take water withal out of the pit. 15  For thus saith the Lord GOD, the Holy One of Israel; In returning and rest shall ye be saved; in quietness and in confidence shall be your strength: and ye would not. 16  But ye said, No; for we will flee upon horses; therefore shall ye flee: and, We will ride upon the swift; therefore shall they that pursue you be swift. 17  One thousand shall flee at the rebuke of one; at the rebuke of five shall ye flee: till ye be left as [∥]a beacon upon the top of a mountain, and as an ensign on an hill.

18 ¶ And therefore will the LORD wait, that he may be gracious unto you, and therefore will he be exalted, that he may have mercy upon you: for the LORD is a God of judgment: [*]blessed are all they that wait for him. 19  For the people shall dwell in Zion at Jerusalem: thou shalt weep no more: he will be very gracious unto thee at the voice of thy cry; when he shall hear it, he will answer thee. 20 And though the Lord give you the bread of adversity, and the water of [∥]affliction, yet shall not thy teachers be removed into a corner any more, but thine eyes shall see thy teachers: 21  And thine ears shall hear a word behind thee, saying, This is the way, walk ye in it, when ye turn to the right hand, and when ye turn to the left. 22  Ye shall defile also the covering of [†]thy graven images of silver, and the ornament of thy molten images of gold: thou shalt [†]cast them away as a menstruous cloth; thou shalt say unto it, Get thee hence. 23  Then shall he give the rain of thy seed, that thou shalt sow the ground withal; and bread of the increase of the earth, and it shall be fat and plenteous: in that day shall thy cattle feed in large pastures. 24  The oxen likewise and the young asses that ear the ground shall eat [∥][†]clean provender, which hath been winnowed with the shovel and with the fan. 25  And there shall be upon every high mountain, and upon every [†]high hill, rivers and streams of waters in the day of the great slaughter, when the towers fall. 26  Moreover the light of the moon shall be as the light of the sun, and the light of the sun shall be sevenfold, as the light of seven days, in the day that the LORD bindeth up the breach of his people, and healeth the stroke of their wound.

27 ¶ Behold, the name of the LORD cometh from far, burning with his anger, [∥]and the burden thereof is [†]heavy: his lips are full of indignation, and his tongue as a devouring fire: 28  And his breath, as an overflowing stream, shall reach to the midst of the neck, to sift the nations with the sieve of vanity: and there shall be a bridle in the jaws of the people, causing them to err. 29  Ye shall have a song, as in the night when a holy solemnity is kept; and gladness of heart, as when one goeth with a pipe to come into the mountain of the LORD, to the [†]mighty One of Israel. 30  And the LORD shall cause [†]his glorious voice to be heard, and shall shew the lighting down of his arm, with the indignation of his anger, and with the flame of a devouring fire, with scattering, and tempest, and hailstones. 31  For through the voice of the LORD shall the Assyrian be beaten down, which smote with a rod. 32 And [†]in every place where the grounded staff shall pass, which the LORD shall [†]lay upon him, it shall be with tabrets and harps: and in battles of shaking will he fight [∥]with it. 33  For Tophet is ordained [†]of old; yea, for the king it is prepared; he hath made it deep and large: the pile thereof is fire and much wood; the breath of the LORD, like a stream of brimstone, doth kindle it.

31

1  Woe to them that go down to Egypt for help; and stay on horses, and trust in chariots, because they are many; and in horsemen, because they are very strong; but they look not unto the Holy One of Israel, neither seek the LORD! 2 Yet he also is wise, and will bring evil, and will not [†]call back his words: but will arise against the house of the evildoers, and against the help of them that work iniquity. 3  Now the Egyptians are men, and not God; and their horses flesh, and not spirit. When the LORD shall stretch out his hand, both he that helpeth shall fall, and he that is holpen shall fall down, and they all shall fail together. 4  For thus hath the LORD spoken unto me, Like as the lion and the young lion roaring on his prey, when a multitude of shepherds is called forth against him, he will not be afraid of their voice, nor abase himself for the [∥]noise of them: so shall the LORD of hosts come down to fight for mount Zion, and for the hill thereof. 5  As birds flying, so will the LORD of hosts defend Jerusalem; defending also he will deliver it; and passing over he will preserve it.

6 ¶ Turn ye unto him from whom the children of Israel have deeply revolted. 7  For in that day every man shall [*]cast away his idols of silver, and [†]his idols of gold, which your own hands have made unto you for a sin.

8 ¶ Then shall the Assyrian fall with the sword, not of a mighty man; and the sword, not of a mean man, shall devour him: but he shall flee [∥]from the sword, and his young men shall be [∥][†]discomfited. 9  And [†]he shall pass over to [∥]his strong hold for fear, and his princes shall be afraid of the ensign, saith the LORD, whose fire is in Zion, and his furnace in Jerusalem.

32

1  Behold, a king shall reign in righteousness, and princes shall rule in judgment. 2  And a man shall be as an hiding place from the wind, and a covert from the tempest; as rivers of water in a dry place, as the shadow of a [†]great rock in a weary land. 3  And the eyes of them that see shall not be dim, and the ears of them that hear shall hearken. 4  The heart also of the [†]rash shall understand knowledge, and the tongue of the stammerers shall be ready to speak [∥]plainly. 5  The vile person shall be no more called liberal, nor the churl said to be bountiful. 6  For the vile person will speak villany, and his heart will work iniquity, to practise hypocrisy, and to utter error against the LORD, to make empty the soul of the hungry, and he will cause the drink of the thirsty to fail. 7  The instruments also of the churl are evil: he deviseth wicked devices to destroy the poor with lying words, even [∥]when the needy speaketh right. 8  But the liberal deviseth liberal things; and by liberal things shall he [∥]stand.

9 ¶ Rise up, ye women that are at ease; hear my voice, ye careless daughters; give ear unto my speech. 10 [†] Many days and years shall ye be troubled, ye careless women: for the vintage shall fail, the gathering shall not come. 11  Tremble, ye women that are at ease; be troubled, ye careless ones: strip you, and make you bare, and gird sackcloth upon your loins. 12  They shall lament for the teats, for [†]the pleasant fields, for the fruitful vine. 13  Upon the land of my people shall come up thorns and briers; [∥]yea, upon all the houses of joy in the joyous city: 14  Because the palaces shall be forsaken; the multitude of the city shall be left; the [∥]forts and towers shall be for dens for ever, a joy of wild asses, a pasture of flocks; 15  Until the spirit be poured upon us from on high, and [*]the wilderness be a fruitful field, and the fruitful field be counted for a forest. 16  Then judgment shall dwell in the wilderness, and righteousness remain in the fruitful field. 17  And the work of righteousness shall be peace; and the effect of righteousness quietness and assurance for ever. 18  And my people shall dwell in a peaceable habitation, and in sure dwellings, and in quiet resting places; 19  When it shall hail, coming down on the forest; [∥]and the city shall be low in a low place. 20  Blessed are ye that sow beside all waters, that send forth thither the feet of the ox and the ass.

33

1  Woe to thee that spoilest, and thou wast not spoiled; and dealest treacherously, and they dealt not treacherously with thee! when thou shalt cease to spoil, thou shalt be spoiled; and when thou shalt make an end to deal treacherously, they shall deal treacherously with thee. 2  O LORD, be gracious unto us; we have waited for thee: be thou their arm every morning, our salvation also in the time of trouble. 3  At the noise of the tumult the people fled; at the lifting up of thyself the nations were scattered. 4  And your spoil shall be gathered like the gathering of the caterpiller: as the running to and fro of locusts shall he run upon them. 5  The LORD is exalted; for he dwelleth on high: he hath filled Zion with judgment and righteousness. 6  And wisdom and knowledge shall be the stability of thy times, and strength of [†]salvation: the fear of the LORD is his treasure. 7  Behold, their [∥]valiant ones shall cry without: the ambassadors of peace shall weep bitterly. 8  The highways lie waste, the wayfaring man ceaseth: he hath broken the covenant, he hath despised the cities, he regardeth no man. 9  The earth mourneth and languisheth: Lebanon is ashamed and [∥]hewn down: Sharon is like a wilderness; and Bashan and Carmel shake off their fruits. 10  Now will I rise, saith the LORD; now will I be exalted; now will I lift up myself. 11  Ye shall conceive chaff, ye shall bring forth stubble: your breath, as fire, shall devour you. 12  And the people shall be as the burnings of lime: as thorns cut up shall they be burned in the fire.

13 ¶ Hear, ye that are far off, what I have done; and, ye that are near, acknowledge my might. 14  The sinners in Zion are afraid; fearfulness hath surprised the hypocrites. Who among us shall dwell with the devouring fire? who among us shall dwell with everlasting burnings? 15  He that [*]walketh [†]righteously, and speaketh [†]uprightly; he that despiseth the gain of [∥]oppressions, that shaketh his hands from holding of bribes, that stoppeth his ears from hearing of [†]blood, and shutteth his eyes from seeing evil; 16  He shall dwell on [†]high: his place of defence shall be the munitions of rocks: bread shall be given him; his waters shall be sure. 17  Thine eyes shall see the king in his beauty: they shall behold [†]the land that is very far off. 18  Thine heart shall meditate terror. [*]Where is the scribe? where is the [†]receiver? where is he that counted the towers? 19  Thou shalt not see a fierce people, a people of a deeper speech than thou canst perceive; of a [∥]stammering tongue, that thou canst not understand. 20  Look upon Zion, the city of our solemnities: thine eyes shall see Jerusalem a quiet habitation, a tabernacle that shall not be taken down; not one of the stakes thereof shall ever be removed, neither shall any of the cords thereof be broken. 21  But there the glorious LORD will be unto us a place [†]of broad rivers and streams; wherein shall go no galley with oars, neither shall gallant ship pass thereby. 22  For the LORD is our judge, the LORD is our [†]lawgiver, the LORD is our king; he will save us. 23 [∥] Thy tacklings are loosed; they could not well strengthen their mast, they could not spread the sail: then is the prey of a great spoil divided; the lame take the prey. 24  And the inhabitant shall not say, I am sick: the people that dwell therein shall be forgiven their iniquity.

34

1  Come near, ye nations, to hear; and hearken, ye people: let the earth hear, and [†]all that is therein; the world, and all things that come forth of it. 2  For the indignation of the LORD is upon all nations, and his fury upon all their armies: he hath utterly destroyed them, he hath delivered them to the slaughter. 3  Their slain also shall be cast out, and their stink shall come up out of their carcases, and the mountains shall be melted with their blood. 4  And all the host of heaven shall be dissolved, and the heavens shall be [*]rolled together as a scroll: and all their host shall fall down, as the leaf falleth off from the vine, and as a [*]falling fig from the fig tree. 5  For my sword shall be bathed in heaven: behold, it shall come down upon Idumea, and upon the people of my curse, to judgment. 6  The sword of the LORD is filled with blood, it is made fat with fatness, and with the blood of lambs and goats, with the fat of the kidneys of rams: for the LORD hath a sacrifice in Bozrah, and a great slaughter in the land of Idumea. 7  And the [∥]unicorns shall come down with them, and the bullocks with the bulls; and their land shall be [∥]soaked with blood, and their dust made fat with fatness. 8 For it is the day of the LORD’s [*]vengeance, and the year of recompences for the controversy of Zion.

9  And the streams thereof shall be turned into pitch, and the dust thereof into brimstone, and the land thereof shall become burning pitch. 10  It shall not be quenched night nor day; [*]the smoke thereof shall go up for ever: from generation to generation it shall lie waste; none shall pass through it for ever and ever.

11 ¶ [*][‡]But the [∥]cormorant and the bittern shall possess it; the owl also and the raven shall dwell in it: and he shall stretch out upon it the line of confusion, and the stones of emptiness. 12  They shall call the nobles thereof to the kingdom, but none shall be there, and all her princes shall be nothing. 13  And thorns shall come up in her palaces, nettles and brambles in the fortresses thereof: and it shall be an habitation of dragons, and a court for [∥][†]owls. 14 [†] The wild beasts of the desert shall also meet with [†]the wild beasts of the island, and the satyr shall cry to his fellow; the [∥]screech owl also shall rest there, and find for herself a place of rest. 15  There shall the great owl make her nest, and lay, and hatch, and gather under her shadow: there shall the vultures also be gathered, every one with her mate.

16 ¶ Seek ye out of the book of the LORD, and read: no one of these shall fail, none shall want her mate: for my mouth it hath commanded, and his spirit it hath gathered them. 17  And he hath cast the lot for them, and his hand hath divided it unto them by line: they shall possess it for ever, from generation to generation shall they dwell therein.

35

1  The wilderness and the solitary place shall be glad for them; and the desert shall rejoice, and blossom as the rose. 2  It shall blossom abundantly, and rejoice even with joy and singing: the glory of Lebanon shall be given unto it, the excellency of Carmel and Sharon, they shall see the glory of the LORD, and the excellency of our God.

3 ¶ [*]Strengthen ye the weak hands, and confirm the feeble knees. 4  Say to them that are of a [†]fearful heart, Be strong, fear not: behold, your God will come with vengeance, even God with a recompence; he will come and save you.

5  Then the [*]eyes of the blind shall be opened, and [*]the ears of the deaf shall be unstopped. 6  Then shall the [*]lame man leap as an hart, and the [*]tongue of the dumb sing: for in the wilderness shall [*]waters break out, and streams in the desert. 7  And the parched ground shall become a pool, and the thirsty land springs of water: in the habitation of dragons, where each lay, shall be [∥]grass with reeds and rushes. 8  And an highway shall be there, and a way, and it shall be called The way of holiness; the unclean shall not pass over it; [∥]but it shall be for those: the wayfaring men, though fools, shall not err therein. 9  No lion shall be there, nor any ravenous beast shall go up thereon, it shall not be found there; but the redeemed shall walk there: 10  And the [*]ransomed of the LORD shall return, and come to Zion with songs and everlasting joy upon their heads: they shall obtain joy and gladness, and sorrow and sighing shall flee away.

36

1  Now [*]it came to pass in the fourteenth year of king Hezekiah, that Sennacherib king of Assyria came up against all the defenced cities of Judah, and took them. 2  And the king of Assyria sent Rabshakeh from Lachish to Jerusalem unto king Hezekiah with a great army. And he stood by the conduit of the upper pool in the highway of the fuller’s field. 3  Then came forth unto him Eliakim, Hilkiah’s son, which was over the house, and Shebna the [∥]scribe, and Joah, Asaph’s son, the recorder.

4 ¶ And Rabshakeh said unto them, Say ye now to Hezekiah, Thus saith the great king, the king of Assyria, What confidence is this wherein thou trustest? 5  I say, sayest thou, (but they are but [†]vain words) [∥]I have counsel and strength for war: now on whom dost thou trust, that thou rebellest against me? 6  Lo, thou trustest in the [*]staff of this broken reed, on Egypt; whereon if a man lean, it will go into his hand, and pierce it: so is Pharaoh king of Egypt to all that trust in him. 7  But if thou say to me, We trust in the LORD our God: is it not he, whose high places and whose altars Hezekiah hath taken away, and said to Judah and to Jerusalem, Ye shall worship before this altar? 8  Now therefore give [∥]pledges, I pray thee, to my master the king of Assyria, and I will give thee two thousand horses, if thou be able on thy part to set riders upon them. 9  How then wilt thou turn away the face of one captain of the least of my master’s servants, and put thy trust on Egypt for chariots and for horsemen? 10  And am I now come up without the LORD against this land to destroy it? the LORD said unto me, Go up against this land, and destroy it.

11 ¶ Then said Eliakim and Shebna and Joah unto Rabshakeh, Speak, I pray thee, unto thy servants in the Syrian language; for we understand it: and speak not to us in the Jews’ language, in the ears of the people that are on the wall.

12 ¶ But Rabshakeh said, Hath my master sent me to thy master and to thee to speak these words? hath he not sent me to the men that sit upon the wall, that they may eat their own dung, and drink their own piss with you? 13  Then Rabshakeh stood, and cried with a loud voice in the Jews’ language, and said, Hear ye the words of the great king, the king of Assyria. 14  Thus saith the king, Let not Hezekiah deceive you: for he shall not be able to deliver you. 15  Neither let Hezekiah make you trust in the LORD, saying, The LORD will surely deliver us: this city shall not be delivered into the hand of the king of Assyria. 16  Hearken not to Hezekiah: for thus saith the king of Assyria, [∥][†]Make an agreement with me by a present, and come out to me: and eat ye every one of his vine, and every one of his fig tree, and drink ye every one the waters of his own cistern; 17  Until I come and take you away to a land like your own land, a land of corn and wine, a land of bread and vineyards. 18  Beware lest Hezekiah persuade you, saying, The LORD will deliver us. Hath any of the gods of the nations delivered his land out of the hand of the king of Assyria? 19 Where are the gods of Hamath and Arphad? where are the gods of Sepharvaim? and have they delivered Samaria out of my hand? 20 Who are they among all the gods of these lands, that have delivered their land out of my hand, that the LORD should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand? 21  But they held their peace, and answered him not a word: for the king’s commandment was, saying, Answer him not.

22 ¶ Then came Eliakim, the son of Hilkiah, that was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah, the son of Asaph, the recorder, to Hezekiah with their clothes rent, and told him the words of Rabshakeh.

37

1  And [*]it came to pass, when king Hezekiah heard it, that he rent his clothes, and covered himself with sackcloth, and went into the house of the LORD. 2  And he sent Eliakim, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and the elders of the priests covered with sackcloth, unto Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz. 3  And they said unto him, Thus saith Hezekiah, This day is a day of trouble, and of rebuke, and of [∥]blasphemy: for the children are come to the birth, and there is not strength to bring forth. 4  It may be the LORD thy God will hear the words of Rabshakeh, whom the king of Assyria his master hath sent to reproach the living God, and will reprove the words which the LORD thy God hath heard: wherefore lift up thy prayer for the remnant that is [†]left. 5  So the servants of king Hezekiah came to Isaiah.

6 ¶ And Isaiah said unto them, Thus shall ye say unto your master, Thus saith the LORD, Be not afraid of the words that thou hast heard, wherewith the servants of the king of Assyria have blasphemed me. 7  Behold, I will [∥]send a blast upon him, and he shall hear a rumour, and return to his own land; and I will cause him to fall by the sword in his own land.

8 ¶ So Rabshakeh returned, and found the king of Assyria warring against Libnah: for he had heard that he was departed from Lachish. 9  And he heard say concerning Tirhakah king of Ethiopia, He is come forth to make war with thee. And when he heard it, he sent messengers to Hezekiah, saying, 10  Thus shall ye speak to Hezekiah king of Judah, saying, Let not thy God, in whom thou trustest, deceive thee, saying, Jerusalem shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria. 11  Behold, thou hast heard what the kings of Assyria have done to all lands by destroying them utterly; and shalt thou be delivered? 12  Have the gods of the nations delivered them which my fathers have destroyed, as Gozan, and Haran, and Rezeph, and the children of Eden which were in Telassar? 13 Where is the king of Hamath, and the king of Arphad, and the king of the city of Sepharvaim, Hena, and Ivah?

14 ¶ And Hezekiah received the letter from the hand of the messengers, and read it: and Hezekiah went up unto the house of the LORD, and spread it before the LORD. 15  And Hezekiah prayed unto the LORD, saying, 16  O LORD of hosts, God of Israel, that dwellest between the cherubims, thou art the God, even thou alone, of all the kingdoms of the earth: thou hast made heaven and earth. 17  Incline thine ear, O LORD, and hear; open thine eyes, O LORD, and see: and hear all the words of Sennacherib, which hath sent to reproach the living God. 18  Of a truth, LORD, the kings of Assyria have laid waste all the [†]nations, and their countries, 19  And have [†]cast their gods into the fire: for they were no gods, but the work of men’s hands, wood and stone: therefore they have destroyed them. 20  Now therefore, O LORD our God, save us from his hand, that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that thou art the LORD, even thou only.

21 ¶ Then Isaiah the son of Amoz sent unto Hezekiah, saying, Thus saith the LORD God of Israel, Whereas thou hast prayed to me against Sennacherib king of Assyria: 22 This is the word which the LORD hath spoken concerning him; The virgin, the daughter of Zion, hath despised thee, and laughed thee to scorn; the daughter of Jerusalem hath shaken her head at thee. 23  Whom hast thou reproached and blasphemed? and against whom hast thou exalted thy voice, and lifted up thine eyes on high? even against the Holy One of Israel. 24 [†] By thy servants hast thou reproached the Lord, and hast said, By the multitude of my chariots am I come up to the height of the mountains, to the sides of Lebanon; and I will cut down [†]the tall cedars thereof, and the choice fir trees thereof: and I will enter into the height of his border, and [∥]the forest of his Carmel. 25  I have digged, and drunk water; and with the sole of my feet have I dried up all the rivers of the [∥]besieged places. 26 [∥] Hast thou not heard long ago, how I have done it; and of ancient times, that I have formed it? now have I brought it to pass, that thou shouldest be to lay waste defenced cities into ruinous heaps. 27  Therefore their inhabitants were [†]of small power, they were dismayed and confounded: they were as the grass of the field, and as the green herb, as the grass on the housetops, and as corn blasted before it be grown up. 28  But I know thy [∥]abode, and thy going out, and thy coming in, and thy rage against me. 29  Because thy rage against me, and thy tumult, is come up into mine ears, therefore will I put my hook in thy nose, and my bridle in thy lips, and I will turn thee back by the way by which thou camest. 30 And this shall be a sign unto thee, Ye shall eat this year such as groweth of itself; and the second year that which springeth of the same: and in the third year sow ye, and reap, and plant vineyards, and eat the fruit thereof. 31  And [†]the remnant that is escaped of the house of Judah shall again take root downward, and bear fruit upward: 32  For out of Jerusalem shall go forth a remnant, and [†]they that escape out of mount Zion: the [*]zeal of the LORD of hosts shall do this. 33  Therefore thus saith the LORD concerning the king of Assyria, He shall not come into this city, nor shoot an arrow there, nor come before it with shields, nor cast a bank against it. 34  By the way that he came, by the same shall he return, and shall not come into this city, saith the LORD. 35  For I will [*]defend this city to save it for mine own sake, and for my servant David’s sake. 36  Then the [*]angel of the LORD went forth, and smote in the camp of the Assyrians a hundred and fourscore and five thousand: and when they arose early in the morning, behold, they were all dead corpses.

37 ¶ So Sennacherib king of Assyria departed, and went and returned, and dwelt at Nineveh. 38  And it came to pass, as he was worshipping in the house of Nisroch his god, that Adrammelech and Sharezer his sons smote him with the sword; and they escaped into the land of [†]Armenia: and Esar-haddon his son reigned in his stead.

38

1  In [*]those days was Hezekiah sick unto death. And Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz came unto him, and said unto him, Thus saith the LORD, [†]Set thine house in order: for thou shalt die, and not live. 2  Then Hezekiah turned his face toward the wall, and prayed unto the LORD, 3  And said, Remember now, O LORD, I beseech thee, how I have walked before thee in truth and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy sight. And Hezekiah wept [†]sore.

4 ¶ Then came the word of the LORD to Isaiah, saying, 5  Go, and say to Hezekiah, Thus saith the LORD, the God of David thy father, I have heard thy prayer, I have seen thy tears: behold, I will add unto thy days fifteen years. 6  And I will deliver thee and this city out of the hand of the king of Assyria: and I will defend this city. 7 And this shall be a sign unto thee from the LORD, that the LORD will do this thing that he hath spoken; 8  Behold, I will bring again the shadow of the degrees, which is gone down in the [†]sun dial of Ahaz, ten degrees backward. So the sun returned ten degrees, by which degrees it was gone down.

9 ¶ The writing of Hezekiah king of Judah, when he had been sick, and was recovered of his sickness: 10  I said in the cutting off of my days, I shall go to the gates of the grave: I am deprived of the residue of my years. 11  I said, I shall not see the LORD, even the LORD, in the land of the living: I shall behold man no more with the inhabitants of the world. 12  Mine age is departed, and is removed from me as a shepherd’s tent: I have cut off like a weaver my life: he will cut me off [∥]with pining sickness: from day even to night wilt thou make an end of me. 13  I reckoned till morning, that, as a lion, so will he break all my bones: from day even to night wilt thou make an end of me. 14  Like a crane or a swallow, so did I chatter: I did mourn as a dove: mine eyes fail with looking upward: O LORD, I am oppressed; [∥]undertake for me. 15  What shall I say? he hath both spoken unto me, and himself hath done it: I shall go softly all my years in the bitterness of my soul. 16  O Lord, by these things men live, and in all these things is the life of my spirit: so wilt thou recover me, and make me to live. 17  Behold, [∥]for peace I had great bitterness: but [†]thou hast in love to my soul delivered it from the pit of corruption: for thou hast cast all my sins behind thy back. 18  For the grave cannot praise thee, death can not celebrate thee: they that go down into the pit cannot hope for thy truth. 19  The living, the living, he shall praise thee, as I do this day: the father to the children shall make known thy truth. 20  The LORD was ready to save me: therefore we will sing my songs to the stringed instruments all the days of our life in the house of the LORD. 21  For Isaiah had said, Let them take a lump of figs, and lay it for a plaister upon the boil, and he shall recover. 22  Hezekiah also had said, What is the sign that I shall go up to the house of the LORD?

39

1  At [*]that time Merodach-baladan, the son of Baladan, king of Babylon, sent letters and a present to Hezekiah: for he had heard that he had been sick, and was recovered. 2  And Hezekiah was glad of them, and shewed them the house of his [∥]precious things, the silver, and the gold, and the spices, and the precious ointment, and all the house of his [∥][†]armour, and all that was found in his treasures: there was nothing in his house, nor in all his dominion, that Hezekiah shewed them not.

3 ¶ Then came Isaiah the prophet unto king Hezekiah, and said unto him, What said these men? and from whence came they unto thee? And Hezekiah said, They are come from a far country unto me, even from Babylon. 4  Then said he, What have they seen in thine house? And Hezekiah answered, All that is in mine house have they seen: there is nothing among my treasures that I have not shewed them.

5  Then said Isaiah to Hezekiah, Hear the word of the LORD of hosts: 6  Behold, the days come, that all that is in thine house, and that which thy fathers have laid up in store until this day, shall be carried to Babylon: nothing shall be left, saith the LORD. 7  And of thy sons that shall issue from thee, which thou shalt beget, shall they take away; and they shall be eunuchs in the palace of the king of Babylon. 8  Then said Hezekiah to Isaiah, Good is the word of the LORD which thou hast spoken. He said moreover, For there shall be peace and truth in my days.

40

1  Comfort ye, comfort ye my people, saith your God. 2  Speak ye [†]comfortably to Jerusalem, and cry unto her, that her [∥]warfare is accomplished, that her iniquity is pardoned: for she hath received of the LORD’s hand double for all her sins.

3 ¶ [*]The voice of him that crieth in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the LORD, make straight in the desert a highway for our God. 4  Every valley shall be exalted, and every mountain and hill shall be made low: and the crooked shall be made [∥]straight, and the rough places [∥]plain: 5  And the glory of the LORD shall be revealed, and all flesh shall see it together: for the mouth of the LORD hath spoken it. 6  The voice said, Cry. And he said, What shall I cry? [*]All flesh is grass, and all the goodliness thereof is as the flower of the field: 7  The grass withereth, the flower fadeth: because the spirit of the LORD bloweth upon it: surely the people is grass. 8  The grass withereth, the flower fadeth: but the [*]word of our God shall stand for ever.

9 ¶ [∥]O Zion, that bringest good tidings, get thee up into the high mountain; [∥]O Jerusalem, that bringest good tidings, lift up thy voice with strength; lift it up, be not afraid; say unto the cities of Judah, Behold your God! 10  Behold, the Lord GOD will come [∥]with strong hand, and his arm shall rule for him: behold, [*]his reward is with him, and [∥]his work before him. 11  He shall [*]feed his flock like a shepherd: he shall gather the lambs with his arm, and carry them in his bosom, and shall gently lead those [∥]that are with young.

12 ¶ Who hath measured the waters in the hollow of his hand, and meted out heaven with the span, and comprehended the dust of the earth in [†]a measure, and weighed the mountains in scales, and the hills in a balance? 13 [*] Who hath directed the Spirit of the LORD, or being [†]his counsellor hath taught him? 14  With whom took he counsel, and who [†]instructed him, and taught him in the path of judgment, and taught him knowledge, and shewed to him the way of [†]understanding? 15  Behold, the nations are as a drop of a bucket, and are counted as the small dust of the balance: behold, he taketh up the isles as a very little thing. 16  And Lebanon is not sufficient to burn, nor the beasts thereof sufficient for a burnt offering. 17  All nations before him are as [*]nothing; and they are counted to him less than nothing, and vanity.

18 ¶ To whom then will ye [*]liken God? or what likeness will ye compare unto him? 19  The workman melteth a graven image, and the goldsmith spreadeth it over with gold, and casteth silver chains. 20 He that [†]is so impoverished that he hath no oblation chooseth a tree that will not rot; he seeketh unto him a cunning workman to prepare a graven image, that shall not be moved. 21  Have ye not known? have ye not heard? hath it not been told you from the beginning? have ye not understood from the foundations of the earth? 22 [∥] It is he that sitteth upon the circle of the earth, and the inhabitants thereof are as grasshoppers; that [*]stretcheth out the heavens as a curtain, and spreadeth them out as a tent to dwell in: 23  That bringeth the [*]princes to nothing; he maketh the judges of the earth as vanity. 24  Yea, they shall not be planted; yea, they shall not be sown: yea, their stock shall not take root in the earth: and he shall also blow upon them, and they shall wither, and the whirlwind shall take them away as stubble. 25  To whom then will ye liken me, or shall I be equal? saith the Holy One. 26  Lift up your eyes on high, and behold who hath created these things, that bringeth out their host by number: he calleth them all by names by the greatness of his might, for that he is strong in power; not one faileth.

27  Why sayest thou, O Jacob, and speakest, O Israel, My way is hid from the LORD, and my judgment is passed over from my God?

28 ¶ Hast thou not known? hast thou not heard, that the everlasting God, the LORD, the Creator of the ends of the earth, fainteth not, neither is weary? [*]there is no searching of his understanding. 29  He giveth power to the faint; and to them that have no might he increaseth strength. 30  Even the youths shall faint and be weary, and the young men shall utterly fall: 31  But they that wait upon the LORD shall [†]renew their strength; they shall mount up with wings as eagles; they shall run, and not be weary; and they shall walk, and not faint.

41

1  Keep silence before me, O islands; and let the people renew their strength: let them come near; then let them speak: let us come near together to judgment. 2  Who raised up [†]the righteous man from the east, called him to his foot, gave the nations before him, and made him rule over kings? he gave them as the dust to his sword, and as driven stubble to his bow. 3  He pursued them, and passed [†]safely; even by the way that he had not gone with his feet. 4  Who hath wrought and done it, calling the generations from the beginning? I the LORD, the [*]first, and with the last; I am he. 5  The isles saw it, and feared; the ends of the earth were afraid, drew near, and came. 6  They helped every one his neighbour; and every one said to his brother, [†]Be of good courage. 7  So the carpenter encouraged the [∥]goldsmith, and he that smootheth with the hammer [∥]him that smote the anvil, [∥]saying, It is ready for the sodering: and he fastened it with nails, that it should not be moved. 8  But thou, Israel, art my servant, Jacob whom I have [*]chosen, the seed of Abraham my [*]friend. 9  Thou whom I have taken from the ends of the earth, and called thee from the chief men thereof, and said unto thee, Thou art my servant; I have chosen thee, and not cast thee away.

10 ¶ Fear thou not; for I am with thee: be not dismayed; for I am thy God: I will strengthen thee; yea, I will help thee; yea, I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteousness. 11  Behold, all they that were incensed against thee shall be [*]ashamed and confounded: they shall be as nothing; and [†]they that strive with thee shall perish. 12  Thou shalt seek them, and shalt not find them, even [†]them that contended with thee: [†]they that war against thee shall be as nothing, and as a thing of nought. 13  For I the LORD thy God will hold thy right hand, saying unto thee, Fear not; I will help thee. 14  Fear not, thou worm Jacob, and ye [∥]men of Israel; I will help thee, saith the LORD, and thy redeemer, the Holy One of Israel. 15  Behold, I will make thee a new sharp threshing instrument having [†]teeth: thou shalt thresh the mountains, and beat them small, and shalt make the hills as chaff. 16  Thou shalt fan them, and the wind shall carry them away, and the whirlwind shall scatter them: and thou shalt rejoice in the LORD, and shalt glory in the Holy One of Israel. 17  When the poor and needy seek water, and there is none, and their tongue faileth for thirst, I the LORD will hear them, I the God of Israel will not forsake them. 18  I will open [*]rivers in high places, and fountains in the midst of the valleys: I will make the [*]wilderness a pool of water, and the dry land springs of water. 19  I will plant in the wilderness the cedar, the shittah tree, and the myrtle, and the oil tree; I will set in the desert the fir tree, and the pine, and the box tree together: 20  That they may see, and know, and consider, and understand together, that the hand of the LORD hath done this, and the Holy One of Israel hath created it.

21 [†] Produce your cause, saith the LORD; bring forth your strong reasons, saith the King of Jacob. 22 Let them bring them forth, and shew us what shall happen: let them shew the former things, what they be, that we may [†]consider them, and know the latter end of them; or declare us things for to come. 23  Shew the things that are to come hereafter, that we may know that ye are gods: yea, do good, or do evil, that we may be dismayed, and behold it together. 24 Behold, ye are [∥]of nothing, and your work [∥]of nought: an abomination is he that chooseth you. 25  I have raised up one from the north, and he shall come: from the rising of the sun shall he call upon my name: and he shall come upon princes as upon morter, and as the potter treadeth clay. 26  Who hath declared from the beginning, that we may know? and beforetime, that we may say, He is righteous? yea, there is none that sheweth, yea, there is none that declareth, yea, there is none that heareth your words. 27  The first shall say to Zion, Behold, behold them: and I will give to Jerusalem one that bringeth good tidings. 28  For I beheld, and there was no man; even among them, and there was no counsellor, that, when I asked of them, could [†]answer a word. 29 Behold, they are all vanity; their works are nothing: their molten images are wind and confusion.

42

1  Behold [*]my servant, whom I uphold; mine elect, in whom my soul [*]delighteth; I have put my spirit upon him: he shall bring forth judgment to the Gentiles. 2  He shall not cry, nor lift up, nor cause his voice to be heard in the street. 3  A bruised reed shall he not break, and the [∥]smoking flax shall he not [†]quench: he shall bring forth judgment unto truth. 4  He shall not fail nor be [†]discouraged, till he have set judgment in the earth: and the isles shall wait for his law.

5 ¶ Thus saith God the LORD, he that created the heavens, and stretched them out; he that spread forth the earth, and that which cometh out of it; he that giveth breath unto the people upon it, and spirit to them that walk therein: 6  I the LORD have called thee in righteousness, and will hold thine hand, and will keep thee, and give thee for a covenant of the people, for [*]a light of the Gentiles; 7  To open the blind eyes, to [*]bring out the prisoners from the prison, and them that sit in [*]darkness out of the prison house. 8 I am the LORD: that is my name: and my [*]glory will I not give to another, neither my praise to graven images. 9  Behold, the former things are come to pass, and new things do I declare: before they spring forth I tell you of them. 10  Sing unto the LORD a new song, and his praise from the end of the earth, ye that go down to the sea, and [†]all that is therein; the isles, and the inhabitants thereof. 11  Let the wilderness and the cities thereof lift up their voice, the villages that Kedar doth inhabit: let the inhabitants of the rock sing, let them shout from the top of the mountains. 12  Let them give glory unto the LORD, and declare his praise in the islands.

13  The LORD shall go forth as a mighty man, he shall stir up jealousy like a man of war: he shall cry, yea, roar; he shall [∥]prevail against his enemies. 14  I have long time holden my peace; I have been still, and refrained myself: now will I cry like a travailing woman; I will destroy and [†]devour at once. 15  I will make waste mountains and hills, and dry up all their herbs; and I will make the rivers islands, and I will dry up the pools. 16  And I will bring the blind by a way that they knew not; I will lead them in paths that they have not known: I will make darkness light before them, and crooked things [†]straight. These things will I do unto them, and not forsake them.

17 ¶ They shall be [*]turned back, they shall be greatly ashamed, that trust in graven images, that say to the molten images, Ye are our gods.

18  Hear, ye deaf; and look, ye blind, that ye may see. 19 Who is blind, but my servant? or deaf, as my messenger that I sent? who is blind as he that is perfect, and blind as the LORD’s servant? 20  Seeing many things, [*]but thou observest not; opening the ears, but he heareth not. 21  The LORD is well pleased for his righteousness’ sake; he will magnify the law, and make [∥]it honourable. 22 But this is a people robbed and spoiled; [∥]they are all of them snared in holes, and they are hid in prison houses: they are for a prey, and none delivereth; for [†]a spoil, and none saith, Restore. 23  Who among you will give ear to this? who will hearken and hear [†]for the time to come? 24  Who gave Jacob for a spoil, and Israel to the robbers? did not the LORD, he against whom we have sinned? for they would not walk in his ways, neither were they obedient unto his law. 25  Therefore he hath poured upon him the fury of his anger, and the strength of battle: and it hath set him on fire round about, yet he knew not; and it burned him, yet he laid it not to heart.

43

1  But now thus saith the LORD that created thee, O Jacob, and he that formed thee, O Israel, Fear not: for I have redeemed thee, I have called thee by thy name; thou art mine. 2  When thou passest through the waters, I will be with thee; and through the rivers, they shall not overflow thee: when thou walkest through the fire, thou shalt not be burned; neither shall the flame kindle upon thee. 3 For I am the LORD thy God, the Holy One of Israel, thy Saviour: I gave Egypt for thy ransom, Ethiopia and Seba for thee. 4  Since thou wast precious in my sight, thou hast been honourable, and I have loved thee: therefore will I give men for thee, and people for thy [∥]life. 5 [*] Fear not: for I am with thee: I will bring thy seed from the east, and gather thee from the west; 6  I will say to the north, Give up; and to the south, Keep not back: bring my sons from far, and my daughters from the ends of the earth; 7  Even every one that is called by my name: for I have created him for my glory, I have formed him; yea, I have made him.

8 ¶ Bring forth the blind people that have eyes, and the deaf that have ears. 9  Let all the nations be gathered together, and let the people be assembled: [*]who among them can declare this, and shew us former things? let them bring forth their witnesses, that they may be justified: or let them hear, and say, It is truth. 10 Ye are my witnesses, saith the LORD, and my servant whom I have chosen: that ye may know and believe me, and understand that I am he: [*]before me there was [∥]no God formed, neither shall there be after me. 11 I, even I, [*]am the LORD; and beside me there is no saviour. 12  I have declared, and have saved, and I have shewed, when there was no strange god among you: therefore ye are my witnesses, saith the LORD, that I am God. 13  Yea, before the day was I am he; and there is none that can deliver out of my hand: I will work, and who shall [†][*]let it?

14 ¶ Thus saith the LORD, your redeemer, the Holy One of Israel; For your sake I have sent to Babylon, and have brought down all their [†]nobles, and the Chaldeans, whose cry is in the ships. 15 I am the LORD, your Holy One, the creator of Israel, your King. 16  Thus saith the LORD, which [*]maketh a way in the sea, and a [*]path in the mighty waters; 17  Which bringeth forth the chariot and horse, the army and the power; they shall lie down together, they shall not rise: they are extinct, they are quenched as tow.

18 ¶ Remember ye not the former things, neither consider the things of old. 19  Behold, I will do a [*]new thing; now it shall spring forth; shall ye not know it? I will even make a way in the wilderness, and rivers in the desert. 20  The beast of the field shall honour me, the dragons and the [∥][†]owls: because I give waters in the wilderness, and rivers in the desert, to give drink to my people, my chosen. 21 [*] This people have I formed for myself; they shall shew forth my praise.

22 ¶ But thou hast not called upon me, O Jacob; but thou hast been weary of me, O Israel. 23  Thou hast not brought me the [†]small cattle of thy burnt offerings; neither hast thou honoured me with thy sacrifices. I have not caused thee to serve with an offering, nor wearied thee with incense. 24  Thou hast bought me no sweet cane with money, neither hast thou [†]filled me with the fat of thy sacrifices: but thou hast made me to serve with thy sins, thou hast wearied me with thine iniquities. 25 I, even I, am he that [*]blotteth out thy transgressions for mine own sake, and will not remember thy sins. 26  Put me in remembrance: let us plead together: declare thou, that thou mayest be justified. 27  Thy first father hath sinned, and thy [†]teachers have transgressed against me. 28  Therefore I have profaned the [∥]princes of the sanctuary, and have given Jacob to the curse, and Israel to reproaches.

44

1  Yet now hear, [*]O Jacob my servant; and Israel, whom I have chosen: 2  Thus saith the LORD that made thee, and formed thee from the womb, which will help thee; Fear not, O Jacob, my servant; and thou, Jesurun, whom I have chosen. 3  For I will [*]pour water upon him that is thirsty, and floods upon the dry ground: I will pour my spirit upon thy seed, and my blessing upon thine offspring: 4  And they shall spring up as among the grass, as willows by the water courses. 5  One shall say, I am the LORD’s; and another shall call himself by the name of Jacob; and another shall subscribe with his hand unto the LORD, and surname himself by the name of Israel. 6  Thus saith the LORD the King of Israel, and his redeemer the LORD of hosts; [*]I am the first, and I am the last; and beside me there is no God. 7  And who, as I, shall call, and shall declare it, and set it in order for me, since I appointed the ancient people? and the things that are coming, and shall come, let them shew unto them. 8  Fear ye not, neither be afraid: have not I told thee from that time, and have declared it? ye are even my witnesses. Is there a God beside me? yea, [*]there is no [†]God; I know not any.

9 ¶ They that make a graven image are all of them vanity; and their [†]delectable things shall not profit; and they are their own witnesses; [*]they see not, nor know; that they may be ashamed. 10  Who hath formed a god, or molten a graven image that is profitable for nothing? 11  Behold, all his fellows shall be [*]ashamed: and the workmen, they are of men: let them all be gathered together, let them stand up; yet they shall fear, and they shall be ashamed together. 12 [*] The smith [∥]with the tongs both worketh in the coals, and fashioneth it with hammers, and worketh it with the strength of his arms: yea, he is hungry, and his strength faileth: he drinketh no water, and is faint. 13  The carpenter stretcheth out his rule; he marketh it out with a line; he fitteth it with planes, and he marketh it out with the compass, and maketh it after the figure of a man, according to the beauty of a man; that it may remain in the house. 14  He heweth him down cedars, and taketh the cypress and the oak, which he [∥]strengtheneth for himself among the trees of the forest: he planteth an ash, and the rain doth nourish it. 15  Then shall it be for a man to burn: for he will take thereof, and warm himself; yea, he kindleth it, and baketh bread; yea, he maketh a god, and worshippeth it; he maketh it a graven image, and falleth down thereto. 16  He burneth part thereof in the fire; with part thereof he eateth flesh; he roasteth roast, and is satisfied: yea, he warmeth himself, and saith, Aha, I am warm, I have seen the fire: 17  And the residue thereof he maketh a god, even his graven image: he falleth down unto it, and worshippeth it, and prayeth unto it, and saith, Deliver me; for thou art my god. 18  They have not known nor understood: for he hath [†]shut their eyes, that they cannot see; and their hearts, that they cannot understand. 19  And none [†]considereth in his heart, neither is there knowledge nor understanding to say, I have burned part of it in the fire; yea, also I have baked bread upon the coals thereof; I have roasted flesh, and eaten it: and shall I make the residue thereof an abomination? shall I fall down to [†]the stock of a tree? 20  He feedeth [‡]on ashes: a deceived heart hath turned him aside, that he cannot deliver his soul, nor say, Is there not a lie in my right hand?

21 ¶ Remember these, O Jacob and Israel; for thou art my servant: I have formed thee; thou art my servant: O Israel, thou shalt not be forgotten of me. 22  I have blotted out, as a thick cloud, thy transgressions, and, as a cloud, thy sins: return unto me; for I have redeemed thee. 23  Sing, O ye heavens; for the LORD hath done it: shout, ye lower parts of the earth: break forth into singing, ye mountains, O forest, and every tree therein: for the LORD hath redeemed Jacob, and glorified himself in Israel. 24  Thus saith the LORD, thy redeemer, and he that formed thee from the womb, I am the LORD that maketh all things; that stretcheth forth the heavens alone; that spreadeth abroad the earth by myself; 25  That frustrateth the tokens of the liars, and maketh diviners mad; that turneth wise men backward, and maketh their knowledge foolish; 26  That confirmeth the word of his servant, and performeth the counsel of his messengers; that saith to Jerusalem, Thou shalt be inhabited; and to the cities of Judah, Ye shall be built, and I will raise up the [†]decayed places thereof: 27  That saith to the deep, Be dry, and I will dry up thy rivers: 28  That saith of Cyrus, He is my shepherd, and shall perform all my pleasure: even saying to Jerusalem, [*]Thou shalt be built; and to the temple, Thy foundation shall be laid.

45

1  Thus saith the LORD to his anointed, to Cyrus, whose right hand I [∥]have holden, to subdue nations before him; and I will loose the loins of kings, to open before him the two leaved gates; and the gates shall not be shut; 2  I will go before thee, and make the crooked places straight: I will break in pieces the gates of brass, and cut in sunder the bars of iron: 3  And I will give thee the treasures of darkness, and hidden riches of secret places, that thou mayest know that I, the LORD, which call thee by thy name, am the God of Israel. 4  For Jacob my servant’s sake, and Israel mine elect, I have even called thee by thy name: I have surnamed thee, though thou hast not known me.

5 ¶ I [*]am the LORD, and there is none else, there is no God beside me: I girded thee, though thou hast not known me: 6  That they may know from the rising of the sun, and from the west, that there is none beside me. I am the LORD, and there is none else. 7  I form the light, and create darkness: I make peace, and create evil: I the LORD do all these things. 8  Drop down, ye heavens, from above, and let the skies pour down righteousness: let the earth open, and let them bring forth salvation, and let righteousness spring up together; I the LORD have created it. 9  Woe unto him that striveth with his Maker! Let the potsherd strive with the potsherds of the earth. [*]Shall the clay say to him that fashioneth it, What makest thou? or thy work, He hath no hands? 10  Woe unto him that saith unto his father, What begettest thou? or to the woman, What hast thou brought forth?

11  Thus saith the LORD, the Holy One of Israel, and his Maker, Ask me of things to come concerning my sons, and concerning the work of my hands command ye me. 12  I have made the earth, and created man upon it: I, even my hands, have stretched out the heavens, and all their host have I commanded. 13  I have raised him up in righteousness, and I will [∥]direct all his ways: he shall [*]build my city, and he shall let go my captives, not for price nor reward, saith the LORD of hosts. 14  Thus saith the LORD, The labour of Egypt, and merchandise of Ethiopia and of the Sabeans, men of stature, shall come over unto thee, and they shall be thine: they shall come after thee; in chains they shall come over, and they shall fall down unto thee, they shall make supplication unto thee, saying, Surely God is in thee; and there is none else, there is no God. 15  Verily thou art a God that hidest thyself, O God of Israel, the Saviour. 16  They shall be ashamed, and also confounded, all of them: they shall go to confusion together that are [*]makers of idols. 17  But Israel shall be saved in the LORD with an everlasting salvation: ye shall not be ashamed nor confounded world without end. 18  For thus saith the LORD that created the heavens; God himself that formed the earth and made it; he hath established it, he created it not in vain, he formed it to be inhabited: I am the LORD; and there is none else. 19  I have not spoken in [*]secret, in a dark place of the earth: I said not unto the seed of Jacob, Seek ye me in vain: I the LORD speak righteousness, I declare things that are right.

20 ¶ Assemble yourselves and come; draw near together, ye that are escaped of the nations: they have no knowledge that set up the wood of their graven image, and pray unto a god that cannot save. 21  Tell ye, and bring them near; yea, let them take counsel together: who hath declared this from ancient time? who hath told it from that time? have not I the LORD? and there is no God else beside me; a just God and a Saviour; there is none beside me. 22  Look unto me, and be ye saved, all the ends of the earth: for I am God, and there is none else. 23  I have sworn by myself, the word is gone out of my mouth in righteousness, and shall not return, That unto me every [*]knee shall bow, every tongue shall swear. 24 [∥]Surely, shall one say, in the LORD have I [†]righteousness and strength: even to him shall men come; and all that are incensed against him shall be ashamed. 25  In the LORD shall all the seed of Israel be justified, and shall glory.

46

1  Bel boweth down, Nebo stoopeth, their idols were upon the beasts, and upon the cattle: your carriages were heavy loaden; they are a burden to the weary beast. 2  They stoop, they bow down together; they could not deliver the burden, but [†]themselves are gone into captivity.

3 ¶ Hearken unto me, O house of Jacob, and all the remnant of the house of Israel, which are borne by me from the belly, which are carried from the womb: 4 And even to your old age I am he; and even to hoar hairs will I carry you: I have made, and I will bear; even I will carry, and will deliver you.

5 ¶ [*]To whom will ye liken me, and make me equal, and compare me, that we may be like? 6  They lavish gold out of the bag, and weigh silver in the balance, and hire a goldsmith; and he maketh it a god: they fall down, yea, they worship. 7  They bear him upon the shoulder, they carry him, and set him in his place, and he standeth; from his place shall he not remove: yea, one shall cry unto him, yet can he not answer, nor save him out of his trouble. 8  Remember this, and shew yourselves men: bring it again to mind, O ye transgressors. 9  Remember the former things of old: for I am God, and there is none else; I am God, and there is none like me, 10  Declaring the end from the beginning, and from ancient times the things that are not yet done, saying, [*]My counsel shall stand, and I will do all my pleasure: 11  Calling a ravenous bird from the east, [†]the man that executeth my counsel from a far country: yea, I have spoken it, I will also bring it to pass; I have purposed it, I will also do it.

12 ¶ Hearken unto me, ye stouthearted, that are far from righteousness: 13  I bring near my righteousness; it shall not be far off, and my salvation shall not tarry: and I will place salvation in Zion for Israel my glory.

47

1  Come down, and sit in the dust, O virgin daughter of Babylon, sit on the ground: there is no throne, O daughter of the Chaldeans: for thou shalt no more be called tender and delicate. 2  Take the millstones, and grind meal: uncover thy locks, make bare the leg, uncover the thigh, pass over the rivers. 3  Thy nakedness shall be uncovered, yea, thy shame shall be seen: I will take vengeance, and I will not meet thee as a man. 4  As for our redeemer, the LORD of hosts is his name, the Holy One of Israel. 5  Sit thou silent, and get thee into darkness, O daughter of the Chaldeans: for thou shalt no more be called, The lady of kingdoms.

6 ¶ I was wroth with my people, I have polluted mine inheritance, and given them into thine hand: thou didst shew them no mercy; upon the ancient hast thou very heavily laid [‡]thy yoke.

7 ¶ And thou saidst, I shall be [*]a lady for ever: so that thou didst not lay these things to thy heart, neither didst remember the latter end of it. 8  Therefore hear now this, thou that art given to pleasures, that dwellest carelessly, that sayest in thine heart, I am, and none else beside me; I shall not sit as a widow, neither shall I know the loss of children: 9  But these two [*]things shall come to thee in a moment in one day, the loss of children, and widowhood: they shall come upon thee in their perfection for the multitude of thy sorceries, and for the great abundance of thine enchantments.

10 ¶ For thou hast trusted in thy wickedness: thou hast said, None seeth me. Thy wisdom and thy knowledge, it hath [∥]perverted thee; and thou hast said in thine heart, I am, and none else beside me.

11 ¶ Therefore shall evil come upon thee; thou shalt not know [†]from whence it riseth: and mischief shall fall upon thee; thou shalt not be able to [†]put it off: and desolation shall come upon thee suddenly, which thou shalt not know. 12  Stand now with thine enchantments, and with the multitude of thy sorceries, wherein thou hast laboured from thy youth; if so be thou shalt be able to profit, if so be thou mayest prevail. 13  Thou art wearied in the multitude of thy counsels. Let now the [†]astrologers, the stargazers, [†]the monthly prognosticators, stand up, and save thee from these things that shall come upon thee. 14  Behold, they shall be as stubble; the fire shall burn them; they shall not deliver [†]themselves from the power of the flame: there shall not be a coal to warm at, nor fire to sit before it. 15  Thus shall they be unto thee with whom thou hast laboured, even thy merchants, from thy youth: they shall wander every one to his quarter; none shall save thee.

48

1  Hear ye this, O house of Jacob, which are called by the name of Israel, and are come forth out of the waters of Judah, which swear by the name of the LORD, and make mention of the God of Israel, but not in truth, nor in righteousness. 2  For they call themselves of the holy city, and stay themselves upon the God of Israel; The LORD of hosts is his name. 3  I have declared the former things from the beginning; and they went forth out of my mouth, and I shewed them; I did them suddenly, and they came to pass. 4  Because I knew that thou art [†]obstinate, and thy neck is an iron sinew, and thy brow brass; 5  I have even from the beginning declared it to thee; before it came to pass I shewed it thee: lest thou shouldest say, Mine idol hath done them, and my graven image, and my molten image, hath commanded them. 6  Thou hast heard, see all this; and will not ye declare it? I have shewed thee new things from this time, even hidden things, and thou didst not know them. 7  They are created now, and not from the beginning; even before the day when thou heardest them not; lest thou shouldest say, Behold, I knew them. 8  Yea, thou heardest not; yea, thou knewest not; yea, from that time that thine ear was not opened: for I knew that thou wouldest deal very treacherously, and wast called a transgressor from the womb.

9 ¶ For my name’s sake will I defer mine anger, and for my praise will I refrain for thee, that I cut thee not off. 10  Behold, I have refined thee, but not [∥]with silver; I have chosen thee in the furnace of affliction. 11 For mine own sake, even for mine own sake, will I do it: for how should my name be polluted? and [*]I will not give my glory unto another.

12 ¶ Hearken unto me, O Jacob and Israel, my called; I am he; I am the [*]first, I also am the last. 13  Mine hand also hath laid the foundation of the earth, and [∥]my right hand hath spanned the heavens: when I call unto them, they stand up together. 14  All ye, assemble yourselves, and hear; which among them hath declared these things? The LORD hath loved him: he will do his pleasure on Babylon, and his arm shall be on the Chaldeans. 15 I, even I, have spoken; yea, I have called him: I have brought him, and he shall make his way prosperous.

16 ¶ Come ye near unto me, hear ye this; I have not spoken in secret from the beginning; from the time that it was, there am I: and now the Lord GOD, and his Spirit, hath sent me. 17  Thus saith the LORD, thy Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel; I am the LORD thy God which teacheth thee to profit, which leadeth thee by the way that thou shouldest go. 18  O that thou hadst hearkened to my commandments! then had thy peace been as a river, and thy righteousness as the waves of the sea: 19  Thy seed also had been as the sand, and the offspring of thy bowels like the gravel thereof; his name should not have been cut off nor destroyed from before me.

20 ¶ Go ye forth of Babylon, flee ye from the Chaldeans, with a voice of singing declare ye, tell this, utter it even to the end of the earth; say ye, The LORD hath [*]redeemed his servant Jacob. 21  And they thirsted not when he led them through the deserts: he [*]caused the waters to flow out of the rock for them: he clave the rock also, and the waters gushed out. 22 [*] There is no peace, saith the LORD, unto the wicked.

49

1  Listen, O isles, unto me; and hearken, ye people, from far; The LORD hath called me from the womb; from the bowels of my mother hath he made mention of my name. 2  And he hath made my mouth like a sharp sword; in the shadow of his hand hath he hid me, and made me a polished shaft; in his quiver hath he hid me; 3  And said unto me, Thou art my servant, O Israel, in whom I will be glorified. 4  Then I said, I have laboured in vain, I have spent my strength for nought, and in vain: yet surely my judgment is with the LORD, and [∥]my work with my God.

5 ¶ And now, saith the LORD that formed me from the womb to be his servant, to bring Jacob again to him, [∥]Though Israel be not gathered, yet shall I be glorious in the eyes of the LORD, and my God shall be my strength. 6  And he said, [∥]It is a light thing that thou shouldest be my servant to raise up the tribes of Jacob, and to restore the [∥]preserved of Israel: I will also give thee for a [*]light to the Gentiles, that thou mayest be my salvation unto the end of the earth.

7  Thus saith the LORD, the Redeemer of Israel, and his Holy One, [∥]to him whom man despiseth, to him whom the nation abhorreth, to a servant of rulers, Kings shall see and arise, princes also shall worship, because of the LORD that is faithful, and the Holy One of Israel, and he shall choose thee. 8  Thus saith the LORD, [*]In an acceptable time have I heard thee, and in a day of salvation have I helped thee: and I will preserve thee, and give thee for a covenant of the people, to [∥]establish the earth, to cause to inherit the desolate heritages; 9  That thou mayest say [*]to the prisoners, Go forth; to them that are in darkness, Shew yourselves. They shall feed in the ways, and their pastures shall be in all high places. 10  They shall not [*]hunger nor thirst; neither shall the heat nor sun smite them: for he that hath mercy on them shall lead them, even by the springs of water shall he guide them. 11  And I will make all my mountains a way, and my highways shall be exalted. 12  Behold, these shall come from far: and, lo, these from the north and from the west; and these from the land of Sinim.

13 ¶ Sing, O [‡]heavens; and be joyful, O earth; and break forth into singing, O mountains: for [‡]the LORD hath comforted his people, and will have mercy upon his afflicted. 14  But Zion said, The LORD hath forsaken me, and my Lord hath forgotten me. 15  Can a woman forget her sucking child, [†]that she should not have compassion on the son of her womb? yea, they may forget, yet will I not forget thee. 16  Behold, I have graven thee upon the palms of my hands; thy walls are continually before me. 17  Thy children shall make haste; thy destroyers and they that made thee waste shall go forth of thee.

18 ¶ [*]Lift up thine eyes round about, and behold: all these gather themselves together, and come to thee. As I live, saith the LORD, thou shalt surely clothe thee with them all, as with an ornament, and bind them on thee, as a bride doeth. 19  For thy waste and thy desolate places, and the land of thy destruction, shall even now be too narrow by reason of the inhabitants, and they that swallowed thee up shall be far away. 20  The children which thou shalt have, after thou hast lost the other, shall say again in thine ears, The place is too strait for me: give place to me that I may dwell. 21  Then shalt thou say in thine heart, Who hath begotten me these, seeing I have lost my children, and am desolate, a captive, and removing to and fro? and who hath brought up these? Behold, I was left alone; these, where had they been? 22  Thus saith the Lord GOD, Behold, I will lift up mine hand to the Gentiles, and set up my standard to the people: and they shall bring thy sons in their [†]arms, and thy daughters shall be carried upon their shoulders. 23  And kings shall be thy [†]nursing fathers, and their [†]queens thy nursing mothers: they shall bow down to thee with their face toward the earth, and [*]lick up the dust of thy feet; and thou shalt know that I am the LORD: for they shall not be ashamed that wait for me.

24 ¶ Shall the prey be taken from the mighty, or [†]the lawful captive delivered? 25  But thus saith the LORD, Even the [†]captives of the mighty shall be taken away, and the prey of the terrible shall be delivered: for I will contend with him that contendeth with thee, and I will save thy children. 26  And I will feed them that oppress thee with their own flesh; and they shall be drunken with their own [*]blood, as with [∥]sweet wine: and all flesh shall know that I the LORD am thy Saviour and thy Redeemer, the mighty One of Jacob.

50

1  Thus saith the LORD, Where is the bill of your mother’s divorcement, whom I have put away? or which of my creditors is it to whom I have sold you? Behold, for your iniquities have ye sold yourselves, and for your transgressions is your mother put away. 2  Wherefore, when I came, was there no man? when I called, was there none to answer? [*]Is my hand shortened at all, that it cannot redeem? or have I no power to deliver? behold, at my rebuke I [*]dry up the sea, I make the [*]rivers a wilderness: their fish stinketh, because there is no water, and dieth for thirst. 3  I clothe the heavens with blackness, and I make sackcloth their covering.

4  The Lord GOD hath given me the tongue of the learned, that I should know how to speak a word in season to him that is [*]weary: he wakeneth morning by morning, he wakeneth mine ear to hear as the learned.

5 ¶ The Lord GOD hath opened mine ear, and I was not [*]rebellious, neither turned away back. 6 [*] I gave my back to the smiters, and my cheeks to them that plucked off the hair: I hid not my face from shame and spitting.

7 ¶ For the Lord GOD will help me; therefore shall I not be confounded: therefore have I set my face like a flint, and I know that I shall not be ashamed. 8 [*] He is near that justifieth me; who will contend with me? let us stand together: who is [†]mine adversary? let him come near to me. 9  Behold, the Lord GOD will help me; who is he that shall condemn me? lo, they all shall wax old as a garment; the moth shall eat them up.

10 ¶ Who is among you that feareth the LORD, that obeyeth the voice of his servant, that walketh in darkness, and hath no light? let him trust in the name of the LORD, and stay upon his God. 11  Behold, all ye that kindle a fire, that compass yourselves about with sparks: walk in the light of your fire, and in the sparks that ye have kindled. [*]This shall ye have of mine hand; ye shall lie down in sorrow.

51

1  Hearken to me, ye that follow after righteousness, ye that seek the LORD: look unto the rock whence ye are hewn, and to the hole of the pit whence ye are digged. 2  Look unto Abraham your father, and unto Sarah that bare you: for I called him alone, and blessed him, and increased him. 3  For the LORD shall comfort Zion: he will comfort all her waste places; and he will make her wilderness like Eden, and her desert like the garden of the LORD; joy and gladness shall be found therein, thanksgiving, and the voice of melody.

4 ¶ Hearken unto me, my people; and give ear unto me, O my nation: for a law shall proceed from me, and I will make my judgment to rest for a light of the people. 5  My righteousness is near; my salvation is gone forth, and mine arms shall judge the people; the isles shall wait upon me, and on mine arm shall they trust. 6  Lift up your eyes to the heavens, and look upon the earth beneath: for [*]the heavens shall vanish away like smoke, and the earth shall wax old like a garment, and they that dwell therein shall die in like manner: but my salvation shall be for ever, and my righteousness shall not be abolished.

7 ¶ Hearken unto me, ye that know righteousness, the people [*]in whose heart is my law; [*]fear ye not the reproach of men, neither be ye afraid of their revilings. 8  For the moth shall eat them up like a garment, and the worm shall eat them like wool: but my righteousness shall be for ever, and my salvation from generation to generation.

9 ¶ Awake, awake, put on strength, O arm of the LORD; awake, as in the ancient days, in the generations of old. Art thou not it that hath cut Rahab, and wounded the [*]dragon? 10  Art thou not it which hath [*]dried the sea, the waters of the great deep; that hath made the depths of the sea a way for the ransomed to pass over? 11  Therefore [*]the redeemed of the LORD shall return, and come with singing unto Zion; and everlasting joy shall be upon their head: they shall obtain gladness and joy; and sorrow and mourning shall flee away. 12 I, even I, am he that comforteth you: who art thou, that thou shouldest be afraid [*]of a man that shall die, and of the son of man which shall be made [*]as grass; 13  And forgettest the LORD thy maker, that hath stretched forth the heavens, and laid the foundations of the earth; and hast feared continually every day because of the fury of the oppressor, as if he [∥]were ready to destroy? and where is the fury of the oppressor? 14  The captive exile hasteneth that he may be loosed, and that he should not die in the pit, nor that his bread should fail. 15 But I am the LORD thy God, that [*]divided the sea, whose waves roared: The LORD of hosts is his name. 16  And I have put my words [*]in thy mouth, and I have covered thee in the shadow of mine hand, that I may plant the heavens, and lay the foundations of the earth, and say unto Zion, Thou art my people.

17 ¶ [*]Awake, awake, stand up, O Jerusalem, which hast drunk at the hand of the LORD the cup of his fury; thou hast drunken the dregs of the cup of trembling, and wrung them out. 18  There is none to guide her among all the sons whom she hath brought forth; neither is there any that taketh her by the hand of all the sons that she hath brought up. 19 [*] These two things [†]are come unto thee; who shall be sorry for thee? desolation, and [†]destruction, and the famine, and the sword: by whom shall I comfort thee? 20  Thy sons have fainted, they lie at the head of all the streets, as a wild bull in a net: they are full of the fury of the LORD, the rebuke of thy God.

21 ¶ Therefore hear now this, thou afflicted, and drunken, but not with wine: 22  Thus saith thy Lord the LORD, and thy God that pleadeth the cause of his people, Behold, I have taken out of thine hand the cup of trembling, even the dregs of the cup of my fury; thou shalt no more drink it again: 23  But I will put it into the hand of them that afflict thee; which have said to thy soul, Bow down, that we may go over: and thou hast laid thy body as the ground, and as the street, to them that went over.

52

1  Awake, [*]awake; put on thy strength, O Zion; put on thy beautiful garments, O Jerusalem, the holy city: for henceforth there shall no more come into thee the uncircumcised and the unclean. 2  Shake thyself from the dust; arise, and sit down, O Jerusalem: loose thyself from the bands of thy neck, O captive daughter of Zion. 3  For thus saith the LORD, Ye have sold yourselves for nought; and ye shall be redeemed without money. 4  For thus saith the Lord GOD, My people went down aforetime into [*]Egypt to sojourn there; and the Assyrian oppressed them without cause. 5  Now therefore, what have I here, saith the LORD, that my people is taken away for nought? they that rule over them make them to howl, saith the LORD; and my name continually every day is [*]blasphemed. 6  Therefore my people shall know my name: therefore they shall know in that day that I am he that doth speak: behold, it is I.

7 ¶ [*]How beautiful upon the mountains are the feet of him that bringeth good tidings, that publisheth peace; that bringeth good tidings of good, that publisheth salvation; that saith unto Zion, Thy God reigneth! 8  Thy watchmen shall lift up the voice; with the voice together shall they sing: for they shall see eye to eye, when the LORD shall bring again Zion.

9 ¶ Break forth into joy, sing together, ye waste places of Jerusalem: for the LORD hath comforted his people, he hath redeemed Jerusalem. 10  The LORD hath made bare his holy arm in the eyes of all the nations; and [*]all the ends of the earth shall see the salvation of our God.

11 ¶ [*]Depart ye, depart ye, go ye out from thence, touch no unclean thing; go ye out of the midst of her; be ye clean, that bear the vessels of the LORD. 12  For ye shall not go out with haste, nor go by flight: for the LORD will go before you; and the God of Israel will [†]be your rereward.

13 ¶ Behold, my servant shall [∥]deal prudently, he shall be exalted and extolled, and be very high. 14  As many were astonied at thee; his [*]visage was so marred more than any man, and his form more than the sons of men: 15  So shall he sprinkle many nations; the kings shall shut their mouths at him: for that [*]which had not been told them shall they see; and that which they had not heard shall they consider.

53

1  Who [*]hath believed our [∥][†]report? and to whom is the arm of the LORD revealed? 2  For he shall grow up before him as a tender plant, and as a root out of a dry ground: he hath no form nor comeliness; and when we shall see him, there is no beauty that we should desire him. 3 [*] He is despised and rejected of men; a man of sorrows, and acquainted with grief: and [∥][†]we hid as it were our faces from him; he was despised, and we esteemed him not.

4 ¶ Surely [*]he hath borne our griefs, and carried our sorrows: yet we did esteem him stricken, smitten of God, and afflicted. 5 But he was [∥][*]wounded for our transgressions, he was bruised for our iniquities: the chastisement of our peace was upon him; and with his [*][†]stripes we are healed. 6  All we like sheep have gone astray; we have turned every one to his own way; and the LORD [†]hath laid on him the iniquity of us all. 7  He was oppressed, and he was afflicted, yet [*]he opened not his mouth: he is brought as a [*]lamb to the slaughter, and as a sheep before her shearers is dumb, so he openeth not his mouth. 8 [∥] He was taken from prison and from judgment: and who shall declare his generation? for he was cut off out of the land of the living: for the transgression of my people [†]was he stricken. 9  And he made his grave with the wicked, and with the rich in his [†]death; because he had done no violence, neither was any [*]deceit in his mouth.

10 ¶ Yet it pleased the LORD to bruise him; he hath put him to grief: [∥]when thou shalt make his soul an offering for sin, he shall see his seed, he shall prolong his days, and the pleasure of the LORD shall prosper in his hand. 11  He shall see of the travail of his soul, and shall be satisfied: by his knowledge shall my righteous servant justify many; for he shall bear their iniquities. 12  Therefore will I divide him a portion with the great, and he shall divide the spoil with the strong; because he hath poured out his soul unto death: and he was [*]numbered with the transgressors; and he bare the sin of many, and [*]made intercession for the transgressors.

54

1 [*] Sing, O barren, thou that didst not bear; break forth into singing, and cry aloud, thou that didst not travail with child: for more are the children of the desolate than the children of the married wife, saith the LORD. 2  Enlarge the place of thy tent, and let them stretch forth the curtains of thine habitations: spare not, lengthen thy cords, and strengthen thy stakes; 3  For thou shalt break forth on the right hand and on the left; and thy seed shall inherit the Gentiles, and make the desolate cities to be inhabited. 4  Fear not; for thou shalt not be ashamed: neither be thou confounded; for thou shalt not be put to shame: for thou shalt forget the shame of thy youth, and shalt not remember the reproach of thy widowhood any more. 5  For thy Maker is thine husband; the [*]LORD of hosts is his name; and thy Redeemer the Holy One of Israel; The God of the whole earth shall he be called.

6  For the LORD hath called thee as a woman forsaken and grieved in spirit, and a wife of youth, when thou wast refused, saith thy God. 7  For a small moment have I forsaken thee; but with great mercies will I gather thee. 8  In a little wrath I hid my face from thee for a moment; but with everlasting kindness will I have mercy on thee, saith the LORD thy Redeemer. 9 For this is as the waters of [*]Noah unto me: for as I have sworn that the waters of Noah should no more go over the earth; so have I sworn that I would not be wroth with thee, nor rebuke thee. 10  For the mountains shall depart, and the hills be removed; but my kindness shall not depart from thee, neither shall the covenant of my peace be removed, saith the LORD that hath mercy on thee.

11 ¶ O thou afflicted, tossed with tempest, and not comforted, behold, I will lay thy stones with [*]fair colours, and lay thy foundations with sapphires. 12  And I will make thy windows of agates, and thy gates of carbuncles, and all thy borders of pleasant stones. 13  And all thy children shall be [*]taught of the LORD; and great shall be the peace of thy children. 14  In righteousness shalt thou be established: thou shalt be far from oppression; for thou shalt not fear: and from terror; for it shall not come near thee. 15  Behold, they shall surely gather together, but not by me: whosoever shall gather together against thee shall fall for thy sake. 16  Behold, I have created the smith that bloweth the coals in the fire, and that bringeth forth an instrument for his work; and I have created the waster to destroy.

17 ¶ No weapon that is formed against thee shall prosper; and every tongue that shall rise against thee in judgment thou shalt condemn. This is the heritage of the servants of the LORD, and their righteousness is of me, saith the LORD.

55

1  Ho, [*]every one that thirsteth, come ye to the waters, and he that hath no money; come ye, buy, and eat; yea, come, buy wine and milk without money and without price. 2  Wherefore do ye [†]spend money for that which is not bread? and your labour for that which satisfieth not? hearken diligently unto me, and eat ye that which is good, and let your soul delight itself in fatness. 3  Incline your ear, and come unto me: hear, and your soul shall live; and I will make an everlasting covenant with you, even the [*]sure mercies of David. 4  Behold, I have given him for a witness to the people, a leader and commander to the people. 5  Behold, thou shalt call a nation that thou knowest not, and nations that knew not thee shall run unto thee because of the LORD thy God, and for the Holy One of Israel; for he hath glorified thee.

6 ¶ Seek ye the LORD while he may be found, call ye upon him while he is near: 7  Let the wicked forsake his way, and [†]the unrighteous man his thoughts: and let him return unto the LORD, and he will have mercy upon him; and to our God, for [†]he will abundantly pardon.

8 ¶ For my thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your ways my ways, saith the LORD. 9 For as the heavens are higher than the earth, so are my ways higher than your ways, and my thoughts than your thoughts. 10  For as the rain cometh down, and the snow from heaven, and returneth not thither, but watereth the earth, and maketh it bring forth and bud, that it may give seed to the sower, and bread to the eater: 11  So shall my word be that goeth forth out of my mouth: it shall not return unto me void, but it shall accomplish that which I please, and it shall prosper in the thing whereto I sent it. 12  For ye shall go out with joy, and be led forth with peace: the mountains and the hills shall [*]break forth before you into singing, and all the trees of the field shall clap their hands. 13  Instead of the thorn shall come up the fir tree, and instead of the brier shall come up the myrtle tree: and it shall be to the LORD for a name, for an everlasting sign that shall not be cut off.

56

1  Thus saith the LORD, Keep ye [∥]judgment, and do justice: for my salvation is near to come, and my righteousness to be revealed. 2  Blessed is the man that doeth this, and the son of man that layeth hold on it; that keepeth the sabbath from polluting it, and keepeth his hand from doing any evil.

3 ¶ Neither let the son of the stranger, that hath joined himself to the LORD, speak, saying, The LORD hath utterly separated me from his people: neither let the eunuch say, Behold, I am a dry tree. 4  For thus saith the LORD unto the eunuchs that keep my sabbaths, and choose the things that please me, and take hold of my covenant; 5  Even unto them will I give in mine house and within my walls a place and a name better than of sons and of daughters: I will give them an everlasting name, that shall not be cut off. 6  Also the sons of the stranger, that join themselves to the LORD, to serve him, and to love the name of the LORD, to be his servants, every one that keepeth the sabbath from polluting it, and taketh hold of my covenant; 7  Even them will I [*]bring to my holy mountain, and make them joyful in my house of prayer: their burnt offerings and their sacrifices shall be accepted upon mine altar; for [*]mine house shall be called an house of prayer for all people. 8  The Lord GOD which gathereth the outcasts of Israel saith, Yet will I gather others to him, [†]beside those that are gathered unto him.

9 ¶ All ye beasts of the field, come to devour, yea, all ye beasts in the forest. 10  His watchmen are blind: they are all ignorant, they are all dumb dogs, they cannot bark; [∥]sleeping, lying down, loving to slumber. 11 Yea, they are [†]greedy dogs which [†]can never have enough, and they are shepherds that cannot understand: they all look to their own way, every one for his gain, from his quarter. 12  Come ye, say they, I will fetch wine, and we will fill ourselves with strong drink; and to morrow shall be as this day, and much more abundant.

57

1  The righteous perisheth, and no man layeth it to heart: and [†][*]merciful men are taken away, none considering that the righteous is taken away [∥]from the evil to come. 2  He shall [∥]enter into peace: they shall rest in their beds, each one walking [∥]in his uprightness.

3 ¶ But draw near hither, ye sons of the sorceress, the seed of the adulterer and the whore. 4  Against whom do ye sport yourselves? against whom make ye a wide mouth, and draw out the tongue? are ye not children of transgression, a seed of falsehood, 5  Enflaming yourselves [∥]with idols [*]under every green tree, slaying the children in the valleys under the clifts of the rocks? 6  Among the smooth stones of the stream is thy portion; they, they are thy lot: even to them hast thou poured a drink offering, thou hast offered a meat offering. Should I receive comfort in these? 7  Upon a lofty and high mountain hast thou set thy bed: even thither wentest thou up to offer sacrifice. 8  Behind the doors also and the posts hast thou set up thy remembrance: for thou hast discovered thyself to another than me, and art gone up; thou hast enlarged thy bed, and [∥]made [‡]thee a covenant with them; thou lovedst their bed [∥]where thou sawest it. 9  And [∥]thou wentest to the king with ointment, and didst increase thy perfumes, and didst send thy messengers far off, and didst debase thyself even unto hell. 10  Thou art wearied in the greatness of thy way; yet saidst thou not, There is no hope: thou hast found the [∥]life of thine hand; therefore thou wast not grieved. 11  And of whom hast thou been afraid or feared, that thou hast lied, and hast not remembered me, nor laid it to thy heart? have not I held my peace even of old, and thou fearest me not? 12  I will declare thy righteousness, and thy works; for they shall not profit thee.

13 ¶ When thou criest, let thy companies deliver thee; but the wind shall carry them all away; vanity shall take them: but he that putteth his trust in me shall possess the land, and shall inherit my holy mountain; 14  And shall say, [*]Cast ye up, cast ye up, prepare the way, take up the stumblingblock out of the way of my people. 15  For thus saith the high and lofty One that inhabiteth eternity, whose name is Holy; I dwell in the high and holy place, with him also that is of a contrite and humble spirit, to revive the spirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones. 16  For I will not contend for ever, neither will I be always wroth: for the spirit should fail before me, and the souls which I have made.

17  For the iniquity of his covetousness was I wroth, and smote him: I hid me, and was wroth, and he went on [†]frowardly in the way of his heart. 18  I have seen his ways, and will heal him: I will lead him also, and restore comforts unto him and to his mourners. 19  I create the fruit of the lips; Peace, peace to him that is far off, and to him that is near, saith the LORD; and I will heal him. 20  But the wicked are like the troubled sea, when it cannot rest, whose waters cast up mire and dirt. 21 [*] There is no peace, saith my God, to the wicked.

58

1  Cry [†]aloud, spare not, lift up thy voice like a trumpet, and shew my people their transgression, and the house of Jacob their sins. 2  Yet they seek me daily, and delight to know my ways, as a nation that did righteousness, and forsook not the ordinance of their God: they ask of me the ordinances of justice; they take delight in approaching to God.

3 ¶ Wherefore have we fasted, say they, and thou seest not? wherefore have we afflicted our soul, and thou takest no knowledge? Behold, in the day of your fast ye find pleasure, and exact all your [∥][†]labours. 4  Behold, ye fast for strife and debate, and to smite with the fist of wickedness: [∥]ye shall not fast as ye do this day, to make your voice to be heard on high. 5  Is it [*]such a fast that I have chosen? [*][∥]a day for a man to afflict his soul? is it to bow down his head as a bulrush, and to spread sackcloth and ashes under him? wilt thou call this a fast, and an acceptable day to the LORD? 6  Is not this the fast that I have chosen? to loose the bands of wickedness, to undo [†]the heavy burdens, and to let the [†]oppressed go free, and that ye break every yoke? 7  Is it not [*]to deal thy bread to the hungry, and that thou bring the poor that are [∥]cast out to thy house? when thou seest the naked, that thou cover him; and that thou hide not thyself from thine own flesh?

8 ¶ Then shall thy light break forth as the morning, and thine health shall spring forth speedily: and thy righteousness shall go before thee; the glory of the LORD [†]shall be thy rereward. 9  Then shalt thou call, and the LORD shall answer; thou shalt cry, and he shall say, Here I am. If thou take away from the midst of thee the yoke, the putting forth of the finger, and speaking vanity; 10 And if thou draw out thy soul to the hungry, and satisfy the afflicted soul; then shall thy light rise in obscurity, and thy darkness be as the noonday: 11  And the LORD shall guide thee continually, and satisfy thy soul in [†]drought, and make fat thy bones: and thou shalt be like a watered garden, and like a spring of water, whose waters [†]fail not. 12 And they that shall be of thee [*]shall build the old waste places: thou shalt raise up the foundations of many generations; and thou shalt be called, The repairer of the breach, The restorer of paths to dwell in.

13 ¶ If thou turn away thy foot from the sabbath, from doing thy pleasure on my holy day; and call the sabbath a delight, the holy of the LORD, honourable; and shalt honour him, not doing thine own ways, nor finding thine own pleasure, nor speaking thine own words: 14  Then shalt thou delight thyself in the LORD; and I will cause thee to [*]ride upon the high places of the earth, and feed thee with the heritage of Jacob thy father: for the mouth of the LORD hath spoken it.

59

1  Behold, the LORD’s hand is not [*]shortened, that it cannot save; neither his ear heavy, that it cannot hear: 2  But your iniquities have separated between you and your God, and your sins [∥]have hid his face from you, that he will not hear. 3  For [*]your hands are defiled with blood, and your fingers with iniquity; your lips have spoken lies, your tongue hath muttered perverseness. 4  None calleth for justice, nor any pleadeth for truth: they trust in vanity, and speak lies; [*]they conceive mischief, and bring forth iniquity. 5  They hatch [∥]cockatrice’ eggs, and weave the spider’s web: he that eateth of their eggs dieth, and [∥]that which is crushed breaketh out into a viper. 6 [*] Their webs shall not become garments, neither shall they cover themselves with their works: their works are works of iniquity, and the act of violence is in their hands. 7 [*] Their feet run to evil, and they make haste to shed innocent blood: their thoughts are thoughts of iniquity; wasting and [†]destruction are in their paths. 8  The way of peace they know not; and there is no [∥]judgment in their goings: they have made them crooked paths: whosoever goeth therein shall not know peace.

9 ¶ Therefore is judgment far from us, neither doth justice overtake us: we wait for light, but behold obscurity; for brightness, but we walk in darkness. 10  We grope for the wall like the blind, and we grope as if we had no eyes: we stumble at noonday as in the night; we are in desolate places as dead men. 11  We roar all like bears, and mourn sore like doves: we look for judgment, but there is none; for salvation, but it is far off from us. 12  For our transgressions are multiplied before thee, and our sins testify against us: for our transgressions are with us; and as for our iniquities, we know them; 13  In transgressing and lying against the LORD, and departing away from our God, speaking oppression and revolt, conceiving and uttering from the heart words of falsehood. 14  And judgment is turned away backward, and justice standeth afar off: for truth is fallen in the street, and equity cannot enter. 15  Yea, truth faileth; and he that departeth from evil [∥]maketh himself a prey: and the LORD saw it, and [†]it displeased him that there was no judgment.

16 ¶ And he saw that there was no man, and wondered that there was no intercessor: [*]therefore his arm brought salvation unto him; and his righteousness, it sustained him. 17 [*] For he put on righteousness as a breastplate, and an helmet of salvation upon his head; and he put on the garments of vengeance for clothing, and was clad with zeal as a cloke. 18 [*] According to their [†]deeds, accordingly he will repay, fury to his adversaries, recompence to his enemies; to the islands he will repay recompence. 19  So shall they fear the name of the LORD from the west, and his glory from the rising of the sun. When the enemy shall come in [*]like a flood, the Spirit of the LORD shall [∥]lift up a standard against him.

20 ¶ And [*]the Redeemer shall come to Zion, and unto them that turn from transgression in Jacob, saith the LORD. 21 As for me, this is my covenant with them, saith the LORD; My spirit that is upon thee, and my words which I have put in thy mouth, shall not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy seed, nor out of the mouth of thy seed’s seed, saith the LORD, from henceforth and for ever.

60

1  Arise, [∥]shine; for thy light is come, and the glory of the LORD is risen upon thee. 2  For, behold, the darkness shall cover the earth, and gross darkness the people: but the LORD shall arise upon thee, and his glory shall be seen upon thee. 3  And the [*]Gentiles shall come to thy light, and kings to the brightness of thy rising. 4 [*] Lift up thine eyes round about, and see: all they gather themselves together, they come to thee: thy sons shall come from far, and thy daughters shall be nursed at thy side. 5  Then thou shalt see, and flow together, and thine heart shall fear, and be enlarged; because the [∥]abundance of the sea shall be converted unto thee, the [∥]forces of the Gentiles shall come unto thee. 6  The multitude of camels shall cover thee, the dromedaries of Midian and Ephah; all they from Sheba shall come: they shall bring [*]gold and incense; and they shall shew forth the praises of the LORD. 7  All the flocks of Kedar shall be gathered together unto thee, the rams of Nebaioth shall minister unto thee: they shall come up with acceptance on mine altar, and I will glorify the house of my glory. 8 Who are these that fly as a cloud, and as the doves to their windows?

9  Surely the isles shall wait for me, and the ships of Tarshish first, [*]to bring thy sons from far, their silver and their gold with them, unto the name of the LORD thy God, and to the Holy One of Israel, because he hath glorified thee. 10  And the sons of strangers shall build up thy walls, and their kings shall minister unto thee: for in my wrath I smote thee, but in my favour have I had mercy on thee. 11  Therefore thy gates [*]shall be open continually; they shall not be shut day nor night; that men may bring unto thee the [∥]forces of the Gentiles, and that their kings may be brought. 12  For the nation and kingdom that will not serve thee shall perish; yea, those nations shall be utterly wasted. 13  The glory of Lebanon shall come unto thee, the fir tree, the pine tree, and the box together, to beautify the place of my sanctuary; and I will make the place of my feet glorious. 14  The sons also of them that afflicted thee shall come bending unto thee; and all they that despised thee shall [*]bow themselves down at the soles of thy feet; and they shall call thee, The city of the LORD, The Zion of the Holy One of Israel.

15  Whereas thou hast been forsaken and hated, so that no man went through thee, I will make thee an eternal excellency, a joy of many generations. 16  Thou shalt also suck the milk of the Gentiles, and shalt suck the breast of kings: and thou shalt know that I the LORD am thy Saviour and thy Redeemer, the mighty One of Jacob. 17  For brass I will bring gold, and for iron I will bring silver, and for wood brass, and for stones iron: I will also make thy officers peace, and thine exactors righteousness. 18  Violence shall no more be heard in thy land, wasting nor destruction within thy borders; but thou shalt call thy walls Salvation, and thy gates Praise. 19 [*] The sun shall be no more thy light by day; neither for brightness shall the moon give light unto thee: but the LORD shall be unto thee an everlasting light, and thy God thy glory. 20  Thy sun shall no more go down; neither shall thy moon withdraw itself: for the LORD shall be thine everlasting light, and the days of thy mourning shall be ended. 21  Thy people also shall be all righteous: they shall inherit the land for ever, the branch of my planting, the work of my hands, that I may be glorified. 22  A little one shall become a thousand, and a small one a strong nation: I the LORD will hasten it in his time.

61

1  The [*]Spirit of the Lord GOD is upon me; because the LORD hath anointed me to preach good tidings unto the meek; he hath sent me to bind up the brokenhearted, to proclaim liberty to the captives, and the opening of the prison to them that are bound; 2  To proclaim the acceptable year of the LORD, and the day of vengeance of our God; to comfort all that mourn; 3  To appoint unto them that mourn in Zion, to give unto them beauty for ashes, the oil of joy for mourning, the garment of praise for the spirit of heaviness; that they might be called trees of righteousness, the planting of the LORD, that he might be glorified.

4 ¶ And they shall [*]build the old wastes, they shall raise up the former desolations, and they shall repair the waste cities, the desolations of many generations. 5  And strangers shall stand and feed your flocks, and the sons of the alien shall be your plowmen and your vinedressers. 6  But ye shall be named the Priests of the LORD: men shall call you the Ministers of our God: [*]ye shall eat the riches of the Gentiles, and in their glory shall ye boast yourselves.

7 ¶ For your shame ye shall have double; and for confusion they shall rejoice in their portion: therefore in their land they shall possess the double: everlasting joy shall be unto them. 8  For I the LORD love judgment, I hate robbery for burnt offering; and I will direct their work in truth, and I will make an everlasting covenant with them. 9  And their seed shall be known among the Gentiles, and their offspring among the people: all that see them shall acknowledge them, that they are the seed which the LORD hath blessed.

10  I will greatly rejoice in the LORD, my soul shall be joyful in my God; for he hath clothed me with the garments of salvation, he hath covered me with the robe of righteousness, as a bridegroom [†]decketh himself with ornaments, and as a bride adorneth herself with her jewels. 11  For as the earth bringeth forth her bud, and as the garden causeth the things that are sown in it to spring forth; so the Lord GOD will cause righteousness and praise to spring forth before all the nations.

62

1  For Zion’s sake will I not hold my peace, and for Jerusalem’s sake I will not rest, until the righteousness thereof go forth as brightness, and the salvation thereof as a lamp that burneth. 2  And the Gentiles shall see thy righteousness, and all kings thy glory: and thou shalt be called by a new name, which the mouth of the LORD shall name. 3  Thou shalt also be a crown of glory in the hand of the LORD, and a royal diadem in the hand of thy God. 4 [*] Thou shalt no more be termed Forsaken; neither shall thy land any more be termed Desolate: but thou shalt be called [∥]Hephzi-bah, and thy land [∥]Beulah: for the LORD delighteth in thee, and thy land shall be married.

5 ¶ For as a young man marrieth a virgin, so shall thy sons marry thee: and [†]as the bridegroom rejoiceth over the bride, so shall thy God rejoice over thee.

6  I have set watchmen upon thy walls, O Jerusalem, which shall never hold their peace day nor night: [∥]ye that make mention of the LORD, keep not silence, 7  And give him no [†]rest, till he establish, and till he make Jerusalem a praise in the earth. 8  The LORD hath sworn by his right hand, and by the arm of his strength, [†]Surely I will no more give thy corn to be meat for thine enemies; and the sons of the stranger shall not drink thy wine, for the which thou hast laboured: 9  But they that have gathered it shall eat it, and praise the LORD; and they that have brought it together shall drink it in the courts of my holiness.

10 ¶ Go through, go through the gates; [*]prepare ye the way of the people; cast up, cast up the highway; gather out the stones; lift up a standard for the people. 11  Behold, the LORD hath proclaimed unto the end of the world, [*]Say ye to the daughter of Zion, Behold, thy salvation cometh; behold, his [*]reward is with him, and his [∥]work before him. 12  And they shall call them, The holy people, The redeemed of the LORD: and thou shalt be called, Sought out, A city not forsaken.

63

1 Who is this that cometh from Edom, with dyed garments from Bozrah? this that is [†]glorious in his apparel, travelling in the greatness of his strength? I that speak in righteousness, mighty to save. 2 Wherefore [*]art thou red in thine apparel, and thy garments like him that treadeth in the winefat? 3  I have trodden the winepress alone; and of the people there was none with me: for I will tread them in mine anger, and trample them in my fury; and their blood shall be sprinkled upon my garments, and I will stain all my raiment. 4  For the [*]day of vengeance is in mine heart, and the year of my redeemed is come. 5  And I looked, and there was none to help; and I wondered that there was none to uphold: therefore mine own [*]arm brought salvation unto me; and my fury, it upheld me. 6  And I will tread down the people in mine anger, and make them drunk in my fury, and I will bring down their strength to the earth.

7 ¶ I will mention the lovingkindnesses of the LORD, and the praises of the LORD, according to all that the LORD hath bestowed on us, and the great goodness toward the house of Israel, which he hath bestowed on them according to his mercies, and according to the multitude of his lovingkindnesses. 8  For he said, Surely they are my people, children that will not lie: so he was their Saviour. 9  In all their affliction he was afflicted, and the angel of his presence saved them: [*]in his love and in his pity he redeemed them; and he bare them, and carried them all the days of old.

10 ¶ But they [*]rebelled, and vexed his holy Spirit: therefore he was turned to be their enemy, and he fought against them. 11  Then he remembered the days of old, Moses, and his people, saying, Where is he that [*]brought them up out of the sea with the [∥]shepherd of his flock? where is he that put his holy Spirit within him? 12  That led them by the right hand of Moses with his glorious arm, [*]dividing the water before them, to make himself an everlasting name? 13  That led them through the deep, as an horse in the wilderness, that they should not stumble? 14  As a beast goeth down into the valley, the Spirit of the LORD caused him to rest: so didst thou lead thy people, to make thyself a glorious name.

15 ¶ [*]Look down from heaven, and behold from the habitation of thy holiness and of thy glory: where is thy zeal and thy strength, [∥]the sounding of thy bowels and of thy mercies toward me? are they restrained? 16  Doubtless thou art our father, though Abraham be ignorant of us, and Israel acknowledge us not: thou, O LORD, art our father, [∥]our redeemer; thy name is from everlasting.

17 ¶ O LORD, why hast thou made us to err from thy ways, and hardened our heart from thy fear? Return for thy servants’ sake, the tribes of thine inheritance. 18  The people of thy holiness have possessed it but a little while: our adversaries have trodden down thy sanctuary. 19 We are thine: thou never barest rule over them; [∥]they were not called by thy name.

64

1  Oh that thou wouldest [‡]rend the heavens, that thou wouldest come down, that the mountains might flow down at thy presence, 2 As when [†]the melting fire burneth, the fire causeth the waters to boil, to make thy name known to thine adversaries, that the nations may tremble at thy presence! 3  When thou didst terrible things which we looked not for, thou camest down, the mountains flowed down at thy presence. 4  For since the beginning of the world [*]men have not heard, nor perceived by the ear, neither hath the eye [∥]seen, O God, beside thee, what he hath prepared for him that waiteth for him. 5  Thou meetest him that rejoiceth and worketh righteousness, those that remember thee in thy ways: behold, thou art wroth; for we have sinned: in those is continuance, and we shall be saved.

6  But we are all as an unclean thing, and all our righteousnesses are as filthy rags; and we all do [*]fade as a leaf; and our iniquities, like the wind, have taken us away. 7 And there is none that calleth upon thy name, that stirreth up himself to take hold of thee: for thou hast hid thy face from us, and hast [†]consumed us, because of our iniquities. 8  But now, O LORD, thou art our father; we are the clay, and thou our potter; and we all are the work of thy hand.

9 ¶ Be not [*]wroth very sore, O LORD, neither remember iniquity for ever: behold, see, we beseech thee, we are all thy people. 10  Thy holy cities are a wilderness, Zion is a wilderness, Jerusalem a desolation. 11  Our holy and our beautiful house, where our fathers praised thee, is burned up with fire: and all our pleasant things are laid waste. 12  Wilt thou refrain thyself for these things, O LORD? wilt thou hold thy peace, and afflict us very sore?

65

1  I [*]am sought of them that asked not for me; I am found of them that sought me not: I said, Behold me, behold me, unto a nation that was not called by my name. 2  I have spread out my hands all the day unto a rebellious people, which walketh in a way that was not good, after their own thoughts; 3  A people that provoketh me to anger continually to my face; that sacrificeth in gardens, and burneth incense [†]upon altars of brick; 4  Which remain among the graves, and lodge in the monuments, which eat swine’s flesh, and [∥]broth of abominable things is in their vessels; 5  Which say, Stand by thyself, come not near to me; for I am holier than thou. These are a smoke in my [∥]nose, a fire that burneth all the day. 6 Behold, it is written before me: I will not keep silence, but will recompense, even recompense into their bosom, 7  Your iniquities, and the iniquities of your fathers together, saith the LORD, which have burned incense upon the mountains, and blasphemed me upon the hills: therefore will I measure their former work into their bosom.

8 ¶ Thus saith the LORD, As the new wine is found in the cluster, and one saith, Destroy it not; for a blessing is in it: so will I do for my servants’ sakes, that I may not destroy them all. 9  And I will bring forth a seed out of Jacob, and out of Judah an inheritor of my mountains: and mine elect shall inherit it, and my servants shall dwell there. 10  And Sharon shall be a fold of flocks, and the valley of Achor a place for the herds to lie down in, for my people that have sought me.

11 ¶ But ye are they that forsake the LORD, that forget my holy mountain, that prepare a table for that [∥]troop, and that furnish the drink offering unto that [∥]number. 12  Therefore will I number you to the sword, and ye shall all bow down to the slaughter: [*]because when I called, ye did not answer; when I spake, ye did not hear; but did evil before mine eyes, and did choose that wherein I delighted not. 13  Therefore thus saith the Lord GOD, Behold, my servants shall eat, but ye shall be hungry: behold, my servants shall drink, but ye shall be thirsty: behold, my servants shall rejoice, but ye shall be ashamed: 14  Behold, my servants shall sing for joy of heart, but ye shall cry for sorrow of heart, and shall howl for [†]vexation of spirit. 15  And ye shall leave your name for a curse unto my chosen: for the Lord GOD shall slay thee, and call his servants by another name: 16  That he who blesseth himself in the earth shall bless himself in the God of truth; and he that sweareth in the earth shall swear by the God of truth; because the former troubles are forgotten, and because they are hid from mine eyes.

17 ¶ For, behold, I create [*]new heavens and a new earth: and the former shall not be remembered, nor [†]come into mind. 18  But be ye glad and rejoice for ever in that which I create: for, behold, I create Jerusalem a rejoicing, and her people a joy. 19  And I will rejoice in Jerusalem, and joy in my people: and the [*]voice of weeping shall be no more heard in her, nor the voice of crying. 20  There shall be no more thence an infant of days, nor an old man that hath not filled his days: for the child shall die an hundred years old; but the sinner being an hundred years old shall be accursed. 21  And they shall build houses, and inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, and eat the fruit of them. 22  They shall not build, and another inhabit; they shall not plant, and another eat: for as the days of a tree are the days of my people, and mine elect [†]shall long enjoy the work of their hands. 23  They shall not labour in vain, nor bring forth for trouble; for they are the seed of the blessed of the LORD, and their offspring with them. 24  And it shall come to pass, that [*]before they call, I will answer; and while they are yet speaking, I will hear. 25  The [*]wolf and the lamb shall feed together, and the lion shall eat straw like the bullock: and dust shall be the serpent’s meat. They shall not hurt nor destroy in all my holy mountain, saith the LORD.

66

1  Thus saith the LORD, [*]The heaven is my throne, and the earth is my footstool: where is the house that ye build unto me? and where is the place of my rest? 2 For all those things hath mine hand made, and all those things have been, saith the LORD: but to this man will I look, even to him that is poor and of a contrite spirit, and trembleth at my word. 3  He that killeth an ox is as if he slew a man; he that sacrificeth a [∥]lamb, as if he cut off a dog’s neck; he that offereth an oblation, as if he offered swine’s blood; he that [†]burneth incense, as if he blessed an idol. Yea, they have chosen their own ways, and their soul delighteth in their abominations. 4  I also will choose their [∥]delusions, and will bring their fears upon them; [*]because when I called, none did answer; when I spake, they did not hear: but they did evil before mine eyes, and chose that in which I delighted not.

5 ¶ Hear the word of the LORD, ye that tremble at his word; Your brethren that hated you, that cast you out for my name’s sake, said, [*]Let the LORD be glorified: but he shall appear to your joy, and they shall be ashamed. 6  A voice of noise from the city, a voice from the temple, a voice of the LORD that rendereth recompence to his enemies. 7  Before she travailed, she brought forth; before her pain came, she was delivered of a man child. 8  Who hath heard such a thing? who hath seen such things? Shall the earth be made to bring forth in one day? or shall a nation be born at once? for as soon as Zion travailed, she brought forth her children. 9  Shall I bring to the birth, and not [∥]cause to bring forth? saith the LORD: shall I cause to bring forth, and shut the womb? saith thy God. 10  Rejoice ye with Jerusalem, and be glad with her, all ye that love her: rejoice for joy with her, all ye that mourn for her: 11  That ye may suck, and be satisfied with the breasts of her consolations; that ye may milk out, and be delighted with the [∥]abundance of her glory. 12  For thus saith the LORD, Behold, I will extend peace to her like a river, and the glory of the Gentiles like a flowing stream: then shall ye suck, ye shall be [*]borne upon her sides, and be dandled upon her knees. 13  As one whom his mother comforteth, so will I comfort you; and ye shall be comforted in Jerusalem. 14  And when ye see this, your heart shall rejoice, and your bones shall flourish like an herb: and the hand of the LORD shall be known toward his servants, and his indignation toward his enemies.

15  For, behold, the LORD will come with fire, and with his chariots like a whirlwind, to render his anger with fury, and his rebuke with flames of fire. 16  For by fire and by his sword will the LORD plead with all flesh: and the slain of the LORD shall be many. 17  They that sanctify themselves, and purify themselves in the gardens [∥]behind one tree in the midst, eating swine’s flesh, and the abomination, and the mouse, shall be consumed together, saith the LORD. 18 For I know their works and their thoughts: it shall come, that I will gather all nations and tongues; and they shall come, and see my glory. 19  And I will set a sign among them, and I will send those that escape of them unto the nations, to Tarshish, Pul, and Lud, that draw the bow, to Tubal, and Javan, to the isles afar off, that have not heard my fame, neither have seen my glory; and they shall declare my glory among the Gentiles. 20  And they shall bring all your brethren for an offering unto the LORD out of all nations upon horses, and in chariots, and in [∥]litters, and upon mules, and upon swift beasts, to my holy mountain Jerusalem, saith the LORD, as the children of Israel bring an offering in a clean vessel into the house of the LORD. 21  And I will also take of them for [*]priests and for Levites, saith the LORD. 22  For as the [*]new heavens and the new earth, which I will make, shall remain before me, saith the LORD, so shall your seed and your name remain. 23 And it shall come to pass, that [†]from one new moon to another, and from one sabbath to another, shall all flesh come to worship before me, saith the LORD. 24  And they shall go forth, and look upon the carcases of the men that have transgressed against me: for their [*]worm shall not die, neither shall their fire be quenched; and they shall be an abhorring unto all flesh.

* 1.2 Deut. 32 1.

* 1.3 Jer. 8. 7.

† 1.4 Heb. of heaviness.

† 1.4 Heb. alienated, or, separated.

† 1.5 Heb. increase revolt.

∥ 1.6 Or, oil.

* 1.7 Deut. 28. 51, 52. ch. 5. 5

† 1.7 Heb. as the overthrow of strangers.

* 1.9 Lam 3. 22. Rom. 9. 29.

* 1.9 Gen 19. 24.

* 1.11 Prov. 15 8. &c 21 27. ch 66. 3 Jer 6. 20. Amos 5. 21.

† 1.11 Heb. great he goats.

† 1.12 Heb. to be seen.

∥ 1.13 Or, grief.

* 1.15 Prov. 1. 28 Jer. 14. 12. Mic. 3. 4.

† 1.15 Heb. multiply prayer.

* 1.15 ch. 59 3.

† 1.15 Heb. bloods.

* 1.16 1 Pet. 3. 11.

∥ 1.17 Or, righten.

* 1.23 Jer. 5. 28 Zech. 7. 10.

† 1.25 Heb. according to pureness.

∥ 1.27 Or, they that return of her.

* 1.28 Job 31. 3. Ps. 1 6. &c 5 6. &c 73 27. &c 92 9. &c 104. 35

† 1.28 Heb. breaking.

∥ 1.31 Or, and his work.

* 2.2 Mic 4. 1, &c.

∥ 2.2 Or, prepared.

∥ 2.4 Or, scythes.

∥ 2.6 Or, more than the east.

∥ 2.6 Or, abound with the children, &c.

* 2.11 ch. 5. 15.

† 2.16 Heb. pictures of desire.

∥ 2.18 Or, the idols shall utterly pass away.

* 2.19 Hos. 10. 8. Luke 23. 30. Rev 6 16. &c 9. 6.

† 2.19 Heb. the dust.

† 2.20 Heb. the idols of his silver, &c.

∥ 2.20 Or, which they made for him.

† 3.3 Heb. a man eminent in countenance.

∥ 3.3 Or, skilful of speech.

* 3.4 Eccles. 10. 16.

† 3.7 Heb. lift up the hand.

† 3.7 Heb. binder up.

* 3.9 Gen. 13. 13. &c 18. 21. &c 19. 5.

† 3.11 Heb done to him.

∥ 3.12 Or, they which call thee blessed.

† 3.12 Heb. swallow up.

∥ 3.14 Or, burnt.

† 3.16 Heb. deceiving with their eyes.

∥ 3.16 Or, tripping nicely.

† 3.17 Heb. make naked.

∥ 3.18 Or, networks.

∥ 3.19 Or, sweet balls.

∥ 3.19 Or, spangled ornaments.

† 3.20 Heb houses of the soul.

† 3.25 Heb. might.

∥ 3.26 Or, emptied.

† 3.26 Heb. cleansed.

† 4.1 Heb. let thy name be called upon us.

∥ 4.1 Or, take thou away.

† 4.2 Heb. beauty and glory.

† 4.2 Heb. for the escaping of Israel.

∥ 4.3 Or, to life.

* 4.5 Ex. 13. 21.

∥ 4.5 Or, above.

† 4.5 Heb. a covering.

* 5.1 Jer. 2. 21. Matt. 21. 33. Mark 12. 1. Luke 20. 9.

† 5.1 Heb. the horn of the son of oil.

∥ 5.2 Or, made a wall about it.

† 5.2 Heb. hewed.

† 5.5 Heb. for a treading.

† 5.7 Heb. plant of his pleasures.

† 5.7 Heb. a scab.

* 5.8 Mic. 2. 2.

∥ 5.9 Or, This is in mine ears, saith the Lord, &c.

† 5.9 Heb. If not, &c.

* 5.11 Prov. 23. 29, 30.

∥ 5.11 Or, pursue them.

† 5.13 Heb. their glory are men of famine.

* 5.15 ch 2. 9, 11, 17.

∥ 5.16 Or, the holy God.

† 5.16 Heb. the God the holy.

† 5.20 Heb. that say concerning evil, It is good, &c.

* 5.21 Prov. 3. 7. Rom. 12. 16

† 5.21 Heb. before their face.

* 5.23 Prov. 17 15.

† 5.24 Heb. the tongue of fire.

∥ 5.25 Or, as dung.

* 5.25 ch. 9. 12, 17, 21. &c 10. 4.

∥ 5.30 Or, distress.

∥ 5.30 Or, when it is light, it shall be dark in the destructions thereof.

* 6.1 John 12. 41.

∥ 6.1 Or, the skirts thereof.

† 6.3 Heb. this cried to this

* 6.3 Rev. 4 8.

† 6.3 Heb. his glory is the fulness of the whole earth.

† 6.4 Heb. thresholds.

† 6.5 Heb. cut off.

† 6.6 Heb. and in his hand a live coal.

† 6.7 Heb. caused it to touch.

* 6.8 Gen. 1. 26.

‡ 6.8 [1611 I said]

† 6.8 Heb. Behold me.

* 6.9 Matt. 13. 14. Mark 4. 12. Luke 8. 10. John 12. 40 Acts 28. 26. Rom. 11. 8.

∥ 6.9 Or, without ceasing, &c.

† 6.9 Heb. hear ye in hearing, &c.

† 6.11 Heb. desolate with desolation.

∥ 6.13 Or, when it is returned, and hath been broused.

∥ 6.13 Or, stock, or, stem.

* 7.1 2 Kin. 16. 5.

† 7.2 Heb. resteth on Ephraim.

∥ 7.3 That is, the remnant shall return.

* 7.3 2 Kin. 18 17.

∥ 7.3 Or, causeway.

† 7.4 Heb. let not thy heart be tender.

∥ 7.6 Or, waken.

† 7.8 Heb. from a people

∥ 7.9 Or, Do ye not believe? it is because ye are not stable.

† 7.10 Heb. And the Lord added to speak.

∥ 7.11 Or, make thy petition deep.

* 7.14 Matt. 1. 23. Luke 1. 31.

∥ 7.14 Or, thou, O Virgin, shalt call.

∥ 7.19 Or, commendable trees.

* 7.20 2 Kin. 19. 35.

† 7.22 Heb. in the midst of the land.

† 8.1 Heb. in making speed to the spoil he hasteneth the prey, or, make speed, &c.

† 8.3 Heb. approached unto.

∥ 8.4 Or, he that is before the king of Assyria shall take away the riches, &c.

† 8.8 Heb. the fulness of the breadth of thy land shall be the stretchings out of his wings.

∥ 8.9 Or, yet.

† 8.11 Heb in strength of hand.

* 8.14 ch. 28 16 Luke 2. 34. Rom. 9. 33. 1 Pet. 2 8

* 8.15 Matt. 21. 44 Luke 20. 18.

* 8.18 Heb. 2. 13.

* 8.20 Luke 16. 29.

† 8.20 Heb. no morning.

∥ 9.1 Or, populous

* 9.2 Matt. 4. 16. Eph. 5. 14.

∥ 9.3 Or, to him.

∥ 9.4 Or, When thou brakest.

* 9.4 Judg 7. 22. ch. 10. 26.

∥ 9.5 Or, When the whole battle of the warrior was, &c.

∥ 9.5 Or, and it was, &c.

† 9.5 Heb. meat.

* 9.6 John 3. 16.

* 9.7 Luke 1. 32, 33.

* 9.7 2 Kin. 19 31. ch. 37. 32.

† 9.11 Heb. mingle.

† 9.12 Heb. with whole mouth.

* 9.12 ch. 5 25. &c 10. 4.

∥ 9.16 Or, they that call them blessed.

∥ 9.16 Or, they that are called blessed of them.

† 9.16 Heb. swallowed up.

∥ 9.17 Or, villany.

† 9.19 Heb. meat.

† 9.20 Heb. cut.

∥ 10.1 Or, to the writers that write grievousness.

* 10.4 ch. 5 25. &c 9. 12.

∥ 10.5 Or, Woe to the Assyrian.

† 10.5 Heb. Asshur.

∥ 10.5 Or, though.

† 10.6 Heb. to lay them a treading.

* 10.8 2 Kin. 18. 24, 33. &c 19. 10, &c.

* 10.12 2 Kin. 19 31.

† 10.12 Heb visit upon

† 10.12 Heb of the greatness of the heart.

∥ 10.13 Or, like many people.

∥ 10.15 Or, as if a rod should shake them that lift it up.

∥ 10.15 Or, that which is not wood.

† 10.18 Heb. from the soul and even to the flesh.

† 10.19 Heb. number.

* 10.22 Rom 9 27.

† 10.22 Heb. in, or, amongst

* 10.22 ch. 28 22.

∥ 10.22 Or, in.

* 10.23 ch. 28. 22.

∥ 10.24 Or, but he shall lift up his staff for thee.

* 10.24 Exod. 14.

* 10.26 Judg. 7. 25. ch. 9. 4.

† 10.27 Heb. shall remove.

† 10.30 Heb. Cry shrill with thy voice.

‡ 10.34 [1611 forests]

∥ 10.34 Or, mightily.

* 11.1 Acts 13. 23.

† 11.3 Heb. scent or, smell.

∥ 11.4 Or, argue.

* 11.4 Job 4 9. 2 Thess. 2. 8.

* 11.6 ch. 65. 25.

∥ 11.8 Or, adder's.

* 11.10 Rom. 15 12.

† 11.10 Heb. glory.

† 11.12 Heb. wings.

† 11.14 Heb. the children of the east.

† 11.14 Heb. Edom and Moab shall be the laying on of their hand.

† 11.14 Heb. the children of Ammon their obedience.

† 11.15 Heb. in shoes.

* 11.16 Ex. 14 29.

* 12.2 Ex. 15. 2. Ps. 118. 14.

* 12.4 1 Chr. 16. 8. Ps. 105. 1.

∥ 12.4 Or, proclaim his name.

† 12.6 Heb. inhabitress.

† 13.4 Heb. the likeness of.

∥ 13.7 Or, fall down.

† 13.8 Heb wonder.

† 13.8 Heb. every man at his neighbour.

† 13.8 Heb. faces of the flames

* 13.10 Ezek. 32 7 Joel 2. 31. &c 3. 15. Matt. 24 29. Mark 13. 24. Luke 21. 25.

* 13.16 Ps. 137. 9.

† 13.19 Heb. as the overthrowing.

* 13.19 Gen. 19. 24. Jer. 50. 40.

† 13.21 Heb. Ziim.

† 13.21 Heb. Ochim.

∥ 13.21 Or, ostriches.

† 13.21 Heb. daughters of the owl.

† 13.22 Heb. Ochim.

∥ 13.22 Or, palaces.

† 14.2 Heb that had taken them captives.

∥ 14.4 Or, taunting speech.

∥ 14.4 Or, exactress of gold.

† 14.6 Heb a stroke without removing.

∥ 14.9 Or, The grave.

† 14.9 Heb. leaders.

∥ 14.9 Or, great goats.

∥ 14.12 Or, O day star.

∥ 14.17 Or, did not let his prisoners loose homeward.

* 14.20 Job 18. 19. Ps. 21. 10. &c 37. 28. &c 109. 13.

* 14.21 Ex. 20. 5 Matt. 23. 35.

* 14.27 2 Chr. 20. 6. Job 9. 12. Prov. 21. 30. Dan. 4. 32.

∥ 14.29 Or, adder.

∥ 14.31 Or, he shall not be alone.

∥ 14.31 Or, assemblies.

* 14.32 Ps. 87. 1. 5. &c 102 16.

∥ 14.32 Or, betake themselves unto it.

∥ 15.1 Or, cut off.

* 15.2 Jer. 48. 37. 38. Ezek. 7. 18.

† 15.3 Heb. descending into weeping: or, coming down with weeping.

∥ 15.5 Or, to the borders thereof, even to Zoar, as an heifer.

* 15.5 Jer. 48. 5, 34.

† 15.5 Heb. breaking.

† 15.6 Heb. desolations.

∥ 15.7 Or, valley of the Arabians.

† 15.9 Heb. additions.

∥ 16.1 Or, Petra.

† 16.1 Heb. A rock.

∥ 16.2 Or, a nest forsaken.

† 16.3 Heb. Bring.

† 16.4 Heb. wringer.

† 16.4 Heb. the treaders down.

* 16.5 Dan. 7. 14, 27. Mic. 4. 7. Luke 1. 33.

∥ 16.5 Or, prepared.

* 16.6 Jer. 48. 29.

* 16.7 Jer. 48. 20.

∥ 16.7 Or, mutter.

∥ 16.8 Or, plucked up.

∥ 16.9 Or, the alarm is fallen upon, &c.

* 16.10 Jer. 48. 33.

∥ 16.14 Or, not many.

∥ 17.8 Or, sun images.

∥ 17.11 Or, removed in the day of inheritance, and there shall be deadly sorrow.

∥ 17.12 Or, noise.

∥ 17.12 Or, many.

∥ 17.13 Or, thistle-down.

∥ 18.2 Or, outspread and polished.

∥ 18.2 Or, a nation that meteth out, and treadeth down.

† 18.2 Heb. a nation of line, line, and treading under foot.

∥ 18.2 Or, whose land the rivers despise.

∥ 18.4 Or, regard my set dwelling.

∥ 18.4 Or, after rain.

∥ 18.7 Or, outspread and polished, &c.

† 19.2 Heb. mingle.

† 19.3 Heb. shall be emptied.

† 19.3 Heb swallow up.

∥ 19.4 Or, shut up

† 19.7 Heb. and shall not be.

∥ 19.9 Or, white works.

† 19.10 Heb. foundations.

† 19.10 Heb. of living things.

∥ 19.13 Or, governors.

† 19.13 Heb. corners.

† 19.14 Heb. a spirit of perversities.

† 19.18 Heb. the lip.

∥ 19.18 Or, of Heres, or, of the sun.

† 20.2 Heb. by the hand of Isaiah.

† 20.4 Heb. the captivity of Egypt.

† 20.4 Heb. nakedness.

∥ 20.6 Or, country.

† 21.2 Heb. hard.

∥ 21.4 Or, My mind wandered.

† 21.4 Heb. put.

∥ 21.8 Or, cried as a lion.

* 21.8 Hab. 2 1

∥ 21.8 Or, every night.

* 21.9 Jer. 51. 8 Rev 14. 8 &c 18 2.

† 21.10 Heb. son.

∥ 21.14 Or, bring ye

∥ 21.15 Or, for fear.

† 21.15 Heb. from the face.

† 21.17 Heb. bows.

† 22.3 Heb. of the bow.

* 22.4 Jer. 4. 19. &c 9. 1.

† 22.4 Heb. I will be bitter in weeping.

† 22.6 Heb. made naked.

† 22.7 Heb. the choice of thy valleys.

∥ 22.7 Or, towards.

* 22.13 ch. 56. 12. Wisd 2. 6. 1 Cor. 15. 32.

∥ 22.16 Or, O he.

∥ 22.17 ver 18

† 22.17 Heb. the captivity of a man.

† 22.18 Heb. large of spaces.

* 22.22 Job 12. 14. Rev. 3. 7.

∥ 22.24 Or, instruments of viols.

† 23.2 Heb. silent.

† 23.7 Heb. from afar off.

† 23.9 Heb. to pollute.

† 23.10 Heb. girdle.

∥ 23.11 Or, concerning a merchantman.

† 23.11 Heb. Canaan.

∥ 23.11 Or, strengths.

† 23.15 Heb. it shall be unto Tyre as the song of an harlot.

† 23.18 Heb. old.

† 24.1 Heb. perverteth the face thereof.

∥ 24.2 Or, prince.

* 24.2 Hos. 4 9.

† 24.4 Heb. the height of the people.

* 24.8 Jer 7. 84. &c 16 9 &c 25 10. Ezek 26. 13. Hos. 2. 11.

∥ 24.15 Or, valleys.

† 24.16 Heb. wing.

† 24.16 Heb. Leanness to me, or, My secret to me.

* 24.17 Jer. 48. 43, 44.

† 24.21 Heb. visit upon.

† 24.22 Heb. with the gathering of prisoners.

∥ 24.22 Or, dungeon.

∥ 24.22 Or, found wanting.

* 24.23 ch. 13. 10. Ezek. 32 7. Joel 2. 31. &c 3. 15.

∥ 24.23 Or, there shall be glory before his ancients.

† 25.7 Heb. swallow up.

† 25.7 Heb. covered.

* 25.8 1 Cor. 15 54.

* 25.8 Rev 7. 17. &c 21. 4.

∥ 25.10 Or, threshed.

∥ 25.10 Or, threshed in Madmenah.

† 26.2 Heb. truths.

† 26.3 Heb. peace, peace.

∥ 26.3 Or, thought, or, imagination.

† 26.4 Heb. the rock of ages.

∥ 26.11 Or, towards thy people.

∥ 26.12 Or, for us.

† 26.16 Heb. secret speech.

* 26.21 Mic. 1. 3.

† 26.21 Heb. bloods.

∥ 27.1 Or, crossing like a bar.

∥ 27.4 Or, march against.

† 27.7 Heb. according to the stroke of those.

∥ 27.8 Or, when thou sendest it forth.

∥ 27.8 Or, when he removeth it.

∥ 27.9 Or, sun images.

† 28.1 Heb. broken.

† 28.3 Heb. with feet.

‡ 28.4 [1611 seeth it]

† 28.4 Heb. swalloweth.

† 28.9 Heb. the hearing?

∥ 28.10 Or, hath been.

† 28.11 Heb. stammerings of lips.

* 28.11 1 Cor. 14. 21.

∥ 28.11 Or, he hath spoken.

* 28.16 Ps. 118. 22. Matt. 21. 42. Acts 4. 11. Rom. 9. 33. &c 10 11. 1 Pet. 2. 6, 7, 8.

† 28.18 Heb. a treading down to it.

∥ 28.19 Or, when he shall make you to understand doctrine.

* 28.21 2 Sam. 5 20. 1 Chr. 14. 11.

* 28.21 Josh. 10. 10, 12. 2 Sam. 5. 25. 1 Chr. 14. 16.

∥ 28.25 Or, the wheat in the principal place, and barley in the appointed place.

∥ 28.25 Or, spelt.

† 28.25 Heb. border?

∥ 28.26 Or, And he bindeth it in such sort as his God doth teach him.

∥ 29.1 Or, O Ariel, that is, the lion of God.

∥ 29.1 Or, of the city.

† 29.1 Heb. cut off the heads.

† 29.4 Heb. peep or, chirp.

∥ 29.9 Or, take your pleasure, and riot.

† 29.10 Heb. heads.

∥ 29.11 Or, letter.

* 29.13 Matt. 15 8. Mark 7. 6.

† 29.14 Heb. I will add.

* 29.14 Jer. 49. 7. Obad 8. 1 Cor. 1. 19.

* 29.15 Ecclus. 23. 18.

* 29.16 ch. 45. 9.

† 29.19 Heb shall add.

† 29.24 Heb. shall know understanding.

∥ 30.7 Or, to her.

† 30.8 Heb. the latter day.

∥ 30.12 Or, fraud.

† 30.14 Heb. the bottle of potters.

∥ 30.17 Or, a tree bereft of branches, or, boughs. or, a mast.

* 30.18 Ps. 2 12 &c 34. 8. Prov 16. 20. Jer. 17. 7.

∥ 30.20 Or, oppression.

† 30.22 Heb. the graven images of thy silver.

† 30.22 Heb. scatter.

∥ 30.24 Or, savoury.

† 30.24 Heb. leavoned.

† 30.25 Heb. lifted up.

∥ 30.27 Or, and the grievousness of flame

† 30.27 Heb. heaviness.

† 30.29 Heb. Rock.

† 30.30 Heb. the glory of his voice.

† 30.32 Heb. every passing of the rod founded.

† 30.32 Heb. cause to rest upon him.

∥ 30.32 Or, against them.

† 30.33 Heb. from yesterday.

† 31.2 Heb. remove.

∥ 31.4 Or, multitude.

* 31.7 ch 2. 20.

† 31.7 Heb. the idols of his gold.

∥ 31.8 Or, for fear of the sword.

∥ 31.8 Or, tributary.

† 31.8 Heb. for melting, or, tribute.

† 31.9 Heb. his rock shall pass away for fear.

∥ 31.9 Or, his strength.

† 32.2 Heb. heavy.

† 32.4 Heb. hasty.

∥ 32.4 Or, elegantly.

∥ 32.7 Or, when he speaketh against the poor in judgment.

∥ 32.8 Or, be established.

† 32.10 Heb. Days above a year.

† 32.12 Heb. the fields of desire.

∥ 32.13 Or, burning upon, &c.

∥ 32.14 Or, clifts and watch-towers.

* 32.15 ch. 29. 17.

∥ 32.19 Or, and the city shall be utterly abased.

† 33.6 Heb. salvations.

∥ 33.7 Or, messengers.

∥ 33.9 Or, withered away.

* 33.15 Ps. 15. 2. &c 24. 4.

† 33.15 Heb in righteousnesses.

† 33.15 Heb. uprightnesses.

∥ 33.15 Or, deceits.

† 33.15 Heb. bloods.

† 33.16 Heb. heights, or, high places.

† 33.17 Heb. the land of far distances.

* 33.18 1 Cor. 1. 20

† 33.18 Heb. weigher?

∥ 33.19 Or, ridiculous

† 33.21 Heb. broad of spaces, or, hands.

† 33.22 Heb. statutemaker.

∥ 33.23 Or, They have forsaken thy tacklings.

† 34.1 Heb. the fulness thereof.

* 34.4 Rev. 6. 14.

* 34.4 Rev. 6. 13.

∥ 34.7 Or, rhinocerots.

∥ 34.7 Or, drunken.

* 34.8 ch. 63. 4.

* 34.10 Rev. 18. 18 &c 19 3.

* 34.11 Zeph. 2. 14. Rev 18 2.

‡ 34.11 [1611 The]

∥ 34.11 Or, pelican.

∥ 34.13 Or, ostriches.

† 34.13 Heb. daughters of the owl.

† 34.14 Heb. Zum.

† 34.14 Heb. Ijim.

∥ 34.14 Or, nightmonster.

* 35.3 Heb. 12. 12

† 35.4 Heb. hasty.

* 35.5 Matt. 9. 27. &c 11. 5. &c 12. 22. &c 20. 30 &c 21. 14. John 9. 6, 7.

* 35.5 Matt. 11 5. Mark 7. 32

* 35.6 Matt. 11. 5. &c 15. 30. &c 21. 14. John 5. 8, 9. Acts 3. 2. &c 8. 7. &c 14. 8.

* 35.6 Matt. 9. 33. &c 12. 22. &c 15. 30.

* 35.6 John 7. 38, 39.

∥ 35.7 Or, a court for reeds, &c.

∥ 35.8 Or, for he shall be with them.

* 35.10 ch 51. 11.

* 36.1 2 Kin. 18. 13. 2 Chr. 32. 1.

∥ 36.3 Or, secretary.

† 36.5 Heb. a word of lips.

∥ 36.5 Or, but counsel and strength are for the war.

* 36.6 Ezek. 29. 6, 7.

∥ 36.8 Or, hostages

∥ 36.16 Or, Seek my favour by a present.

† 36.16 Heb. Make with me a blessing.

* 37.1 2 Kin. 19. 1, &c.

∥ 37.3 Or, provocation.

† 37.4 Heb. found.

∥ 37.7 Or, put a spirit into him.

† 37.18 Heb. lands.

† 37.19 Heb. given.

† 37.24 Heb. By the hand of thy servants.

† 37.24 Heb. the tallness of the cedars thereof, and the choice of the fir trees thereof.

∥ 37.24 Or, the forest and his fruitful field.

∥ 37.25 Or, fenced and closed.

∥ 37.26 Or, Hast thou not heard how I have made it long ago, and formed it of ancient times? should I now bring it to be laid waste, and defenced cities to be ruinous heaps?

† 37.27 Heb. short of hand.

∥ 37.28 Or, sitting.

† 37.31 Heb. the escaping of the house of Judah that remaineth.

† 37.32 Heb. the escaping.

* 37.32 2 Kin. 19. 31. ch. 9. 7.

* 37.35 2 Kin. 20. 6.

* 37.36 2 Kin. 19. 35.

† 37.38 Heb. Ararat.

* 38.1 2 Kin. 20. 1. 2 Chr. 32. 24.

† 38.1 Heb. Give charge concerning thy house.

† 38.3 Heb. with great weeping.

† 38.8 Heb. degrees by, or, with the sun.

∥ 38.12 Or, from the thrum.

∥ 38.14 Or, ease me.

∥ 38.17 Or, on my peace came great bitterness.

† 38.17 Heb. thou hast loved my soul from the pit.

* 39.1 2 Kin. 20. 12, &c.

∥ 39.2 Or, spicery.

∥ 39.2 Or, jewels.

† 39.2 Heb. vessels, or, instruments.

† 40.2 Heb. to the heart,

∥ 40.2 Or, appointed time.

* 40.3 Matt. 3 3 Mark 1. 3. Luke 3 4. John 1. 23.

∥ 40.4 Or, a straight place.

∥ 40.4 Or, a plain place.

* 40.6 Job 14. 2. Ps. 102. 11. &c 108 15. James 1 10. 1 Pet. 1. 24.

* 40.8 John 12. 34. 1 Pet. 1. 25.

∥ 40.9 Or, O thou that tellest good tidings to Zion.

∥ 40.9 Or, O thou that tellest good tidings to Jerusalem.

∥ 40.10 Or, against the strong.

* 40.10 ch. 62. 11.

∥ 40.10 Or, recompence for his work.

* 40.11 Ezek. 34 23. John 10. 11.

∥ 40.11 Or, that give suck.

† 40.12 Heb. a tierce.

* 40.13 Wisd. 9. 13. Rom. 11. 34 1 Cor. 2. 16

† 40.13 Heb. man of his counsel.

† 40.14 Heb. made him understand.

† 40.14 Heb. understandings?

* 40.17 Dan. 4. 35.

* 40.18 Acts 17. 29.

† 40.20 Heb. is poor of oblation.

∥ 40.22 Or, Him that sitteth, &c.

* 40.22 Ps. 104. 2.

* 40.23 Job 12. 21. Ps. 107. 40.

* 40.28 Ps. 147. 5.

† 40.31 Heb. change.

† 41.2 Heb. righteousness.

† 41.3 Heb. in peace.

* 41.4 ch. 43. 10. &c 44. 6. &c 48. 12. Rev. 1. 17. &c 22. 13.

† 41.6 Heb Be strong.

∥ 41.7 Or, founder.

∥ 41.7 Or, the [Editor: illegible word]

∥ 41.7 Or, saying of the soder, It is good.

* 41.8 Deut. 7. 6. &c &c 10. 15. &c 14. 2. Ps. 135. 4. ch 43 1. &c 44. 1.

* 41.8 2 Chr. 20. 7. James 2. 23.

* 41.11 Ex. 23. 22 ch. 60. 12. Zech. 12. 3.

† 41.11 Heb. the men of thy strife.

† 41.12 Heb. the men of thy contention.

† 41.12 Heb. the men of thy war.

∥ 41.14 Or, few men.

† 41.15 Heb. mouths.

* 41.18 ch. 35. 7. &c 44. 3.

* 41.18 Ps. 107. 35.

† 41.21 Heb. Cause to come near.

† 41.22 Heb. set our heart upon them.

∥ 41.24 Or, worse than nothing.

∥ 41.24 Or, worse than of a viper.

† 41.28 Heb. return.

* 42.1 Matt, 12 18.

* 42.1 Matt. 3 17. &c 17. 5. Eph. 1. 6.

∥ 42.3 Or, dimly burning.

† 42.3 Heb. quench it.

† 42.4 Heb. broken.

* 42.6 ch. 49. 6. Luke 2. 32. Acts 13. 47.

* 42.7 ch. 61. 1. Luke 4. 18. Heb. 2. 14, 15.

* 42.7 ch. 9. 2.

* 42.8 ch. 48. 11.

† 42.10 Heb the fulness thereof.

∥ 42.13 Or, behave himself mightily.

† 42.14 Heb swallow, or, sup up.

† 42.16 Heb. into straightness

* 42.17 Ps. 97 7 ch. 1. 29. &c 44 11. &c 45 16.

* 42.20 Rom. 2. 21.

∥ 42.21 Or, him.

∥ 42.22 Or, in snaring all the young men of them.

† 42.22 Heb a treading.

† 42.23 Heb. for the after time?

∥ 43.4 Or, person.

* 43.5 ch. 44. 2. Jer. 30. 10. &c 46. 27.

* 43.9 ch. 41. 21.

* 43.10 ch 41 4. &c 44. 8.

∥ 43.10 Or, nothing formed of God.

* 43.11 ch. 45. 21. Hos. 13. 4.

† 43.13 Heb. turn it back?

* 43.13 Job 9. 12. ch. 14. 27.

† 43.14 Heb. bars.

* 43.16 Ex. 14. 16, 22.

* 43.16 Josh. 3. 13, 16.

* 43.19 2 Cor. 5 17. Rev. 21. 5.

∥ 43.20 Or, ostriches.

† 43.20 Heb. daughters of the owl.

* 43.21 Luke 1. 74, 75.

† 43.23 Heb. lambs. or, kids.

† 43.24 Heb. made me drunk, or, abundantly moistened.

* 43.25 Ezek. 36. 22, &c.

† 43.27 Heb. interpreters.

∥ 43.28 Or, holy princes.

* 44.1 ch. 41. 8. &c 43 1. Jer. 30. 10. &c 46. 27.

* 44.3 ch. 35. 7. Joel 2. 28. John 7. 38. Acts 2. 18.

* 44.6 ch. 41 4. &c 48. 12. Rev. 1. 8, 17. &c 22. 13.

* 44.8 ch. 45. 5. Deut 4. 35, 39. &c 32. 39. 1 Sam. 2. 2.

† 44.8 Heb. rock.

† 44.9 Heb. desirable.

* 44.9 Ps. 115. 4, &c.

* 44.11 Ps 97. 7. ch. 1. 29. &c 42. 17. &c 45. 16.

* 44.12 Jer. 10. 3.

∥ 44.12 Or, with an axe.

∥ 44.14 Or, taketh courage.

† 44.18 Heb. daubed.

† 44.19 Heb. setteth to his heart.

† 44.19 Heb. that which comes of a tree?

‡ 44.20 [1611 of]

† 44.26 Heb. wastes.

* 44.28 2 Chr. 36 22 Ezra 1. 1. ch. 45. 13.

∥ 45.1 Or, strengthened.

* 45.5 Deut. 4. 35, 39 &c 32. 39. ch. 44. 8.

* 45.9 Jer. 18. 6. Rom 9. 20.

∥ 45.13 Or, make straight.

* 45.13 2 Chr. 36 22. Ezra 1. 1. ch. 44. 28.

* 45.16 ch. 44. 11.

* 45.19 Deut. 30. 11.

* 45.23 Rom. 14 11 Phil. 2. 10.

∥ 45.24 Or, Surely he shall say of me, In the Lord is all righteousness and strength.

† 45.24 Heb. righteousnesses.

† 46.2 Heb. their soul.

* 46.5 ch 40. 18, 25.

* 46.10 Ps. 33. 11. Prov. 19. 21. &c 21. 30. Heb. 6. 17.

† 46.11 Heb. the man of my counsel.

‡ 47.6 [1611 the]

* 47.7 Rev. 18. 7.

* 47.9 ch. 51. 19.

∥ 47.10 Or, caused thee to turn away.

† 47.11 Heb. the morning thereof.

† 47.11 Heb. expiate.

† 47.13 Heb. viewers of the heavens.

† 47.13 Heb. that give knowledge concerning the months.

† 47.14 Heb. their souls.

† 48.4 Heb. hard.

∥ 48.10 Or, for silver.

* 48.11 ch. 42. 8.

* 48.12 ch. 41. 4. &c 44. 6. Rev. 1 17. &c 22. 13.

∥ 48.13 Or, the palm of my right hand hath spread out.

* 48.20 Ex. 19. 4, 5, 6.

* 48.21 Ex 17. 6. Num 20. 11.

* 48.22 ch. 57. 21.

∥ 49.4 Or, my reward.

∥ 49.5 Or, That Israel may be gathered to him, and I may, &c.

∥ 49.6 Or, Art thou lighter than that thou shouldest, &c.

∥ 49.6 Or, desolations.

* 49.6 ch. 42. 6.

∥ 49.7 Or, to him that is despised in soul.

* 49.8 2 Cor. 6. 2.

∥ 49.8 Or, raise up.

* 49.9 ch. 42. 7.

* 49.10 Rev. 7. 16.

‡ 49.13 [1611 heaven]

‡ 49.13 [1611 God]

† 49.15 Heb. from having compassion.

* 49.18 ch. 60. 4

† 49.22 Heb. bosom.

† 49.23 Heb nourishers

† 49.23 Heb. princesses.

* 49.23 Ps. 72. 9.

† 49.24 Heb. the captivity of the just.

† 49.25 Heb. captivity.

* 49.26 Rev. 14. 20. &c 16. 6.

∥ 49.26 Or, new wine.

* 50.2 Num. 11. 23. ch. 59. 1.

* 50.2 Ex. 14. 21.

* 50.2 Josh. 3. 16.

* 50.4 Matt. 11. 28.

* 50.5 John 14. 31 Phil. 2. 8. Heb. 10. 5, &c.

* 50.6 Matt. 26 67 &c 27. 26.

* 50.8 Rom. 8 32, 33.

† 50.8 Heb. the master of my cause?

* 50.11 John 9. 39.

* 51.6 Ps. 102. 26. Matt. 24. 35.

* 51.7 Ps. 37. 31.

* 51.7 Matt. 10. 28.

* 51.9 Ps. 74. 13, 14. Ezek. 29. 3.

* 51.10 Ex. 14. 21.

* 51.11 ch. 35. 10.

* 51.12 Ps. 118. 6.

* 51.12 ch. 40. 6. 1 Pet. 1. 24.

∥ 51.13 Or, made himself ready.

* 51.15 Jer. 31. 35.

* 51.16 ch. 49. 2, 3.

* 51.17 ch. 52. 1.

* 51.19 ch. 47. 9.

† 51.19 Heb. happened.

† 51.19 Heb. breaking.

* 52.1 ch. 51. 17.

* 52.4 Gen. 46. 6.

* 52.5 Ezek. 36 20, 23. Rom. 2 24.

* 52.7 Nah. 1. 15. Rom. 10. 15.

* 52.10 Ps. 98 3. Luke 3 6

* 52.11 2 Cor. 6 17 Rev 18 4

† 52.12 Heb. gather you up.

∥ 52.13 Or prosper

* 52.14 ch 53. 3.

* 52.15 Rom. 15 21.

* 53.1 John 12 38 Rom. 10. 16

∥ 53.1 Or, doctrine

† 53.1 Heb hearing

* 53.3 ch. 52. 14 Mark 9 12.

∥ 53.3 Or, he hid as it were his face from us.

† 53.3 Heb. as a hiding of faces from him, or, from us.

* 53.4 Matt 3 17.

∥ 53.5 Or, tormented.

* 53.5 Rom. 4. 25 1 Cor. 15. 3

* 53.5 1 Pet. 2 24.

† 53.5 Heb. bruise.

† 53.6 Heb. hath made the iniquity of us all to meet on him

* 53.7 Matt. 26. 63 &c 27. 12. Mark 14. 61. &c 15. 5.

* 53.7 Acts 8. 32.

∥ 53.8 Or, He was taken away by distress and judgment: but, &c.

† 53.8 Heb. was the stroke upon him.

† 53.9 Heb. deaths.

* 53.9 1 Pet. 2. 22. 1 John 3. 5.

∥ 53.10 Or, when his soul shall make an offering.

* 53.12 Mark 15. 28. Luke 22 37

* 53.12 Luke 23. 34.

* 54.1 Gal. 4. 27.

* 54.5 Luke 1. 32.

* 54.9 Gen. 9. 11.

* 54.11 1 Chr. 29. 2.

* 54.13 John 6. 45.

* 55.1 John 7. 37.

† 55.2 Heb. weigh.

* 55.3 Acts 13. 34.

† 55.7 Heb. the man of iniquity.

† 55.7 Heb. he will multiply to pardon.

* 55.12 ch. 35. 1.

∥ 56.1 Or, equity.

* 56.7 ch. 2. 2.

* 56.7 Matt. 21. 13. Mark 11. 17. Luke 19. 46.

† 56.8 Heb. to his gathered.

∥ 56.10 Or, dreaming, or, talking in their sleep.

† 56.11 Heb. strong of appetite.

† 56.11 Heb. know not to be satisfied.

† 57.1 Heb. men of kindness, or, godliness.

* 57.1 Ps. 12. 1. Mic. 7. 2.

∥ 57.1 Or, from that which is evil.

∥ 57.2 Or, go in peace.

∥ 57.2 Or, before him.

∥ 57.5 Or, among the oaks.

* 57.5 2 Kin. 16. 4.

∥ 57.8 Or, hewed it for thyself larger than theirs.

‡ 57.8 [1611 omits thee]

∥ 57.8 Or, thou providedst room.

∥ 57.9 Or, thou respectedst the king.

∥ 57.10 Or, living.

* 57.14 ch. 40. 3. &c 62. 10.

† 57.17 Heb. turning away.

* 57.21 ch. 48. 22.

† 58.1 Heb. with the throat.

∥ 58.3 Or, things wherewith ye grieve others.

† 58.3 Heb. griefs.

∥ 58.4 Or, ye fast not as this day.

* 58.5 Zech 7. 5.

* 58.5 Lev. 16. 29

∥ 58.5 Or, to afflict his soul for a day?

† 58.6 Heb. the bundles of the yoke.

† 58.6 Heb. broken.

* 58.7 Ezek. 18. 7.

∥ 58.7 Or, afflicted.

† 58.8 Heb. shall gather thee up.

† 58.11 Heb. droughts.

† 58.11 Heb. lie, or, deceive.

* 58.12 ch. 61. 4.

* 58.14 Deut. 32. 13.

* 59.1 Num. 11. 23. ch. 50. 2.

∥ 59.2 Or, have made him hide.

* 59.3 ch. 1. 15.

* 59.4 Job 15. 35. Ps. 7. 14.

∥ 59.5 Or, adders'.

∥ 59.5 Or, that which is sprinkled is as if there brake out a viper.

* 59.6 Job 8. 14, 15.

* 59.7 Prov. 1. 16. Rom. 3. 15.

† 59.7 Heb. breaking.

∥ 59.8 Or, right.

∥ 59.15 Or, is accounted mad.

† 59.15 Heb. it was evil in his eyes.

* 59.16 ch 63. 5.

* 59.17 Eph. 6. 17. 1 Thess. 5. 8.

* 59.18 ch. 63. 6.

† 59.18 Heb. recompences.

* 59.19 Rev. 12. 15.

∥ 59.19 Or, put him to flight.

* 59.20 Rom. 11. 26.

∥ 60.1 Or, be enlightened; for thy light cometh.

* 60.3 Rev. 21. 24.

* 60.4 ch. 49. 18.

∥ 60.5 Or, noise of the sea shall be turned toward thee.

∥ 60.5 Or, wealth.

* 60.6 ch. 61. 6.

* 60.9 Gal. 4. 26.

* 60.11 Rev. 21. 26;

∥ 60.11 Or, wealth.

* 60.14 Rev. 3. 9.

* 60.19 Rev. 21. 23. &c 22. 5.

* 61.1 Luke 4. 18.

* 61.4 ch. 58. 12.

* 61.6 ch. 60. 6.

† 61.10 Heb. decketh as a priest.

* 62.4 Hos. 1. 10. 1 Pet. 2. 10

∥ 62.4 That is, My delight is in her.

∥ 62.4 That is, Married.

† 62.5 Heb with the joy of the bridegroom.

∥ 62.6 Or, ye that are the Lord's remembrancers.

† 62.7 Heb. silence.

† 62.8 Heb If I give, &c.

* 62.10 ch 40. 3. &c 57. 14.

* 62.11 Zech 9. 9 Matt. 21. 5 John 12. 15.

* 62.11 ch. 40. 10.

∥ 62.11 Or, recompence.

† 63.1 Heb. decked.

* 63.2 Rev. 19. 13.

* 63.4 ch. 34. 8.

* 63.5 ch. 59. 16.

* 63.9 Deut. 7. 7, 8.

* 63.10 Ex. 15 24. Num 14 11. Ps. 78. 56. &c 95. 9.

* 63.11 Ex. 14. 30.

∥ 63.11 Ps. 77. 20.

* 63.12 Ex. 14. 21 Josh. 3. 16

* 63.15 Deut. 26 15.

∥ 63.15 Or, the multitude.

∥ 63.16 Or, our redeemer from everlasting is thy name.

∥ 63.19 Or, thy name was not called upon them.

‡ 64.1 [1611 rent]

† 64.2 Heb. the fire of meltings.

* 64.4 Ps. 31. 19. 1 Cor. 2. 9.

∥ 64.4 Or, seen a God beside thee, which doeth so for him, &c.

* 64.6 Ps. 90. 5, 6.

† 64.7 Heb melted.

* 64.9 Ps. 79. 8.

* 65.1 Rom. 9. 24, 25, 26. &c 10 20. Eph. 2. 12.

† 65.3 Heb. upon bricks.

∥ 65.4 Or, pieces.

∥ 65.5 Or, anger.

∥ 65.11 Or, Gad.

∥ 65.11 Or, Meni.

* 65.12 Prov. 1. 24. &c. ch. 66 4. Jer. 7. 13.

† 65.14 Heb. breaking.

* 65.17 ch. 66. 22. 2 Pet. 3. 13. Rev 21. 1

† 65.17 Heb. come upon the heart.

* 65.19 Rev. 21. 4.

† 65.22 Heb. shall make them continue long, or, shall wear out.

* 65.24 Ps. 32. 5.

* 65.25 ch. 11. 6, 7.

* 66.1 1 Kin. 8. 27. 2 Chr. 6. 18. Acts 7. 49. &c 17. 24.

∥ 66.3 Or, kid.

† 66.3 Heb. maketh a memorial of.

∥ 66.4 Or, devices.

* 66.4 Prov. 1. 24. ch. 65. 12. Jer. 7. 13.

* 66.5 ch. 5. 19.

∥ 66.9 Or, beget.

∥ 66.11 Or, brightness.

* 66.12 ch. 49. 22. &c 60. 4.

∥ 66.17 Or, one after another.

∥ 66.20 Or, coaches.

* 66.21 Ex 19 6. ch 61 6 1 Pet. 2. 9. Rev 1. 6.

* 66.22 ch. 65. 17. 2 Pet. 3. 13. Rev. 21. 1.

† 66.23 Heb. from new moon to his new moon, and from sabbath to his sabbath.

* 66.24 Mark 9. 44.

Judith

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16

The Book of Judith

1

1 In the twelfth year of the reign of [a]Nabuchodonosor, who reigned in Nineve, [b]the great city; in the days of Arphaxad, which reigned over the [c]Medes in [d]Ecbatane,

2 And built in Ecbatane walls round about of stones hewn three cubits broad and six cubits long, and made the height of the wall seventy cubits, and the breadth thereof fifty cubits:

3 And set the towers thereof upon the gates of it an hundred cubits high, and the breadth thereof in the foundation threescore cubits:

4 And he made the gates thereof, even gates that were raised to the height of seventy cubits, and the breadth of them was forty cubits, for the going forth of his mighty armies, and for the setting in array of his footmen:

5 Even in those days king Nabuchodonosor made war with king Arphaxad in the great plain, which is the plain in the borders of [e]Ragau.

6 And there came unto him all they that dwelt in the hill country, and all that dwelt by Euphrates, and [f]Tigris and Hydaspes, and the plain of Arioch the king of the [g]Elymeans, and very many nations of the sons of Chelod, assembled themselves to the battle.

7 Then Nabuchodonosor king of the Assyrians sent unto all that dwelt in [h]Persia, and to all that dwelt westward, and to those that dwelt in [i]Cilicia, and [j]Damascus, and [k]Libanus, and Antilibanus, and to all that dwelt upon the sea coast,

8 And to those among the nations that were of [l]Carmel, and [m]Galaad, and [n]the higher Galilee, and the great plain of [o]Esdrelom,

9 And to all that were in [p]Samaria and the cities thereof, and beyond Jordan unto Jerusalem, and Betane, and [q]Chelus, and [r]Kades, and [s]the river of Egypt, and Taphnes, and [t]Ramesse, and all the land of [u]Gesem,

10 Until ye come beyond [w]Tanis and [x]Memphis, and to all the inhabitants of Egypt, until ye come to the borders of [y]Ethiopia.

11 But all the inhabitants of the land [z]made light of the commandment of Nabuchodonosor king of the Assyrians, neither went they with him to the battle; for they were not afraid of him: yea, he was before them as one man, and they sent away his ambassadors from them without effect, and with disgrace.

12 Therefore Nabuchodonosor was very angry with all this country, and sware by his throne and kingdom, that he would surely be avenged upon all those coasts of [i]Cilicia, and [j]Damascus, and [a]Syria, and that he would slay with the sword all the inhabitants of the land of [b]Moab, and the children of [c]Ammon, and all Judea, and all that were in Egypt, till ye come to the borders of [d]the two seas.

13 Then he marched in battle array with his power against king Arphaxad [dd]in the seventeenth year, and he prevailed in his battle: for he overthrew all the power of Arphaxad, and all his horsemen, and all his chariots,

14 And became lord of his cities, and came unto [e]Ecbatane, and took [f]the towers, and spoiled the streets thereof, and turned the beauty thereof into shame.

15 He took also Arphaxad in the mountains of [g]Ragau, and smote him through with his darts, and destroyed him utterly that day.

16 So he returned afterward to Nineve, both he and all his [h]company of sundry nations being a very great multitude of men of war, and there he took his ease, and banqueted, both he and his army, an hundred and twenty days.

2

1 And [a]in the eighteenth year, the two and twentieth day of the first month, there was talk in the house of Nabuchodonosor king of the Assyrians that he should, [b]as he said, avenge himself on all the earth.

2 So he called unto him all his officers, and all his [c]nobles, and communicated with them his secret counsel, and [d]concluded the afflicting of the whole earth out of his own mouth.

3 Then they decreed to destroy all flesh, [dd]that did not obey the commandment of his mouth.

4 And when he had ended his counsel, Nabuchodonosor king of the Assyrians called Holofernes the chief captain of his army, which was [*]next unto him, and said unto him.

5 Thus saith [e]the great king, the lord of the whole earth, Behold, thou shalt go forth from my presence, and take with thee men that trust in their own strength, of footmen an hundred and twenty thousand; and the number of horses with their riders twelve thousand.

6 And thou shalt go against all the west country, because [d]they disobeyed my commandment.

7 And thou shalt declare unto them, that they prepare for me [*]earth and water: for I will go forth in my wrath against them and will cover the whole face of the earth with the feet of mine army, and I will give them for a spoil unto them:

8 So that their slain shall fill their valleys and brooks and the river shall be filled with their dead, till it overflow:

9 And I will lead them captives to the utmost parts of all the earth.

10 Thou therefore shalt go forth. and take beforehand for me all their coasts: and if they will yield themselves unto thee, thou shalt reserve them for me till the day of their punishment.

11 But concerning them that rebel, [f]let not thine eye spare them; but put them to the slaughter, and spoil them wheresoever thou goest.

12 For [g]as I live, and by the power of my kingdom, whatsoever I have spoken, that will I do by mine hand.

13 And take thou heed that thou transgress none of the commandments of thy lord, but accomplish them fully, as I have commanded thee, and defer not to do them.

14 Then Holofernes went forth from the presence of his lord, and called all the [h]governors and captains, and the officers of the army of Assur;

15 And he mustered the chosen men for the [i]battle, as his lord had commanded him, [j]unto an hundred and twenty thousand, and twelve thousand archers on horseback;

16 And he ranged them, as a great army is ordered for the war.

17 And he took [jj]camels and asses for their [k]carriages, a very great number; and sheep and oxen and goats without number for their provision:

18 And plenty of victual for every man of the army, and very much gold and silver out of the king’s house.

19 Then he went forth and all his power to go before king Nabuchodonosor in the voyage, and [l]to cover all the face of the earth westward with their chariots, and horsemen, and their chosen footmen.

20 A great number also [m]sundry countries came with them like [n]locusts, and [o]like the sand of the earth: for the multitude was without number.

21 And they went forth of Nineve three days’ journey toward the plain of Bectileth, and pitched from Bectileth near the mountain which is at the left hand of the upper [p]Cilicia.

22 Then he took all his army, his footmen, and horsemen and chariots, and went from thence into the hill country;

23 And destroyed [q]Phud and [q]Lud, and spoiled all the children of Rasses, and [r]the children of Israel, which were toward the wilderness at the south of the land of the [s]Chellians.

24 Then he went over Euphrates, and went through [t]Mesopotamia, and destroyed all the high cities that were upon the river Arbonai, till ye come to the sea.

25 And he took the borders of [p]Cilicia, and killed all that resisted him, and came to [u]the borders of Japheth, which were toward the south, over against Arabia.

26 He compassed also all the children of [v]Madian, and burned up their tabernacles, and spoiled their sheepcotes.

27 Then he went down into the plain of [w]Damascus in the time of wheat harvest, and burnt up all their fields, and destroyed their flocks and herds, also he spoiled their cities, and [x]utterly wasted their countries, and smote all their young men with [y]the edge of the sword.

28 Therefore the fear and dread of him fell upon all the inhabitants of the sea coasts, which were in [z]Sidon and Tyrus, and them that dwelt in Sur and Ocina, and all that dwelt in [a]Jemnaan; and they that dwelt in [b]Azotus and [c]Ascalon feared him greatly.

3

1 So they sent ambassadors unto him to treat of peace, saying,

2 Behold, we the servants of Nabuchodonosor [a]the great king lie before thee; use us as shall be good in thy sight.

3 Behold, our houses, and all our places, and all [b]our fields of wheat, and flocks, and herds, and all the lodges of our tents lie before thy face; use them as it pleaseth thee.

4 Behold, even our cities and the inhabitants thereof are thy servants; come and deal with them as seemeth good unto thee.

5 So the men came to Holofernes, and declared unto him after this manner.

6 Then came he down toward [c]the sea coast, both he and his army, and set garrisons in the high cities, and took out of them chosen men for aid.

7 So they and all the country round about received them [d]with garlands, [e]with dances, and with [e]timbrels.

8 Yet he did cast down their frontiers, and [f]cut down their groves: for he had decreed to destroy all the gods of the land, that all nations should worship Nabuchodonosor only, and that all tongues and tribes should call upon him as god.

9 Also he came over against [*]Esdraelon near unto [*]Judea, over against the [*]great strait of Judea.

10 And he pitched between [g]Geba and [h]Scythopolis, and there he tarried a whole month, that he might gather together all the [i]carriages of his army.

4

1 Now the children of Israel, that dwelt in Judea, heard all that Holofernes the chief captain of Nabuchodonosor king of the Assyrians had done to the nations, and after what manner he had spoiled all their temples, and brought them to nought.

2 Therefore they were exceedingly afraid of him, and were troubled for Jerusalem, and for the temple of the Lord their God:

3 [a]For they were newly returned from the captivity, and all the people [*]of Judea were lately gathered together: and the vessels, and [b]the altar, and [b]the house, were sanctified after the profanation.

4 Therefore they sent into all the coasts of [c]Samaria, and the villages and to [d]Bethoron, and Belmen, and Jericho, and to [e]Choba, and Esora, and to the valley of [f]Salem:

5 And [g]possessed themselves beforehand of all the tops of the high mountains, and fortified the villages that were in them, and laid up victuals for the provision of war: for [h]their fields were of late reaped.

6 Also [i]Joacim the high priest, which was in those days in Jerusalem, wrote to them that dwelt in [j]Bethulia, and [k]Betomestham, which is over against [*]Esdraelon toward the [*]open country, near to [l]Dothaim,

7 Charging them to keep [m]the passages of the hill country: for by them there was an entrance into Judea, and it was easy to stop them that would come up, because the passage was straight, [*]for two men at the most.

8 And the children of Israel did as [i]Joacim the high priest had commanded them, with the [*]ancients of all the people of Israel, which dwelt at Jerusalem.

9 Then every man of Israel cried to God with great [n]fervency, and with great [n]vehemency did they humble their souls:

10 Both they, and their wives and their children, and their cattle, and every stranger and hireling, and their servants bought with money, [o]put sackcloth upon their loins.

11 Thus every man and women, and the little children, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, [p]fell before the temple, and [q]cast ashes upon their heads, and [r]spread out their sackcloth before the face of the Lord: also they put sackcloth about the altar,

12 And cried to the God of Israel all with one consent earnestly, that he would not give their children for a prey, and their wives [s]for a spoil, and the cities of their inheritance to destruction, and the sanctuary to profanation and reproach, and for the nations to rejoice at.

13 So God heard their prayers, and [t]looked upon their afflictions: for the people fasted many days in all Judea and Jerusalem [u]before the sanctuary of the Lord [v]Almighty.

14 And [i]Joacim the high priest, and all the priests that stood before the Lord, and they which ministered unto the Lord, [o]had their loins girt with sackcloth, and [w]offered the daily burnt offerings, with the vows and free gifts of the people,

15 And [q]had ashes on their [x]mitres, and cried unto the Lord with all their power, that he would look upon all the house of Israel graciously.

5

1 Then was it declared to Holofernes, the chief captain of the army of Assur, that the children of Israel had prepared for war, and had shut up [a]the passages of the hill country, and had fortified [*]all [b]the tops of the high hills and had laid [bb]impediments in the champaign countries:

2 Wherewith he was very angry, and called all the princes of [c]Moab, and the captains of [c]Ammon, and all the governors of [d]the sea coast,

3 And he said unto them, Tell me now, ye sons of Chanaan, who this people is, that dwelleth in the hill country, and what are the cities that they inhabit, and what is the multitude of their army, and wherein is their power and strength, and what king is set over them, or captain of their army;

4 And why have they determined not to come and meet me, more than all the inhabitants of the west.

5 Then said [e]Achior, the captain of all the sons of [c]Ammon, Let my lord now hear a word from the mouth of thy servant, and I will declare unto thee the truth concerning this people, which dwelleth near thee, and inhabiteth the hill countries: and there shall no lie come out of the mouth of thy servant.

6 This people are descended of the Chaldeans:

7 And [f]they sojourned heretofore in [g]Mesopotamia, because [h]they would not follow the gods of their fathers, which were in the land of Chaldea.

8 For they [*]left the way of their ancestors, and worshipped [i]the God of heaven, the God whom they knew: so they cast them out from the face of their gods, and they fled into [g]Mesopotamia, and sojourned there many days.

9 Then [j]their God commanded them to depart from the place where they sojourned, and to go into the land of Chanaan: where they dwelt, and [k]were increased with gold and silver, and with very much cattle.

10 But when a famine covered all the land of Chanaan, [l]they went down into Egypt, and sojourned there, while they were nourished, and [m]became there a great multitude, so that one could not number their nation.

11 Therefore [n]the king of Egypt rose up against them, and [o]dealt subtilly with them, and brought them low with labouring in brick, and made them slaves.

12 [p]Then they cried unto their God, and [q]he smote all the land of Egypt with incurable plagues: so [r]the Egyptians cast them out of their sight.

13 And [s]God dried the Red sea before them,

14 And [t]brought them [*]to mount Sina, and [u]Cades-Barne, and cast forth all that dwelt in the wilderness.

15 [x]So they dwelt in the land of the Amorites, and they destroyed by their strength all them of [x]Esebon, and [y]passing over Jordan they possessed [z]all the hill country.

16 And they cast forth before them the [a]Chanaanite, the [a]Pherezite, the [a]Jebusite, and the [a][b]Sychemite, and all the [c]Gergesites, and they dwelt in that country many days.

17 And whilst they sinned not before their God, they prospered, because the [d]God that hateth iniquity was with them.

18 But [e]when they departed from the way which he appointed them, they were destroyed in many battles very sore, and [f]were led captives into a land that was not their’s, and the temple of their God was cast to the ground, and their cities were taken by the enemies.

19 But now are they returned to their God, and [g]are come up from the places where they were scattered, and have possessed Jerusalem, where their sanctuary is, and [*]are seated in the hill country; for it was desolate.

20 Now therefore, my lord and governor, if there be any error against this people, and they sin against their God, let us consider that this shall be their [h]ruin, and let us go up, and we shall overcome them.

21 But if there be no iniquity in their nation, let my lord now pass by, lest their Lord defend them, and their God be for them, and we become a reproach before all the world.

22 And when Achior had finished these sayings, all the people standing round about the tent murmured, and the [i]chief men of Holofernes, and all that dwelt by [ii]the sea side, and in [ii]Moab, spake that he should kill him.

23 For, [j]say they, we will not be afraid of the face of the children of Israel: for, lo, it is a people that have no strength nor power [*]for a strong [k]battle

24 Now therefore, lord Holofernes, we will go up, and they shall be [l]a prey to be devoured of all thine army.

6

1 And when the tumult of men that were about the council was ceased, Holofernes the chief captain of the army of Assur said unto Achior and all the [a]Moabites before all the company of other nations,

2 And who art thou, Achior, and [b]the hirelings of Ephraim, that thou hast prophesied against us as to day, and hast said, that we should not make war with the people of Israel, [c]because their God will defend them? and who is God but Nabuchodonosor?

3 He will send his power, and will destroy them from the face of the earth, and [d]their God shall not deliver them: but we his servants will destroy them as one man; for they are not able to sustain the power of our horses.

4 For with them we will tread them under foot, and their mountains [e]shall be drunken with their blood, and their fields shall be filled with their dead bodies, and their footsteps shall not be able to stand before us, for they shall utterly perish, saith king Nabuchodonosor, lord of all the earth: for he said, None of my words shall be in vain.

5 And thou, Achior, [b]an hireling of [f]Ammon, which hast spoken these words in the day of thine iniquity, shalt see my face no more from this day, until I take vengeance of this nation [g]that came out of Egypt.

6 And then shall the sword of mine army, and the multitude of them that serve me, pass through thy sides, and thou shalt fall among their slain, [h]when I return.

7 Now therefore my servants shall bring thee back into the hill country, and shall set thee in one of the cities of [i]the passages:

8 And thou shalt not perish, till thou be destroyed with them.

9 And if thou persuade thyself in thy mind that they shall not be taken, let not [k]thy countenance fall: I have spoken it, and none of my words shall be in vain.

10 Then Holofernes commanded his servants, that waited in his tent, to take Achior, and bring him to [l]Bethulia, and deliver him into the hands of the children of Israel.

11 So his servants took him, and brought him out of the camp into the plain, and they went from the midst of the plain into the hill country, and came unto [m]the fountains that were under Bethulia.

12 And when the men of the city saw them, they took up their weapons, and went out of the city to the top of the hill: and every man that used a sling kept them from coming up by casting of stones against them.

13 Nevertheless having gotten privily under the hill, they bound Achior, and cast him down, and left him at the foot of the hill, and returned to their lord.

14 But the Israelites descended from their city, and came unto him, and loosed him, and brought him to Bethulia, and presented him to the governors of the city:

15 Which were in those days Ozias the son of Micha, of the tribe of Simeon, and Chabris the son of Gothoniel, and Charmis the son of Melchiel.

16 And they called together all [n]the ancients of the city, and all their youth ran together, and their women, to the assembly, and they set Achior in the midst of all their people. Then Ozias asked him of that which was done.

17 And he answered and declared unto them the words of [o]the council of Holofernes, and all the words that he had spoken in the midst of the princes of Assur, and whatsoever Holofernes had spoken proudly against the house of Israel.

18 Then the people fell down and worshipped God, and cried unto God. saying,

19 O Lord [p]God of heaven, behold their pride, and pity the low estate of our nation, and [q]look upon the face of those that are sanctified unto thee this day.

20 Then they comforted Achior, and praised him greatly.

21 And Ozias took him out of the assembly unto his house, and [r]made a feast to [n]the elders; and they called on the God of Israel all that night for help.

7

1 The next day Holofernes commanded all his army, and all his people which were come to take his part, that they should remove their camp against Bethulia, to take aforehand [a]the ascents of the hill country, and to make war against the children of Israel.

2 Then their strong men removed their camps in that day, and the army of the men of war was [b]an hundred and seventy thousand footmen, and twelve thousand horsemen, beside the baggage, and other men that were afoot among them, a very great multitude.

3 And they camped in the valley near unto Bethulia, [c]by the fountain, and they spread themselves in breadth [*]over [d]Dothaim even to [e]Belmaim, and in length from Bethulia unto [*]Cynamon, which is over against [f]Esdraelon.

4 Now the children of Israel, when they saw the multitude of them, were greatly troubled, and said every one to his neighbour, Now will these men [g]lick up the face of the earth; for neither the high mountains, nor the valleys, nor the hills, are able to bear their weight.

5 Then every man took up his weapons of war, and when they had kindled fires upon their towers, they remained and watched all that night.

6 But in the second day Holofernes brought forth all his horsemen in the sight of the children of Israel which were in Bethulia,

7 And viewed [a]the passages up to the city, and came to [c]the fountains of their waters, and took them, and set [h]garrisons of men of war over them, and he himself removed toward his people.

8 Then came unto him all the chief of [i]the children of Esau, and all the governors of the people of [k]Moab, and the captains of [l]the sea coast, and said,

9 Let our lord now hear a word, that there be not an overthrow in thine army.

10 For this people of the children of Israel do not trust in their spears, but in the height of the mountains wherein they dwell, because it is not easy to come up to the tops of their mountains.

11 Now therefore, my lord, fight not against them in battle [ll]array, and there shall not so much as one man of thy people perish.

12 Remain in thy camp, and keep all the men of thine army, and let thy servants get into their hands [c]the fountain of water, which issueth forth of the foot of the mountain:

13 For all the inhabitants of Bethulia have their water thence; so shall thirst kill them, and they shall give up their city, and we and our people shall go up to the tops of the mountains that are near, and will camp upon them, to watch that none go out of the city.

14 So they and their wives and their children shall be consumed with fire, and before the sword come against them, they shall be overthrown in the streets where they dwell.

15 Thus shalt thou render them an evil reward; because they rebelled, and met not thy person peaceably.

16 And these words pleased Holofernes and all his servants, and he appointed to do as they had spoken.

17 So the [h]camp of the children of [m]Ammon departed, and with them five thousand of the Assyrians, and they pitched in the valley, and took the waters, and [c]the fountains of the waters of the children of Israel.

18 Then [i]the children of Esau went up with the children of [m]Ammon, and camped in the hill country over against [d]Dothaim: and they sent some of them toward the south, and toward the east over against Ekrebel, which is near unto Chusi, that is upon the brook Mochmur; and the rest of the army of the Assyrians camped in the plain, and [n]covered the face of the whole land; and their tents and [o]carriages were pitched to a very great multitude.

19 Then the children of Israel cried unto the Lord their God, because their heart failed, for all their enemies had compassed them round about, and there was no way to escape out from among them.

20 Thus all the [h]company of Assur remained about them, both their footmen, chariots, and horsemen, four and thirty days, so that all their vessels of water failed all the inhibitants of Bethulia.

21 And the [*][p]cisterns were emptied, and they had not water to drink their fill for one day; for they gave them drink [q]by measure.

22 Therefore their young children were out of heart, and their women and young men [r]fainted for thirst, and fell down in the streets of the city, and by the passages of the gates, and there was no longer any strength in them.

23 Then all the people assembled to [s]Ozias, and to the chief of the city, both young men, and women, and children, and cried with a loud voice, and said before all [t]the elders,

24 [u]God be judge between us and you: for ye have done us great injury, in that ye have not required peace of the children of Assur.

25 For now we have no helper: but [x]God hath sold us into their hands, that we should be thrown down before them with thirst and great destruction.

26 Now therefore call them unto you, and deliver the whole city [y]for a spoil to the people of Holofernes, and to all his army.

27 For it is better for us to be made a spoil unto them, than to die for thirst: for we will be his servants, that our souls may live, and not see the death of our infants before our eyes, nor our wives nor our children to die.

28 [z]We take to witness against you the heaven and the earth, and our God and Lord of our fathers, which punisheth us according to our sins and [a]the sins of our fathers, [*]that he do not [b]according as we have said this day.

29 Then there was great weeping with one consent in the midst of the assembly; and they cried unto the Lord God with a loud voice.

30 Then said Ozias to them, Brethren, be of good courage, [c]let us yet endure five days, in the which space the Lord our God may turn his mercy toward us; for he will not forsake us [d]utterly.

31 And if these days pass, and there come no help unto us, I will do [e]according to your word.

32 And he dispersed the people, every one to their own charge; and they went unto the walls and towers of their city, and sent the women and children into their houses: and they were very low brought in the city.

8

1 Now at that time Judith heard thereof, which was the daughter of Merari, the son of Ox, the son of Joseph, the son of Ozel, the son of Elcia, the son of Ananias, the son of Gedeon, the son of Raphaim, the son of Acitho, the son of Eliu, the son of Eliab, the son of Nathanael, the son of [*]Samael, the son of Salasadal, [a]the son of Israel.

2 And Manasses was her husband, of her tribe and kindred, who died in [b]the barley harvest.

3 For as he stood overseeing them that bound sheaves in the field, [c]the heat came upon his head, and he fell on his bed, and died in the city of Bethulia: and they buried him with his fathers in the field between [d]Dothaim and [e]Balamo.

4 So Judith was a widow in her house three years and [f]four months.

5 And she made her a tent upon [g]the top of her house, and [h]put on sackcloth upon her loins and ware [i]her widow’s apparel.

6 And she fasted all the days of her widowhood, save [k]the eves of the sabbaths, and [l]the sabbaths, and the eves of the new moons, and [l]the new moons and the feasts and solemn days of the house of Israel.

7 She was also of a goodly countenance, and very beautiful to behold: and her husband Manasses had left her gold, and silver, and menservants and maidservants, and cattle, and lands; [*]and she remained upon them.

8 And there was none that gave her an ill word; as she feared God greatly.

9 Now when she heard the evil words of the people against the governor, [m]that they fainted for lack of water; for Judith had heard [n]all the words that Ozias had spoken unto them, and [n]that he had sworn to deliver the city unto the Assyrians after five days;

10 Then she sent her waitingwoman, that had the government of all things that she had, to call [o]Ozias and Chabris and Charmis, [p]the ancients of the city.

11 And they came unto her, and she said unto them, Hear me now, O ye governors of the inhabitants of Bethulia: for your words that ye have spoken before the people this day are not right, touching this oath which ye made and pronounced between God and you, and have promised to deliver the city to our enemies, unless within these days the Lord turn to help you.

12 And now who are ye [q]that have tempted God this day, and stand instead of God among the children of men?

13 And now try the Lord [r]Almighty, but ye shall never know any thing.

14 For [s]ye cannot find the depth of the heart of man, neither can ye perceive the things that he thinketh: then how can ye search out God, that hath made all these things, and [t]know his mind, or comprehend his purpose? Nay, my brethren, [u]provoke not the Lord our God to anger.

15 For if he will not help us within these five days, he hath power to defend us when he will, even every day, or to destroy us before our enemies.

16 Do not [*]bind the counsels of the Lord our God: for [x]God is not as man, that he may be threatened; [x]neither is he as the son of man, that he should be wavering.

17 Therefore let us wait for salvation of him, and call upon him to help us, and he will hear our voice, if it please him.

18 For there arose none in our age, neither is there any now in these days neither tribe, nor family, nor [*]people, nor city among us, which worship gods made with hands, [y]as hath been aforetime.

19 For the which cause our fathers were given to the sword, and for a spoil, and had a great fall before our enemies.

20 But we know none other god, therefore we trust that he will not despise us, nor any of our nation.

21 For if we be taken so, all Judea shall lie waste, and our sanctuary shall be spoiled; and he will require the profanation thereof at our mouth.

22 And the [*]slaughter of our brethren, and the captivity of the country, and the desolation of our inheritance, will he turn upon our heads among the Gentiles, wheresoever we shall be in bondage; and we shall be [z]an offence and a reproach to all them that possess us.

23 For our servitude shall not be directed to favour: but the Lord our God shall turn it to dishonour.

24 Now therefore, O brethren, let us shew an example to our brethren, because their hearts depend upon us, and the sanctuary, and the house, and the altar, rest upon us.

25 Moreover let us give thanks to the Lord our God, which trieth us, even as he did our fathers.

26 Remember what things he did to [a]Abraham, and how he tried [a]Isaac, and [b]what happened to Jacob in Mesopotamia of Syria, when he kept the sheep of Laban his mother’s brother.

27 For he hath not tried us in the fire, as he did them, for the examination of their hearts, neither hath he taken vengeance on us: but [c]the Lord doth scourge them that come near unto him, to admonish them.

28 Then said Ozias to her, All that thou hast spoken hast thou spoken with a good heart, and there is none that may gainsay thy words.

29 For this is not the first day wherein thy wisdom is manifested; but from the beginning of thy days all the people have known thy understanding, because the disposition of thine heart is good.

30 But [d]the people were very thirsty, and compelled us to do unto them as we have spoken, and to bring an oath upon ourselves, which we will not break.

31 Therefore now pray thou for us, because thou art a godly woman, and the Lord will send us rain to fill our [e]cisterns, and we shall faint no more.

32 Then said Judith unto them, Hear me, and I will do a thing, which shall go throughout all generations to the children of our nation.

33 Ye shall stand this night in the gate, and I will go forth with my [f]waitingwoman: and within the days that ye have promised to deliver the city to our enemies [g]the Lord will visit Israel by mine hand.

34 But enquire not ye of mine act: for I will not declare it unto you, till the things be finished that I do.

35 Then said Ozias and the princes unto her, [h]Go in peace, and the Lord God be before thee, to take vengeance on our enemies.

36 So they returned from [i]the tent, and went to their wards.

9

1 Judith [a]fell upon her face, and [a]put ashes upon her head, and uncovered [b]the sackcloth wherewith she was clothed; and about [c]the time that the incense of that evening was offered in Jerusalem in the house of the Lord Judith cried with a loud voice, and said,

2 O Lord God of my father Simeon, [d]to whom thou gavest a sword to take vengeance of the strangers, who loosened the girdle of a maid to defile her, and discovered the thigh to her shame, and polluted her virginity to her reproach; for thou saidst, [e]It shall not be so; and yet they did so:

3 Wherefore thou gavest their rulers to be slain, so that they dyed their bed in blood, being deceived, and smotest the servants with their lords, and the lords upon their thrones;

4 And [f]hast given their wives [g]for a prey, and [f]their daughters to be captives, and all [f]their spoils to be divided among thy dear children; which [h]were moved with thy zeal, and abhorred the pollution of their blood, and called upon thee for aid: O God, O my God, hear me also a widow.

5 For thou hast wrought not only those things, but also the things which fell out before, and which ensued after; thou hast thought upon the things which are now, and which are to come.

6 Yea, what things thou didst determine were ready at hand, and said, Lo, we are here: for all thy ways are prepared, and thy judgments are in thy foreknowledge.

7 For, behold, the Assyrians are multiplied in their power; they are exalted with horse and man; they glory in the strength of their footmen; [i]they trust in shield, and spear, and bow, and sling; and know not that thou art [j]the Lord that breakest the battles: [j]the Lord is thy name.

8 [jj]Throw down their strength in thy power, and bring down their force in thy wrath: for they have purposed to defile thy sanctuary, and to pollute the tabernacle where thy glorious name resteth and to cast down with sword [k]the horn of thy altar.

9 Behold their pride, and send thy wrath upon their heads: give into mine hand, which am a widow, the power that I have conceived.

10 [l]Smite by the deceit of my lips the servant with the prince, and the prince with the servant: break down their [m]stateliness [n]by the hand of a woman.

11 For [o]thy power standeth not in multitude nor thy might in strong men: for thou art a God of the afflicted, an helper of the oppressed, an upholder of the weak, a protector of the forlorn, a [p]saviour of [q]them that are without hope.

12 I pray thee, I pray thee, O God of my father, and God of the inheritance of Israel, [r]Lord of the heavens and earth, Creator of the waters, king of every creature, hear thou my prayer:

13 And make my speech and deceit to be their wound and stripe, who have purposed cruel things against thy covenant, and thy hallowed house, and against the top of Sion, and against the house of the possession of thy children.

14 And make every nation and tribe to acknowledge that thou art the God of all power and might, and that there is none other that protecteth the people of Israel but thou.

10

1 Now after that she had ceased to cry unto the God of Israel, and had made an end of all these words.

2 She rose [a]where she had fallen down, and called her maid, and went down into the house [b]in the which she abode in the sabbath days, and in her feast days,

3 And pulled off [b]the sackcloth which she had on, and put off [b]the garments of her widowhood, and [c]washed her body all over with water, and [c]anointed herself with precious ointment, and braided the hair of her head, and put on a [*][d]tire upon it, and put on her garments of gladness, wherewith she was clad during the life of [e]Manasses her husband.

4 And [d]she took sandals upon her feet, and put about her her [f]bracelets, and [g]her chains, and her [h]rings, and her [g][h]earrings, and all her ornaments, and decked herself bravely, to allure the eyes of all men that should see her.

5 Then she gave her maid a bottle of wine, and [i]a cruse of oil, and filled a bag with parched corn, and [j]lumps of figs, and with fine bread; so she [*]folded all these things together, and laid them upon her.

6 Thus they went forth to the gate of the city of Bethulia, and [k]found standing there Ozias and [l]the ancients of the city, Chabris and Charmis.

7 And when they saw her, that her countenance was altered, and her apparel was changed, they wondered at her beauty very greatly, and said unto her.

8 The God, the God of our fathers give thee favour, and accomplish thine [m]enterprizes to the glory of the children of Israel, and to the exaltation of Jerusalem. Then they worshipped God.

9 And she said unto them, Command the gates of the city to be opened unto me, that I may go forth to accomplish the things whereof ye have spoken with me. So they commanded the young men to open unto her, as she had spoken.

10 And when they had done so, Judith went out, she, and her maid with her; and the men of the city looked after her, until she was gone down the mountain, and till she had passed the valley, and could see her no more.

11 Thus they went straight forth in the valley: and the [mm]first watch of the Assyrians met her,

12 And took her, and asked her, Of what people art thou? and whence comest thou? and whither goest thou? And she said, I am a woman of the Hebrews, and am fled from them: for they shall be given you [n]to be consumed:

13 And I am coming before Holofernes the chief captain of your army, to declare words of truth; and I will shew him a way, whereby he shall go, and win all the hill country, without losing the body or life of any one of his men.

14 Now when the men heard her words, and beheld her countenance, they wondered greatly at her beauty, and said unto her,

15 Thou hast saved thy life, in that thou hast hasted to come down to the presence of our lord: now therefore come to his tent, and some of us shall [o]conduct thee, until they have delivered thee to his hands.

16 And when thou standest before him, be not afraid in thine heart, but shew unto him according to thy word; and he will entreat thee well.

17 Then they chose out of them an hundred men [*]to accompany her and her maid; and they brought her to the tent of Holofernes.

18 Then [p]was there a concourse throughout all the camp: for her coming was noised among the tents, and they came about her, as she stood without the tent of Holofernes, till they told him of her.

19 And they wondered at her beauty, and admired the children of Israel because of her, and every one said to his neighbour, Who would despise this people, that have among them such women? surely it is not good that one man of them be left who being let go might deceive the whole earth.

20 And they that [r]lay near Holofernes went out, and all his servants and they brought her into the tent.

21 Now Holofernes rested upon his bed under a [q]canopy, which was woven with purple, and gold, and emeralds, and precious stones.

22 So they shewed him of her; and he came out before his tent with [r]silver lamps going before him.

23 And when Judith was come before him and his servants they all marvelled at the beauty of her countenance; and [s]she fell down upon her face, and did reverence unto him: and his servants took her up.

11

1 Then said Holofernes unto her, Woman, be of good comfort, fear not in thine heart: for I never hurt any that was willing to serve Nabuchodonosor, the king of all the earth.

2 Now therefore, if thy people that dwelleth in the mountains had not [a]set light by me, I would not have lifted up my spear against them: but they have done these things to themselves.

3 But now tell me wherefore thou art fled from them, and art come unto us: for thou art come for safeguard; be of good comfort, thou shalt live [b]this night, and hereafter:

4 For none shall hurt thee, but entreat thee well, as they do the servants of king Nabuchodonosor my lord.

5 Then Judith said unto him, Receive the words of thy servant, and suffer thine handmaid to speak in thy presence, and I will declare no lie to my lord [b]this night.

6 And if thou wilt follow the words of thine handmaid, God will bring the thing perfectly to pass by thee; and my lord shall not fail of his [bb]purposes.

7 [c]As Nabuchodonosor king of all the earth liveth, and as his power liveth, who hath sent thee for the upholding of every living thing: for not only men shall serve him by thee, but also [cc]the beasts of the field, and the cattle, and the fowls of the air, shall live by thy power under Nabuchodonosor and all his house.

8 For we have heard of thy wisdom and thy policies, and it is reported in all the earth, that thou only art [*]excellent in all the kingdom, and mighty in knowledge, and wonderful in feats of war.

9 Now as concerning the matter, which [d]Achior did speak in thy council, we have heard his words; for the men of Bethulia [*][e]saved him, and he declared unto them all that he had spoken unto thee.

10 Therefore, O lord and governor, reject not [f]his word; but lay it up in thine heart, for it is true: for our nation shall not be punished, neither can sword prevail against them, except they sin against their God.

11 And now, that my lord be not defeated and frustrate of his purpose, even death is now fallen upon them, and their sin hath overtaken them, wherewith they will [g]provoke their God to anger whensoever they shall do that which is not fit to be done:

12 For their victuals fail them, and all their water is scant, and they have determined to lay hands upon their cattle, and purposed to consume all those things, that God hath forbidden them to eat by his laws:

13 And are resolved to spend [h]the firstfruits of the tenths of wine and oil, which they had sanctified, and [h]reserved for the priests that serve in Jerusalem before the face of our God; the which things it is not lawful for any of the people so much as to touch with their hands.

14 For they have sent some to Jerusalem, because they also that dwell there have done the like, to bring them a licence from the [i]senate.

15 Now when they shall bring them word, they will forthwith do it, and they shall be given to thee to be destroyed the same day.

16 Wherefore I thine handmaid, knowing all this, am fled from their presence; and God hath sent me to work things with thee, whereat all the earth shall be astonished, and whosoever shall hear it.

17 For thy servant is [j]religious, and serveth [k]the God of heaven [l]day and night: now therefore, my lord, I will remain with thee, and thy servant will go out by night into the valley, and I will pray unto God, and he will tell me when they have committed their sins:

18 And I will come and shew it unto thee: then thou shalt go forth with all thine army, and there shall be none of them that shall resist thee.

19 And I will lead thee through the midst of Judea, until thou come before Jerusalem; and I will set thy throne in the midst thereof; and thou shalt drive them [m]as sheep that have no shepherd, and [n]a dog shall not so much as [*]open his mouth at thee: for [*]these things [o]were told me according to my foreknowledge, and they were declared unto me, and I am sent to tell thee.

20 Then her words pleased Holofernes and all his servants; and they marvelled at her wisdom, and said,

21 There is not such a woman from one end of the earth to the other, both for beauty of face, and wisdom of words.

22 Likewise Holofernes said unto her. God hath done well to send thee before the people, that strength might be in our hands and destruction upon them that [a]lightly regard my lord.

23 And now thou art both beautiful in thy countenance, and witty in thy words: surely if thou do as thou hast spoken [p]thy God shall be my God, and thou shalt dwell in the house of king Nabuchodonosor, and shalt be renowned through the whole earth.

12

1 Then he commanded to bring her in where [a]his plate was set; and bade that they should prepare for her of his own meats, and that she should drink of his own wine.

2 And Judith said, [aa]I will not eat thereof, lest there be an offence: but provision shall be made for me [b]of the things that I have brought.

3 Then Holofernes said unto her, If thy provision should fail, how should we give thee the like? for there be none with us of thy nation.

4 Then said Judith unto him [c]As thy soul liveth, my lord, thine handmaid shall not spend those things that I have, before the Lord work by mine hand the things that he hath determined.

5 Then the servants of Holofernes brought her [d]into the tent, and she slept [e]till midnight, and she arose when it was toward [f]the morning watch,

6 And sent to Holofernes, saving, Let my lord now command that thine handmaid may go forth unto prayer.

7 Then Holofernes commanded his guard that they should not stay her: thus she abode in the camp three days, and went out in the night into the valley of Bethulia, and washed herself [g]in a fountain of water by the camp.

8 And when she came out, she besought the Lord God of Israel to direct her way to [h]the raising up of the children of her people.

9 So she came in clean, and remained in [d]the tent, until she did eat her meat at evening.

10 And in the fourth day Holofernes [i]made a feast to his own servants only, and called none of the officers to the banquet.

11 Then said he to Bagoas the eunuch, who had charge over all that he had, Go now, and persuade this Hebrew woman [d]which is with thee, that she come unto us, and eat and drink with us.

12 For, lo, it will be a shame for our person, if we shall let such a woman go, not having had her company; for if we draw her not unto us, she will laugh us to scorn.

13 Then went Bagoas from the presence of Holofernes, and came to her, and he said, Let not this fair damsel fear to come to my lord, and to be honoured in his presence, and drink wine, and be merry with us and be made this day as one of the daughters of the Assyrians, which [j]serve in the house of Nabuchodonosor.

14 Then said Judith unto him, Who am I now, that I should gainsay my lord? surely whatsoever pleaseth him I will do speedily, and it shall be my joy unto the day of my death.

15 So she arose, and decked herself with her apparel and all her woman’s attire, and her maid went and laid soft skins on the ground for her over against Holofernes, which she had received of Bagoas for her daily use, that she might sit and eat upon them.

16 Now when Judith came in and sat down, Holofernes [k]his heart was ravished with her, and his mind was moved, and he desired greatly her company; for he waited a time to deceive her, from the day that he had seen her.

17 Then said Holofernes unto her, Drink now, and be merry with us.

18 So Judith said, I will drink now, my lord, because my life is magnified in me this day more than all the days since I was born.

19 Then she took and ate and drank before him [l]what her maid had prepared.

20 And Holofernes took great delight in her, and drank more wine than he had drunk at any time in one day since he was born.

13

1 Now when the evening was come, [a]his servants made haste to [b]depart, and Bagoas shut his tent without, and dismissed [c]the waiters from the presence of his lord; and they went to their beds: for they were all weary, because the feast had been long.

2 And Judith was left alone in the tent, and Holofernes lying alone upon his bed: for [d]he was filled with wine.

3 Now Judith had commanded her maid to stand without her bedchamber, and to wait for her. coming forth, as she did daily: for she said she would go forth to her prayers, and she spake to Bagoas according to the same purpose.

4 So all went forth and none was left in the bedchamber, [e]neither little nor great. Then Judith, standing by his bed, said in her heart, O Lord God of all power, look at this present upon the works of mine hands for the exaltation of Jerusalem.

5 For now is the time [f]to help thine inheritance, and to execute thine [g]enterprizes to the destruction of the enemies which are risen against us.

6 Then she came to the [l]pillar of the bed, which was at Holofernes’ head, and took down his [h]fauchion from thence,

7 And approached to his bed, and took hold of the hair of his head, and said, Strengthen me, O Lord God of Israel, this day.

8 And she smote twice upon his neck with all her might, and [i]she took away his head from him.

9 And tumbled his body down from the bed, and pulled down the [k]canopy from the [l]pillars; and [m]anon after she went forth, and gave Holofernes his head to her maid;

10 And she put it in her [n]bag of meat: so they twain went together according to their custom unto prayer: and when they passed the camp, they compassed [o]the valley, and went up the mountain of Bethulia, and came to the gates thereof.

11 Then said Judith afar off, to the watchmen at the gate, Open, open now the gate: God, even our God, is with us, to shew his power yet in Jerusalem, and his forces against the enemy, as he hath even done this day.

12 Now when the men of her city heard her voice, they made haste to go down to the gate of their city, and they called [p]the elders of the city.

13 And then they ran all together, [e]both small and great, for it was strange unto them that she was come: so they opened the gate, and received them, and made a fire for a light, and stood round about them.

14 Then she said to them with a loud voice, Praise, praise God, praise God, I say, for he hath not taken away his mercy from the house of Israel, but hath destroyed our enemies by mine hands this night.

15 So she took the head out of [m]the bag, and shewed it, and said unto them, behold the head of Holofernes, the chief captain of the army of Assur, and behold the [k]canopy, wherein he did lie in his drunkenness; and [q]the Lord hath smitten him by the hand of a woman.

16 [r]As the Lord liveth, who hath kept me in my way that I went, my countenance hath deceived him to his destruction, and yet hath he not committed sin with me, to defile and shame me.

17 Then all the people were wonderfully astonished, and bowed themselves and worshipped God, and said with one accord, Blessed be thou, O our God, which hast this day brought to nought the enemies of thy people.

18 Then said Ozias unto her, O daughter, blessed art thou of [s]the most high God above all the women upon the earth; and blessed be the Lord God, [t]which hath created the heavens and the earth, which hath directed thee to the cutting off of the head of the chief of our enemies.

19 For this thy confidence shall not depart from the heart of men, which remember the power of God for ever.

20 And God turn these things to thee for a perpetual praise, to visit thee in good things because thou hast not spared thy life for the affliction of our nation, but hast revenged our ruin, walking a straight way before our God. [u]And all the people said; So be it, so be it.

14

1 Then said Judith unto them, Hear me now, my brethren, and take this head, and [a]hang it upon the highest place of your walls.

2 And so soon as the morning shall appear, and the sun shall come forth upon the earth, take ye every one his weapons, and go forth every valiant man out of the city, and set ye a captain over them, as though ye would go down into the field toward the [b]watch of the Assyrians; but go not down.

3 Then they shall take their armour, and shall go into their camp, and raise up the captains of the army of Assur, and shall run to the tent of Holofernes, but shall not find him: then fear shall fall upon them, and they shall flee before your face.

4 So ye, and all that inhabit the coast of Israel, shall pursue them, and overthrow them as they go.

5 But before ye do these things, call me [c]Achior the Ammonite, that he may see and know him that despised the house of Israel, and that sent him to us as it were to his death.

6 Then they called Achior [d]out of the house of Ozias; and when he was come, and saw the head of Holofernes in a man’s hand in the assembly of the people, he fell down on his face, and [e]his spirit failed.

7 But when they had recovered him, [f]he fell at Judith’s feet, and reverenced her, and said, Blessed art thou in all the tabernacles of Juda, and in all nations, which hearing thy name shall be [s]astonished.

8 Now therefore tell me all the things that thou hast done in these days. Then Judith declared unto him in the midst of the people all that she had done, from the day that she went forth until that hour she spake unto them.

9 And when she had left off speaking, the people shouted with a loud voice, and made a joyful noise in their city.

10 And when Achior had seen all that the God of Israel had done, he believed in God greatly, and [g]circumcised the flesh of his foreskin, and was joined unto the house of Israel [h]unto this day.

11 And as soon as the morning arose, [i]they hanged the head of Holofernes upon the wall, and [k]every man took his weapons, and they went forth by bands unto the [*]straits of the mountain.

12 But [l]when the Assyrians saw them, they sent to their leaders, which came to their captains and [m]tribunes, and to every one of their rulers.

13 So [l]they came to Holofernes’ tent, and said to [n]him that had the charge of all his things, Waken now our lord: for the slaves have been bold to come down against us to battle, that they may be [o]utterly destroyed.

14 Then went in [n]Bagoas, and knocked at the door of the tent; for he thought that he had slept with Judith.

15 But because none answered, he opened it, and went into the bedchamber, and found him cast upon the floor dead, and his head was taken from him.

16 [*]Therefore he cried with a loud voice, with weeping, and sighing, and a mighty cry, and [p]rent his garments.

17 After he went into [q]the tent where Judith lodged: and when he found her not, he leaped out to the people, and cried,

18 These slaves have [r]dealt treacherously; one woman of the Hebrews hath brought shame upon the house of king Nabuchodonosor: for, behold, Holofernes lieth upon the ground without a head.

19 When the captains of the Assyrians’ army heard these words, they [p]rent their coats and their minds were wonderfully [s]troubled, and there was a cry and a very great noise throughout the camp.

15

1 And when they that were in the tents heard, they were astonished at the thing that was done.

2 And [a]fear and trembling fell upon them, so that there was no man that durst abide in the sight of his neighbour, but rushing out all together, they fled into every way of the plain, and of the hill country.

3 They also [b]that had camped in the mountains round about Bethulia fled away. Then the children of Israel, every one that was a warrior among them, rushed out upon them.

4 Then sent Ozias to [c]Betomasthem, and to Bebai, and [d]Chobai, and Cola and to all the coasts of Israel, such as should tell the things that were done, and that all should rush forth upon their enemies to destroy them.

5 Now when the children of Israel heard it, they all fell upon them with one consent, and slew them unto [d]Chobai: likewise also they that came from Jerusalem, and from all the hill country, (for men had told them what things were done in the camp of their enemies) and they that were in [e]Galaad, and in [e]Galilee, [*]chased them with a great slaughter, until they were past [f]Damascus and the borders thereof.

6 And the residue that dwelt at Bethulia, fell upon the camp of Assur, and spoiled them, and were greatly enriched.

7 And the children of Israel that returned from the slaughter had that which remained; and the villages and the cities, that were in the mountains and in the plain, gat many spoils: for the multitude was very great.

8 Then [g]Joacim the high priest, and the [h]ancients of the children of Israel that dwelt in Jerusalem, came to behold the good things that God had shewed to Israel, and to see Judith, and to [i]salute her.

9 And when they came unto her, they blessed her with one accord, and said unto her, Thou art the exaltation of Jerusalem, thou art the great glory of Israel, thou art the great rejoicing of our nation:

10 Thou hast done all these things by thine hand: thou hast done much good to Israel, and God is pleased therewith: blessed be thou of the [k]Almighty Lord for evermore. [l]And all the people said, So be it.

11 And the people spoiled the camp the space of thirty days: and they gave unto Judith Holofernes his tent, and all [m]his plate, and beds, and vessels, and all his [n]stuff: and she took it and laid it on her mule; and made ready her carts, and laid them thereon.

12 Then all the women of Israel ran together to see her, and blessed her, and made a dance among them for her: and she took [o]branches in her hand, and gave also to the women that were with her.

13 And they put a garland of olive upon her and her maid that was with her, and she went before all the people [p]in the dance, leading all the women: and all the men of Israel followed in their armour [q]with garlands, and with songs in their mouths.

16

1 Then Judith began to sing this thanksgiving in all Israel, and all the people sang after her [*]this song of praise.

2 And Judith said, Begin unto my God with [a]timbrels, sing unto my Lord with [b]cymbals: tune unto him a [*]new psalm: exalt him, and call upon his name.

3 For God [c]breaketh the battles: for among the camps in the midst of the people he hath delivered me out of the hands of them that persecuted me.

4 Assur came out of the mountains [d]from the north, he came with ten thousands of his army, the multitude whereof stopped the torrents, and [e]their horsemen have covered the hills.

5 [f]He bragged that he would burn up my borders, and kill my young men with the sword, and [g]dash the sucking children against the ground, and make mine infants [h]as a prey, and my virgins as a spoil.

6 But the [i]Almighty Lord hath disappointed them [k]by the hand of a woman.

7 For the mighty one did not fall by the young men, neither did the sons of the [l]Titans smite him, nor high [m]giants set upon him: but [n]Judith the daughter of Merari weakened him with the beauty of her countenance.

8 For she put off [o]the garment of her widowhood for the exaltation of those that were oppressed in Israel, and [o]anointed her face with ointment, and [o]bound her hair in a [*]tire, and took a linen garment to deceive him.

9 [p]Her sandals ravished his eyes, her beauty took his mind prisoner, and the [q]fauchion passed through his neck.

10 The [r]Persians quaked at her boldness, and the [s]Medes were [*][t]daunted at her hardiness.

11 Then my afflicted shouted for joy, and my weak ones cried aloud; but [*]they were astonished: these lifted up their voices, but they were overthrown.

12 The sons of the damsels have pierced them through, and wounded them as fugatives’ children: they perished by the [u]battle of the Lord.

13 I will sing unto the Lord [*]a new song: [w]O Lord, thou art great and glorious, wonderful in strength, and invincible.

14 Let all creatures serve thee: [x]for thou spakest, and they were made, [y]thou didst send forth thy spirit, and it created them, and there is none that can resist thy voice.

15 For [z]the mountains shall be moved from their foundations with the waters, the rocks [a]shall melt as wax at thy presence: yet thou art merciful to them that fear thee.

16 For all sacrifice is too little for [b]a sweet savour unto thee, and all the fat is not sufficient for thy burnt offering: but he that feareth the Lord is great at all times.

17 Woe to the nations that rise up against my kindred! the Lord [i]Almighty will take vengeance of them [c]in the day of judgment, in putting fire and [d]worms in their flesh; and they shall feel them, and weep for ever.

18 Now as soon as they entered into Jerusalem, they worshipped the Lord; and as soon as the people were purified, they offered their burnt offerings, and their free offerings, and their gifts.

19 Judith also dedicated all the [e]stuff of Holofernes, which the people had given her, and gave the [f]canopy, which she had taken out of his bedchamber, for a [g]gift unto the Lord.

20 So the people continued feasting in Jerusalem [h]before the sanctuary for the space of three months and Judith remained with them.

21 After this time every one returned to his own inheritance, and Judith went to Bethulia, and remained in her own possession, and was in her time honourable in all the country.

22 And many desired her, but none knew her all the days of her life, after that [i]Manasses her husband was dead, and [k]was gathered to his people.

23 But she increased more and more in honour, and waxed old in her husband’s house, being [l]an hundred and five years old, and made [m]her maid free; so she died in Bethulia: and they buried her in the [*][n]cave of her husband Manasses.

24 And the house of Israel lamented her [o]seven days: and before she died, she did distribute her goods to all them that were nearest of kindred to Manasses her husband, and to them that were the nearest of her kindred.

25 And there was none that made the children of Israel any more afraid in the days of Judith, nor a long time after her death.

a 1.1 Comp. Tobit 14. 15.

b 1.1 See Jonah 1. 2.

c 1.1 ch. 16. 10. See Acts 2. 9.

d 1.1 See Tobit 3. 7.

e 1.5 ver. 15. See Tobit 1. 14.

f 1.6 See Tobit 6. 1.

g 1.6 See Isai. 11. 11.

h 1.7 ch. 16. 10.

i 1.7 See ch. 2. 21.

j 1.7 See Isai. 7. 8.

k 1.7 1 Esdr. 4. 48. & 5. 55. 2 Esdr. 15. 20. Ecclus. 24. 13. & 50. 12.

l 1.8 See Josh. 19. 26.

m 1.8 ch. 15. 5. So Num. 32. 1. Ps. 60. 7.

n 1.8 Comp. Isai. 9. 1.

o 1.8 See ch. 3. 9 marg.

p 1.9 See 1 Kin. 16. 24.

q 1.9 Comp. ch. 2. 23.

r 1.9 See Num. 13. 26.

s 1.9 Gen. 15. 18? or see Josh. 15. 4.

t 1.9 See Gen. 47. 11.

u 1.9 See Gen. 45. 10.

w 1.10 Gk. of Num. 13. 22. Ps. 78. 12, 43. Isai. 19. 11, 13. Ezek. 30. 14.

x 1.10 See Hos. 9. 6.

y 1.10 See 2 Kin. 19. 9. & Zeph. 3. 10.

z 1.11 ch. 11. 2, 22 (Gk.).

i 1.12 See ch. 2. 21.

j 1.12 See Isai. 7. 8.

a 1.12 See Acts 18. 18.

b 1.12 ch. 5. 2, 22. & 6. 1. & 7. 8. See Num. 22. 1. & 2 Chr. 20. 1.

c 1.12 ch. 5. 2, 5. & 6. 5. & 7. 17, 18. See 1 Sam. 11. 1.

d 1.12 See Zech. 9. 10.

dd 1.13 Comp. ch. 2. 1.

e 1.14 ver. 1.

f 1.14 ver. 3.

g 1.15 ver. 5.

h 1.16 So ch. 2. 20.

a 2.1 Comp. ch. 1. 13.

b 2.1 ch. 1. 12.

c 2.2 See Rev. 6. 15.

d 2.2 See 1 Sam. 20. 7.

dd 2.3 ch. 1. 11, 12.

* 2.4 Gr. second man. So Esther 13. 6.

e 2.5 2 Kin. 18. 28. Isai. 36. 13. ch. 3. 2.

d 2.6 See 1 Sam. 20. 7.

* 2.7 After the manner of the kings of Persia, to whom earth and water was wont to be given, to acknowledge that they were lords of land and sea. Herodotus.

f 2.11 See Isai. 13. 18.

g 2.12 Comp. ch. 11. 7.

h 2.14 Acts 8. 27 (Gk.).

i 2.15 See ch. 5. 23.

j 2.15 ver. 5. Comp. ch. 7. 2.

jj 2.17 See Tobit 9. 2.

k 2.17 ch. 3. 10. & 7. 18. See Judg. 18. 21.

l 2.19 ch. 7. 18. So Ex. 10. 5, 15. Num. 22. 5, 11. Comp. ch. 16. 4.

m 2.20 So ch. 1. 16.

n 2.20 See Ex. 10. 4.

o 2.20 See Gen. 22. 17.

p 2.21 ch. 1. 7, 12. ver. 25. 2 Macc. 4. 36. Acts 6. 9. & 15. 23, 41. & 21. 39. & 22. 3. & 23. 34. & 27. 5. Gal. 1. 21.

q 2.23 See Ezek. 27. 10.

q 2.23 See Ezek. 27. 10.

r 2.23 Gen. 25. 18.

s 2.23 Comp. ch. 1. 9.

t 2.24 ch. 5. 7. See Acts 2. 9.

p 2.25 ch. 1. 7, 12. ver. 25. 2 Macc. 4. 36. Acts 6. 9. & 15. 23, 41. & 21. 39. & 22. 3. & 23. 34. & 27. 5. Gal. 1. 21.

u 2.25 Gen. 10. 5.

v 2.26 See Judg. 6. 1.

w 2.27 ch. 1. 12. See Isai. 7. 8.

x 2.27 So Dan. 2. 44. Matt. 21. 44. Luke 20. 18 in the Gk.

y 2.27 Gen. 34. 26 marg. Ecclus. 28. 18. 1 Macc. 5. 28. Luke 21. 24. Heb. 11. 34.

z 2.28 See Matt. 15. 21.

a 2.28 See 1 Macc. 4. 15 ?

b 2.28 See 1 Sam. 5. 1. & 1 Macc. 4. 15.

c 2.28 1 Macc. 10. 86. & 11. 60. & 12. 33. See Judg. 1. 18.

a 3.2 See ch. 2. 5.

b 3.3 ch. 2. 27. Comp. ch. 4. 5.

c 3.6 ch. 2. 28. & 5. 2, 22. & 7. 8.

d 3.7 ch. 15. 13. Comp. Acts 14. 13.

e 3.7 ch. 16. 2. See Ex. 15. 20.

e 3.7 ch. 16. 2. See Ex. 15. 20.

f 3.8 See Ex. 34. 13.

* 3.9 Or, Esdrelom. ch. 1. 8. & 4. 6 marg. & 7. 3 (Gk.). See Josh. 17. 16.

* 3.9 Or, Dotea, Dothan, Junius. Gen. 37. 17. See ch. 7. 3.

* 3.9 Gr. great saw. Comp. 1 Sam. 13. 23. & 14. 4.

g 3.10 See Josh. 18. 24.

h 3.10 2 Macc. 12. 29, 30. See Josh. 17. 11.

i 3.10 See ch. 2. 17.

a 4.3 Comp. 2 Chr. 33. 11–13 ? or rather ch. 5. 19.

* 4.3 Or, out of Judea.

b 4.3 2 Chr. 33. 15, 16 ?

b 4.3 2 Chr. 33. 15, 16 ?

c 4.4 See 1 Kin. 16. 24.

d 4.4 1 Macc. 3. 16. See Josh. 10. 11.

e 4.4 Comp. ch. 15. 4, 5 ?

f 4.4 See John 3. 23 ?

g 4.5 ch. 5. 1.

h 4.5 Comp. ch. 2. 27. & 3. 3.

i 4.6 ver. 8, 14. ch. 15. 8. Comp. 1 Esdr. 5. 5 marg.

j 4.6 ch. 6. 10, &c. & 7. 1, &c.

k 4.6 So ch. 15. 4.

* 4.6 Or, Esdrelom. See ch. 3. 9.

* 4.6 Or, plain.

l 4.6 See ch. 7. 3.

m 4.7 ch. 6. 7. & 7. 1 (Gk.), 7. & 14. 11 (Gk.). So ch. 5. 1.

* 4.7 Or, two against all.

i 4.8 ver. 8, 14. ch. 15. 8. Comp. 1 Esdr. 5. 5 marg.

* 4.8 Or, governors. ch. 11. 14. & 15. 8. 2 Macc. 1. 10. & 4. 44. Acts 5. 21 in the Gk. Gk. not as ch. 6. 16.

n 4.9 See Acts 12. 5 marg.

n 4.9 See Acts 12. 5 marg.

o 4.10 ch. 8. 5. See 1 Kin. 20. 31.

p 4.11 Ezra 10. 1.

q 4.11 So ch. 9. 1. See Josh. 7. 6.

r 4.11 Comp. 2 Sam. 21. 10?

s 4.12 See 1 Esdr. 8. 77.

t 4.13 See Ex. 3. 7.

u 4.13 ch. 16. 20.

v 4.13 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

i 4.14 ver. 8, 14. ch. 15. 8. Comp. 1 Esdr. 5. 5 marg.

o 4.14 ch. 8. 5. See 1 Kin. 20. 31.

w 4.14 Ex. 29. 38.

q 4.15 So ch. 9. 1. See Josh.7.6.

x 4.15 Ex. 28. 4, &c. Ecclus. 45. 12 (Gk. and Engl.). Gk. not as ch. 10. 3 marg.

a 5.1 See ch. 4. 7.

* 5.1 Gr. all the top.

b 5.1 So ch. 4. 5. & 7. 10.

bb 5.1 ver. 20 (Gk.).

c 5.2 See ch. 1. 12.

c 5.2 See ch. 1. 12.

d 5.2 See ch. 3. 6.

e 5.5 ch. 6. 5. & 11. 9. & 14. 5.

c 5.5 See ch. 1. 12.

f 5.7 Gen. 11. 31. Comp. Acts. 7. 2.

g 5.7 See Acts 2. 9.

h 5.7 Comp. Josh. 24. 2.

* 5.8 Or, went out of.

i 5.8 Tobit 10. 11. ch. 6. 19. & 11. 17. 1 Macc. (3. 18. &) 4. 55.

g 5.8 See Acts 2. 9.

j 5.9 Gen. 12. 1.

k 5.9 Gen. 13. 2.

l 5.10 Gen. 46. 6.

m 5.10 Ex. 1. 7.

n 5.11 Ex. 1. 8–14.

o 5.11 Ex 1. 10. Acts 7. 19 in the Gk.

p 5.12 Ex. 2. 23.

q 5.12 Ex. ch. 7–ch. 10.

r 5.12 Ex. 12. 31, 33.

s 5.13 EX. 14. 21, 29.

t 5.14 Ex. 19. 1.

* 5.14 Gr. into the way of the wilderness of Sina.

u 5.14 Numb. 13. 26. & 20. 1. Deut. 1. 19.

x 5.15 Numb. 21. 25.

x 5.15 Numb. 21. 25.

y 5.15 Josh. 3. 16.

z 5.15 Josh. 10. 40

a 5.16 Josh. 12. 8.

a 5.16 Josh. 12. 8.

a 5.16 Josh. 12. 8.

a 5.16 Josh. 12. 8.

b 5.16 Comp. Gen. 34. 2.

c 5.16 Deut. 7. 1. Josh. 3. 10. & 24. 11.

d 5.17 Ps. 5. 5.

e 5.18 Judg. 2. 11–15. & 3. 7, 8.

f 5.18 2 Kin. 25. 9–11.

g 5.19 ch. 4. 3. Comp. Ezra 1. 1–3.

* 5.19 Or, have their dwellings.

h 5.20 Gk. as ver. 1. Rather as Rom. 14. 13.

i 5.22 See Rev. 6. 15.

ii 5.22 See ver. 2.

ii 5.22 See ver. 2.

j 5.23 Comp. Ex. 18. 4.

* 5.23 Gr. against a mighty army.

k 5.23 ch. 2. 15. & 7. 11 (Gk.). & 16. 12. Wisd. 12. 9.

l 5.24 So ch. 10. 12 (Gk.).

a 6.1 See ch. 1. 12.

b 6.2 ver. 5.

c 6.2 ch. 5. 21.

d 6.3 So 2 Kin. 18. 33–35. Isai. 36. 18–20.

e 6.4 See Isai. 34. 7.

b 6.5 ver. 5.

f 6.5 See ch. 5. 5.

g 6.5 ch. 5. 12.

h 6.6 Comp. 1 Kin. 22. 27.

i 6.7 See ch. 4. 7.

k 6.9 Gen. 4. 6.

l 6.10 ch. 4. 6.

m 6.11 ch. 7. 3, 7, 12, 17. & 12. 7.

n 6.16 ver. 21. ch. 7. 23. & 8. 10. & 10. 6. & 13. 12 in the Gk. See 1 Esdr. 6. 8. Gk. not as ch. 4. 8.

o 6.17 ver. 1.

p 6.19 See ch. 5. 8.

q 6.19 So Ps. 84. 9.

r 6.21 2 Sam. 3. 20 (Gk.). ch. 12. 10.

n 6.21 ver. 21. ch. 7. 23. & 8. 10. & 10. 6. & 13. 12 in the Gk. See 1 Esdr. 6. 8. Gk. not as ch. 4. 8.

a 7.1 See ch. 4. 7. Comp. ch. 15. 3.

b 7.2 Comp. ch. 2. 15.

c 7.3 ch. 12. 7 (Gk.). See ch. 6. 11.

* 7.3 from Dothaim, Junius.

d 7.3 ver. 18. ch. 4. 6. & 8. 3. See ch. 3. 9.

e 7.3 Not as ch. 4. 4 ?

* 7.3 Gr. Bean field.

f 7.3 ch. 3. 9 marg.

g 7.4 Numb. 22. 4.

a 7.7 See ch. 4. 7. Comp. ch. 15. 3.

c 7.7 ch. 12. 7 (Gk.). See ch. 6. 11.

h 7.7 ver. 17, 20. 1 Macc. 5. 45. Heb. 11. 34 in the Gk.

i 7.8 ver. 18. 1 Macc. 5. 3, 65.

k 7.8 See ch. 1. 12. Comp. ver. 17, 18.

l 7.8 See ch. 3. 6.

ll 7.11 See ch. 5. 23.

c 7.12 ch. 12. 7 (Gk.). See ch. 6. 11.

h 7.17 ver. 17, 20. 1 Macc. 5. 45. Heb. 11. 34 in the Gk.

m 7.17 See ch. 1. 12. Comp. ver. 8.

c 7.17 ch. 12. 7 (Gk.). See ch. 6. 11.

i 7.18 ver. 18. 1 Macc. 5. 3, 65.

m 7.18 See ch. 1. 12. Comp. ver. 8.

d 7.18 ver. 18. ch. 4. 6. & 8. 3. See ch. 3. 9.

n 7.18 ch. 2. 19.

o 7.18 See ch. 2. 17.

h 7.20 ver. 17, 20. 1 Macc. 5. 45. Heb. 11. 34 in the Gk.

* 7.21 Or, pits.

p 7.21 2 Chr. 26. 10 marg. (Gk.). ch. 8. 31.

q 7.21 See Ezek. 4. 11.

r 7.22 Tobit 14. 11. Luke 16. 9? in the Gk.

s 7.23 ch. 6. 15.

t 7.23 See ch. 6. 16.

u 7.24 So Ex. 5. 21.

x 7.25 See Deut. 32. 30.

y 7.26 See 1 Esdr. 8. 77. Gk. not as ver. 27.

z 7.28 2 Esdr. 2. 14. See Deut. 4. 26.

a 7.28 See Ps. 106. 6.

* 7.28 Or, lest he do, meaning Olofernes.

b 7.28 ver. 27.

c 7.30 ver. 20.

d 7.30 ch. 14. 13. 1 Thess. 2. 16 (Gk.).

e 7.31 ver. 26.

* 8.1 Or, Samaliel.

a 8.1 Comp. ch. 9. 2.

b 8.2 See Ruth 1. 22.

c 8.3 So 2 Kin. 4. 18, 19.

d 8.3 See ch. 7. 3.

e 8.3 So Cant. 8. 11.

f 8.4 Comp. ch. 4. 5.

g 8.5 Acts 10. 9. See 2 Sam. 11. 2.

h 8.5 ch. 4. 10, 14. & 9. 1. & 10. 3. See 1 Kin. 20. 31.

i 8.5 Gen. 38. 14, 19. ch. 10. 3. & 16. 8

k 8.6 Mark 15. 42 (Gk.).

l 8.6 See Isai. 1. 13.

l 8.6 See Isai. 1. 13.

* 8.7 Or, and she kept them.

m 8.9 ch. 7. 19, (22).

n 8.9 ch. 7. 26, 30, 31. ver. 30.

n 8.9 ch. 7. 26, 30, 31. ver. 30.

o 8.10 ch. 6. 15.

p 8.10 See ch. 6. 16.

q 8.12 Acts 15. 10.

r 8.13 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

s 8.14 1 Cor. 2. 11.

t 8.14 1 Cor. 2. 16.

u 8.14 ch. 11. 11. See Deut. 31. 29.

* 8.16 Or, engage.

x 8.16 Numb. 23. 19 (Gk.).

x 8.16 Numb. 23. 19 (Gk.).

* 8.18 Or, town.

y 8.18 Judg. 2. 11. & 4. 1. & 6. 1.

* 8.22 Or, fear.

z 8.22 Rom. 14. 13 (Gk.).

a 8.26 Gen. 22. 1.

a 8.26 Gen. 22. 1.

b 8.26 Gen. 28. 2, 7. & 29. 20. & 31. 7.

c 8.27 Prov. 3. 12. See Heb. 12. 6.

d 8.30 ver. 9.

e 8.31 ch. 7. 21.

f 8.33 ver. 10. ch. 10. 2, 5, 17. & 13. 9. & 16. 23. Esther 15. 2, 7 in the Gk.

g 8.33 See Ex 3. 16.

h 8.35 See 1 Sam. 1. 17.

i 8.36 ver. 5.

a 9.1 See ch. 4. 11.

a 9.1 See ch. 4. 11.

b 9.1 See ch. 8. 5.

c 9.1 Ex. 30. 8.

d 9.2 Gen. 34. 2, 25. But comp. Gen. 49. 7.

e 9.2 Gen. 34. 7.

f 9.4 Gen. 34. 28, 29.

g 9.4 2 Esdr. 2. 6. So Tobit 3. 4. ch. 7. 27. See 1 Esdr. 8. 77.

f 9.4 Gen. 34. 28, 29.

f 9.4 Gen. 34. 28, 29.

h 9.4 Num. 25. 11 [marg.].

i 9.7 So 1 Sam. 17. 45, 47.

j 9.7 ch. 16. 3. So Ex. 15. 3.

j 9.7 ch. 16. 3. So Ex. 15. 3.

jj 9.8 ch. 16. 10 (Gk.)?

k 9.8 Ex. 27. 2.

l 9.10 Judg. 4. 21. & 5. 26.

m 9.10 ch. 12. 8 (Gk.).

n 9.10 Judg. 4. 9. ch. 13. 15. & 16. 6.

o 9.11 Judg. 7. 2. 2 Chr. 14. 11. & 16. 8. & 20. 6.

p 9.11 Esther 15. 2.

q 9.11 Esther 14. 19(Gk.).

r 9.12 So ch. 13. 18.

a 10.2 ch. 9. 1.

b 10.2 ch. 8. 5, 6.

b 10.3 ch. 8. 5, 6.

b 10.3 ch. 8. 5, 6.

c 10.3 2 Sam. 12. 20. ch. 16. 8. See Ps. 23. 5.

c 10.3 2 Sam. 12. 20. ch. 16. 8. See Ps. 23. 5.

* 10.3 Gr. mitre. ch. 16. 8. Not as ch. 4. 15. See Ezek. 24. 17.

d 10.3 ch. 16. 9.

e 10.3 ch. 8. 2.

d 10.4 ch. 16. 9.

f 10.4 Ecclus. 21. 21.

g 10.4 Gen. 24. 22, 30 (Gk.).

h 10.4 Isai. 3. 21 (Gk.).

g 10.4 Gen. 24. 22, 30 (Gk.).

h 10.4 Isai. 3. 21 (Gk.).

i 10.5 1 Kin. 17. 12, 14, 16.

j 10.5 1 Sam. 25. 18. & 30. 12 (Gk.).

* 10.5 [Or,] wrapped, or, packed.

k 10.6 ch. 8. 33.

l 10.6 ch. 6. 15, 16.

m 10.8 ch. 11. 6 (Gk.). & 13. 5.

mm 10.11 ch. 14. 2 (Gk.).

n 10.12 So ch. 5. 24 (Gk.).

o 10.15 Wisd. 19. 2 (Gk.). See Acts 15. 3.

* 10.17 Or, and they prepared a chariot for her. Comp. 1 Kin. 18. 44. & ch. 15. 11 (Gk.).

p 10.18 Acts 21. 30 (Gk.).

r 10.20 Comp. ver. 20. ch. 11. 3, 5.

q 10.21 ch. 13. 9, 15. & 16. 19.

r 10.22 Comp. ver. 20. ch. 11. 3, 5.

s 10.23 ch. 14. 7.

a 11.2 ch. 1. 11. ver. 22 in the Gk.

b 11.3 ch. 8. 33. & 10. 20, 22. & 12. 5.

b 11.5 ch. 8. 33. & 10. 20, 22. & 12. 5.

bb 11.6 See ch. 10. 8.

c 11.7 So Gen. 42. 15. Comp. ch. 2. 12.

cc 11.7 See Baruch 3. 16.

* 11.8 Or, in favour.

d 11.9 See ch. 5. 5.

* 11.9 Or, gat him. So 1 Macc. 6. 44.

e 11.9 Gen. 12. 12 (Gk.).

f 11.10 ch. 5. 20, 21.

g 11.11 See ch. 8. 14.

h 11.13 Num. 18. 12.

h 11.13 Num. 18. 12.

i 11.14 See ch. 4. 8 marg.

j 11.17 John 9. 31 (Gk.).

k 11.17 See ch. 5. 8.

l 11.17 See Luke 2. 37.

m 11.19 See Num. 27. 17.

n 11.19 See Ex. 11. 7.

* 11.19 Or, bark.

* 11.19 Or, these things have I spoken.

o 11.19 Gk. construction as Luke 1. 45. Acts 9. 6. & 13. 42, 46. & 22. 10. Heb. 9. 19.

a 11.22 ch. 1. 11. ver. 22 in the Gk.

p 11.23 Comp. Ruth 1. 16. Dan. 6. 26.

a 12.1 ch. 15. 11.

aa 12.2 So Esther 14. 17. See Tobit 1. 10.

b 12.2 ch. 10. 5.

c 12.4 See 1 Sam. 1. 26.

d 12.5 ch. 10. 20. & 14. 17. Comp. ver. 9, 11.

e 12.5 See ch. 11. 3.

f 12.5 Ex. 14. 24. 1 Sam. 11. 11.

g 12.7 ch. 7. 3 (Gk.).

h 12.8 ch. 9. 10 (Gk.).

d 12.9 ch. 10. 20. & 14. 17. Comp. ver. 9, 11.

i 12.10 See ch. 6. 21.

d 12.11 ch. 10. 20. & 14. 17. Comp. ver. 9, 11.

j 12.13 ch. 13. 1 (Gk.).

k 12.16 See Matt. 5. 28.

l 12.19 ver. 2, 9.

a 13.1 ch. 12. 10.

b 13.1 See 1 Esdr. 3. 3.

c 13.1 ch. 12. 13 (Gk.).

d 13.2 ch. 12. 20. Comp. Ecclus. 31. 20, 25.

e 13.4 See Jer. 6. 13.

f 13.5 Luke 1. 54 (Gk.).

g 13.5 See ch. 10. 8.

l 13.6 Gk. not as ver. 6.

h 13.6 ch. 16. 9.

i 13.8 See 1 Sam. 17. 51.

k 13.9 See ch. 10. 21.

l 13.9 Gk. not as ver. 6.

m 13.9 Matt. 13. 20. Mark 1. 30 (English).

n 13.10 ch. 10. 5.

o 13.10 So ch. 7. 3.

p 13.12 See ch. 6. 16.

e 13.13 See Jer. 6. 13.

m 13.15 Matt. 13. 20. Mark 1. 30 (English).

k 13.15 See ch. 10. 21.

q 13.15 See ch. 9. 10.

r 13.16 See Ruth 3. 13.

s 13.18 See 1 Esdr. 6. 31.

t 13.18 So ch. 9. 12.

u 13.20 ch. 15. 10.

a 14.1 2 Macc. 15. 35.

b 14.2 ch. 10. 11 (Gk.).

c 14.5 See ch. 5. 5.

d 14.6 ch. 6. 21.

e 14.6 So 1 Kin. 10. 5.

f 14.7 ch. 10. 23.

s 14.7 ver. 7 (Gk.). ch. 16. 10 marg.

g 14.10 Comp. Ex. 12. 48, 49.

h 14.10 So Deut. 34. 6. Josh. 4. 9. Judg. 1. 26. Matt. 27. 8. & 28. 15.

i 14.11 ver. 1.

k 14.11 ver. 2.

* 14.11 Or, ascents. See ch. 4. 7.

l 14.12 ver. 3.

m 14.12 See 1 Macc. 16. 19 marg.

l 14.13 ver. 3.

n 14.13 ver. 14. ch. 12. 11, 13. & 13. 1, 3.

o 14.13 See ch. 7. 30.

n 14.14 ver. 14. ch. 12. 11, 13. & 13. 1, 3.

* 14.16 [Or,] Then.

p 14.16 See Gen. 44. 13.

q 14.17 See ch. 12. 5.

r 14.18 Jer. 3. 20 (Gk.). So Judg. 9. 23 (Gk.).

p 14.19 See Gen. 44. 13.

s 14.19 ver. 7 (Gk.). ch. 16. 10 marg.

a 15.2 ch. 14. 3.

b 15.3 ch. 7. 1.

c 15.4 So ch. 4. 6.

d 15.4 Comp. ch. 4. 4?

d 15.5 Comp. ch. 4. 4?

e 15.5 ch. 1. 8.

e 15.5 ch. 1. 8.

* 15.5 Or, overcame.

f 15.5 See Isai. 7. 8.

g 15.8 See ch. 4. 6.

h 15.8 See ch. 4. 8.

i 15.8 Comp. Judg. 18. 15 marg.

k 15.10 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

l 15.10 ch. 13. 20.

m 15.11 ch. 12. 1.

n 15.11 So ch. 16. 19. Luke 17. 31 (Gk.& Engl.).

o 15.12 2 Macc. 10. 7.

p 15.13 ch. 3. 7. See Ex. 15. 20.

q 15.13 See ch. 3. 7.

* 16.1 Or, this praising.

a 16.2 See ch. 3. 7.

b 16.2 1 Esdr. 5. 59. 1 Macc. 4. 54. See Ps. 150. 5.

* 16.2 Or, psalm and praise.

c 16.3 ch. 9. 7.

d 16.4 ch. 2. 21–27.

e 16.4 See ch. 2. 19.

f 16.5 Comp. Ex. 15. 9.

g 16.5 See 2 Kin. 8. 12.

h 16.5 See 1 Esdr. 8. 77.

i 16.6 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

k 16.6 See ch. 9. 10.

l 16.7 2 Sam. 5. 18, 22 (Gk.).

m 16.7 1 Chr. 11. 15. & 14. 9 (Gk.). Comp. Gen. 6. 4.

n 16.7 ch. 8. 1.

o 16.8 ch. 10. 3.

o 16.8 ch. 10. 3.

o 16.8 ch. 10. 3.

* 16.8 Gr. mitre. ch. 10. 3.

p 16.9 ch. 10. 4. Comp. Cant. 7. 1.

q 16.9 ch. 13. 6.

r 16.10 ch. 1. 7.

s 16.10 ch. 1. 1.

* 16.10 Or, confounded. ch. 14. 7, 19 (Gk.).

t 16.10 ch. 9. 8 (Gk.)?

* 16.11 [That is,] the Assyrians.

u 16.12 See ch. 5. 23.

* 16.13 Or, a song of praise.

w 16.13 Comp. Ex. 15. 11.

x 16.14 Ps. 33. 9. Comp. Gen. 1. 3, &c. So ch. 9. 12. Esther 13. 10.

y 16.14 Ps. 104. 30.

z 16.15 Comp. 2 Sam. 22. 8, 16.

a 16.15 See Ps. 68. 2.

b 16.16 Eph. 5. 2. Phil. 4. 18 in the Gk. So Ecclus. 45. 16. See Gen. 8. 21 marg.

i 16.17 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

c 16.17 Esther 10. 11. Matt. 10. 15. & 11. 22, 24. & 12. 36. Mark 6. 11. 2 Pet. 2. 9. & 3. 7. 1 John 4. 17. So Jude 6.

d 16.17 Comp. Job 14. 22. Isai. 66. 24.

e 16.19 See ch. 15. 11.

f 16.19 See ch. 10. 21.

g 16.19 2 Macc. 9. 16. Luke 21. 5.

h 16.20 ch. 4. 13.

i 16.22 ch. 8. 2.

k 16.22 See Gen. 25. 8. See Bel &amp; Drag. 1. 1 Macc. 2. 69.

l 16.23 Comp. Tobit 14. 11, 14.

m 16.23 See ch. 8. 33.

* 16.23 Or, sepulchre.

n 16.23 Gen. 23. 19, &c. John 11. 38.

o 16.24 Gen. 50. 10. 1 Sam. 31. 13. Ecclus. 22. 12.